Hello, and welcome to our talk, chaos in the cloud.
I'm going to start by telling you a little bit about what we are going
to do in the next 45 minutes. We are
going to start with a recap on what is chaos engineering.
Then we are going to talk about chaos engineering in the cloud.
Taking an aside into what the cloud is and what
its resiliency features are, we're going to talk about the
AWS fault injection simulator, which is the AWS
fully managed chaos engineering service. Then we're going
to have a demonstration of how that looks in practice.
Then we're going to finally share some best practices on working
with the fault injection simulator and architecting
for resiliency in general.
What is chaos engineering and why do we do it?
I like to start this talk with a quote from
Werner Fogeld. He's the CDO of Amazon.com,
and he said, failures are a given, and everything will
eventually fail over time. And that's so because
with the rise of microservices and distributed architectures,
the web and our applications have grown increasingly complex.
And as a result of that, random failures,
random failures have grown difficult to predict.
At the same time, our dependence on those systems has only
ever increased. And so as we moved away from monolithic architectures
towards microservices to become more agile,
build faster, and be able to scale, we naturally adds
some complexity between those microservices.
And chaos engineering is experimenting on those
distributed systems to build confidence in those systems and
make sure they can survive failure,
and to get a better understanding of their failure conditions
and of the performance envelopes. And that's all contained
in the quote I have on the slide from principlesofchaos.org.
So, diving a little bit deeper into chaos engineering, what is
it? We generally talk about kind of a loop,
stressing a system, observing how it reacts, and then improving
the system. And we do that to improve
resiliency and performance, uncover hidden issues in our architectures,
and expose blind spots, for example, in monitoring observability
and alarming. And usually we also achieve
a degree of improvement in recovery times, improving our operational
skills with the system, and a culture in
our technical. Sorry. And a culture in our tech.org.
And I talked about that being a loop and going
deeper into the loop. We see a loop of setting an
objective. We want to achieve something with our system.
We want to make it resilient against single ac failure,
for example. We set that objective, then we
design and implement our system.
We design an experiment to test
if our objective is actually achieved. We run the
test, we operate the system, and from the experiment
and the system operation we learn about the
system. We can respond to failure conditions, improve the system and
set new objectives and get better over time.
So chaos engineering locally on
your local machine, on your server, versus in the cloud. I'm going to
start by talking about chaos engineering in Java,
and I just choose Java because it's one
of the most widely used languages and it has awesome
support for chaos testing, both via libraries and via
tooling. What you generally see here
is that a lot of those tests are either JVM based,
they run inside the local JVM, they might be
agent based, they run as a sidecar next to the JVM on
the same machine, or they might be moved into the service
mesh connecting many systems together. And that's really an awesome
way to test your application code and to make sure it's resilient
and to be able to control those experiments from
your application code. And if
that is so awesome and it already works quite well, it's a great
improvement and everybody should do more of it. Why would we
want to move chaos engineering into the cloud?
We believe that using cloud services we
gain a more holistic monitoring view of how
our system works. We can identify cloud
based challenges, for example around limits, around scaling,
around interacting with other accounts. For example,
we can run dedicated scaling experiments to
learn where the failure points of our application is if
we scale to a very large degree or
very fast. And finally, we can do
validation of disaster recovery strategies where we gain
the ability to run chaos experiments
on a system and see if it, for example, can be switched over to
another region without
an time or in a specified timeframe.
And this is the point where I'm going to take an insight into
resiliency features of the cloud of AWS
and how they interact with applications.
What we see on the slide is the region design of AWS.
And we see a region is made up of multiple availability zones
here, abbreviated as AZ.
And each AZ is made up of one or more data
centers. And that's the only time I'm actually going to talk about data
centers. The fundamental
logical part of resiliency in AZ
you should think about is an availability zone, because those
availability zones are independent from each other.
And what that means is they have independent network
providers, they have independent power connections,
and if there is a geographic feature
in the city where the region is located, the AZ will be
located while being mindful of that geographic
feature. So for example, if there is a river flowing through the city,
not all of the AWS will be close to the river so
that we can be sure that in case of a flooding, not all of
the AWS go down. And so as you distribute
an application across AWS,
it will become resilient against single AZ failure
and gain a degree of resilience.
It will become resilient against single
availability zone failure, even though those failures are
quite unlikely in practice.
What does it actually look like? How do we distribute an application
across multiple availability zones?
What we see here is a simplified architecture
of a web application. We see cloud balancing,
distributing traffic to different instances, and that means EC two
instances for us and those instances act as application
servers. And then underneath
that we see a primary and a standby DB
instance, and we see that those are also distributed across
availability zones. And so in the end, like the event that,
for example, availability zone r goes down, the load
balancer would distribute traffic to b and C,
and there would be an automatic DB switch over to make the
current standby instance and c the primary instance,
and your application would continue to work.
Now that we have a certain understanding of resiliency in the cloud
and why we would want to actually test it, let me
go deeper into the AWS fault injection simulator and how
it supports you in running chaos experiments.
The AWS fault injection simulator is our
fully managed chaos engineering service.
It's an easy way to get started and it lets you reproduce
real world failures, whether they are very simple like stopping an
instance, or more complex like swapping APIs.
And finally, the service fully embraces the idea
of safeguards. So you can make sure that a
running chaos experiment does not impact your productive deployment.
I'm going to go into detail about all of those three features
that I just mentioned. It's easy to get started
because we spent actually a lot of time making it easy to get started,
because when we talk to customers about chaos engineering,
what customers repeatedly told us is that it is a little bit hard
to get started with chaos engineering. And so we want to make that as
easy as possible. You can use the console to
get familiar with the service and actually try things out,
and then you can use the CLI to take advantage of the templates and
integrate the service with your CI CD pipelines.
And those templates are JSon or YAML files that you can share
with your team. You can version control them and use all of the benefits
and best practices associated with version control,
like code review.
You can run experiments in sequence. You can
run impact of gradual degradation like a secret.
Gradual degradation experiments are to test
the impact of multiple concurrent issues, which is actually
how a lot of real world outages happen. You don't see outages because of
a single failure, but because of a chain of single failures
leading up to a real world outage.
It currently supports services like EC two rds,
ecs and eks. So virtual instances,
databases, container runtimes and managed
kubernetes. And we are working all the time to
provide support for more service, for more services,
sorry. And for more complex conditions.
And just to hit a nail on the head here, those faults,
they are really happening at the service control plane level.
So an instance might actually be terminated, memory is actually being
utilized, APIs are actually being throttled.
It's not faking something with metric manipulation,
but it's actually impacting how things
work at the control plane level. So you will
have to take extra or use extra caution when using the
service. And to enable you to do that, we have
safeguards. Safeguards act as the automated stop
button. Avoid to monitor the blast radius of your experiments and
make sure that it's contained and that failures created with the experiment
are rolled backed if alarms go off. And that's kind
of runtime controls what happens during an experiment.
And the service of course integrates with identity
and access management. IAM and Im controls can
be used to control what fault types can be used in an
experiment and what resource can be affected. And that's
of course working with stack based policies. So for example,
only EC two instances with a tag environment
equals test can be affected. That's one of many
possible safeguards you can implement.
What kind of targets and actions are supported?
There's a host of targets
and actions supported across the categories of compute,
storage, networking databases and management service
services. Sorry. And management services.
And I will dive somewhat deeper into the architecture
of default injection service and how it interacts
with the different components of the AWS cloud.
And we see here a diagram of how the
service works. At a high level, we start with an experiment
template which will comprise,
sorry. At a high level we will start with an
experiments template which is or which contains
different fault injection actions, targets that will be affected
and safeguards to be run during the experiment. And you can see that here slightly
to the left of center called experiment template
and white.
And then when we start an experiments, default injection
simulator performs the actions. So it
injects faults into supported resources that
are specified as the targets, and then
those faults interact with your
resources and that will change what happens in
monitoring, in monitoring in Amazon Cloudwatch for example, or in
your third party monitoring solution and then you can take
action based on those observability metrics
you have there on those alarms you have there on those logs you have there
by using Amazon eventbridge to, for example, stop an experiment
if the wrong alarm is triggered, or to start
a second experiment at that point in time.
And so now we have an understanding of what chaos engineering
is, why we want to do it in the cloud, and how the
AWS fault injection simulator works. And it's the point where I'm
going to hand over to bent to tell you about
some exciting new scenarios we saw from reinvent,
and to show you a demonstration of how the fault injection
simulator works in practice.
All right, thank you very much, Oliver. We're now going to
take a closer look at those two new scenarios
we launched at reinvent. So the first one is
about cross region connectivity disruptions.
So we have customers who have the requirement of operating
their application at the highest possible availability
rates, and those customers typically tend to
architect their applications to span two regions.
And those customers also asked us that we could
maybe help them to make chaos testing even easier for
them to test whether their applications can really withstand
a connectivity disruption between two regions. So for instance,
think of an active active or active passive
kind of setup between two regions where all of a sudden your
database, like a dynamodb, won't replicate new data.
This is now possible with the new cross region
connectivity disruption scenario that is available with the fault injection
simulator. Another new scenario that we also launch
is around availability zone power interruptions.
So we already mentioned that those kind of scenarios
have a really low likelihood of happening. However,
there are customers who still want to experience how
their application would behave in such an event. So in the event
of a power interruption, you would see, for instance, scenarios like
EC two instances or containers stopping out of
nowhere. And with the new scenario of AC
availability power disruptions, you will basically be able to
test how your application behaves under those kind of events.
But now we basically want to have a look
at our own demo. So we will take you
through a journey of testing an application
and improving its resiliency when it comes to availability
zones failures. So what we brought for
today here is a simple workload that is currently running
in a single container. So we have a container
that is basically a simple API that responds with a pong to
every request to send to the container. And this is currently
running on eks. It's a single pod
hosted on a single node that we have in our cluster, which is
currently running in the availability zone. A and I
personally am not the most Kubernetes experienced
guy. So I'm not really sure how Kubernetes behaves
in the case of an availability zone disruption.
And I personally want to have a really low
cost with my application. So I just want to check whether
running a single pod is enough to tolerate the failure
of an AC or if for instance, Kubernetes will automatically
for me schedule this pod on a new
node that is hosted in a different availability zone.
But before we jump into the console, I already want to show you
the result of the experiment.
So of course this is not going to happen. We won't see an automatic
pod reassignment to a different node hosted in a different
availability zone. This is not how it actually
works. So instead what we would want to do here to make
the system more resilient is basically by updating
our deployment to at least run in two
different availability zones. And this is actually
what we are going to take a look at now in the demo. Now it's
time to look at the fault injection simulator in action. For this
we are going to first take a look at the application that we deployed
in Kubernetes. Then we are going to set up a load testing tool to
send frequent requests against our application to
inspect some metrics like the availability and also the
response time of our request.
Then we are setting up the fizz
to introduce some chaos in our application.
And then we are revisiting our load testing tool to see the impact of
our chaos experiment. So let's start with taking a look at
the Kubernetes manifest so
we can quickly see here with our deployment. This is basically the Kubernetes
resource that you need to deploy containers in
your cluster. We can see here that we have one container
that we are deploying on our cluster. This is
basically pulling the container image from my application
from a elastic container registry of my account.
Then I'm also using a node
selector here to ensure that this container
will basically be scheduled on a node
that is running in the US east one, a availability zone.
Besides our deployment we also have a service
and an ingress resource. Those are required
to expose our deployment in the Internet and
we need that in order to run our load testing here
for this use case. One thing to highlight here is the ingress
section. So we are using the AWS load balancer
controller to create an application load balancer
in the cloud from this ingress resource that we just deployed.
So both the ingress and the deployment yaml files are already
deployed. So let's have a look if that was successful.
So I'm jumping in the console. Now I'm
running Kubectl get pod.
This should now return one pod. This looks good.
And now we want to basically double check whether this node
here is really running in the correct availability
zone. And this looks good. So the node is
running in the US east one a availability zone.
So that basically means that the container is running in the availability
zone that we want to run a chaos experiment on.
Now let's get the URL of
the ingress controller or to be more precise
of the load balancer. So let's say Kubectl get ingresses.
That looks good and
here's the address. Let's send a curl request
here and we are getting
a response pong. This looks good. So now let's copy this
URL and let's set up the cloud testing
tool. So for this case I'm using locost.
Locost is basically running on my local machine and will send a
good amount of requests per second to my application.
Let's start this here on the top
right corner we can see the requests per second that are sent against
our application. And here we can see the failures.
So failures would indicate a status code 400 ish.
Now we can take a look at the chart and we can see here that
we slowly ramped up on requests per seconds. And now we are
around sending around 240 requests per
second. And this looks good. We have no big failures.
Our response time is quite static and
with 120 milliseconds this looks good.
So I would say this is a successful deployment of
our application. So now let's check how the resiliency
of our application really looks like. And let's
see the impact of a chaos experiment. For this I'm using to
the AWS console. And here I'm basically
searching for the service called AWS.
AWS fizz.
I'm going to open up this one here.
I'm basically taking a look at the experiment templates
here we can see one template that I already created. This is called disrupt
Aza and this is doing exactly that. Let's have a look at
it. So the name is disrupt Aza and this is
exactly what happens here. Let's quickly take
a look at the update wizard. I think this is really good for the
visualization what's happening here. So we can see that
this template is quite small. So we have one action which
is called disrupt aza. Let's have a look
at it first. So here we basically specify
the action type. This is disrupt connectivity.
Disrupt connectivity will prevent packets
from leaving and entering the given subnet.
And down here we can see the duration. In this case we
have two minutes configured and we have configured the target.
So the target are the subnets that are impacted by this event. Now let's
have a look at the targets. So I'm quickly opening up the target
here we can see the subnet
target one. We are using a resource
filter here to ensure that not every single subnet
is targeted, but instead we are only taking subnets
in the US east one a availability zone in
scope of this experiments. So a subnet in
AWS is a zonal resource. So that means that a
subnet is deployed in one availability zone.
And this configuration really just makes sure that no
network traffic is leaving or entering every single subnet
in the availability zone. Us east one a so I would say
let's go back here and start this experiment to take a
look at what's going on. So I'm
clicking start here and
it takes some time until the experiment is actually
executed so you can take a look at timeline to see what's
going on. So currently this one is pending.
This is just taking a couple of seconds to deploy
the disruption. So let's wait. There we go. Now it's actually
running. So if we go back to the locals page.
Yeah, there we go. We should see a drop in availability.
So you can see that straight away we
have a really reduced amount of
requests per seconds and now we can see that there's no request
being successful anymore. So that's basically
showing us that there's not a single request going through.
What's interesting, if you can go back here we can see that
those requests right now are somehow dangling.
So there is no bad response code
like a HTTP 400 ish,
but the connection is just not completely opened and closed.
So this is really the impact of our availability zone
outage here. So let's wait
for some time until this experiments is finished.
Here we go. The experiment is
now finished. Let's go back to the console and we can see straight
away once the experiment was finished
our network is available again and our application continues
to serve traffic. So here we can see that our
current architecture with one container being
deployed in one availability zone is not really able to
handle this situation well. So let's see how we can improve
the availability. I will first stop
the load test here and we are now jumping back into
the editor because I already prepared an
updated deployment. So here we have the updated deployment.
It's pretty similar to the previous one,
besides two major updates.
So first of all, we have two replicas. So this basically
means that we deploy two containers. And then what's even more important
is we have an affinity rule created. So this affinity rule
will basically ensure that those containers will
be spread across the nodes and specifically
spread across the different availability zones. So now let's
go back to the terminal.
And now let's delete the old deployment.
And now
let's apply the updated deployment.
So this will take just a couple of seconds to deploy our
pods. Let's have a look at them.
There they are running on two different nodes.
And if we now again open up the nodes
here, we will see that those
two nodes are actually running in two different availability
zones. So now we can test again.
So let's go back to the load testing tool. Let's do a new test.
Let's configure the same amount of users being and
run the load test.
Give it some seconds here to create seconds.
So here we go.
This looks good. Now let's go back into
the AWS console to rerun the
experiment. So we
are going to experiment,
going to the templates, opening up the
template. We're now starting another experiments
here. Let's start this one.
So this again
just takes some time.
Still pending. Let's see. Now it's running.
So let's also wait for.
So we can see quite a different result now. So what we
see here is a very, very short time
period where our service wasn't available. And this
is basically because of the load balancer health check
that checks the availability of its targets
every 5 seconds. And this is just
the small time gap where the load balancer thought
that the container is available. And then
after the next evaluation figured out, no, I cannot
send any further request to the target. And as we can see
here with this update, our application now
reacted way better to the outage. And this
would be a. Yeah,
would basically show you the full lifecycle of running an experiment.
So we made an assumption, figured out that this is not correct,
updated our application to
see an improvement in the resiliency. And this basically
here concludes the demo of today.
I now also want to share some best practices to
get started with chaos engineering for your own applications.
So I would recommend you to start with very
small templates in the beginning that maybe only,
as in our demo, only include one single action,
because this allows you to very quickly understand the impact of
a certain template action. The second
tip that I have for you here is testing close to your
production environment. So let's say you have a containerized workload that is
in your staging environment, running on Docker compose, for instance,
and on your production environment, those containers run
on a fully fledged eks cluster.
Here I would recommend you to basically maybe add
a new test environment that is in the architecture more
closer to what you have in production, because else
you won't be able to basically catch
AWS in your staging application architecture that you
can basically apply in production to increase the resiliency of your
application. So always try to test as close
as possible to production as possible, maybe even in production.
The next one is about minimizing the blast radios. So we
mentioned that with the port injection simulator on AWS,
it's possible basically to minimize the blast radios
to two ways. So the first one being with limiting the access that the
service has to your resources. So for instance,
with principle of least privilege in your IAM policies,
you can basically limit the access to the resources that
the fault injection simulator has by, for instance, making sure that only your
application servers and your databases of the staging
environment are accessible by the service.
And also we would recommend you to basically use
the health check capabilities, the emergency brake stops,
to stop an experiment when you
see that you really have degraded when you, for instance, test in
production. To get started
with collecting your first hands on experience, I can recommend this
workshop that we have for you here. With this workshop you basically
have a guided step by step experience where you
basically will learn and understand those different functionalities of
the fault injection service firsthand. And I
would recommend you to check it out either by scanning the QR
code or visiting the URL on the screen. And this concludes
the session. So you see another QR code on the screen.
This is really important. So if you scan this QR
code or visit the URL, you can give us feedback. And we really, really need
your feedback. We want to understand if you like this session and
what we could improve next time. So please take a
minute and fill out the form. It would really mean a lot
to us and we thank you really much and we wish you a great
day ahead and also fun with all the other interesting sessions.