Everyone and thanks for watching my talk at the Con 42
conference on JavaScript. I'm Peleg and I'm
thrilled to explore the configurations as code approach with
you today. Over the 15 to 20 minutes, we will
uncover how configuration as code can revolutionize your approach to
configuration management and software development.
Before diving into configuration, let me introduce myself.
My name is Peleg and I've been a software developer for
more than 80 years. I mainly focused on cybersecurity and
in the past three years I've been leading configu.
My journey has led me to the exciting world of configuration management,
where I've been explored the ascode approach and especially
the configuration as code approach.
So let me start by outlining what we will explore
in this talk. Our journey will include understanding
application configuration, tackling the challenges they
present, and diving deep into these configuration as
code approach. Great. Let's start our
exploration. Begin with our software Bible, the twelve factory
guide. I know some folks find this guide a bit old school,
but it does a good job of explaining the basics.
In particular, we'll focus on the config section and talk
about application configuration. So every software is a
combination of code that specify the logic and
configuration that define the behavior of the software.
Think of configuration as a bench of setting that tell
our software how to act. It's like giving specific
instruction to a video game so that it know how
to start and what level difficulty to use.
As developers, we keep configurations separate from our code
and store them in separate locations or dedicated files.
This includes configuration like environment variables,
secrets to keep data safe, feature flag to turn certain
functions on or off, and other such setting data.
As we delve into the world of configuration and configuration
management, it's essential to understand the versus formats available.
One prevalent format you will encounter is the dot and
file format it flavored for its simplicity and
adaptability, making it a common choice among developers.
But it's worth nothing that the need for effective configuration
management extend beyond just n file.
There are other formats like JSON,
YaML, and more, each with its own set of
advantages and disadvantages.
In fact, the importance of configuration management has grown so
much that even node js, starting from version 26,
offers built in supports for dot and files, recognizing the
significance of keeping configurations separate and secure.
So whether you choose dot and files, explore alternative
formats, or utilize built in support, remember that the
quest for efficient and secure configuration management
is a shared journey for all developers.
Configuration are essential, but managing them bring challenges.
This includes complexity, development slowdowns and
scalability issues. At Configu we invested lot
of time talking with developers and DevOps engineers from
small startups to big corporates, and we found a
major common problem in how they handle application configuration.
Most of them say their configurations are fragment and
distributed all over the place. They are saved as a
simple raw text in many different locations like databases,
files or even third party services. This mixup
leads to internal friction, governance gaps,
developer distractions. Yeah, and even data risks
if not managed effectively. Wrong or outdated
setting can cause problems making our software act
up, which could lead to downtime and lost money.
Managing this setting correctly is super important to
keep our system stable and our team working smoothly.
It's key to know what setting are being used and
to have a way to keep them accurate, reliable and up
to date. For example, a company we met told
us about a developer they have who accidentally changed a
single character in their database connection string.
And yeah, connection string may seem humanly readable,
but they often contain special characters, making it challenging
to tell the difference between necessary components
and potentials error. As a result,
the application experienced a critical failure
and it took them too much time to figure it out and
fix the issue. Showing how important
is to have a strong and reliable way to manage configurations.
Understanding these challenges requires a transformative
concept, and after looking into infrastructure
as code and seeing the good stuff it bring to the table,
we thought why not to build on these winning formula.
And that's how configuration as code came to
our life. Let's dive into the
heart of our discussion. Configuration as code configuration
as code is a powerful solution designed to streamline configuration management,
making it a game changer for developers.
These core of configurations as code appeal lies on
its benefits and these include consistency
and reproducibility. Configuration as code keeps configuration consistent
across different settings because they are handled as
code, versioning and tracking,
changes to configurations are tracked over
time, making it easy to see who change what
and when. Automation and efficiency
no more manual mess configuration as code automates configurations
processes, making deployments faster and smoother.
Scalability and agility. Configuration as code make it
easy to adjust and scale configurations to meet
changing needs more quickly. Collaboration and
teamwork it helps developers, operations teams
and stakeholders work together more harmoniously.
Auditability and security all changes
can be reviewed and audited, ensuring configurations remain
secure simplifies configuration management.
Configurations as code brings a clear structure to managing
configurations, making them easier to understand and evolve.
Eliminates manual errors by managing configuration
as code, it reduce manual mistakes, leading to
more reliable setup. Last but not least,
enhances efficiency and productivity. So configuration
as code frees up time for teams to focus on
building a great applications and achieving
their business goals. So now that we understand
configuration as code, let me briefly introduce configu,
an open source tool that brings configuration as code principles to life.
Configure provides a structured approach to managing configuration
across all different environments, systems, and technologies.
It is built to provide a common, flexible and extensible
process for storing, mutating, and orchestrating
configuration data across different environments and
systems. With configu, you can leverage the
power of configuration as code ensure streamlined and efficient
configuration management for your application. So,
to gain better understanding of how configu works, I would like
to introduce a few of Config's core concepts. The first concept
is config, which is a data model that represents a
single application configuration. On configu, it includes
three parameters, a key, a value, and a context
set. For example, imagine debug level equals
error on a production set. Config store
Config store is where those configu are saved and read from.
It could be any storage engines and includes
any type of configuration data, from text files and databases
to secret managers and any configuration manager
you use. Config set config set is the context
of the configuration. It could be an environment like development
or production, but it also can be a
region, a customer, or basically any context
you need to group configurations for. The last and
most important concept is config schema. The config
is implementation for the configuration as code
approach. So basically it's a file
that is part of your service code. It declare how the
code looks and behave, and lets you
to add useful metadata on each configu for collaboration,
testing, local development, and many more.
We called it a CFGU file, and we
will see an example of it in a moment. And now let's
move to the fun part and see some code examples. We will
use the configured open source as our management interface
and the CFGU format as our configuration as
code. I'm going to use an hello word
JavaScript app and describe its configurations on the
schema file, and then I will manage it as I manage code.
In this example, I will use a JSON file as my config store,
but you can choose any config storage you want or need.
So here's my super complex JavaScript application
that prints any message that it gets from the environment
variable. As you can see here, we will start with
installing the configure CLI. In this case,
I already have it installed on my
computer. Sorry, configu,
let's run it okay, so this
is a configu CLI command and
now that we have configu, let's create our first schema.
We'll do that by running the configure init command
and in this case we will use the
get started flag so it will generate
a premade hello world example. Awesome.
As you can see here, our schema file contain three keys,
greeting, subject and
message over greeting. We are enforcing
type rejects with greeting pattern
and we gave it a default value of hello on
subject. It's free string with
a default of world and message
is template which is additional feature of configu
and it creates a value by templating other values.
Very handy if you need to build string like
connection string or endpoints. And in
general there are many other capabilities that you can achieve with the CFDU
file. It offers additional attributes
like description, test restrictions
and many others. So to be able
to work with the JSON store as we mentioned
before, I will need to add the details of the JSON
file to the config file. I already
have it here and I already insert
all the relevant details, which is the JSON stored
JSon. It's a stored from JSON
file type and it's ready to use. As you can see here,
it's empty for now, but we will generate configu
very soon. Great. So everything is ready
and we can insert some values. We will use the upset
command and save values for
my development environment. Let's start configure
absurd.
Observe.
Let's sorry for all
the junk, but we'll use my JSON store for
set development. I will use the schema
get started schema that we generated and
we will start with the greeting.
For example, let's add hey and
also let's insert for subject
the value conf 42
successfully. Note that in the background configure
validating the type and all the restrictions you added
to the CFG file. In this case, for greeting,
it must meet the regex we defined. If you want
to check it out, let's do the same thing,
but instead of hey, let's just
add blah and
we will get an error that blah is not meet the regex.
Now let's see how it's saved. Let's open our JSOn store
and as you can see, we have two configs.
Each one of them is built from key, set and value.
For example, the first one, the key is greeting under
development and the value is going to be hey great.
Now let's add additional configs to
a different set for example, let's use production and maybe we
will do additional set that's going to be under production,
a child set of production that can inherit the
values from it and add a
different one. Let's choose a specific
customer for example under production and it's going to be
look like this one. So as you can see, I'm doing multiple upset
together. The first one is going to add welcome
greeting to the production and the second one is going to be
to add the user one subject to
my customer, one set.
Great. As you should see in live everything is saved
to my JSON store for ending this process.
Let's run our application with these configurations. First I will run
it for my local environment, so let's run it using the
default only. So I won't need anything except
my schema will look like it
will look like that and sorry,
I'm missing space. Great.
Yeah, so my Javascript is run and we
got the hello word example. If you want to see how it looks like
without the configure so node
index it will get undefined. Running it
with the defaults will get the hello word. And now
instead of running it, let's generate a dot and file.
Let's do it for the development environment
it's going to look like that. So we
have again exporting JSOn store development
set and now instead of running it we'll
export into a n format, it will look like
that. So we got the dot and these. If I want, I can
also pipe it into a n file
and it will generate the dotten file. Let's see
it. Here is the dotten
file and for the finale let's
do the same. But now we
want to run it again and instead
of development let's just export
the production.
Customer one yay.
Welcome customer one. You can see how our team implemented
and visit Configure's open source project on GitHub if you find
it useful. We would appreciate your star and support. And better yet,
if you want, join our team and contribute to the project
for helping everyone to improve configurations. Thanks for
watching my talk and feel free to reach out if you have any questions
or thoughts.