Hey there. Hi. So, let's get
started. So, my name
is Chetanya, and based out of London.
Today I'm gonna discuss the way,
how we leverage relentless marketing.
We're gonna discuss different aspects,
how do we measure conversion rates,
leverage data to do certain actions.
Uh, we're gonna understand the whole scenario. Many might
have had talks about people talking about building an
LLM or maybe fine tuning them.
Yeah, but those are concepts which are
around. But leveraging LLM
in marketing is something which I haven't thought of
before, according tweaked with AI and
stuff like that, and probably wanted to learn more
and then figured out there are ways where I can improve my marketing conversions
or bring in more revenue, understand more data
by using certain tools like Big ML or maybe
Amazon party. We're gonna discuss all of this, but let me deep dive
into this now.
So today's agenda,
we want to talk about introduction, a brief history,
introduction to web elements, the layers
of generative AI optimizing
metrics. How do we, how marketing change with AI,
building your own LLM with
Amazon party rock, and maybe other tools like that.
So let's know each other a bit.
Yeah, think. Had a good understanding
of AI and things, and I was working with the company called Writesonic.
I don't know if you guys have heard of it, but it's one of
the fastest growing AI tech companies joining the company,
the initial first few employees.
It's. I didn't have any reference
on how to grow the product. Right. Since AI is a
new industry, we couldn't really understand
a lot of things. But, yeah, be made of me.
I was able to grow the company at a good scale, generating our
$9 million in about a year.
Previously to that,
it was mostly leading growth
marketing and product marketing functions in various tech
companies, mostly cybersecurity,
deep tech AI. Yeah, that's pretty
much partly,
yeah. Let's deep down now.
So what's an LLM? Right. I think
the different definitions and different
forms of LLM. But to keep it simple,
let's imagine LLM
as a bunch of data, bunch of unorganized,
unscattered data,
where it's sitting in a maybe, let's say something like
a Google Drive. Right. So how do
we leverage this data is by building a
problem set. It's building a solution and optimizing the
solution. So that's how I look at defining
an LLM. And there are different, like, fine tuning,
optimizing. We can do
100 different things. The core depends on how,
what data you have, how do you acquire the data
and what are the other forms of data?
Yeah, probably database. Now we can look
at it, right. I think this is a key in
building in code LLm or the best LLM.
Now let's look at the layers of generative AI
and then like to understand the technology stack and.
Yeah, bits and buttons of it. So when you look at the layers of
generative AI, you see applications fine tuning,
foundation models and infrastructure applications.
Right. So a drive sonic. We had our own
llm, which is open
sourced llm. We found shown that we released in a product
called as botsonic with an open API and people were able to use
it. So that's an application level
use of LLM and how we could use
buildings on top of an application or an API
using different tools and techniques. Then let's
look at fine tuning. Let's suppose we
have a data of next, which was not
really accurate. Maybe you're getting,
trying to give some input to it and output
is not what we are expecting. In the instance like that,
you try to fine tune things and you trying
to optimize things and you try to get more relevant
outputs.
Next, let's go to the foundation models.
The market for the foundation models is really
huge. A lot of companies who are working on
fine tuning, pre training, optimizing these
models. So I would see
adopting decision models would change
before and after a few years. Think right
now we're at the pace where we're able to see more foundation
models with rapid data sets.
The last comes the infrastructure, like for
running this use, application, using OpenAI or whatever,
hugging phase and all of that. We need large
infrastructure. You heard about Nvidia, Nvidia going
into this direction. And probably all of this
needs a heavy lifting, probably a good retro lifting. That's what
I would do.
Let's go back and look at the technology step.
You see the technology at the current
state, I mean, not at the current state. Technology is
always evolving, right? And you see what you see today
and you don't see after a week or couple of
months. So, which means that we need to adapt according to it.
Consider the amount of data and the amount of things
which we need to think through when you're building a
last language model. So now doubling that
every 3.45 to ten
months is, yeah,
pretty much a hard job. I've read
reports where the cost of carbon emissions and therefore the central
conditions we need to maintain the temperature in
the data centers. We need to make sure that
there are no halls with extensive emulsion
of different, different emissions and keeping at the right
things in the right place is an important place in
an important place.
Now let's get into the actual customizing
market efforts through LMSFO visual engagement.
So when we look at, when we looked at how
do we leverage AI in our marketing efforts, right?
So we're working with a company called as mixed panel, which was pretty much
has a more sophisticated technology and
they were able to pull out data and where I could search certain
things on how I wanted to see measure
things between. Usually at this point,
before the eye, we're able to go
to Google Analytics or pretty much other tools
like that, select a date and look at a conversion rate. Right?
But now we're able to ask tools, hey, what was my conversion
rate between this and this? What, what was my conversion
rate of an ad campaign? So to get more inaccurate,
accurate data with different forms of
data, similarly, we're able to measure things like conversion
rate or analysis and customer segmentation.
Let's get a bit detail here. So let's
say conversion rate,
improving the conversion rate is where we use data to understand
what's working in. It's not working. Then we measure
this in form of ROI. Could be a payback period. Like I
spending to $100. How much time will I need to
keep running my campaigns to get hundred
dollars back? And how much profitability, when does my profitability
start? Takes three months. So that's what we do.
And then customer segmentation from the
customer segmentation using AI, we were able
to personalize segments of marketing,
personalized marketing strategies. I was able to personalize certain
campaigns where I know that, hey, this guy is from us,
this guy is from India, some other person is from UK.
And we're able to have different messaging
for all the different people, so on and so forth.
Yeah. And that was one of the key changing
things of personalization where
we could do so many things in terms of personalizing
with gifs, images. Yeah, I think the
world keeps going on there.
Use cases. So let's talk about the
use cases for marketing. So one thing we
previously discussed, like searching for data, you have
one or two branch numbers, probably for me as
personal, I hate Excel. Yeah.
Can manage with Google sheets and all of that, but probably not
a big fan of Excel. Then there are
situations where I had to struggle,
use other tools and pretty much
it's a hard job for me, but with AI, I was able to
crunch numbers, create formulas, create calculations,
lot of things. So the tools like sheets,
AI, which makes this job pretty easy. So kudos
to the makers.
Then let's talk about sales intelligence right here, you probably
seen tools like Gong, which were adaptable
in terms of understanding what does it sell. So,
to give an instance, right, you could tell
a number, talk to a customer saying that, hey,
I saw that you signed up on my website and I
wanted to understand more about what you're looking for.
Then Gong will understand his reactions
and analyze and understand
those, and gives you word cloud and
gives you the sentiment where you're doing better in
your pitch, where you're doing bad and compares with your other
teammates calls. And that's probably what are we looking
at and how things are changing. Last one would
be data analytics, where from asking your
customers what you're doing and start saying
why they do it. So you can see that,
hey, conversion rate improved of x, which means that this change,
which I made a week back, is coming today.
So use that for a similar way.
I mean, these are not the two or three use
cases. There are different use cases. It depends on how
we look at it and how we probably look at
building it into our workflows and systems.
So let's. Now let's.
So there's a tool called as bigml, where you can
load your own data and
analyze things, and there are different sources. It's a mix of
a machine learning model. You can also look
at building your own alum and analyzing and
building multiple distribution. Right. So I have different data
which have already uploaded in the past. So that's while
we do, we train some data and.
And also let's look at this one.
So if we go back,
oops,
yeah, this one. So how all
of these details where I can take
some different parameters, like add name, campaign name, placement optimization
into the consideration. Now,
multiple things. All the things which you see in an ad group.
Right. Now I also see this one,
CPa. I'm just putting weight
as three, create fusion,
some issue with that model. But let's get into this.
This is like, based on reviews, we're able to see
the importance of a review or
54 instances. It shows me an error rate of 4.815
and unexpected error.
Now, this is one. Let's go
to models.
And you have associations, topic models determine
this, but let's do this.
So this is another data set where
I wanted to figure out the branching
grouping of different keywords
in those ad campaigns, where top terms,
you can see the commercial terms like this,
and you can also see the probability,
rent and topic probabilities.
Now let's go to domain.
Let me try again.
Yes, got it. So now I have
this amount of likes which generated repeat
followers. I can see the instances
of impressions and then how the overall
campaign is looking at it. Let's go
back and then now we see it instances
like video views, ad name
which are probably secured data set for me.
So we'll just see number of pair
like cpms are less than this is an average
different different averages. So this gives
me clear understanding
of how my campaigns are going. Probably third
base and we
could able to predict lot of things using this data.
So let's
play around that. Also see
video is at 50% three videos
less than 50% at two Ctrl
expected azure traffic instances
CpC cpl yeah,
that's what it is. So considering the time,
we won't be deep diving into all of these links, but I would be sharing
these links with you personally where you can play around and tweet
things. Maybe figure out a better way to
do Dhanmi.
So let's wrap it up with
challenges in this whole LLM
navigation. One I see
is adaptation of
is hard. Getting a buy in where we say
someone is using one wants to get an open source.
One will conclude on
points where hey, is it safe? Is it,
are we leaking up any data? Are we getting a third party
data or what are we training it for?
Navigating the privacy regulations in the customer trust
is key, so we need to educate people about how
privacy could be maintained. It's a narrow game, but still the
best to figure it out. If you have any questions,
drop down your questions in the comments and you can also connect
with me or LinkedIn. That's all. Thank you,