Hi everybody. I'm Dana Scheider, a senior software engineer at
Envato, and today I'm going to talk to you about software quality management
when you don't have dedicated QA staff and about what software
quality can learn from manufacturing.
I want to start off with a definition of quality.
For the purpose of this talk. Quality is the suitability of a
product for its intended purpose, aided from the perspective
of the consumer. That last part is really important.
It's the customer who ultimately decides the quality of
your product and what quality dimensions matter to them.
So the first step towards establishing
software quality in an environment without QA, or with QA
for that matter, is going to be
identifying those quality dimensions that the consumer
requires of your product. There are a few elements of software
quality or quality dimensions, including functionality,
the features that your product provides, how well they
work, performance or speed, ux,
freedom from bugs or defects, and security a
lot of the time when we talk about quality, we talk about it in a
really narrow way, focused on freedom
from defects or bugs. But in fact,
all of these elements, all of these components kind of play into
the consumer's ultimate satisfaction with your product.
And so all of choose should be considered dimensions of quality.
So in this talk, I'm going to talk to you a little bit about traditional
software QA, but I'm going to focus on total quality management
and I'll go into what TQM is in a moment.
Traditionally, when we're doing QA and software,
we do it toward the end of the process. QA is
a separate process that happens during or after the
development phase. Quality analysts or
qas don't influence product's definition or design,
so they strictly get involved later in the process.
Make sure that nothing has bugs. Make sure that
edge cases have been accounted for. Sometimes they'll
check up on security, things like that. The page still
requires HTTPs if it's a web app, that kind
of thing. But mostly they're focused on keeping things
but free and aren't involved in
defining those quality attributes that may matter to
the customer or designing the product. Quality management
in this model is focused on finding and fixing defects,
and not on overall suitability of the product for its intended
use. And that's where TQM really differs.
Additionally, qas usually have training and experience
that most developers don't. This is really
key difference as well, and it's something that needs to
be accounted for when you're moving to a model without qas,
the knowledge that qas have is essential and needs
to be imparted to your development team, if you
are going to be having them take on more of that work.
More to the point, that training and experience has to be
imparted to everyone in your organization. But I'll get
to that in a minute. So what is total quality management?
Total quality management, or TQM,
is a quality management philosophy widely
adopted in japanese engineering. It was developed
in the 1950s by management consultant William Deming,
and is largely responsible for the primacy of japanese
engineering in the manufacturing world. I developed
a quality process that was implemented at Envato and
realized subsequently that it had a lot in common with TQM,
and felt that TQM had a lot to offer. So in this
talk, I'm going to focus on TQM principles and
how we can bring more of them to our quality management and software.
TQM starts with a customer focus, and that
means asking the right questions at the very beginning of the process.
Are we building the right produces? Are we building it in
the right way? And how well does it serve the customer's
needs or wants? There's a story about the
railroads in the US. The railroads didn't do so
well as new shipping routes came
to be developed, as trucks and planes came to be used
to transport goods and people.
And an analysis of the situation reveals
that the railroads saw their business as running
trains along tracks, and that that was a
service that they were offering to their customers.
But what they didn't take into account was that what
they were actually doing for their customers was transporting
them or their goods from point a to point b,
and that prevented them from developing
the right product, developing it with the kind of flexibility that
they needed to continue to be successful as customer needs
evolved. So that's just one compelling business case for
focusing on quality in this way. Another dimension of
TQM is employee empowerment. In TQM,
everyone is responsible for quality, and everyone is
empowered to make decisions and to
make interventions on behalf of quality.
Employees can speak up when something isn't right without
fear of retaliation or repercussions.
Employees have adequate autonomy to do their jobs.
If they feel that something needs to be done differently in the interest
of quality, they should be able to do that without too much red
tape. Employees are not overworked or burned out.
People who work too much or are
grinding too hard make mistakes. And so it's
really important to, from an organizational perspective, focus on
employee well being and making sure that employees are working
the right amount, which for knowledge workers,
the data indicates, is probably under
40 hours a week. So that's really important,
too. Employees get ongoing training to improve
their skills and to develop new skills that become relevant as
the software world evolves. So those are all components
of the employee empowerment that total quality management requires,
and that good software quality management also would
entail. Fact based decision making is
another component. This is of course much
easier said than done, but it's
important to foster an organisational culture
that's built more around fact based decision making
than around political decision making. Making sure that
whoever has a good idea, that idea is adopted,
even if it's the janitor, that person has
had the best idea and that's going to serve the interests
of the organization. People need to
feel empowered to speak up against people more powerful
than them. So at Envato I know that I can
take my disagreement directly to the CEO, and the worst that's
going to happen is he'll disagree. And that's a critical
component to creating an environment where employees
are able to speak up about issues pertaining to quality
or security, or a number of other factors.
I strongly recommend baking this into your culture as
much as you can. The final key component of
TQM is continuous improvement of products
and processes, which fits in really well with agile,
focusing on an ongoing basis on whether youre
doing things in the right way. What incremental improvements
can you make to your produces so that they'll serve your customers
better? Are there any process changes that
could be made to make this happen? An example is I'm a
big fan of checklists. You need to make sure that
tests and docs are being written on every Jira
issue, while just add a checklist to your Jira card and make
it not done until that's done. Those sorts of things are the kinds of
small incremental process improvements that can make a big difference in
quality. So if you're not sold yet,
I want to go into the kind of advantages
of TQM a little more. The big advantage with
TQM is that quality management starts from the very beginning.
In this approach, you're starting with product specifications,
visual design, UI design. Your approach
to development so agile is going to be more conducive
to quality management than waterfall, for example, since it
will enable you to quickly respond to
changes in customer needs or changes in specifications.
Code quality is a component of quality management,
since again it will affect your ability to quickly add
new features to keep your code up to date and secure.
It's really important to think broadly about quality.
Quality is not about a freedom from bugs. Anything that's
done well in your organization will contribute to quality, and anything
that's done poorly, I guarantee will take away from it.
Quality management in TQM is focused on all elements of
design and development, so you're not just fixing bugs.
It also results in a produces need to release patches or make
additional changes to a released product. Since by starting
earlier in that process and getting more people involved, youll get
it right the first time more often. Quality is always
the responsibility of the entire organization. And in some ways
I think that it's better to not have a dedicated QA department
because that drives this point home. Sometimes when
you have a dedicated QA department, it's easy to say that quality
is those people's responsibility. Keep it in a silo,
throw stuff over the fence to them and everybody else can wash
their hands of it. Quality is always the responsibility of
the entire organization, and everybody in the organization
needs to be formally vested with that responsibility,
needs to have the opportunity to distinguish themselves
by producing quality work, and needs
to be held accountable for the quality of their work and for
what they contribute to the overall final product.
Some companies are going to have an easier time adopting TQM
than others. So what are the characteristics of
organizations that can adopt TQM?
It's going to be cheaper and easier for you to adopt this approach if you
have some of the components built in already. As the upshot,
one of the most important things is having the total buy in
of management. Unfortunately, as with a lot of
things that you can do to make your software development
go smoother and your product quality higher,
there's only so much you can do without total management buy in.
And remember that total management buy in, in the
case of TQM, means management accepting that they
and everyone under them is collectively and individually
responsible for quality. So it's really important
to make sure that there's that buy in and that understanding.
It's going to be easier to adopt TQM if
you recognize that quality management will always require time
and resources. TQM will
often result in cost reduction over having traditional QA.
But that comes from making higher quality work the
first time and not having to go back and fix things that
you've messed up. It's not about not
investing in quality in the first place. Youll will always
have to invest in quality. And the sooner
you accept that, the sooner you can start implementing good quality practices.
Yeah, if you already have some of the elements of TQM in place,
like for example, one of Envato's core values is
that we tell it like it is, and whether it's with each other
or with customers, we always speak up when something
isn't right and are always honest and straightforward
about problems. And that made it a lot
easier to adopt some of these components of TQM
because it relies on people individually
having that ability to speak up about issues. You'll have
an easier time if your organization has a culture of effective and
multidirectional cross functional communication.
That means that at each stage of the process, there's a collaboration happening.
It's not management dictates to design what
product needs to happen, what product needs to be developed, design dictates
to development what that product needs to look like. Development dictates
to everyone past them what the overall
design of the software is going to be, and so on and so forth.
Because that results in a total lack of empowerment for everyone
later in the process. As it happens, sometimes designers
have good input on what product needs to be developed. Sometimes developers
have good input on design. Well, you never know.
It could be any group of people. Youll just need
to have a culture where that communication
goes both ways and no one is dictating to anybody
else. You're going to also have an easier time adopting a
TQM approach if your code bases already have good automated
test covers, if you currently have a
QA department, all of that stuff is going to have to
be moved into your code bases and that's
going to be a certain amount of work. So if you
already have good automated test bases in your code base, or test coverage
in your code bases, that's going to be a lot easier.
You're going to have an easier time if management already produces
resources and creates conditions where employees at each point in
the process can do their job well. If people are
having to fight to get the tools or resources that
they need to do their jobs, that's going to have an impact on quality.
And finally, it's important that employees not be
rushed, burned out or under excessive pressure to produces
quickly. That just ends up consistently
being at odds with the fact that quality management requires resources
and employee time. People who are rushed, burned out,
or under excessive pressure tend to cut
covers and quality is usually the corner
that gets cut along with security. So what are some success
factors then, in terms of your organizational
culture? Openness and safety are critical components
to a culture of quality. Even junior engineers
should feel comfortable asking questions and critiquing their own
and others work. Someone once pointed out to me that
engineers at different levels of their careers have different strengths.
Senior engineers are great at project management
and high level problems. Mid level engineers are great
at coding, and junior engineers are great at theory
that's really stuck with me and has borne out in my experience.
And what that means is that everyone in the organization has
something unique that they're able to contribute. So making sure
that people are able to both feel comfortable asking questions
and critiquing each other's work, as well as have
their critiques listened to, is critical.
Additionally, employees need to feel safe admitting
and discussing their own weaknesses and mistakes.
Collaboration is key to quality management under TQM
and stands in opposition to competition.
Competitive environments don't do as well with this approach,
and the reason is because when you're focused on advancing
yourself and on distinguishing your work
above that of the others around you, you're not focused
on holistically doing a good job as a team to bring a quality
product to the market. Accountability is critical to
developing quality products and delivering them to happy
customers, but pressure is not the way
to affect that. It's important to
look at people's work holistically, look at the way they contribute to
the team and understand that as often as not,
when someone is failing to meet their goals
or perform as well as they could, it's often because they
don't have the right environment or resources to do their job,
or because something else such as illness is getting in the way.
And true culture of accountability understands
that and is focused on enabling and empowering
people to do their jobs well, not on pressuring them to
do so. Appropriate management involvement is critical.
Management needs to be available to provide necessary resources
to enhance product quality, create conditions where
everyone cant succeed, give employees the autonomy
to do their jobs and to make decisions about quality,
and focus on a collaborative environment
that's oriented towards results. I want to go into
a few recommended practices for Dev teams as far as
how development work plays out in an organization
that has implemented a TQM like approach to
software quality. Number one is that you need to communicate regularly
with product and design. Like I said
before, bi directional communication.
Know, maybe design gives you something that at a
certain viewport width is going to look really strange on
your UI. Developers should be able to give that feedback
and designers should take it in stride. So everyone should
be willing to take feedback from everyone else.
People need to feel safe, constructively criticizing
their own and others work. So if a developer
looks at a design and thinks hell
no, if I was a user this would not work for me. They need to
hopefully, tactfully give that feedback to the designer and say,
I think it would be better UX if users had the ability
to do this, that and the other thing again, like with QA
itself, there should be ongoing communication between product
and design with no siloing, no throwing things
over the fence. There's not a point where design is done and
development begins. Quality is the responsibility of everyone.
Using agile rituals and practices greatly
enhances quality and your ability to respond
quickly to changes in customer needs. Kickoffs are
great. They enable you as a team to decide on
an appropriate approach to each piece of development work
and involve people from other functions or teams as appropriate.
Pairing and mobbing using structured techniques and
if you're pairing remotely, using appropriate tools for remote
pairing that enable remote control of a single development
machine are also really valuable things to
improve quality. Generally, having a couple of pairs
of eyes on something is always going
to be helpful to producing a better product,
providing you do have a culture of collaboration
over competition. Retrospectives where you candidly
discuss what did or didn't go well in a particular sprint
are really important and where you're focused on
improvement rather than pointing fingers. Culture of blame
is not useful for improving quality
and that feeds into the next bullet point as well,
which is blameless post mortems where if something
goes wrong, you want to think about improvements to
process and communication, what actually was
done wrong, not who did it. Robust code review
is really important, and I can't overstate this. Code review
is the stage where you look for bugs. Code review should be conducted
by at least one qualified reviewer who did not contribute
code to the pull request. Qualified means
this person is familiar with the stack. This person
is familiar with the problem space.
If you have back end code that you're
having reviewed, you want people who know back end code
reviewing it more than your front end people. Again,
it's important for everyone to have potential input into the process,
and everyone's input is potentially valuable. So I'm not saying
to exclude reviewers that have less experience
in a particular area, but make sure
that code is reviewed by at least one person who does have extensive
experience in that area. Code reviewers should do manual
testing. They should run the code on their local machine
or in staging and try to think of edge cases that will
break it. During that review, they should be asking themselves
how and what has been tested with this, and whether
those test cases are adequate. Are there additional edge cases that
haven't been considered? It's important to keep in mind in this
process that the happy path is often not the most common one.
In one of my previous roles, I asked our head of product how
many customers went through the happy path, and he told
me 5%. So sometimes the happy path is
actually quite rare, and it's important to make sure
that your test cases are equally robust towards
the kinds of situations your customers are
actually encountering more frequently.
Security should also be a part of this code review code
reviewers should be informed about security and
a kind of rule of thumb here to take away is that
a reviewer who doesnt suggest changes is usually not thorough
enough. And I'm not talking but a one line change that updates
a third party library or something. But if it's a larger pull
request that implements a feature or fixes
a more complex but then reviewers should
be suggesting changes and it's important
to kind of as a reviewer, take it as a red flag
if you find yourself having no suggestions.
Tracking all your work will also help with software
quality. You want to create issues or Trello cards
or however it is that you track your work, you want to create one for
even small changes. Even small changes
should have adequate opportunity for review and testing.
And that's a big part of the reason why you should create issues for them
is that it's not just a oh, I'm just going to dash off this
pull request, okay, I'm going to pick up this issue and I'm going to do
a good job on it. Establish standards for pull
request descriptions and comments and I'm talking about technical
writing here. Information that should be included in
every pull request description, such as context and
links to relevant information or to the Jira
ticket or Trello card or issue report that this
is related to a summary of changes made.
A section on the considerations and reasoning what alternatives
did you consider? What alternatives did you maybe try and
not have them work out? Why didn't they work out?
What don't you like about the approach that you took and why did you take
it anyway? Those kinds of things need to go into a PR description.
And finally, there should be detailed information in each
PR description about testing and documentation,
how the code has been tested, what test cases have been
tested, and what documentation has been written
or updated as a result of these changes.
Testing post release is another really important practice.
So using the same manual testing procedures
as during code review you cant to test in production.
Ideally you want to test in a pre production environment like staging as
well. And when you test your final product,
you want to test it in as many environments as possible where it might be
run. So if this is an app that might be run
on different operating systems or hardware,
older and newer machines, web apps that could be
run in different browsers, apps that could be run on different devices
or screen sizes. You want to make sure to incorporate all of
those into your post releasing testing and as much as
possible into your pre releasing testing. I recommend
using detailed pull request templates to make sure that pull
requests include the amount of information that
they need and the type of information that they need in an organized fashion.
I've encountered some disagreement with this from certain people,
but I stand by it. I think that having a pull request
template ensures that people include the appropriate information
with each pull request that the others around them need to
understand the changes they made and review their code effectively.
PR templates need to include context,
technical changes, considerations that were
made in the process of development,
detailed information about testing what kinds of teams,
what kinds of automated teams have been used to test
this code. How can a reviewer produces a but
how can a reviewer manually test the changes? And as
far as writing this stuff out, I recommend actually
fleshed out test cases with steps 12345.
These are the steps you should go through to manually test these changes.
Click this button, fill out this form with this
data, that level of detail what
youll go wrong sometimes, no matter how
hard you try to make everything good, there's still a
certain risk that once you get stuff out in production,
something goes wrong. We can't always change
the fact that certain configuration is different in deployed
environments from development environments, or that it's different in
production from staging. So again, this is kind of
part of people being empowered to speak up when things can
go wrong and to admit their weaknesses and mistakes.
People should be comfortable talking about what
could still go wrong despite all their best efforts.
What are the security risks? I recommend calling
this one, but specifically, you also can
often benefit from screenshots or videos or gifs
that illustrate the changes that you've made.
Our PR templates always also include a note
that a PR is the start of a conversation, not the
end of one, and that's a really important thing to remember.
So these are just a few of the ways that you
can enhance quality in your organization in the absence of
a dedicated QA department. Total quality management,
which was developed for manufacturing environments, turns out to
have significant advantages in software organizations as
well, in that it approaches quality from an organizational standpoint
and makes quality the responsibility of every
person in the organization, both collectively and individually.
TQM can produces defects, improve efficiency,
and make the end product more suitable for its intended purpose.
TQM can also reduce your QA and defect
related costs, provided that you understand
that you still need to invest a certain amount of resources
and employee time in quality management.
Adopting TQM requires allocation of resources
and full management support. It. And the last takeaway
that I'd like you to get from this is that dev teams can make simple
changes to their process to improve quality and make
it an integral part of their work. Thank you.