Hi, everyone. Welcome to my talk. My name is Riaz Virani.
I'm a freelance web developer and you can read more
of my stuff at Riazv me. Today's topic, the thing
I'm going to talk about is called five tips for success. How to thrive at
your first dev job. And forgive me, this next slide
is designed obviously for a talk that's live. But I do want to
take a second and actually have you introspect a little bit
because I'm assuming that a number of you especially
are kind of from this perspective of like you actually are breaking into the industry.
You either are about to start your first job, you're either in a boot camp
looking to finish your first job or, sorry, finish the camp and get your first
job. Or maybe you're just in the throes of the challenges I'm going to talk
about in the first few months. If you're not, if you've been doing this for
a few years, this is kind of your chance to just take a second to
reset yourself and think about what your experience was like when you did join the
industry and kind of break into your first job. I want you to kind of
channel that energy because it'll help you empathize and help
other people on your team as they're joining. So I'm
going to tell you a little bit of a story. Right. It's going to kind
of guide us through this talk. So I want you to meet a friend of
mine. Her name is Ruby. She wants to be a developer.
And yes, I am a ruby developer. So that's kind of the inside
joke there. Sure, some of you don't like Ruby or rails or whatever, that's fine,
you don't have to, but our character is going to be named
Ruby. So Ruby musters up
the courage to go join a software bootcamp.
It's one of these bootcamps that is sort of fairly common. It's a huge source
of sort of developers into our industry. One of these like three to six month
things. She's a little bit nervous and anxious, as you would be
if you're leaving your job and entering something new and paying a lot
of money. Those of you might notice there is
a boot on top of the building because it's a boot camp. That's what they
did. So Ruby comes in and kills at the boot
camp, right? And some of you may have actually felt that
you struggled a bit in the boot camp, but in this case, doesn't really matter.
Our character, Ruby, did a fantastic job and
soaked in a ton of knowledge and information. She finishes the
bootcamp and she is really diligent about working all of the things
that the bootcamp and everything on the Internet is telling you about how
to get a job. She does everything in her power to get a job.
She builds a portfolio site. She's out at meetups, networking.
I guess in today's age, if you're in a place that is mostly doing virtual
work, you're networking on slack or other sort of online technology
groups. She's doing open source projects. She's doing codecadas to prepare for interviews
and she lands the job. She does an amazing job at
her interviews and she lands the job. Some of you may have again, had more
of a struggle to get to this part. And I don't want to dismiss how
much of a challenge it is to get someone to trust you when you don't
have a ton of experience to say, yes, I'll take a chance on this person
and give, give them a shot and have them join my team. It is actually
quite challenging, and a number of you probably are in that phase where you're trying
to get it. But now here comes the next question. Now what?
So the gist of this talk is not about everything
we've talked about so far. It's that a number of people, especially now
that I've been doing this for like twelve years, really struggle when
they join a team. I'm a freelance developer right now, but in my past life
I've been a CTO, I've been a project manager and run teams.
A lot of new developers have come onto my teams. It turns
out that there's a lot of commonalities
in the struggle that first year devs experience
across companies. Again, first year. I'm talking specifically about their first year in programming
in general as a professional engineer, not necessarily just their
first year at that particular company.
I'm hoping somebody can sympathize. Yeah, there's a lot of challenges that kind of occur.
I just don't think we talk about it enough. We talk so much about how
to get people jobs, we don't often talk about the things that
they need to do to succeed at those jobs when they break in. And there's
a couple of skill sets that aren't even purely technical that I found consistently help
people out. In some ways, I'm actually coming to this talk from
the perspective of actually had a lot of challenges, just like
everyone has when I'm also helping first year devs as well, because it's a really
big adjustment. And I think a lot of the failures actually come from people like
me and leadership who don't actually know how to onboard those people.
But if you're a junior dev, you can only kind of control what's in front
of you, what you can do. And these are some of the tips.
So here are the famous five tips.
Here's the meat and potatoes of this talk. I put kind of catchphrases
around them and we're going to dive into each single one as we go along.
The first one is ask and you shall receive. So the idea
there is to make sure that you are not just struggling silently like
there is a time and a place to ask for help. And knowing
when the right time is is kind of an art that sometimes senior developers
have gained over time. But a lot of junior developers,
they just don't ask enough for help when they get stuck. Secondly,
it's called right now, worry later. And that's really about not
being afraid of your code. You're going to make mistakes, you're going to write
a lot of stuff that doesn't work, and you need
to have the courage to kind of just go through that process. Three is go
deep, not wide. Specifically, this is a response to a lot
of boot camps that try to, as a marketing pharmaceutist, teach you a
lot of different things because you can kind of say, oh, I learned this.
I learned how to do iOS development and python development and front end development
and Ruby development, but it's not actually the
right way to approach it. When you're trying to enter a company
and make sure that you can contribute in a way that's productive and respectful
of your team and for your own growth. Fourth, dont put your teammates in
a pedestal. So the crux of that idea is to not assume everything
that a senior developer tells you is actually the right answer. Most of
the time, they're your peers. They're figuring it out as well. I've seen a number
of times where I might give someone an idea when they ask me for help.
Turns out it's a bad idea. And they didn't tell me when we
kind of went through it, when they worked on it for a little bit because
they were afraid to tell me I was wrong. And this just came from kind
of the culture of that company, which causes
a lot of problems because people actually need to be able to
voice their opinions freely. The final one is more of a tactical
tip. It's one of the few that's less sort of abstract. It's called pseudocode is
your friend. The idea here is when you're joining a
new company, you're starting out, you don't actually have the syntax of second nature
of whatever programming language you're in and senior developers generally do.
And so to separate out the stages of when you're programming into different phases,
that'll actually help you get through the logic and then the syntax separately.
But let's get into detail. So the very first tip,
ask and you shall receive. So we're going to go
back to our story. Ruby's going to join us along the way.
She's our friend, of course. So Ruby gets a ticket, but she's not sure how
to proceed. She's afraid she's going to do it wrong and be found out as
a fraud. What does she do? So this is the classic, like imagine
you're a brand new developer, you join a company and they're like, great, they do
some onboarding, but at some point they're going to ask you to write some code
and they give you a ticket and you're sitting there.
Some cultures, they may pair program with you and that's great, but in many they
don't. In which case you're sitting there being like, I don't know how to approach
this, or you may have an inkling of how to approach it, but you're absolutely
terrified of being found out as an imposter. And sort of impostor syndrome
in the software world is a really common thing. And that
probably should have been the title of this section.
So here's a really important
point. You cannot wait forever to ask for
help, or you cannot just throw your hands up and give up.
I've kind of seen people generally, when they're doing this
wrong, oscillate on one of the two extremes. They'll get
a ticket and every morning in a stand up they might be saying, I'm working
on this, I'm working on this. Without telling anyone. They're really struggling
and they have kind of just been thrashing around. They haven't really figured out how
to tackle it. And the other one is they at some point get so frustrated,
they come and say, I just can't do this, and they throw their hands up
in the air. And that tends to be sort of the worst outcome.
Also the fact that more time they spend on it now, the harder
it is to ask for help. And therefore, like, you'd be kind of being,
obviously, I haven't gone anywhere in three days and I've just been giving an update
that I'm just working on it. Obviously the answer is to ask for help,
but I want to kind of address a quick point. Usually whenever
I do these kinds of presentations and I've been in the audience, there's an element
in me that listens to sort of the proposal of the sort of soft
skills thing to do. And there's always a hidden part of my mind that's kind
of like, yeah, it's not that easy. And there's this sort
of like secret internal link of what the argument is that doesn't really hang up.
And the argument here is a junior developer could say, but won't
I annoy people if I ask for it? Won't I be found out as an
imposter? And there's kind of a very specific answer here,
which is you have to ask, but you have to ask intelligently. And I just
put a paragraph in here of what I would say if I was in that
circumstance, which is probably the best illustration. Right. I'm just going to read
it out loud. So let's say you're in a morning stand up. Hi, everyone.
So I'm currently working on x feature. I'm still working through the right approach for
it, but right now y seems the best. I'm going to keep at it for
today, but if I dont make good progress, I'd like to grab someone else from
the team really quickly tomorrow to talk it through and get me unstuck.
So kind of think through what happened there,
right? I didn't just go and say, I don't know how to do this,
and throw my hands up in the air and ask
for someone else to come and get involved and just sort of give me the
answer. I kind of was like, look, I do need to do some work on
this. I need to spend a little bit of time thrashing to
poke at kind of the approaches I'm thinking of. As a result,
when I do have, if I can't make any progress and I don't feel confident
with the approach, whenever I do ask for someone's time, I can be like,
okay, here is the problem. I thought this, I tried that.
I tried that. I looked this up online, it's not working.
Help me get unstuck. And I didn't also ask. Unstuck is a pretty specific
word. It's not do this for me. I can't do this. It's help me
get the next incremental bit of information that I need in order
to move forward to maybe the next part of the challenge. Right. The next part
of the ticket. And as a manager, this would be amazing to me
because I'd be sitting there going, okay, so you've identified there's a problem. You've given
me those information that right now you're actually struggling. So I'm already forewarned about that.
You've given me a timetable in which you're going to work on it yourself.
And then you've told me what your next step is going to be, which is
not to throw your hands up in the air. It's to ask for a limited
piece of help to get you to the next phase. And I'm like,
you have done my job for me as a manager. Right? You will gain so
many brownie points if you try this approach where you're being very considerate
about how much time you're drawing, but also making sure you keep progressing
and communicating versus doing one of those two extremes
of either working on it silently and thrashing or just giving
up too quickly. So next point right
now, worry later. So this is a little bit of play
on words and we'll go back to Ruby to kind of get an
example of what we mean. So Ruby does the
best she can and puts up a pr to the ticket we talked about in
the last point. The next day, it's got 20 comments
and has been sent back. She will have to start over. She's crushed.
She's not even sure if she wants those job anymore.
If you're someone, and again, if, you know, if you're more experienced, this happened to
you, right? And if you're a junior developer, it's definitely happened to you where you
think you've got it and you put it in and someone just shits all
over your code and it just really crushes you.
So I'm not going to really spend a lot of time on the point that
it's completely okay to mark up a pr, but if you recognize someone's
new and they may really be trying to get their confidence, you should probably
include a note in there being like, hey, by the way, I know this is
a lot. You still did a really good job. Let's just
work on these and we'll continue to improve.
Like, giving them that little pat on the back can be really dramatic, but let's
say you didn't get that because it's, again, as a junior developer, not within your
control. Here's my answer,
and this is somewhat controversial. When I've kind of talked about this with other people,
the thing within your control is kind of how you respond and the answer
isn't be perfect. And the answer isn't, oh, just feel good generically.
You have to kind of get an understanding of the fact that you are new.
You're going to write a lot of mediocre code as you improve.
You need to embrace it and just ask your teammates to embrace the process
as well. What I mean specifically by that
is like, interview examples. You think about classic
ways to get good at anything. You're going to be bad at it whenever you
start. If you're just starting in the industry as the first time you're really writing
code in a professional context, that means most of
the time you're not going to be doing things as well as someone else who's
doing it for five years. That doesn't mean you're bad, it just means you're
learning. Fitness is a good example.
You cannot beat yourself up. If you think of fitness when you go into the
gym and you can't do the pull up like someone else can, it just means
it's part of the process. You need to embrace the process and not necessarily be
upset that you're not meeting some standard you've set out.
So here's the sort of like, little voice in the back of your head,
right, thinks it's like, right, so I just do my job poorly, just like,
write shitty code and that's somehow okay, right?
And have everyone look me that I'm the weak link on the team.
Not really your job. This is kind of all of our jobs
as engineers is really to try. And if you're new, I know there's a whole
bunch of personal emotion mixed up in that because you're also trying to establish your
own career. But there's a very big difference between
someone who's trying their best and continuing to improve,
and people notice that. And the thing I put on here is like, shitty code
is very different from flawed code written by people trying their best. It just is.
I mean, I'm sure everyone who's been doing this for a while has noticed people
who just don't care. And if you are also consistently
showing that when someone does point out a way to make your stuff better,
that you really respond, they'll give you a lot of leeway
in the sense that you're not going to be constantly
battling people's response to you as like, oh, you're the
one who's just doing stuff, really. So don't be afraid of your code.
Like, the biggest point here is don't be afraid. Whatever it is, just keep
going, just keep going, just keep going, you'll get there.
All right, point number three, go deep, not wide.
So as I mentioned earlier, this is really a response to
how sometimes I've noticed boot camps teaching way too many things or people on
their own because there's such a plethora of things you need to do to
learn DevOps to front end, to backend to whatever in the world of web
development, they just spread themselves too wide at the start.
So let's go back to Ruby continued.
Ruby loves learning. At her boot camp they taught her seven programming languages and frameworks.
She feels overwhelmed with where to focus on her new job. It all seems too
advanced compared to her boot camp.
I think what kind of happens here, this is really what happens.
Boot camps and those tech zeitgeist if you're trying to beat up on the
news, especially in the JavaScript world, there's a little bit of
an excessive obsession with the new and excessive variety and
it's kind of your job not to get sucked into it. Not because learning
new things is bad, but most junior
developers don't fail because they dont know enough of a diversity of things. It's because
they don't know any one thing sufficiently well to be productive on
the team. So they're
kind of like master of none. And that's kind of where you want to get
in the long run. But in the immediate term when you're just new, you want
to be able to get really good at one thing,
and sort of voice in those back of your head is like, well, if I
do that, I'll never really be a fully routed developer. The answer is
not exactly focus is important when
you start, you get really good at things when you focus on them,
and so you focus on one specific technology that your team needs help with and
then specific expertise will give you the credibility and the
ability over time to be productive. Like you'll learn the rest.
And what I mean by that is like hey, you're a junior developer, they know
that you're going to need additional time, additional support, but let's say you
have a good example is like there's a lot of developers that are more backend
heavy and then I'm thinking from a rails perspective, right, because rails is
backend heavy and then they'll learn JavaScript in
the front end really just because they have to to deliver
their application. But usually they're not design experts,
right? Most back end developers dont really like CSS,
so they've kind of hacked things together or maybe just used
bootstrap or sort of a theme and they really
struggle with that. Well, it turns out maybe you specifically
like CSS and you like design and you like learning about that stuff
even though you want to learn everything else. Focus in that area. Talk with your
manager, be like, hey, what if I focused here? I really cleaned up our css.
Well, now your manager has this sort of foundation so
that when you're interacting with the team, you have a locus of expertise
and credibility. You can be productive and contribute. And now you've got
all this time, all those other stuff that goes on in that team is going
to get absorbed into your head right, over time. Because you're probably going to go
from CSS to more and more into front end stuff, right? Because you're
going to be executing features and then from there you'll expand more and more
to the back end and then more and more to the DevOps, right. It'll always
be that there's another challenge you can focus on. But if
you're always in training and not really able to contribute to the team, that's going
to cause them to have a much difficult or
different opinion on of you. Because if you solve the CSS problem and
then you ask for help, well, now it's like, no, this person was awesome.
They did a great job on that. It is worth my time to try to
teach them and help them. So that's a
really good thing to keep in mind. So next point, don't put
your teammates on a pedestal. We talked earlier about the fact
that senior developers are not magicians.
Right. Software engineering is an art. So it's
a very different perspective than maybe some other things that have these very precise inputs
and outputs. So don't assume they always know what they mean
or that they've communicated it clearly, or that they wouldn't try the idea they gave
you and then realize, oh, it sucks, and try something else. Right.
So let's go back to Ruby. A senior developer
gives Ruby some guidance on the ticket, but it's not working. What does she
do? She doesn't want to disrespect the senior developer by doing it her.
Hmm. So what do you do?
I think here it's kind of related to the first point and it's really about
communication. But you do have to have some courage to realize
that you cannot force a square peg into a round
hole. And your job, like your responsibility to the team,
is not necessarily to not say, I don't know if this is the right approach.
I'm trying this and it's causing a lot of friction. It's your job to
voice the pain and friction that you're noticing.
That is actually the most important thing you can do.
Oftentimes what will happen is it turns out like whatever you're noticing,
if you actually point it out, the senior developer is going to be like,
yeah, actually, now that I look at it, it doesn't exactly work the way I
think. Or the other most common one is, no,
you misinterpreted what I said because developers are pretty bad at saying,
like, speaking code. I actually kind of mean this. And you're like,
okay, that makes a lot more sense. Now, here's something that's really important.
The longer you wait to do this, like you say, you take the approach,
you start working on it for a day, it's like clearly there's something off.
You wait two or three more days to bring that up.
Now you've got a little bit of a politics problem because let's say there's a
manager who's given that senior developer the assignment to guide
you through this ticket. If you wait really long and then
those becomes a problem, that senior developer now has to cover their ass
because they have to make the points like, no, you're doing it wrong. It wasn't
that I didn't notice that you were trying the wrong approach
for several days. Right. So the earlier you can communicate,
the better benefit you're going to have. And that's why again, the answer here
is communication. Your job is to communicate about the code
across your team. And the final point, again, senior developers are
not God, they're your peers. Tell the senior developer what
you found and ask for clarification. Half the time it turns out their approach was
wrong and they'll admit it. Right?
So pseudocode is your friend.
This is the final point. Now, this is a bit different than the other ones
because it's really a tactical point versus a sort of like philosophical
point, but it's something I've noticed a lot. So,
Ruby, go back to Ruby. This is our finale with Ruby. We're going
to say goodbye to her in a second. She's starting to feel comfortable, but she's
still writing code slower than other devs and team. How can she be more
efficient? So here's
this kind of really unusual point. I haven't heard a lot of people talk about
it. Write your pseudocode in comments and pseudocode. If those of you
who don't know what it is, pseudocode is basically where you write literally words
describing your code, it's almost like someone had to translate the logic you're
putting in your code as sentences, like the way you would talk
about the code if you had to explain it in words. So it
could be literally what you're seeing on the screen, your pseudocode.
So if you write that first because you're thinking through
the business logic, then be like, okay, I think that makes sense.
Now just translate it into the syntax of whatever programming language you're in. You're kind
of separating those two threads. And the reason this is effective is
if you're new, it's very likely that the programming
language syntax is not second nature to you. I don't really think
about syntax much at this point. Personally. Whenever I'm writing Ruby or
Javascript, like the languages that I'm most familiar with, I'm really thinking about the
logic. But if you're new, you're actually spending a lot of those extra cycles being
like, oh wait, where does the closing parentheses go?
That kind of thing. So if you can separate those tasks out, it'll actually make
you more productive because it becomes two
simpler tasks instead of one more complex task.
So the point here is, syntax sucks. Senior devs
have been writing code for so long, the syntax of code is second nature
to them. If you're not there yet, separate the process of thinking about the logic
and writing the syntax of the programming language as separate,
and that's it. That is the presentation.
For those of you that don't know, gravity exists on earth.
I love Neil degrasse Tyson.
And yeah, just going back to my contact information mission, if you
really are interested in some of the stuff I have to say,
there's other talks and podcasts and other things that I put online,
things, some of the things I've written. You can find it all at Riazv,
me and I occasionally, but not very often, will tweet.
Riaz. Virani. Riaz, thank you for joining me and enjoy
your conference.