Ain't no ev one. Welcome to our AI
and disability in asian or in asian.
Dhanan and I are delighted to welcome you
and talk to you about a subject that
is close to our hearts.
We end the scrap transcript.
We give you the link during the live session.
My name is Emanuela Bois and I am happy
to represent this to Wisdan.
I was born deaf with two year implants.
I like to say that I am muni.
I have been a developer since twelve years
and I work at Schuddho in Paris.
Schudo is an IT services company specialized
in development engine and offense an
amity to social justice for
writer in asian intake.
I am very committed to digital accessibility.
I am not an expert in AI, but I use
automated tools on a daily basis
which allow me to analyze
the impact of AI on my daily life.
I am a member of the Duchess France association
which represents women in deaf interests.
I am also a member of the CNCF
Deaf and Hard of hearing initiative
which represents deaf and hard of hearing
people around the world.
Hello, my name is Tanlin Dobrye. I'm very proud to
co present this talk with Emmanuel. I am a
machine learning engineer formerly with Axafrance and
I am volunteer for several french ngo's related to
data, science and technology like data for
good and latitude. As a conference speaker I cover
topics as artificial intelligence including
its legal framework, hemlocks and inclusion.
I am a part of the organizing team of
a conference named Crewneur
which take place in Lille in the north of France.
Additionally, I am a part of the collective of women developer
named Chisdev. Due to a medical
condition affecting various parts of my body,
I am an umbilatory Wilshire user here. I became deaf when
I was a teenager. The media
and science fiction have given a
very highly distorted image of artificial intelligence.
I believe that if you follow the Conf 42
conferences you are already quite familiar with
the reality, but we prefer to provide a brief
theory recap for
explain what is artificial intelligence.
I like to use the example of baking your cake for a cookbook.
Imagine you follow a recipe. This recipe represents your
classic software starting with the ingredient.
It is your input. You execute several instructions and
in the end you have the perfect strawberry pie look like
the one in photo from your recipe book.
But an application with artificial intelligence
work a little different will still
start from your recipe book, but in your pastry you
don't no longer have strawberries, instead you
have apple. Unfortunately in your cookbook doesn't have
any apple pie recipe otherwise full of
other fridge pie recipe P.
Plum so you rely on
the various recipes to try to make your perfect apple pie.
An AI application is based on mathematics, particularly statistics
and probabilities. But the reasoning is the same.
We proven with the data where hold the
pre pie recipe from the recipe book and
you research what is the most likely.
It's the most likely that the recipe anchored sugar,
butter, flour, swandon in whole
recipe of pie rather than
finding some pickles.
Ethics is related to morality and subjectivity.
Just because it's legal doesn't mean it's ethical.
As developer and solution designer, we have a moral responsibility towards
your user. It's not because your country
doesn't legislate against discriminating against minority,
specifically those with disability, that it means
it's ethically correct. Law take time
to be created and modified and often
adding with morality on a given society or where
it means to be appliqu what
is legal in one country is not necessarily moral
for a two citizen of another country. Artificial intelligence
is highly sensitive to the cultural environment in
which its model well create. For example,
the use of AI in video surveillance is ideally unply
in certain countries, but probably by the law and heavily
regulated in other there existing regulation
around AI and more are the origin.
There are AI acts in the European Union,
but some disposition of the GDPR
general data protection regulation
already have an impact on the high integrated
application we have previously. That data is
the foundation of all AI application.
Let me give you an upper view of disability.
Didn't you know that 1 billion
people in the world are disciplined?
Is this estimated that about 15%
of the world population has a disability?
This fear is very difficult to estimate for
several reasons. A person may not
have their disability or doesn't know
they have a disability. A disability can
occur during one's life and be in
diagnostic can be an honest whole host
to have one's disability designed
contrary to popular belief, disability is
not just a problem for people with
wheelchairs. A disability is often
not very visible. Did you know that
80% of disabilities are
not immediately visible.
Nevertheless, we have a fast check on
this error. It is often said that 50%
of disabilities are invisible. We don't
really know the exact rails.
What is certain is that the majority of disabilities
are invisible. We are to eat
to you, but before you address us,
you did not know where deaf
our deafness are invisible as we
are live. You aren't yes that my
partner death is in a welsh air.
According to the source inference, they are
five men families of disabilities.
We see all disabilities socially impairment
antimicrobial disabilities, mental disabilities,
disability diseases such as endometriosis,
ulcer or childhood disease, for example.
There are disabling diseases that can be
disabling on a daily basis. In the short or
medium term, we can have mutine
disabilities around you.
You probably know someone who is
affected by disabilities. Maybe you are
concern yourself in the course of his life.
We are not immune to being effective by
a disability which I do not wish on you,
of course. Thank you, Emmanuel,
for your reminder. Now we have some
theoretical knowledge and a little fact
about disabilities. We can move to the practical example
if we will generate some image of people with disabilities
for using advertising. For example,
we need data and we need to choose
to scrap image on Google image because we don't have
any database. With lots of images of people with disabilities
in your companies, they are the first result
on the Google image. In this little video,
when you search people
with disabilities on Google image, you see
lots of Welshare. And before
Emmanuel said that the majority
of disabilities are invisible
and it's a big problem to the one
representation of disabilities is
the Welshare. This representation is okay
for me because I have disabilities and I am a Welshare user.
But in France and in many western countries,
we used to see this Welshare logo for people with disabilities.
It's the same in the greater Gerwig's Barbie
movies. We have a protagonist in a pic welsh air.
The film is very nice, I like it a lot.
But for a film seen as an ode of diversities,
disability was reduced as a single character
in the wheelchair with no dialogues. This vision of
the disabilities, summed up just by the
wheelchair, is a cognitive b's. It seems
logical for us, but it's wrong.
And this has two negative impacts.
It going to be is
going to be seen as the definition
of disability. If I'm not in my wheelchair,
that doesn't mean I'm not younger disabled or
that I have been cured. And the second negative
impact of that is it will exclude people
or erase certain disabilities. For example,
if the only criterion is the use of a wheelchair,
it excludes many people like Emmanuel, who are still living
with disabilities. And if
we create your model based on the Google image or
another B's dataset, we have this
result. This is some image generated with Microsoft designer.
How this image represents a caucasian woman,
no racism, people, no man and hole in
a wheelchair. When Whacker users are a minority
of people with disabilities.
Jeremy Andrew Davies his audeste and
tested the generation of odyssey people with
you can see it through this video on a
sample of her entering image that
all these images look the same.
The AI she person in
Omani, sad, depressed,
always has the same weird faces in
their diversity. Is she a
white man for AI? Honesty people,
I look the same way. Is it not the
reality? Why does an
person have to be sad and depreciate
that? Doesn't a disabling person have the right
to feel good about themselves, to be happy?
It can be very that artificial intentions
for this part we need you imagine
that we are in the team developing an AI project
and we will focus on the moment when you create
some difficulties for people with disability. The first
step in whole data science project is
taking what is the need? It's a brainstorming
according to your problem. For example,
you need to choose some metric to evaluate the
different models and for monitoring
the model when he was in production.
For example, in disease detection we will use it
less serious to have a false positive positive than a false negative
and potentially miss a patient. In the case
of the false positive, the doctor can always check
the test manually or perform another analyze before
treating the patient on another end.
For a target commercial offer, false negative
may become less serious. If Mister
Hicks didn't specifically receive the
mail about the sale on
the Welshare. This is a little impact.
The second step is exploratory
data analysis. It's Eda.
It's a very important phase in all data
science projects. As we seen
before, whole project
in data science was based on data. In this
phase we analyze the data at your disposal,
their quantity and the quality.
For example,
there are many missing value since the data science
is relied to statistics and probability. We handle
data with extremely apparent value because
they introduce some noises into your model and make
it less performance. If you
see all this car like a
human, because a car is
like a human or person is human,
but all people is different.
Now you see, this is
your data set and this is not just some people
random. It just holds a software
engineer in the typical it company. In the
most of countries the majority of software
engineers are main. However, where if we were a
part of the data set of the software engineer Emmanuelle and
I would be considered as a hot liar.
Not only because we are a woman,
but we also have disabilities,
we don't fit with a typical profile and we
wouldn't want to be completely erased from the tech
industry because your profile is different diversity
measure. It can be a very bad
impact in some projects like
the project relative to the recruitment.
The first. The next part is to
training and select and training the model. It's like
you create a prototype eventually
before breeding a real cow. The goal is to find
the best model with the best results. The height
test score on the metric will determine on the initial
stage a common mistake would be rely this
results to claim your model is performing well.
For example, you can have a little bias
if you use a dataset related to the American Sign language.
You have a validation data
set and test data set.
You have a very good result on this validation
and test data set. But when you put
your model in production you have a very bad
feedback from the user because you
put your model in production. In France and people
doesn't use the American Sign language.
In French we use the french sign language and
it is a big problem because we
have a very unadapted tools in
this project. We have the the common
challenge for whole software maintainability, scalability,
response time. Additionally, you need to monitor performance
and retain the model when the decrease in performance.
This is a discussion about drift and
when you retrain your model, it's like when
you make a little revision
of your car. You need
to remake
an exploratory phase of the data collected
in production. Soft models can be negatively
influenced by their interaction with user. For example,
some models that become more biased like
the model will become more racist or
validists. Yeah,
it's because AI is based
on statistics and probability and it's
same for me. Journey it's not
probable that a woman can be a software
engineer or can be a developer who can be deaf
and be a woman and to
be a developer. It's more
probable for me, Johnny, that we are an
operator. We are definitely not an
operator. Yes, personally I don't use an
aid set. Wait. Well, not anymore.
When I listen to music or when I make for all
my oh yeah, in the plant have bluetooth, then we say nd
airports. This means that I am listening
to music that is neither seen nor know.
I am going to talk to you about innovations
that are having an impact the daily
lives of disabled people. Let's start with
automatic options and transcription. This is one
of the most well known tools.
I'm assuming this year we are seeing
more and more and more automated emission and
transcription in video and video platform.
Automated emotion is used
in everyday life, available in
native language and used for
machine translation. Easy to
use is it? Because easy to
write automatic emission into the tools as
we really rely on it fully.
When you are in the video conference or
when you are watching a live video, there are often
automation errors. We have
to deal with it by using Monton when replacement
sees, we ended up to tell
the AI that is made a mistake.
Thus we are forced
to read leaves when the image is wood,
listen when we have a wind heads
and analyze the context. When there are automatic
emissions, it is so
so exhausting. When the video is
not live and the video is uploaded to video platforms
such as YouTube, for example, there are automatic emissions
unassailed automated emotions are not yet 100%
reliable and therefore rarely remain
in it duration to avoid errors.
Don't insist to use automatic emission
to rate emission because they do
all the work of sizes.
So for them to check that they are all
right if not all right.
If by orienting you are
showing the AI that is main mistake and
we know that she learns from her mistakes.
I am a tool in French on automated emissions
and various web. If you are interested,
I need you to watch it to better understand the emission.
Seeing AII is an application developed by Mikrosoft
that automatic and he describes the environment
around us among other things
around to you. Bring this around as
soon as is in parents in front
of the camera scan and ringing
around be to ember alts and then
analyze them to undefined products to
unite the people around you and they prefer the
emissions. This frame seems under a nice
image unidentified as
m era or be my eyes.
Is it an app that connect brand and version is achieved
before with volunteer volunteer
provides visual instance to blind and
mature in parent users via video rule
with the arrival of CPT and recently CPT
Four o b by has creating
a new virtual volunteer
tools Al would be able to analyze
the context and heal the elsewhere just like
the human volunteer would wachand
and the brand and persian person
blendy trusts AI.
It raises an anti all and moral region.
If the AI makes a mistake, it can
have more or less serious consequences.
There are plenty of innovation in progress
in beta that can be useful.
There are tremendous opportunities to improve the lives of
disabled people like seniors.
AI offer automated American Sign
resource generation and video text
and audios. In France we have alias
and with french sign language
in my French to
help people when Suan
refrains op ed.
Otih release ambient noises in hearing
hands as there are transform tests for
the sin people under AI
voices that unwise the memories specify
range test allowed. Some motor is
used to emulate using images
and symbols. Cesar enables smartphone
and tablet two into hand free
device while maps make in
20 easier by providing detailing
in geo instruction mit detect full
and in real time and alert emergency
services and in the smart
end that detects unchill and helps
blind people to find their way around.
There are a lot ton of possibility and
it's very exciting. Exciting.
In addition to the biases that are
present in Ayi Afrocini,
there have been traumas with aye aye
a person tracing about global warming.
So his maintain as
is overseas with Elisa and
of indeed he's finished with her.
This person has found in the Ayi and
has for help that Aza is devoid of feelings
of obesity. So one day the
person said, I want to die. Do you
think I should? Is there a pain?
I would like to see you dead.
The person omitted suicide as a result
of this, the startup that breed ESa puts
off errors in place to prevent it
from happening again. When there
are obvious signs of suicide, of depression,
there are numbers available.
Our bacs have a strong impact and
ends up tie have a dramatic impact on disability people.
That's why it's important to work with
disabling people to prevent this from happening
again. Let me remind you.
And we turn to end them. Artificial intentions
is a tool. For example, sound positive.
I have used this system and I have so many
false positives that I end up not
using it anymore. And at the home
and doorbell ringing when there no
one behind my door, I have so many
alerts telling me I didn't know
what and what was not. So I
turned it off. Term and
context then don't mean anything. I said
he learned with automatization and I
said, mistakes exist and must
be arrested. Tim Hoon once gave
a speech at Yellow Day University,
a university for deaf and hard.
Of every student saying aye
is ood but is not the wood.
This means that we are not reliably on
it and we still need
human attention to correct errors about
mistake. This picture is a little robot. In Estonia they
deliver your parcel like food.
It's something that works quite quiet well in the country where
it's deployed. During your research, you see projects to develop
autonomous whale share a bite like this robot.
But when I see this photo, I can only be worried.
The same goes for the plight people with electronic
blind white skin.
This mistake can have serious consequences even
more for disabled people than if you just
deliver. You are delivering a burger
like Emmanuel. I test and abundant sound recognization
because it wasn't reliable enough.
And projects sometimes are too expensive for
disabled people, even if they are technologically interesting,
are also little interest.
You need as often different from that uninvolved
people can imagine by
example, translating a sign language
like a french sign language or American
Sign Language is very different from the image of
lots of people of it. Deaf people seen
very quickly. Body posture and facial expression are
very important for the comprehension.
What's more, this won't make the content accessible
for all deaf people. I'm deaf and I don't
use any sign language can
improve website accessibility,
but you can use automating testing to detect accessibility
issues. I have already asked HGBT
to incorporate accessibility into the hood.
It did not work very well and also
no overlap. Tools can make the website accessible.
The only way to make a website accessible to everyone is
to get your hand on the hold.
AI has already changed our lives.
Every day I use
automatic emissions, even if it's not
perfect. I use an automatic tools
to translate my content or reformulate
it. Terrific because my sentence is
not very old. I am sure sorry that the
AI doesn't understand me very
well because of my deaf voices.
But progress is being made. And for
you Dandan, I'm deaf since 20
years ago now and thought
with AI changed my life. Like with
reducing ambience on my hair ring. AIDS is more comfortable
and tools like for detection means
I'm safe when I'm alone at home.
When I was a teenager I cannot imagine all
the things I can be able
to do. Like we
can have chatting with people by
phone and have a transcription automatic.
We can prepare these conferences by distance. With Emmanuel
we have both dev and it's
amazing to make this one by
distance just with tools.
With AI 20 years
ago he was impossible for two
deaf people to prepare something by distance
just with webcam and automatic
subtitles. When I was a teenager I
don't all the things is possible.
I never truly had like to do so much
on my home and tools like for detection.
I mean, I'm safe when I'm alone at home.
Now I can have some discussion
by phone with transcription automatic. It's so
nothing about us without us is a mantra from
USA. It is important to design tools
with disabling people to hire together so
as not to bias is we need
to evaluate with disabled people to reduce risk
and bias and to communicate with
them to build useful tools and make
them effective. Better yet,
we need to hire disabled people in
the tech industry to do this. Of course
they need to be trained and therefore made accessible
to them. We end where
you project army in an impact in the lives
of these.
Today we are talking about disabilities,
but where some we
are someone else to other people. It's important
that more diversity in tech to combat
bias in the design of model and products.
Diversity is not just disabilities, but also
by gender, ethnicity and religions. Your users are
varied, so it's important that the diversity exists.
Two in your team. Thank you so much
for listening to us. You to
find our presentation transcript and resources.
Thank you so much.