Hello everyone. Today, we are diving into a fascinated
the impact of artificial intelligence on creative
thinking in design. We will explore how AI
and human creativity intersect and how they are
shaping our future. AI is having a deep
impact on the evolution of design, shaping innovations,
and transforming creative workflows worldwide.
Before we begin, maybe we should define some
creativity. I guess it's the ability to
think outside the box, to come up with new ideas,
and to solve problems in innovative ways.
Also making connections between
unrelated things and also producing something original
or innovative. Take risks and
embrace failure. It's a fundamental aspect of creativity.
Now let's talk about how AI and humans
differ in creativity. AI and artificial
intelligence can be creative by using data and
algorithms, but it lacks human emotional emotions
and experiences. Human creativity
comes from feelings, thoughts, and culture
make it more complex and unique.
While AI can produce innovative solutions,
it may lack the depth and intuition that
humans bring to creative tasks.
Human creativity often involves
personal connection, sympathy, and, for example,
understanding, which is harder for AI to
replicate. As a result,
while AI can excel in certain areas,
human creativity remains essential for many
aspects of life and work.
The best practice is to combine AI and
human creativity. So let's talk about it.
AI helps us understand data,
and people bring feelings and instincts.
Making new ideas better, working together combines
their capabilities, making amazing solutions.
We will see this in many areas, from design
to healthcare. Using AI as a
tool, not a replacement for people help us
move forward and make better things together.
The key is mixing technology with human
cleverness for a better tomorrow,
let's talk about how we can use
both artificial intelligence and human creativity
effectively together. In design,
there are some tools and methods that can make
our work easier and help us be better at our creative tasks.
The first one is Uizert. Uizur scans
your sketches and automatically transforms them into
editable prototypes. This service uses
machine learning machine vision to
turn sketches into digital screens
and components. If you enjoy starting interface work
by sketching it out on a paper, this tool
is definitely for you. With midjourney,
you can create high quality images from simple text prompts
for free. Just enter text description of the image
and get the result in a few seconds. This is very,
very easy. No special hardware or software
is required to use mijourney as it runs directly in
the browser of your computer or phone.
Dali two is an advanced version of the artificial
intelligence model developed by OpenAI,
capable of generating images based on textual
descriptions. It's an evolution of the original
daily model, which was introduced in early 2021.
Utilizes deep learning technologies to create
unique and creative images that match
the given text. Visual electric is the first
image generator designed for creatives,
and it's like a canvas that facilitates the flow
of ideas so you just can truly spread out and see
where the tool takes you. It's like, you know Figma.
It's designed to help give form
to the vision in your mind's eye,
or also lead you to something even better.
Adobe Firefly is a standalone web application.
It offers new ways to create and communicate while
significantly improving creative workflows using generative AI.
It's designed to be safe for commercial use.
The next one is magician. Magician is
magical design tool for Figma powered by AI
design with the power of AI to do everything from copywriting to
generating unique icons from text. I have
included only a few tools in this presentation that
will help you create professionals expand their creative potential.
To discover even more tools for enhancing creativity,
visit tools design all
right, what do you think about can AI
truly replicate the unique creativity and intuition?
Or creative, creative professionals?
While technology advanced rapidly, the essence
of creativity remains a complex human trait. AI may
enhance but cannot fully replace the creative spark
that defines our imagination and innovation.
Let's explore that AI learned by
studying what already exists. It get
smarter by using data from the past.
But when it comes to creating new stuff, AI isn't
as good. To be honest, it's like having a really big book
of answers, but it doesn't know how to write a new story.
While it's great at learning from what's been done before,
it's so good. It's not so good at making something
totally fresh. AI is mainly a tool at
that moment, assisting with tasks, but not
yet fully creative or independent. He's like a
reliable assistant, but still needs human
guidance for innovation and originality.
AI hasn't taken over from creative
experts, not quite yet, but anyway,
while it's great at some tasks, like data analysis or
repetitive work, it lacks the human touch needed for
true creativity of a helpful assistant,
leaving the creative decisions to humans.
For example, AI can assist graphic designers by
automating repetitive tasks like resizing images
or generating basic layout, saving them
valuable time to focus on their artistic aspects of their
work. AI raises ethical concerns.
Will it replace human intuition and design? How ethical
will AI algorithm be?
Can they avoid violating morality and laws?
These questions are crucial as AI becomes
more prevalent in various fields.
Let's answer on these questions below may
streamline processes, but losing the human
touch and design in a concern. Humans bring
intuition and emotional understanding to the
table elements that AI struggles to replicate.
By the way, while AI can assist in tasks like
generating designs or layouts. It may lack the deeper understanding
of human emotions, and maintaining
a balance between AI efficiency and human creativity
is essential to preserve
the integrity of design.
Also, AI might not always know
what is right or wrong. They can do what they
are told, but they don't have human feelings
about what is fair or not. It's really important
to make sure they don't do the right thing and follow the
law. But because AI can make its
own decisions, some people worry
it might do something wrong. We need strong rules and
ways to check on AI to stop it from doing things it
shouldn't. We have to keep an eye on AI
all the time and make changes when needed to
make sure it keeps doing the right thing.
Using artificial intelligence indesign opens up
new horizons for shaping the future.
Because AI aids designers in creating innovative and
functional products, ensuring unique and creative solutions.
From like, for example, automating routine
tasks to generating unique design concepts,
AI accelerates the development processes
and enhances efficiency, thereby offering
new opportunities for designers in shaping the future.
Visual landscape machine learning
algorithms can analyze vast
data sets and design trends, user preferences,
and also historical data to identify patterns
and insights. This data driving approach
enables designers to make informed decisions,
predict trends, and tailor designs to meet specific
user needs. Also, machine learning can
help designers with repetitive design tasks.
This gives designers more time to think of
new and cool ideas for their work. In the
end, machine learning makes designers faster and better,
bringing in new ideas and making designers
designs that are more about what users want.
How do you put into practice everything we
have talked about before? For instance, there is
a great example from APG company AI
in their work and saved money and designers resources.
APG stands for independence pet
Group. It's well known companies that provides pet insurance.
They saved 90% of designers work hours,
saved about 50
$20,000 and generated over
750 high quality images. Their goal
was to create a cheerful style of illustrations for
internal communications and enrich their company's
internal culture. They developed 750
such images featuring cute household pets
using AI. Just take a look at how great
they look. It's really amazing. They used
the generated images for internal products and
merchandise. For instance, here is an example of
a coffee coaster featuring these
illustrations. The entire campaign was
produced by a single creative team of illustrations,
designers and copywriters, showing how powerful
AI can be in the hands of talented humans.
When we mix AI with human creativity,
we keep the feelings and understanding
that humans bring that also more
humans. Not one. Only AI brings new ideas,
but it's even better when humans add
their thoughts by putting them together carefully.
Human thinking stays
really important in design, making sure we still get what
feels right. AI doesn't take over
from creative people just yet, showing that human
creativity still really matters. Thank you so much for
listening to my presentation. I hope you found it inspiring and
discovered useful ideas that will allow you
to use the power of AI and your creative
potential.