You. Hello and welcome to ten
ways to doom your DevOps. My name is Sheen Godimer. I'm a DevOps
engineer with a government contractor called praeses,
and I've been through a lot of DevOps transformations.
Almost every organization has managed to sabotage their
own transformation or get in their own way. So the transformation
is virtually guaranteed to fail. Here are ten policy
that I run into time and time again that doom a DevOps effort
from the get go. Number one,
slow onboarding. It takes days or weeks
or months for a new team member to contribute meaningfully to
the team. The problem with this is it makes them feel like
they're a burden or it bores them, or it sets an
expectation of pace that's really slow and they don't ever get really
engaged and want to work faster and be
truly engaged to contribute to the team. Most importantly,
it shows them how important we consider them, which is to say, not at all,
because we did nothing to prepare for them. Arriving on the team,
have a laptop or a workstation ready, install the necessary
tools, grant the necessary permissions, and then
be prepared to pair or mob or ensemble code or work
with them so that they really learn your process and your system
and practice it ahead of time because they may not be used to it.
Your team should have that as part of the culture so that they can onboard
people quickly. The next doom is using the cloud.
Not the regular cloud, but a pretend cloud. We run our data center
in the cloud instead of leveraging the cloud. Well,
that ignores the advantages of the cloud. So there are no advantages of the
cloud. There are five essential characteristics of cloud
computing as defined by NIST, but the one I see missing most often is
self service. If you put your cloud resources
behind a long request process or a complex ticketing and
approval process, you aren't using the cloud.
Then executives get frustrated because the cloud was supposed to make things faster
and more flexible, but the organization is actively
preventing that from happening by not actually using the
cloud the way it was supposed to be. Similarly,
doing agile instead of actually being agile,
our organization has standardized the way teams will be agile, and there's no
flexibility to change. Well, if you have a
top down, mandated, unified process, you aren't doing agile.
Agile is driven by self organizing teams.
But you say we have a stand up for an hour every day.
Exactly what we're talking about. Agile is supposed to encourage agility,
right? And it's based on a couple of things, but one of the really strong
pieces is remembering that
it's individuals and interactions over processes and tools and responding
to change over following a plan. And you can't have those if you're not a
self organizing team. A great sign that you aren't agile
is that you require status meetings and status reports and then
status roll ups and then monthly summaries of all of those because
there's too many status reports to really pay attention, to have your stakeholders
join the standups, or at least the reviews, and that way they see
what's actually going on and your team can actually get to agile.
Doom number four, the change control board or change advisory
board or review, whatever you call it. Every production
change must be approved by a group that has no idea what we do.
First off, you can't release multiple times a day if it needs approval from
a group that meets multiple times a month. Right?
Besides, what value are they adding
in Devsecops? The process has reviews by the team and
quality tools and quality gates all along the way so that our
DevOps process itself manages risk, not some disinterested
and uninformed group. The Dora report has shown us that ccbs
increase risk, not reduce it. So show
the rest of the organization that you have a process
that you are disciplined in following, that you do pull request
approvals, that you have quality gates, that you follow the principle of least privilege.
And if there's a real question about what's
being pushed out when, show them that you're using infrastructure as
code and immutable infrastructure, so there's always really
clear what's being pushed out to production, then you
don't need the team or a board there to restrict
what you're doing and how you're doing it. Next, being afraid
to fail a failed experiment means we'll have a lot of explaining to do to
management. Well, real Rogers has said good judgment
comes from experience, and a lot of that comes from bad judgment.
No failure means no learning. We're not going to get different results
if we don't change what we're doing or how we're doing it. You need to
work to the point where you're aggressively and
ruthlessly protecting psychological safety and you're striving for
a generative culture where learning, experimentation is just
part of the way you work doesn't mean you just open up to the
wild, wild west and anybody can do whatever they feel like. You can try to
constrain the blast radius of any experiment you do. Make sure it only
affects a small piece so that there's not much damage done. You don't lose a
lot of time or a lot of goodwill. And be
loud and public about learning from your experiments, both the good ones and
the bad ones. Let other teams learn from your mistakes,
and let other teams benefit from the things that you've shown that have worked.
Plus, it lets the organization understand that you're
getting to a different type of culture, a generative culture,
where you protect psychological safety. Speaking of which,
the unchanging culture will do anything it takes to get to DevOps.
But we aren't allowed to change our culture. Well, bad news for
you. DevsecOps is a culture, not a set
of tools or practices. Right? And this has to be something that
changes beyond just the team. It can't just be our
team changes the culture, but the culture outside is terrible
or restrictive or it doesn't like what we're doing because
you're not going to get the benefits of DevOps if we restrict all
the changes to only within the team. Now, you're not going to change the entire
organization's culture at once, but maybe you can make some inroads and prepare
the way and let them see that there are ways for the
organizations to start changing because the DevOps team is showing
them how it's working. If you don't manage your culture,
your culture will manage you. Evangelize to other
teams, make them want what our team has, show them how things are working,
how things are going well, and maybe most importantly,
find a champion, someone who's going to keep us from getting into trouble for doing
things differently. They're going to help evangelize our
culture. They're going to help show the rest of the organization how our
culture is changing and how DevOps is helping similarly
unchanging policies. We'll do anything it takes to get to DevOps, but we aren't allowed
to change our policies. Well, existing policies are often
designed around infrequent changes. Monthly,
quarterly, annually, whatever it is. Right.
And again, this needs to happen outside the team. We can't set
policies just within the team and then have to deal with the
rest of the organization's policies. When, as soon as we step out and have to
deal with something that's not completely self contained, we're not going to get the benefits
of DevOps. If we restrict change to only within the team, we're going to
have to start making inroads to the rest of the organization. If there are policies
that are standing in your way and you can't just ignore them, find out
why that policy exists. Use automation in our process to
generate evidence that we're going to meet the intent that we're
going to constrain the risk. We're going to reduce the problems,
right. And show how our process reduces risk via automation
and via the process itself, rather than just somebody blindly
following it for fear of getting caught, or worse,
not following it and hiding the fact that they're not following it and
just trying to get away with it. Too many decision makers.
Every decision means meeting with multiple stakeholders to get consensus.
If multiple people are responsible for a decision to be made, then no
one's actually responsible. Remember the scene from
office space? I have eight different bosses right now,
so that means when I make a mistake, I have eight different people coming by
to tell me about it. That's my only real motivation. It's not to be hassled.
That and the fear of losing my job. But, you know, that will only
make someone work just hard enough not to get fired,
right? This type of too many decision makers,
too many people having to have a say and approve things often goes back
to being afraid to fail. Right? Again.
Find a champion, highlight some of your early wins and make them want to take
credit and responsibility. And that's going to lead you towards a generative
culture where you're protecting psychological safety, where experimentation and learning
is just part of the way you do business. Having too
many metrics, we can't do that or it'll hurt our monthly or
quarterly, our yearly numbers, right. Well,
when a measure becomes a target, it ceases to be a good measure.
Metrics should measure desired
outcomes, right? We shouldn't just be blindly using any metric
that we can find or what's available. And too many metrics in a complex system
leads to management. Whack a mole. What you want to do is pick
a target metric, improve that add process
to protect it, to make sure it's going to stay where we got it
to, and then pick the next metric. And slowly but surely focus on
one metric or a few metrics at a time. Don't be trying
to measure many, many metrics at once. It'll never work.
And the last doom is unrealistic expectations.
All of our problems will disappear as soon as we get to devsecops.
Well, the actual case is DevOps won't make
your problems vanish. In fact, it usually just shines the light on them and makes
them more visible. The reality is we're going to
need more discipline, not less. We're going to fail more often,
not less. We're going to pick what we want to improve. We're going to work
on it till that's better, and then we're going to pick the next thing.
It's a long process. It doesn't magically wave a
wand and fix everything. But if you set realistic expectations,
people will see that you're constantly making progress towards improving.
In summary, the ten ways to doom your DevOps slow
onboarding using the cloud being
agile having change control board change advisory
boards being afraid to fail having an
unchanging culture having unchanging policies
having too many decision maker ers,
watching too many metrics and setting unrealistic
expectations. Please let me know on the conference 42 discord
if you've seen these or other common problems when you've been adopting DevOps.
Also, I'm other devsecops gene on X,
Twitter, YouTube, GitHub, other social media. Reach out and let
me know what you think. Thanks for coming.