Hi, I'm sure you've seen the introductory video already, but I'm Francesco.
I'm 15. I'm a student pen tester, student web developer,
and today I just wanted to generally go through the importance of integrating security measures
throughout development. Now I'll be going through some well known security
vulnerabilities, primarily in web development, and I'll also just really
quickly demonstrate them in Kali. So to start off with, I just wanted to talk
about input sanitization and specifically xss.
I'm also going to be talking about SQL, but for now I just wanted to
talk about cross site scripting and how we can exploit these
unsanitized input fields, whether it's with reflected XSS,
stored xss, or any other type of xss.
So to understand how XSS can lead to compromised accounts,
I'm just showing you a really quick snippet of some code that should
be vulnerable, even though it's probably not. But I'm going to show it anyway
just to kind of understand how these logic works behind XSS.
So to give a little bit of context, what this code is meant
to do, or the general model of this website is to just store
comments that users can post. And here we can actually see the user comment
variable which I now filled in with just some HTML saying
hi just as a proof of concept. And I've also created a function to
handle the request which takes in a URL and an input.
And here we can see that we're making a post request to these designated
URL passing in the input and to call the function we're
just giving it a locally hosted API route
that leads to comments and giving in the user comment.
And if these input truly is not sanitized in the front end or
the backend, then as a response these text high will be
displayed on the user's page. And moving on from the code here we can see
a really quick flow diagram which actually displays a malicious payload
as opposed to the high in HTML. And what this payload
actually does is it tries to render an image which we know it definitely won't
because the source is given as x, which is just invalid.
So it will inevitably call this on error function, which in turn makes
a request to the attacker's ip, giving the attacker the
cookies of whoever views the web page. Now obviously for
this to work, the attacker would have to have a web server hosted, but this
is just to generally show how it would work. Now, to test XSS
on a vulnerable website, I've loaded up owasp zoo shop
which basically is just a training tool for hackers. And here
we can see that we have a search bar. And since we know that this
input is not sanitized, we could try run something like a h one tag
saying hi like we showed in the code and
just closing it and it should return high. Now we
know it's vulnerable to XSS because it actually displayed high.
But if we wanted to just test a range, we could try to test a
h two, which makes it smaller,
or a h four even makes it even smaller.
Or if we wanted we could just do a p tag right
here and it got bigger.
But you get the point. Now another thing you could do is you could test
if the website will run JavaScript,
which you could just test by doing script and typing
like Cert and giving it something. But I'm
not going to do that because in this case it doesn't work. Now going back
to the presentation, this really shows us that we really need to make sure that
all of our inputs are sanitized. And to further show the extent of the damages
that an unsanitized input could cause, I'm going to show
how these can lead to SEO,
which the general concept is the same.
They're both based off an unsanitized input and
injecting something in that input field. In this case,
the only thing is that we're going to inject an SQL query, whether it's a
union select or whether it's just a dump. The users,
there's a lot more you can do with SQL in my opinion, than you can
with XSS. And here I just displayed an example that you could use
if this password field was indeed vulnerable. And for this to work over
here, we need to make sure that the email is actually correct in the database
and it actually exists. Otherwise we need to flip these parameters and we need to
hope that the email field is also injections. And to show how this would look
like on the code base, we could just see that it's actually selecting all
from users, where email equals this
and password equals or one equals one and comment the rest of the
code. Now we need this quotation mark here at the start because
it actually closes the password variable,
allowing us to actually put SQL statements after it.
Now once again we're back on the OASP gshop. And just
to test that same thing, and just to test that it works,
you can try the same thing on the login maybe whatever at
Gmail, whatever.
And password or one
equals one comment. Now I dont think
this will actually work for now. Yeah. Invalid email or password
because this is not a valid email. But if we don't
know the email, we could always just try to
put that statement here or one equals
one comment, the rest of the code and literally whatever
over here. And if we log in,
we have admin at juice shop. Now. Just signing
into someone's account is really the least you could do with an SQL injection
vulnerability. If you really wanted to, you could go on SQL
map and fully dump the database contents,
which actually I might show if we go here on
this DVWA. Go on SQL
injection. I might need to load.
Okay, so I have burp suite loaded. I'll just intercept
the traffic here and user
id one or whatever. Yeah.
So here's a request. So I might actually use this request to
put this into SQL map. I'm just going to copy the cookie that we need
right here and bring
it over here so we could do SQL map,
tacu the link.
And I've already done this, so just
add in the cookie just in case it changed.
It didn't for some reason. But yeah, we're just going
to enumerate these database like this
and we can see that we have DBWA and information
schema. And if we wanted to, we can just select the
DVWA and then enumerate
the tables. We have guest book and users.
We just go for users,
users.
And I didn't dump it columns
and say we wanted the password or user id
or anything. We could just go here and then select which column
we want. In this case password dump. Since I've already done this,
we have everything here. And then we actually have the MD five hash
which you could just try crack. I'm sure it's probably going to be some simple
hashes to crack because it's a vulnerable website. But yeah, this really shows
the extent of SQL injections and how they can really damage your business.
Now moving on from SQL injections, I just wanted to talk about broken authentication,
which in my opinion is not as bad as SQL injections,
but it still can cause a lot of damage and it's just a bad look
to have any of these vulnerabilities anyway.
Now with broken authentication, there's actually several types
of it. For example, there's insecure cookies, which is what we're going to talk
about. Now. There's unsafe password policy, which is when you allow your
user to pick whatever password he or she wants, even if it's just like
a three character password, which can be easily crackable. Now on the more serious
side of broken authentication, there's also no request restrictions,
which is probably one of the worst ones because it lets
any user make a limited amount of requests to these
login or sign up field for example, which just allows them to brute force
these password of any users they want and they can just leave it running.
Now you can easily change the amount of requests that you want a user to
make per hour, for example on the back end. So that should really
just be a quick fix. And moving on to unhashed passwords, this is also
pretty serious because if you're storing user passwords in
plain text in the database, say in your MySQL database
or your MongoDB database, because by doing so you can allow the
effects of any other vulnerabilities such as SQL
injection to be way worse. Because now if someone can perform an
SQL injection on your website and instead of receiving passed
MD five passwords, they just receive plain text passwords,
then the purpose of making a really complicated and hard
to crack password just gets defeated. Now even with this broken authentication,
it should be really simple to just encrypt users passwords.
For example, you can use bcryptjs if you're using a node JS
backend to easily encrypt these passwords and that should at least increase your
security by a bit. So yeah, all of these types of broken authentication,
they all have their respective solution down here. But moving on
to the insecure cookie type of broken authentication, we can see here that
we have a cookie called privilege with a value of user.
Now the reason as to why this isn't optimal is because anyone can
just change the value of the cookies as something really predictable,
say admin for example, which if you're having this type of cookie
structure, then you probably have a value for admin that
might lead to a dashboard, for example. Now the point is that you should just
not have insecure cookies like this and instead just make unique
cookies to anyone that visits the website, say with JWT
cookies, or just anything that's encrypted and unique for each user so
that an attacker can't just guess another user's cookie. Now carrying
on, I also wanted to mention directory exploits and specifically
local file inclusion vulnerabilities because these are really simple to exploit
and cause basically anyone can dump the contents of the Linux machine hosting the
web server. Now here I've just included the most common example of
vulnerable PHP code, which basically just takes in any directory
from the user and displays its contents. Now to showcase how we
can exploit it, I just took a screenshot of a random domain which just shows
the vulnerable parameter lang where we can replace en,
where presumably it's for language, but basically we
can just replace en with any directory and basically
we can just use path traversal to escape the directory that we're currently in
and to get to for example Etsy shadow
or Etsy password and once again to exploit it. I'm just
going to go back to this DVWA find
file inclusion and I need to
turn off intercept on burp suite.
Yes, and I need to also turn it off here.
And yeah, here we have just an example of the vulnerable
parameter, which in this case is page.
And if we just type for example
here to just escape the directory Etsy password.
These are the contents of the root user and if you wanted to
crack it you should go to Etsy shadow.
And I dont know why nothing loads here, but usually
to crack it you need to unshadow the contents of the password
and shadow and then you can crack the hash that way. And also
aside from just displaying shadow or password, one thing that
you could do is in here you could just put the link to
your local server hosting a reverse shell and then
that turns into RFI where you actually get a remote
shell on the website. So this should really show that you should really
be careful when you write code. And if you're not sure about something
just comment it out and leave it for later or at least before pushing
the branch, get a pen test done on it. There's many ways that you
can just check that your website is relatively secure
before you actually push it, which I'm actually going to talk about later on.
So yeah, like I said, we're going to be going over some prevention methods and
what we can do to generally make our website secure.
But it's not just websites, this can also be relevant to your servers or whatever
you want to keep secure. So one thing that I actually found useful was
listening to your package manager. Now the first
two screenshots are actually react and anytime you do NPMI
or NPM install to install any new package basically just highlights
anything it wants you to take a look at, which most of the
time it's probably nothing important,
but the times that it can be something serious, it might be worth taking
a look at it and checking with your senior developer.
Now about checking with your senior developer. Just getting
code reviews done in general are really useful.
Again to make sure that your inputs are sanitized, that you don't have some LFI
vulnerabilities or just some basic mistakes that junior
developers can make, even seniors, that can lead to
serious vulnerabilities. Now most companies already have
a system of code reviews in place, but if your company doesn't
already have these code reviews in place, it might be worth bringing that up.
And another thing aside from Code reviews is just updating your libraries.
For example, Apache had vulnerabilities before where they had some serious Tomcat
version vulnerabilities. I can't remember exactly which, but I remember
some black box that I did involve some Tomcat vulnerabilities
which you could just easily exploit with metasploit. They had a bunch of modules
on that, and for another vulnerability there was these Grafana
path reversal exploit that was found. So yeah,
it's really important that you make sure that all your libraries are updated, that you
get these code reviews done, and that you also listen to your package manager.
Now if your company can't afford the correct employees to do
code reviews, you could always just go open source. But also
going open source you just kind of have to hope that there's going to be
more good people trying to help you with your code than bad people
trying to craft exploits for your website or whatever it is
that you're developing. Now I probably mentioned this before, but you should most likely
get a pen test scheduled before publishing a new
branch. Now again, most companies do have systems like
this in place where they have full time pen testers, where every time a new
branch is supposed to get passed before it actually gets pushed to the public,
they have pen testers check it and make sure that everything's secure. But what
if you just don't have money for a pen tester? You're just a small
business. Well, in that case, the best thing I could
recommend is just to use these surface level vulnerability
scanners like Nessus or whatever
it is, to just generate a user friendly chart or
list of all these vulnerabilities that you may have. So in here you can see
I listed out NMap, which is probably one of the more
advanced ones out of all of these because this is something that you
need to do on the command line and you need to kind of learn all
the companies for it. But if you just search up how to do a script
can on Nmap, that should give you a rough idea on
how secure website is. And aside from NMap, there's Nessus, which is
really user friendly. Once you get it set up, all you need to do is
just select what type of scan you want and it will perform it for
you. Once it's done, it will give you a list of all the possible
vulnerabilities that you may have. And while we're talking about
vulnerability scanners, I also wanted to mention Openvas. It's like
Nessus, but way more thorough. It has way more
vulnerabilities to check. It generally takes way longer, but it's really worth
the time and effort that you put into getting an Openvascan set up.
Now if you know that you've recently set up a reverse proxy
or a web application firewall like Cloudflare, then you should probably
take a look at security trails, tiny and zoomai and going
in order. Security trail just checks if you've had
the actual IP of your server leaked. And it also lists out
all the MX emails, a lot of information that it can pick up on the
website. And Tinye and Zumai, they're both really similar. They're really
powerful search engines that once again help
you see if you've had the actual ip of your website leaked.
And I've actually used Zoomi and security trails for a pen test I've done
where I actually was able to find the actual ip
of the web server, which was probably really lucky.
But it just goes to show that these tools are really easy to
use yet really effective. I also forgot to mention Mascan,
which is just an ip port scanner, just to make sure that
there's no ports that you don't want open. Like you might have an FTP port
open that you don't want. You might have an SSH port open that you don't
want. Just generally making sure that the ports that you have open
are the ports that you need to have the website running. And that just really
limits the attack vectors that are available for attackers.
Now this is a really important one. Setting up an ACL is
one of the things that you definitely do want.
And here you're actually seeing a real screenshot
of a pen test I did where I
actually had to blur out the ip because I don't want that to be leaked.
But yeah, basically I was trying to access a MySQL server or a
MySQL server. And on the third line you can
see that my ip was not allowed to connect to that MySQL server because
of the ACL that they had set up. And in the diagram you can actually
see that my ip tried to contact the server and it was rejected.
But another ip that might be in the
ACL list was actually accepted and was able to get through.
So it might be really worth implementing this. And the last thing
I wanted to talk about was how you could prevent lateral movement
and what this is. It's basically once an
attacker gets a foothold on one machine that was easy to exploit,
whether they use LFI to get remote control execution or
anything that could get them remote control access to one machine.
What we're trying to do here is we're trying to prevent lateral movement from taking
place so they can access the more important machines. And generally this is overlooked
because most people don't think that attacks are going to get into one machine
anyway. But it's usually that one vulnerable machine that allows the attackers
to get access to everything else using privilege escalation.
And here you can actually see that I'm showing a terminal
picture of a. I believe that's linpie's output,
which, in red, it highlights all the directories that
might be worth taking a look at, because they
might be that one thing that allows for privilege escalation to take place in
order to get access to all the other machines. And the leaks framework
is actually just one of the tools that attackers can use to perform
lateral movement and get that privilege escalation done.
There's a really popular one called bloodhound, which is way more in depth.
It actually displays a whole map of
the entire network of everything it could find. It's just generally
way more in depth and just highlights absolutely everything that even
has a chance of getting you that rc on the next machine. So,
yeah, that should really just show the importance of integrating security
measures throughout development. You really want to make sure that all your inputs
are sanitized, that you don't have some LFI vulnerabilities. And it's not just
vulnerabilities that I displayed in this presentation. It's just a
bunch of CVE vulnerabilities that you really want to look out for,
since it can really cause a lot of damage. So, yeah, with that being said,
thanks for listening. If you have any questions, you can email me on
my proton mail, or you can just contact me through LinkedIn.