Hi, my name is Philippe and I'm here to share our vision and
how businesses can start in cryptocurrency with confidence.
Today at UTrust, well soon to be named XMoney,
our mission is to democratize access to new digital money,
making it easy for any business to access and
accept. We want to make digital assets accessible and
universal, so that any user can pay in any merchant
with less intermediaries and more freedom.
But before talking about our solution and how we help companies
capture this market, it's important to understand some of the technology
foundations of digital assets, blockchain in particular,
not the technical elements per se, but the new concept it enables.
Blockchain technology has brought about the paradigm shift by
allowing direct transfer of value in the public network. Not a
message, a request or an extension, or an
external representation, but true direct transfer of value between two parties
without intermediaries. This is taken to the transfer of physical cash,
but in a digital verse. If you consider transfer of value in a
digital space without blockchain technology, for example,
your typical home banking, these are mere representations
of value. With blockchain, it is possible for users
to have direct custody of their own assets in a
similar way to physical assets like cash or gold,
as long as of course, they have access to private keys. Hence the popular expression
not your keys, not your crypto.
While digital assets are based upon blockchain technology layer,
there are different types of assets with varying
degrees of openness, different use cases, value and properties
that can be less or more decentralized. Think of bitcoin
versus ethereum with a volatile or fixed value USDC
USDT as examples of stablecoins that
can be issued by anyone from a single individual, a group,
to institutions or governments.
Digital asset is thus a broad category,
despite similar underlying technology.
Not all digital assets are the same, even in
specific cases. In payments, for example, there are
differences. Just think of for example the difference between paying
with an american dollar or venezuelan peso,
for example. The different accepting and issuer risks affect
the market price of one versus the other in FX markets and
others, and these same applies in the case of stablecoins.
For the use case of payments, cryptocurrency or digital
assets have been through narrative evolution,
which has been showcased in the terminology and target uses or use
cases. This evolution translated into a higher degree of maturity and
adoption to specialized use cases. For example,
today there are stable coins with a one to one pegged to the US dollar.
Well, not all the times, but that's a topic
for another discussion and presentation. Maybe in the future.
And this evolution in the narrative in the
usability use cases of cryptocurrency is also cumulative.
Bitcoin has evolved from pure payment narrative, to a speculative investment,
to an inflation edge asset, to a store of value.
In the future, we will no longer have CDBCs, central bank digital
currencies or national currencies issued by central
banks which hybrid elements from different
aspects of these technology. They might have more
or centralized or decentralized elements. There will
certainly be a hybrid of different elements using
blockchain technology as a foundation.
And of course customers of the future will be digital
natives. It's not already this is a young
segment of a very young, connected and demanding users,
hyperconnected, holding cryptocurrency and part of a connected
metaverse. This is a prime audience for any business to capture
and retain, especially when it comes to payments.
For businesses crypto adoption, this is a really relevant
topic. Adding cryptocurrency as a means of payment will no longer be
optional, but the status quo. Almost 32% of
SMEs in the US accept cryptocurrency and this number
is trending. The decision in adding payments in crypto has translated
into increase of transactional volume of more than 100%
with a return on investment of more than 300%
in some. This is an audience that any business should
be paying attention, close attention to because these are
different, the way they interact and how they consume information,
how they're influenced and how they pay. Most brands
have either started or are already catering to this trend,
introducing crypto gamification metaverse elements to
position themselves as appealing and leaders in their respective markets.
And this is exactly where we come in.
UTrust is the gateway to this market.
For years our solution has been allowing merchants across all verticals
to accepting crypto payments, making it accessible to
tap into this new rising market. It is a payment gateway,
allowing any business to accept crypto as means of payment,
be it at a checkout or through invoicing. Simple and
without any risk of volatility. A trusted intermediary
that settles in fiat in the merchant's bank account.
We provide low transactional fees at 1%
end to end, no chargeback risks,
a drastic reduction of fraud and fast transactional settlement
versus legacy solutions. We make the checkout integration
super simple. These plug and play experience with
support for the most widely used market plugins, as well
as an API for custom integrations with no
blockchain technical expertise required for the merchant.
We also make the payment experience seamless to the consumer
and support any wallet in the market. It's an blockchain experience
open to all, with no ecosystem lock in.
We solve all the hurdles of crypto payments for merchants
without any risk of volatility. The merchant always
receives a steady value as a regulated and compliant
institution, employing state of the art blockchain screening technology for
AML. That's antimoney laundering to protect users and
merchants in the ecosystem from malicious actors,
making the whole experience reliable and secure
with no hidden costs or fees, no annual subscription
nor commitment. Merchants only pay 1% of any
transacted volume, providing flexibility and choice.
Our solution is extremely competitive given the base layer we
operate upon blockchain. By reducing these amount of intermediaries
in a transaction, we obtain a lower degree of complexity.
Less intermediaries translate into more simplicity and
lower costs. With less costs, more of the value can
be captured and passed to the client. This is a market of users
that already uses crypto for payments, but obfuscated
under more intermediary layers. Many users already pay
with crypto using their linked cards, paying extra fees
for the conversion. At the same time, the merchant pays a
higher percentage to receive the transaction because of the underlying rails.
These also allows for new business models. For example,
how is it possible to transform a fee into an additional revenue?
Like instead of a merchant paying a processing fee, this can
be truly offset to zero,
perhaps even becoming a net positive. Well,
is this entirely new? At its core,
no. This model already exists,
and it's currently used by legacy payment processors such
as PayPal. And it's not optional. All you have to do is
read their terms of service. How do they do it then?
Well, during the transit time of the funds, from the moment the client pays
until the merchant actually receives the money in their bank, these funds in
transit can be used and reinvested to generate
additional revenue. The difference? With us, they retain all
the funds to themselves. We won't retain that extra
money and pass it to the merchant, offsetting their costs a more fair and
transparent way to take on a core model. And of
course, this is entirely optional. But it's
something that the current model and the foundation of blockchain
technology allow us to pass on and to
provide that extra mile to merchants. And this universe
of merchants keeps growing, especially in the sectors of ecommerce,
real estate, fashion, luxury items and
digital goods. Many of our clients want to establish themselves
as pioneers in their sector, and we are prepared to help them
take the maximum advantage of this new segment, be it
in co marketing initiatives, ecosystem reach out or through
our network of partners. Because payments
in crypto have unique challenges when compared with traditional
gateways. Our approach helps to maximize impact
in reach. At UTrUst, we see our merchants as partners
in these whole ecosystem journey, so don't
get left behind. As a merchant, this is these time to adopt and
join the ecosystem. Although the perception may be it's
early, this is the perfect moment for you to position yourself
as a market leader. In a similar way to the adoption of the Internet,
this is a critical moment for the mass adoption of
digital assets. Looking at the past, we see that companies that
persevere are the ones that keep adapting, the ones that align
with the trends of the future before they become tomorrow's
status quo. So we
invite you, web invite your business to start accepting the money
of the future by visiting our website and onboard today.
Thank you all.