Hi, this is a presentation on using the new MySQL
Shell with Python and I'd like to
start by introducing myself. My name is Dave Stokes. I'm a
community manager. I've been on the MySQL community team for just over a
decade using MySQL since it first came out,
and this will hopefully be a quick introduction to the MySQL shell and
how to extend it with Python. Safe harbor statement
I work for Oracle. During the course of this presentation
I'm talking about the free open source version of MySQL and the MySQL Shell
all out there under the GPL. However, in Q-A-I might very
often some new functionality coming in future releases
since I don't have perfect knowledge of those perfect releases and what
I know is probably wrong. Take anything I say about a future release with a
grain of salt. So about me
once again I'm on the MyScope community team. I live in Texas. The slides
would be available@slideshare.net Slash Dave Stokes I got a blog at elephantdolphin
blogspot.com. If you need to get a hold of me, I'm at Stoker on Twitter
or David stokes@oracle.com so what
is the new MySQL Shell? Well, if you used our old interface,
anything before 80 it was a simple commandline editor.
The new shell is much more advanced in that it allows you to process
queries in structured query language. Big surprise there,
eh? Also there's a JavaScript mode and a Python
mode. So between these three modes you've got a lot of flexibility. And by the
way, if you have something that's written in Python, you can run it in JavaScript
modes, and JavaScript modes stuff can run in Python.
So if you haven't seen our new shell, it's no longer monochromatic
when you fire it up. It of course gives you the copyright.
And if you notice here, this yellow stuff here says js
for JavaScript. Well what if you don't like JavaScript and you'd want
to use Python? Py moves you into Python mode. And if
you're an old timer like me and you want SQL, there you go. You can
run SQl by the way, you can run SQL code from Python or JavaScript
mode as you wish. Now once you log in,
if you do a backslash s for status or you can do a session get
status, there's some things here I like to point out to you.
First thing, if you can see my mouse here is by default we're secure
we're using SSL with TLS AES 256 by
default. If you don't need it, you can turn it off, but by default we
wanted to give that to you. Also, our default character set now is UTF
eight mb four. That's to help get all four planes of the
90 unit code standard, which means yes, you do get emojis.
Yay. And by the way, if you notice down here, compression,
if you need to compress stuff, that helps a lot sound by default.
So with the new shell you have two types of sessions. The classic, which is
our old port three three six. We've had that for 25 years. Yes,
MySQL is 25 year old. And we also have another port 3360
for the new Xdev API, which is designed to handle
both SQL traffic and NoSQL traffic. You can use MySQL as
a NoSQL JSON document store. By the
way, you can reach the JSON stuff from the classic
side and the classic stuff from the NoSQL
side. Trying to give you more flexibility. Now the reason we're
here today is I want to talk about the functions. If you write functions or
programs or scripts or whatever you want to call it, in either JavaScript or Python,
and you find them handy, you can actually run them under different sessions.
So you can have one session running JavaScript, two more running Python, run all
sorts of reports and all that. Now to log in you can either
type in MySQL shell, root at localhost or whatever thing.
Or once you get the shell fired up, you can do a backslash c for
connect and you log in. Or once you get fired
up you can have multiple sessions. Now this example is in JavaScript where we're having
session one, which we say we're going to do a classic session which
will work to three, three six, account name and password.
Now if I want a second session to generate data and feed it to the
first session, no problem there. Oh, by the way,
if you want encryption, you can specify how you want it,
where you want your definitions for all the stuff.
In this example we're accepting TLS eleven and one
two. Well, by default compression is turned on, but if you want to
specify your algorithms like LZ four or Z standard and
the local compression, you can do that. Also,
something we can offer for you is JSON schema validation. JSon by
default is very loosey goosey. There's no rigor on
there. Traditionally, relational databases is very tightly
structured. One thing we do, thanks to the wonderful, wonderful people@jsonschema.org,
is we can set up an exemplar template that we test your incoming
JSON documents against and we can say hey,
we have this required field and the values,
it takes numbers and the minimum value is -90 the maximum number 90.
Maximum is plus 90. So you can set up required fields range check
and type checks. Very very handy. By the way,
first time you log in using the MySQL shell, it will ask you if you
want to store your password that is hashed very securely.
So if you don't want to keep typing your password, that will do that work
for you too. By the way, if you have some code in Python,
you can just pipe it with a shell and away it will go.
Make sure you're in Python mode of course. By the way, if you have libraries
you like, like this example, I'm using datetime. I import the
datetime library and I get full access to that.
So if you have libraries you'd like to work with the data with, it's all
there for you. Also, if you're using our
new Xdev API as a NoSQL document
store, the MySQL no longer requires you to actually go out and
use SQL if you don't want to. You'll find this is a very straightforward
API. On our system, we're connected to a database called
WorldX. It has a document collection. We've typed get
collection. It'll tell you the name of that collection is country info. So the
current database pointer to that collection, we're going to find
all the records that have a name like a parameter and we bind
uppercase s wildcard to that parameter and we're going to limit
to one. So our new API is very straightforward,
very easy to use, very similar between all three languages.
Also supports in our other various connectors, very easy to use. Once again,
if you don't like SQL, you do mysql without SQL.
By the way, I'm going to repeat that. You find out your collections,
go out and run your query. By the way, it is not
an Orm, it is actually a totally clean sheet protocol
written on Google protobuffs. Real nice design.
And by the way has a lot of smarts put in there so it gets
rid of things like most SQL injection. Okay, here's another
thing. I'm logged in. I'm in Python mode. For my current session,
I'm going to run underscore SQL on just a straight query. So that'd be the
same as going out to the SQL mode and running the same query by the
way, if you notice this is out in a table output. If you want to
do it in JSon you tell your shell hey, my resort format is
going to be JSON and how it comes in JSOn very
very handy. By the way, I mentioned earlier, you don't need to use SQl
say like you have a project where your bosses tell you hey, go ahead and
start coding, we'll tell you what you're actually doing next week. It's real easy
to go out there and create a document collection and in there
we're going to add a record and haven't gone,
had to go out and set up relations, had to set up indexes. I'm able
to just store data right off the bat. Now if I
do a DB openjs the collection we create up here and in
a record you'll notice that when I do the find command that it gives you
an underscore id. This is the value you can specify or have the
server generate it for you. This is actually a primary key for
the NoDB storage engine. Very important, but I'm not going to go off into that.
So if you have JavaScript libraries, this is an example of JavaScript libraries.
If I type in the libraries require a file.
If I do Dave tab, it shows me the two functions we have defined
over here and I can run them at will. That's about the
same thing for JavaScript. Now you can define your own extensions to
the base functionality of the shell. It forms their reports and
extensions. Now these can be created once again in JavaScript or
Python, and they're accessible from either of those languages.
You can persist these, you can watch them, have them run over and over
again, and they are automatically loaded every time the shell starts. Now here's
an interesting example. We're going to define
a quick little extension in Python.
And the trick down here is we create
a function, this one where I'm just going to call show tables and we have
to make sure that we have a session. You have to be logged into the
database to actually get access to the tables.
So if you don't have a session it kind of tells
you where to go. So if you do have a session, it's basically going
to run underscore SQL, select from world city and then
dump out the results. Now the trick is to register the shell is
we have to have a plugin object and we create an extension for that.
And for that plugin object that we have here, we give it the name of
our function, what we want to call it, and a little bit of help information
as you can see there in what, a dozen lines of code.
Very easy to set up a basic loop query.
So once again, make sure we have a session,
and once we have a session we can run queries all day long.
Now as I mentioned before, all we have to do is register the plugin
object with our function and easy peasy. Now reports
are a little bit different. You can register a report that you define
in any Python or JavaScript. The reporting facility
handles building reports. There's a whole bunch of out there already for you.
And reports can specify a list of report specific options. If you
want to have a v for verbose,
z for compress, however you want to do it and
you could have all sorts of inputs so it actually read
from the screen. Now instead of registering
a plugin, it's register report. Otherwise it's pretty
much like you've seen earlier. You can write your own reports.
This is one where it modes out there and watches the sessions. I believe this
one's actually built into the new shell and when you run
it, it tells you I'm running this with a slash watch sessions
which is the name of our report and
it runs every 2 seconds. When the building
reports you can set up intervals, you can set up global
statuses to watch. You can run things in foreground background
however you want to do it. Now the shell by default also has some
utilities. For those of you who deal with a lot of data.
One very important one is import JSON. So if you have a
lot of JSoN it's very easy to use. You say util
import JSoN, the name of the file, what schema or database you're
loading into, and what you want to call the collection. This works with
the latest version of the shell. Also for those of you who are on five
seven wanting to go to 80, we have a uterus check for server upgrade.
This will go out there and make sure that you're not using reserved words.
We have several new reserved words in 80. Also make sure that you're
not going to run into any problems like converting over to utf eight and before.
Also we can have utilities for importing tables. We have
a lot of interesting stuff off the import table. If you've
been playing with MySQl dump for years and years and years, are looking
for something a little bit faster. We have export table and
that's a very fast way to dump your data. And we also
have the ability to dump in the entire instance. So if
you want everything on the server, you can do that. If you want to
test to see how long it's going to run, you can do that. If you're
using the Oracle cloud, there's some functionality you can do there for setting
up buckets and all that. If you want to dump tables, you can just say
okay, from this schema, I want these two tables.
Very interesting. Fun. Now if you want to learn more about all this,
the MySQL Shell is actually fairly well documented
and there's lots of examples on writing plugins.
This one, developpaper.com is a very good starting
place. My counterpart from Belgium
has a lot of interesting blogs about how to do that.
Also he has a GitHub libraries of a whole bunch of shell plugins
that are very nice, very very handy things like that.
You copy users, check in ODB status and all other stuff.
And before I go, I'd like to say, hey, if you want to run the
MySQL shell under our new MySQL database service,
if you go to this location, you can get $300 in credits. This is
quite a long time, month or two if you stay
in the low end engines for free to go out there and test the MySQL
service. By the way, this is the full enterprise version of MySQL Eight and it
is the latest and greatest, and it is monitored and supported by
MySQL engineers. Also, if you're a member of
the MySQL community, congratulations, you're now a member of the MySQL community.
Please join us on MySQL community manager
on mySql.com under Twitter we're MySQl,
Facebook we're MySQL and LinkedIn Render MySQL.
By the way, if you are a startup and startups only, you can enroll@oracle.com.
Slash startup get a whole bunch of cloud credits, whole bunch of help with other
areas, exposure with marketing,
some good stuff if you want to do some events, because events are coming back.
Thank goodness. This is a great thing if you are a startup because Oracle really
wants to get you off the ground. And by the way, if you're using a
lot of JSON with MySQL, please buy a copy of my book. This is the
second edition. First edition came out three years ago and we keep adding
new features. So a second edition is new. This is for folks who want to
learn how to use JSON with a database. Our manual is good, but it's a
reference guide, not a coding example.
And this is how you do it best. Practices guide available
on Amazon today. And with that, we're going to go into Q A,
and I want to thank you for your time.