Hello you guys, my name is Robert and today I'd
like to talk to you about how my team and I are developing
front end applications with real Kubernetes setups
in the development stage and why we think
that mocking APIs on the backend side is
actually not that good of an idea. We'll be talking
about the cloud native software development process and
how we think it should be approached
when it comes to developing front ends.
But first let me introduce myself. I'm Robert.
I'm a software engineer and co founder at Blue Shoe,
a Munich based cloud native software development agency.
And actually we started out with classic
web development. However, around 2018
we shifted our architectural approach from
building monolithic web applications to a more
service oriented or microservice oriented software
architectural approach. Somehow we landed at Kubernetes and
we're really happy with that. Today we
try to embed our learnings into
tooling and processes we deliver
for other developers to make their life easier and enable
them to build great cloud native software. I'm mostly
responsible for front end technologies. I do some project
management and steer some of our open source efforts.
In my spare time I'm a sourdough bread baker
and a coffee nerd. I really like coffee.
I also love to play the guitar. So in case
you're interested in cloud native software development,
or you're really into sourdough bread baking,
hit me up on LinkedIn or Twitter, I'll definitely respond.
So why do we actually need to talk about
this? Typically when you're developing
a distributed software architecture and the
applications within it, there is some kind of back and
forth communication. Typically this is done
via APIs. And when
you develop a front end there is an API or
maybe a gateway on the back end which wraps all the
APIs of the different services into one,
and we somehow have to
deal with that at the development stage.
There are some approaches on how to cope with that.
So basically you just can read documentation and develop
your front end to the best of your knowledge. Latest in
the CI CD process, you'll test whether things
work or not. So this is not actually a solution.
I just listed it here as you can do it
this way, but probably no one does. Let's just scratch
that from the list and come to the second point. You can mock
the APIs on the backend side. So basically you create
a static response for a certain request,
a certain request body, a certain query parameter,
and this is it. It's just statically
returned from the mock server for
the given request. Another way to approach this is
just to set up a development backend. Basically you can
spin up a VM or maybe a docker compose setup,
or even a local cluster or remote cluster could do
it just for your own, or there could be some kind of shared machine
for different front end developers.
This is another way to approach this at the development cycle,
because when you're developers, the frontend, you somewhat want to
talk to the API, fiddle around with responses, right?
So what's actually the best way on how to approach this?
Obviously when we started out,
we basically did what everyone did at the
time, which was mocking APIs.
And this is actually fairly simple and pretty
quick to do. There are lots of services,
there are lots of tools and even some frameworks
which have built in mocking capabilities
which makes the whole thing really quick to set up and really
simple actually. However,
what we noticed over time is
that there's quite some additional maintenance effort,
right? Because you have to keep the actual
response and the actual requests in
sync with what your real code does.
You have to ask yourself who is actually
responsible over time on
maintaining the mock service? Is it
the frontend developers who is actually mocking with it all the
time? Is it the backend developer who does
the coding of the actual service of the actual API?
Is it the testing team or quality assurance team?
So this is not completely clear. I think
in most cases maybe the back end developer.
But yeah, you have to really make clear
to your team who's responsible for that. And keeping
things in sync, especially code,
is pretty tough, right? So in
case you're adapting a response
in your code, in your application, you have also adapted in
your mocking service, or maybe in
the framework you're using, or maybe
even the service provider you're
using to provide the mock
API. As a profit oriented company we're
running, we also had to think about the costs.
Are the costs worth the value
of a mock API? I think this is pretty hard
to answer, right? Because you
could probably introduce some bugs in
your mock API, you could probably go out
of sync with the real code. And this basically
leads to more and more errors within your development process
and other teams. You have to dive in
why things are not in sync anymore and what change or
what response is actually the right one? Was the mocking
API adapted beforehand or did just
someone forget? These are basically events
which result in additional costs and who's paying
for it? Same thing as testing or documentation.
This is additional effort. And I'm not
saying that this is a bad thing, I'm just saying you have
to be aware that there's additional
costs and effort running into this part
of the process. What I want you to take away is
that mocking APIs is fairly simple, it's quick
to set up, and still it's
pretty hard to keep your code
and your mocking service, the result of
it in sync. Basically what we also believe is
that there is more to a good mock than just
a plain HTTP response or JSON response
XML, you name it. So there may be
some domain related problems. Just think
about cross origin resource sharing,
or maybe there are some timing issues or
even some encryption SSL certificates you have to deal with
which are different in the
production system. What we did is we went
back and looked at our software development process,
or even in the context of cloud native software
development, the cloud native software development process,
there are quite some things involved. Of course,
you have your code with your code style guide and
you have a CI CD process. You have your documentation, the tests,
monitoring, logging, you name it. There are lots of
things involved when it comes to developing good
cloud native software. What we basically
establish for us is that the environments
your software runs in, or the
software is written in are a part of the
software developers process. So you have your development,
your integration, your production environments, maybe even some
more called staging or testing environment.
We are pretty much convinced,
or basically we found out that this has a direct impact
on how you write your software and the
quality of it. So the environments
really play a big role in
your software development cycle.
Let me first explain what
we think about when we talk about an environment.
So basically an environment is
the space, the context, the setting which
your software runs in. Over the past
couple of years, there's been a trend of
equalizing the environment your software runs
in. And the strength was called containerization.
And there are some quite popular technologies like
Docker which do that for you.
Basically what they enable you to do
is federating your code in
a very similar runtime on
different machines. And this makes it more
reproducible, right? You can expect the same results
on your machine and your colleagues
machine. However, there is
more to a service presented
architectural approach than just the runtime of your container,
right? Your container may rely on some cache
in the production system, some open authentication,
there may be ns three storage, there may be some external
services which are woven into
your architecture. Suddenly you
have a pretty different environment
on your production side and
your development side, right? Your development environment may
look really different because maybe
you don't have the external service available.
You're mocking the code of
your other containers. Maybe you don't
use an s three. Instead you use a volume storage,
I mean accessing files on s three
and volume storage within kubernetes or
docker basically works different. So the code
has to work differently, right?
This led us to think, okay, how can we
minimize those differences between
the environments we run our software in,
so that we have something we call environment
parity? And basically what we mean by environment parity
is that the different stages our software runs
in development integration,
production look very very similar and
also not only like the runtime built, also the
orchestration of our services and even the services themselves.
So these are basically the rough
thoughts on why we think mocking just introduces
or does introduce some additional problems
to your development cycle you have
to solve. And by using
the real setup you're actually also using in production,
you eliminate those problems. However,
of course you have to think about how can I replicate
my production environment on my local machine without being
Kubernetes expert and front end developer in one
person, right?
Let me tell you about how we approach this.
We think mocking APIs comes at a cost and
in the long term it's hard to say
if it's worth it or not. We're not really convinced, let's put
it that way. Just be clear
who is responsible for maintaining the mock
of the API in the long term.
And we'd really recommend put
in some effort to make sure the
mocking matches your stack. So just picking
the first service provider that comes to mind or Google spits
out probably is not the best thing
to do here. So we try to maximize
the parity between the different environments our software runs
in and we try to minimize the differences.
Basically what we do is in our development lifecycle
we use a real Kubernetes setup for
our developers. We are pretty much convinced that our
DevOps people are super awesome guys and
they put in so much effort in writing
the Kubernetes description files like the Kubernetes manifest
or maybe helm charts or customize.
Why not make use of this really
great result they created for our
other developers for their development setups?
So there are some solutions, I just
put in some logos here, there's K 3D, there's minicube.
Unicube is something we use and we built.
So disclaimer, we are the creators of Unicube.
Basically it's a pretty thin layer
around K 3D which takes care of setting up
a replica of your production environment on your local machine.
So I guess it's demo time and
I'll show you on how our development
cycle looks like for our front end developers.
But first, let me explain you how the
architecture of our platform basically looks like. We have
a Kubernetes cluster which does look the
same during development and production.
The only differences are the actual secrets which are used
for development and production. So we have some
security concerns there and splitting those
up. And in front of all, we have of course, the frontend which
talks to a gateway which is connected to Keycloak.
Keycloak is an open identity provider which handles authentication
and authorization for us. Basically it works with JSON
web tokens. If you pass authentication,
your request is forwarded to Apollo.
Apollo is a pretty cool thing. It federates
all our backend graphql interfaces,
the public interfaces into one big graphql.
This basically enables the front end developer to run queries
across different services within
one request. So if I
want to have, maybe I want to retrieve all
projects for a given organization and include
the organization name and the project names, et cetera,
in one request. This is totally
possible and pretty easy to write.
Let's head over to how
we basically work with our Unicube
setup. We have a platform which
basically takes care of rendering the Kubernetes resources.
I log in and
after I logged in, there are some projects we
have here the Uniq platform.
There are all deployments listed within the platform.
This is something our developers team set up for
us. What they also did is they
told the platform on how to render the charts,
which values. These are basically hand charts, what values
to use and how to resolve the
secrets for the development charts.
That's basically what they just put into the platform.
And now I can use the unicube CLI
just to set up a cluster on my machine
to basically create my development environment.
All right, let's head over to the CLI.
First thing I need to do is to authenticate
so that the platform knows I'm really
allowed to access the helm charts,
or actually the Kubernetes manifest, which is generated by
the platform. And the CLI opens
tab in the browser where
I can authenticate. As soon as this is done,
I just can spin up the project I
just showed you in the web UI.
And this looks pretty similar to docker compose.
So what this command does,
it creates a new cluster with k machine, or spins
up an existing one, so I can actually manage multiple clusters
on my machine. This one is already running and
already also provisioned with the helm charts.
So no need to wait for this here. Let's have a
look at which resources
or domains the cluster
exposes for my local machine. So we just
had a look before on the deck, on the platform deck.
So running this command actually shows us which
paths are available. So there are quite a
few exposed here. We have the front end and we
have the gateway, our authentication
service key cloak.
All right, so let's have a look at it in the
browser. Basically what I'm doing now is accessing
the link, the ingress command exposed to
me as a user. What happened here actually is
my authentication is tested by
the keycloak service and the front
end is executed from the front end
deployment. And we access the real graphql
interface which runs within the cluster on my machine.
What we also can do is have a look at the
GraphQl interface which is also exposed by
the cluster. Let's have a look at that.
And I can basically run my graphQl
queries as they would run in the production
system, my cluster and get the results here.
Can have a look at the results, how they look like, can have
a look at the documentation. GraphQL is self documenting
how the schema looks like. And basically
I also can execute mutations which really
change things within the cluster. This is pretty cool.
Now I can spin up my webpack development
server and just work with the API.
All right. This is basically it how we
work at blue shoe when it comes to develop frontends KS
applications with Kubernetes setup. I have
to admit it was a bit slow
running obs and running the full
cluster on my machine, but basically it's a
bit faster and working when I
run it without recording a session. It was really fun to
show you guys how we work, how our development
flow looks like. Have a look at all the
awesome projects like mini Cube,
like K 3D. Also have a look at our project unicube.
It's completely open source and really
makes things easier to collaborate between DevOps
back end developers and front end developers. So if you're
interested in this, just hit me up, drop me a message
on LinkedIn or Twitter. I'll be glad
to help you. And well,
mocking APIs is as I told you before,
it's pretty simple and it's quick to set up.
But what we found that this flow flows
more, this development flow is better for us.
It may be better for you or not.
You have to find out if you have any critics
or any additional information you need,
just let me know. Really glad to be here and
hope to hear from you guys. See you
soon.