Hi, my name is Antoinette and I'm really glad that I have the opportunity
to meet you today. I'm happy to be here. I'm excited
to speak to you about why IoT devices are mandating
a zero tolerated security architecture.
And let me tell you why prevention pays. You need
prevention for scalability to increase savings
and massively decrease costs for profitability.
And with that, I mean an increased turnover, increased productivity,
an increased efficiency, basically an improved
daily operations. Reliability is the third one.
And with reliability, I mean, how do you make sure that
device keeps on working as intended, not only today,
but that it's safe for zero days, for tomorrow
as well? All of those three things, scalability,
profitability and reliability, will lift a burner
for us. I always start with this slide. When do you think
the first cyber attack took place? Guess what? It's almost 200
years ago. Two brothers, Francois and Joseph Long,
manipulated data that went into the national
telegraph system. So this clearly demonstrates that criminals
are very creative and always looking for new ways in, and that
you need to man it up to make sure that there's no data poisoning,
that the device is really secure. You are
as strong, as weak, as lean, and as you can see here,
at that time in France, there were all kinds of mechanical telegraph
systems like this, so they can sign letters to each other.
And it's even said that Napoleon had a tiny telegraph system
with him when he took to battle.
But this one is clearly proven, and this one clearly
demonstrates that hackers are opportunistic.
And why do we need zero tolerated IoT
devices require prevention, preventative security controls
rather than detective security controls.
Why you need prevention to make sure that the device
is not acting as a jump host stepping stone into
your network. We have seen, for example,
HVAC administrators directly connecting
from the Internet into a network. They want to make
sure that IoT devices will not be ransomed.
We have seen that due to the geographical
reasons and situation with Russia and Ukraine,
some OT devices are ransomed as well.
We have seen lateral movements. Think for example, the mass
terminal hack propagation attacks. And if you are
unfamiliar with propagation attacks, it means basically
that an infected device is looking for other devices to infect
and imposing a big risk to a company.
We have seen IoT devices stealing sensitive information.
Think, for example, of the IoT fish tank hack in
the US casino. Nobody was assuming that
the IoT fish tank that had a smart thermometer,
that the thermometer was being used as jump
hose to steal sensitive and extract sensitive information from the
network. And we have seen IoT devices
being utilized to start the cyber kill chain.
So the first one is prevention. The second one is making
sure that the IoT device is safe. Mitigation of
physical risk, no misuse or no accident.
The third one is preserving. Remember that I
started this talk with making sure the device keeps on working
as intended. You need resilient IoT devices.
For example, your ring doorbell has a different security posture
and approach than an MRI or an
infusion pump in a healthcare environment. And yet they all,
both the ring doorbell and infusion pump hold sensitive
information and require sensitive and security
preventative security controls to keep the sensitive information safe.
Here we have an overview of the threat landscape 2023.
And let's go over IoT one by one.
Here we see the RTU, the remote terminal unit.
Gostec was the first one to claim that they
ever in the world had encrypted an OT device,
an operational technology device and this telephone.
This device is used in energy companies and
it was ransomed and displaying a code f
booting. Here we have the Cyborg with the colonial pipeline.
I'm sure you all heard about it. The colonial pipeline
was not specifically an attack. IoT was just basically
exploiting unpatched vulnerabilities in a vulnerable
VPN system and shutting down operation,
also causing a massive impact. Here we have
the rice cameras. They had backdoors so they could
be utilized to open a referral shell, allowing device
takeover,
exploiting authentication and so forth. Here we
have cyber warfare as well. Was the danish
ot infrastructure that was vulnerable
due to siteshell devices that were not patched.
Remote code execution could be done. Burf overflows and
account takeover with the sandworm and the candy wiper.
Here on the bottom we have also the sandworm and the candy wiper.
And they caused a massive outage. In Ukraine
there was a blackout. It was immense. In March. Here in
June we have the propagation attack and lateral movement
of the airsofts proxy botnet. And I think this is so
funny because they were posting a picture of themselves,
that they were the Airsofts administrative
team. They were selling high quality proxies,
meaning compromised IoT devices from doorbells,
garage doors, industrial IoT devices,
and later even mobile phones. And they were exploiting
known vulnerabilities and weak credentials. And weak credentials
is also really very high risk for
IoT devices because there are lists out there on
the Internet. What are the default password for IoT
devices, industrial IoT devices or ot
devices. And hackers. Criminals are using
those lists to do automated attacks
ot environments, specific countries for
example with cyber warfare. So combine the weak
credential list and the default passwords with showdown
or Google dorks, and no good can come out of it.
So that's something that's really important. Here we have the Whitehead
research, the experts for cyber news. It's something really
nice. They took over almost
27,000 printers, and they didn't do anything
malicious. The only thing they did was forcing
the printer to print out a five step guide how to
properly secure your printers. Because printers
are often IoT properly secured in small to
medium businesses, and they are always used
as stepping stone into the network if they are not properly secured as well.
So this clearly demonstrates why you need a
zero tolerated security architecture. And I really understand
the challenges when it comes to securing IoT devices.
They are complex interconnectedness.
There's a massive attack surface, and the devices
vary from vertical industry, from a smart
home to industrial IoT, and they have
small hardware resources and how to secure that.
So they flourish in hardware capabilities. And there is
no standardization whatsoever. There's no devices
heterogeneity at all. And what about
the data that's on the devices or being processed by
those devices? And maybe you didn't know,
but there are three types of data. The first one is data
address. That's data on the device itself. Think,
for example, a ring doorbell and a recording. The recording
is on the device itself, and ideally it should be encrypted.
Then we have the data in transit. Think for example, the ring
doorbell again, and it's sending a video over to
a cloud instance. And then we have the third one.
That's the data in use. And the data in use is the most
vulnerable data. It's very easy to override.
And criminals can do remote code execution.
They can allocate memory because that's the most vulnerable.
So you need to man it up. So I understand those IoT
device manufacturers because they have to constantly balance
between efficiency, functionality. And that's why
we need resilient security architectures
and strategies. That's why I'm advocating for zero
tolerated architecture. And guess what?
It doesn't benefit only the security itself. It's also
building trust in IoT devices, and it gives you
ease of operation with improved profitability.
As stated before, higher turnover, increased efficiency.
Because we detect issues in a very early stage.
If you comply and harden the device from
within security, you will detect issues in a
very early stage. The second one is regulations.
You comply with global regulations,
not regulations here in the EU, but also in
the US, because they have key elements and I will
address those key elements later on. But you can make
sure that if you have incorporated IoT
device security embedded on the device itself, you will
comply with those regulations like the US trustmark
for example, in the US and the EU, cyber resilience XcRa
in the EU. And the last one is business continuity
with improved reliability, making sure the device keeps on
working as intended and that there's no harm done whatsoever.
The device is resilient for all kind of attacks.
And here you have a clear distinction what the landscape
look like for an IoT device manufacturer. On the factory
side we have the development and how to maintain
a huge amount of source repos, build and release management,
you name it. It's a huge and daunting task.
In the middle we have the device security root of trust,
secure key storage, things like that. And on the
right hand side we have the market challenges and
the market is very competitive. You have the constant
balance between cost and functionalities and how do you
scale and how do you make sure that you don't fall victim
to supply chain disruptions? Also a big challenge.
And now we see something new on the horizon. We see
mandatory regulations and you don't want
to get a fine reputation damage
whatsoever. And guess what? I told you before we
looked into the global regulations and all
those regulations have key elements. Here you have an
overview of worldwide regulations, but they all
address key elements. Things for example like
secure access and secure access control. Do you have
the correct permissions? Are you allowed to log in?
Then we have the authentication and authorization.
Is there a login protection? Is there a brute force
mechanism in place if they want to brute force, for example,
with the known vulnerabilities and the weak passwords to
see if they can get into your device. And we see the data
protection, how do you make sure that sensitive data
is really properly secured?
So let me uncover some astounding facts from last year.
The NIST is assigning all kinds of vulnerabilities to
security flaws like risk impact, likelihood,
you name it. And when I started working as an engineer
25 years ago, we were already in the panic
code. If there was a critical vulnerability of
eight or seven, we were in panic mode.
We should do something. But the last years we
see a lot of critical vulnerabilities
ranging from nine to ten. And ten is the highest as
you can go. And ten means immediate action,
patch, remediate, disconnect, you name it, you should
do something to eliminate that potential risk.
So that is putting organizations at risk. And if
we do the math and we count it down to a day. You'll see
72 vulnerabilities a day, but eleven critical
that you should address. And how do you make sure that your
device is secured not only today,
but also tomorrow? And that's why you need a
zero tolerant security architecture to make sure that
your device is hardened from within and secure
tomorrow as well. That's why I'm advocating to really
build resilient and trustworthy IoT ecosystem,
not only for end users, but for businesses enterprises.
Because we need those principles of zero tolerance
and zero trust. And here you can see it starts from the device itself.
You want to make sure that business continuity is
okay. You want to have the trust and user confidence, the regulatory
and legislative acts that you should address. And you want
to make sure it's reliable, scalable,
interoperable and profitable, and so forth.
That's why I'm advocating for zero tolerated architecture.
Saving our toasters and possibly the world.
There's another thing I would like to share with you, the Ericsson Drexler's
Grey goo. And please take a look at his book
if you're curious, and he stated that there
will be IoT assemblers, and an assemblers
is being programmed to eliminate all organic matter
in the world and to copy itself. So I'm sure
that if we have the zero tolerance security architecture
in place, break will not happen.
Combine that with AI and machine learning and the right code of
ethics, we will have a great future.
I would like to conclude with a quote of Robert Mueller, the former
director of the FBI. There are only two companies,
those that have been hacked and those that will
be hacked and checkpoint. The company that I'm working for
is adding a third one, those that have been hacked and still don't know.
Thank you so much for attending this session. I'm happy to connect with
you. Feel free to reach out if you have any questions. And thank
you so much.