Hello everyone, I am Sir Terkiazensola and it
is a pleasure to present this presentation with you
today. When we gather like this, I am
reminded of the power of connections and the opportunities
they bring and I introduce myself and
share a bit about my journey.
I am an entrepreneur and visioner and lifelong
learner. I am always seeking new ways to
innovate and make a positive impact on the world around
me. With a background in
data engineering, I have had the privilege of working on various
projects and collaborating with talented individuals from diverse
backgrounds. Throughout my career,
I have been driven by a passion for excellence and determination.
Push the boundaries of what is possible.
Whether it's building and managing successful startups,
mentor inspiring entrepreneurs, or supporting
causes close to my heart,
I always strive to make a difference.
You may have seen my LinkedIn profile also that I have
been involved in projects related advanced visualization.
These experiences have not only shaped my professional
journey, but also reinforced my belief and transformative
power of determination, collaboration and innovation.
But beyond the arts and accomplishment, what a truly
motivates me is the desire to make a meaningful
difference in the life of others. I am
committed to using my skills and souls for the greater
good, whether it is creating jobs,
supporting charitable cultures, or empowering
individuals to pursue their passions.
As I stand before you today, I am excited about the
possibilities that chance to connect with
like minded individuals who share my vision
for a brighter future.
Together, I believe we can overcome challenges
and opportunities and create a world where the innovation
thrives and everyone has a chance to
succeed. Let's get started with the presentation
advanced regulation techniques for complex data
and then my first slide is my introduction.
Firstly, today's topics are hypervolt data
visualization interactive visualization interactive
visualization with the visualization large data set in this combined
and data visualization best practices.
By the way, the introduction of healing,
I want to give importance or benefits with lesion.
For example, the first healing is and has to understand
visual presentation of the data, make complex information
more accessible and understandable. Charts, graphs,
maps, provides and clear insights to trends,
patterns and relationships between the data,
allowing for better cooperation and analysis.
But the second, I think is increased engagement.
This means the visualizations are more engaging and
memorable than the raw data and textual
information. They capture attention and facilitate
the communications leading to the greater engagement and
retention of information among the organs.
At the third hearing, I mentioned the efficiency of communication.
So visualizations serve as a universal
language that unscathed barriers such as language
and expertise. They enabled efficiency communication of the
couple of ideas. From the fluctuating collaboration at the
knowledge sharing among the diverse audiences.
This is the main item of the efficient of the communication.
At 40 there is faster insight I think
at the visual presentation of the data enable faster
insight and understanding compared
to traditional data analyzed methods.
With the interactive visualization user can dynamically
explore the data, drill down, drill out into details
and gain the real time insights. Is accelerating
the decision making process also and top
five heading is storytelling is the most important
one. I think all the storytelling is data visualization
allows for the complete storyteller by
presenting data in a narrative format.
Visualization helps convey the story
behind the data, evoke emotions per se,
the audiences to take action based on the
insight present. This healing is more important for
the time because best practices becomes more
important. I am going to the next slide for
the types of data visualization.
Pie charts, ant histograms, lines, area charts, gantt charts,
network diagrams, read diagrams, scatter portals, all are
data visualization types. If you are in process of
trying to build a story, persuade a group of people
or better understand your data, consider creating
some sort of visual presentation to guide your truths
and truths of the others. So these resolutions
type are become more important to tell this story.
What is the most popular one, do you think giving no,
not I am giving Bangladesh and pie charts more
important terms and the most popular ones
elation types, the other forms
line graphs at histograms, pivot tables,
explodes, scatter plots, radar charts,
bubble charts are the other one and
so I'm going to my next slide. Interactive isolation
refers to used to dynamic user driving feature in the data
visualization to facilitate exploration.
Analyzes the understanding of the complex data sets.
Some benefits of the interactive visualization focusing
on how it enables users to highlight the
keys and explorer may filter the data.
I will mention some important points of manages interactive
visualization firstly enhance of
the engagement. I think interactive isolations captive users
attention and encourage active participation
by allowing them to interact with the data in
real time. It's important. I think the
second one is the deeper understanding. Users can
roll deeper into a data and gain a better understanding
of the pattern's trends and relationships by the interactive
exploring different aspects of the datasets.
It's an important second important one.
Third one is to customize the insights. Writing interactive
visualization empower users to customize their analyzers.
Selecting, filtering and manipulating the data or focus
on specific area or interest or regional
odds and efficient communication.
It is easier to communicate complex insights
by allowing users to interactively explore the data or
discover the key files at their own.
Also and maybe users alternatively
refine their analyzers and hypothesis by dynamically
adjusting visualization parameter,
exploring alternative means and testing differing
scenarios. Users also actionable
decision making by the interactive isolation
for the data driven decision is more important making
by providing end users with actionable insights
and enabling them to explore various options and outcomes
interactively.
Highlights about key insights I'm
going to mention for example, interactive visualization allow users
dynamically highlighting key insights by adjusting
visual elements such as colors,
size, shape or opacity
and draw attention to important data points or
trends. Users annotation is
important also they can add interactive annotations
and labels or tooltips having specific data points to the
region of the interest to provide context and convey
key insight efficiently. Focused and
empathy is another feature that
enables users to focus on a specific area of the data by zooming
in or zooming out or panning or filtering
out load information, making it easier to identify
key findings and enabling user
interaction. Enabling for user interaction
is exploring and filtering data, filtering and
filtering a section or the interactive isolation allow
users to filter and select specific data point category
or the time period of the interest, enabling them
to focus on relevant subsets of data and
also drill down and drill up. Users can drill up
into detailed data on the higher level summary or
lower level summary by interacting with
the heiress or using interactive
navigation controls for this item.
Sorting and ranking is more important for the interactivity
feature, cause the enabled users to dynamically sort
and run data based on different criteria such
as a value or alphabetic order or frequency
or identify the top performer outlier or trends
and another shuffling is the exploratory of the analyzers.
Interactive visualization support exploratory analyzers by
using users to dynamically change isolation time and
adjust the parameter. Experiment with the different view
to encourage hidden patterns or relationships in
the data. So interactively,
isolation empowers users to engage with the data in
meaningful ways, enabling them to key insights
and highlighting key insights. Explore and filter
data efficiently and drive actionable
insights and make informed decisions.
This interaction islation is most important for
the large data sets at the my
next slide is main focus on presentation
visualization technique for the complex data presentation
in our increasing data driven world,
the ability make sense of vast amounts of data
is paramount for informed decision making
and extracting valuable insights.
We should devolve into various techniques that enable
us to tackle the challenge of the visualizing latch
datasets effectively. We should explore
how these methods help us distill the complex
data into meaningful presentations. For example,
sampling and aggregations are foundational
techniques that allow us to extract relevant
insights from large datasets efficiently.
By selecting a subset of data points and combining
them into a summary of the statistics, we can
capture the results of the entire datasets while reducing
the computational overheads and so should
think about the reduction of technique
as methods enable us to decrease the volume
of data while retaining essential
features. Whether taught the principle
of unlike or summarization statistics like
medium, we can still fix data
here to ocs representation.
But what about handling high dimensional data?
That is where the data clustering and
dimensionality reduction come into play.
That is where the clustering and the dimensional reduction
clustering techniques clustering techniques help
us group similarity data points
together, while your dimensionality reduction
method can enable us to visualization high
dimension model into lower dimensional
space. This approach empower crust
explorer and understand complex data structure
more efficiently. And lastly, I should
explore hierarchical and nested with relations that
provide a hierarchical view of data and a
low form drilled out exploration. Three maps
nested pie charts offer insights
into relationships and structure with
the data, enhancing our understanding of
complex data sets.
Conditioning large
data sets requires a multi phase
approach by employing techniques
such as sampling,
aggregation, data reduction, clustering,
dimensional reduction and here are
you can unlock valuable insights and
drive informed decision making. For this,
let's talk about the main subjects of this slide.
Sampling the first one is the sample and aggregation technique.
And this one this is the first
sampling involves selecting a subset of the data
points from a large population to present
the whole. There are various sampling techniques suited
to different type of data and analyze scores.
Also random sampling for example involve
selecting data points randomly from the population,
ensuring that each data point has an equal chance of
being selected. Approach is useful.
The population is homogeneous and
no specific pattern or structure to consider.
Strophite sampling, the other
hand involves wide population
into distinct structures based on certain
characters. For example, age,
location and the sampling of each
rattle separately approach ensure
that each subgroup of population is adequately
represented in the sample, making it useful
when there significant variation within the
population. Once we have our sample, we can
use aggregation technique to summarize the data and
extract meaningful esis. Aggregation involves
combining multiple data points into summary
statistics or aggregates.
Yes. For example, we can calculate the
average count of a certain variable
in the sample to get an overall picture of
its tuition or behavior.
Aggregations help us to reduce the complexity
of the data while absorbing portal
trends and patterns, making it easier to
analyze an inter patent. The second
one is better reduction at the summarize
reduction technique aimed to decrease the volume of
that data while retaining its essential
features a one common approach to data reduction
is dimensionality reduction which involves reducing
the number of the variables and features in the data
set while preserving its essential structure.
Table of two component analysis is a popular
dimensional reduction table that identify
the most important assets,
variation in the data and x two
and lower dimensional space.
Another approach to data reduction is feature
selection which involves selecting a subset of
the original features that are most relevant to
the analyzers and features. Selection methods
can be supervised or pansparized depending
on the weather can into account target variable
in the data set. Once we have reduced
the dimensionality of the data, we can further summarize
using various techniques.
Summary statistics such as median,
standard deviation and percentiles
provide insights into breadth
and data at histograms
box graphical presentation
that visualize the distribution of the data and
have identity outliers
for the data reduction and summarization and
the broadband is using data clustering and dimensional
reduction. The clustering techniques group
similar data poised together based on their
features and attributes. Clustering helps
us identify natural patterns and structures
within the data chats cluster of the customer,
a filler buying behavior for example or clusters
of the genes are similar aspiration
profiles. There are various clustering algorithms
including enemies, clustering, error code clustering
and dust based clustering each suited to
different types of data. After analyzer calls.
Dimensional introduction technique transforms the high dimensional
data into a lower dimensional representations while
preserving its essential structure.
These techniques are particularly useful for
vision high dimensional data into all
three dimensions making it easier
to explore and interpret place data
sets and fourth one
kubernetes nested isolation. This represents
data in a hierarchical structure where elements
are organized into and giant relationship
provide a natural way to explore hierarchical
data structure. Chance of organizational and
maybe lasted categories or sonomist also
remaps on board charts.
Dandograms plots are examples of the
hierarchical regulation that help us
islamic the relationships between different level of the
hierarchy and identity pattern
and also structure within the data nested
with display the data within multiple layers of
the nested structures allowing users to explore
relationships at the different level and the different
regularity. These visualizations provide a
hierarchical view for the data while enabling drill
down and drill down explanation. Nested pie
charts, nested bars charts and nested tree maps
are the example of that help
us with relating the complex data structure and
uncover each size at the different level of the abstraction.
This is the visualization highlights
I mentioned. I'm going to go
the next slide also and
data visualization best practices first
healing is your audience.
This is the important one understand
who will be viewing your visualization.
Tailor them to their level of expertise.
Important for practice because you
must know your audience. And the second
one is right visualization tool.
Right visualization technique is much more
important after the audience. It is a visualization
that efficiently communicate your message
and highlight the pattern and trends in
your data. Consider factors such
as the data type and the message you want to convey.
Audiences familiarity with the different visualization types.
It's the best choice. And the third one
tell a story interactively and structure
your visualization to this story that
has a clear and panic story technical
flow maybe a narrative art and to guide
viewers the data at highlighting
design is also important and trance of the way
also and the fourth one is simply unclearfy.
And please keep your visualization simple and
focused avoiding a cluster and unnecessary
elements. Use clearing labels annotations
to help viewers interpret the data accurately
and the conclusion of my presentation my
presentation is about me.
At the end of my presentation I
have a key takeaways. This is so important
clear data for good information.
This one and second
story storytelling
for the best concept and the third
one is goal and more functionality
for the more function based and the third
one is a visual form for
metaphor. For the best metaphor.
These items are the c none of
the successful data visualization narratives
aware of these items.
As I read our presentation of
advanced isolation techniques important to
recognize that journey is ongoing knowledge
and insights gained. Thus the
boundaries of the utilizing isolation
to unlock the full potential of complexity data sets.
Thanks my sincere graduate for engagement
and attention throughout this presentation and
have a wonderful day. Goodbye. Thank you.