Alright everyone, let's kick off the session with a brief introduction about
what AWS code pipeline is and what are
the advantages of AWS codepipeline. Some of the
key components involved and how a sample
pipeline looks like. And then we can jump off to
our demo session, we can go to the AWS
console, and then we can see how we
can create a simple codepipeline.
First things first, let's talk a little bit
about AWS codepipeline background and why
it's advantages to use it and what
are some of the stages involved. So the AWS code
pipeline is a fully managed, continuous integration
and continuous delivery service.
So it's a cloud native solution, fully managed by AWS
and highly configurable by users. It helps
automate release deployment pipelines for fast and
reliable application and infrastructure updates.
Traditionally, a large number of organizations use
third party tools like Jenkins for software development.
So code pipeline offers native solutions to those organizations
which are already heavily invested in AWS
ecosystem. Coming to the advantages of AWS
codepipeline, first and foremost is obviously the
integration with AWS services. It offers
a native out of box integration with many
of AWS services like lambda,
EC, two, S three and cloud formation.
Now, I'm just comparing it with one of the popular third
party tool Jenkins throughout this session.
So if I were to contrast it with Jenkins,
the main difference would be that while the integration with the cloud services
is possible, it usually requires third party plugins and
additional setup, potentially introducing more points of failure or
compatibility issues. Coming to the next
crucial aspect is obviously scalability.
Since it's part of the AWS suite, it natively scales according
to the demands of the deployment pipeline, so there's no
need for manual intervention, which in itself kind of like ensuring
consistent performance even during peak loads.
Jenkins on the other side requires some
adjustments, such as like adding agent nodes or reallocating
resources, which is both time consuming and resource
intensive since we
need some dedicated personnel taking care of that.
Continuing with the other advantages of AWS
code pipeline, we are going to touch upon the maintenance,
security, the pricing and long term value.
So maintenance wise,
since AWS code pipeline is a managed service,
AWS handles all the updates, patches and backups.
So this ensures that the latest features and
security patches are always in place without us having
to do much there and us
having to not manually intervene there.
Jenkins, on the other hand, requires periodic manual
updates, backups and patching,
which can kind of introduce compatibility issues
or security vulnerabilities, which kind of
demand regular monitoring and adjustments.
Coming to the security aspect of the deployment pipelines.
So one of the advantages of
using AWS solution here is the comprehensive
security model, which we are able to leverage the
features like IAM roles, secrets, managers and
other fine brained controls like service roles.
So all these can be natively tied up to the code pipeline
itself, which kind of ensures robust security standards
along with your other tools. So on the Jenkins
side, if you were to achieve a similar security
level, it requires additional configurations,
plugins and tools, which in itself can again
sometimes introduce more vulnerabilities and
unnecessary complexities and the pricing and
long term value. Since AWS operates
on like a pay as you go model, you only pay for what you
use. So this can be cost effective,
especially if we have variable workloads.
On the Jenkins side, the software itself is open
source, but however, maintaining the Jenkins infrastructure,
accounting for all the patching and keeping it up
to date itself can add up over a long
period of time when you consider the time and resources
invested into it. So that kind of
wraps up on the key advantages of
AWS code pipelines. Now we can briefly discuss
into the working of code pipeline and then
we can jump off to a demo session.
So the key components involved in a codepipeline are
the conceptually similar to any other deployment tool
where you have a source stage. You either have
your application artifact or some deployment assets
which are going to run and deploy the source code,
and then you have a build stage, which is an optional stage,
kind of like for compilation and an object
generation which is eventually going to be deployed.
So the example is AWS code build here,
and then you have the deploy stage. It's the main deployment
stage where the generated artifact
that you supplied or the output of the code build stage
is kind of like deployed in this main stage.
Again, AWS offers multiple tools
that can be plugged into this stage. So code deploy
is one such tool that we are going to look at today for
the demo. So code deploy
ECs blue green deployments are some of these things that can be
plugged into this particular stage. So this is how a sample
pipeline looks like we are going to look at the demo
and get a closer look of it. But the bottom part
is what makes up a code pipeline code
commit action. And the code repository is being pushed here to
an Amazon ECS, the elastic container service,
and which is eventually deployed via
a code deploy ECS blue green action in this
pipeline. So now let's jump on to
the AWS console, and then we
can see how we can create a simple pipeline.
All right, this is the AWS console home.
So you have a list of all these tools here. So let's
go to the AWS code pipeline.
So on the left side if you see it shows like multiple
substages that are kind of associated with the code pipeline,
like the source, the build stage, and the
deploy stage. So it gives us the ability to configure
those stages using these sources
here. So the first thing like we discussed is setting
up the source repository or the deployment artifact.
So I already have an S three bucket that I
created and I have an object there.
So we'll be using that. For the
purpose of this demo, we are going to skip the build stage since we
essentially don't have any compilation or object generation,
but the code deploy stage is necessary
stage. So let's spend a couple of minutes
on the building a code deploy stage, which then
we'll later plug into the code pipeline.
So for the code deploy. So we need to
create an application configuration.
So let's go to the applications. So right
now we don't have any applications, so we can just
create a sample application, say Java
application and the compute platform. As an
EC two, the application configuration
is created and now within the application we need to
create a deployment group. So the deployment
group essentially kind of like configures which
all EC two instances you want to deploy. So that
is determined using this deployment group.
You can add more settings like how many EC two instances you want
to deploy at a time and what would like a failure scenario
look like. Those are like more advanced settings,
but you can explore this on the code deploy
resource page. Let's enter a sample
deployments group.
So the service role essentially needs to have the
code deploy access, which I already created one,
but you can fine tune based upon the level of security
you want for your deployments codepipeline.
And all these are environment configurations.
For filtering the EC two instances related to the deployment
group, it's often done using the tag associated
with the EC two instance, for example, like I want to deploy
to all the prod hosts, like Env
is prod, so it filters out all those such
instances and it creates a deployment group.
And at the end of the day the code pipeline deploys to
that. So all these settings, you can leave the
default ones if you don't have any necessary
changes. And then we create the deployment group.
All right, the deployment group is created for a sample application
that we have now we can go and create
the code pipeline. So right now we don't have anything created
in this section. So we are going to create a brand new code pipeline.
Say sample pipeline again,
you can leave the default options here. It's going to create a
service role by default. If you don't give anything,
it looks like the service role already exists.
Let's see if we can delete this so
that there's no conflict. So if you go to the
roles. So this is the IAM page where
you have all your service roles and the policies.
So I'm just going to remove this for now.
It's probably there from a previous time.
So we are just deleting an existing role.
All right, we deleted that. Now I
believe we should be able to create a sample pipeline.
And the source is going to be s three. And the
bucket is going to be this. Just need to
enter the object inside this bucket.
We can quickly take a look what's the object inside there.
If you go to the s three, and if you pull
up the s three bucket, see that there's an object.
So take this and plug it into the object
key here and then build.
We are going to skip. And then the deploy,
we just configured the code deploy right.
So we are just going to plug in all those. We just created the Java
application and the deployment group and that's
pretty much it. So once we hit the create pipeline, it's going
to take a couple of minutes here and
voila, the pipeline has been created.
It triggered the source and this
is how the pipeline looks. So if you have a valid source
artifact, it kind of triggers that and then based upon
the deploy configuration, goes and deploys there.
So this is how a sample pipeline looks. The scope
for this article next would be for the session,
would next be like exploring more on the code deploy
side and what is needed there.