Hi everyone, welcome to this session. My name is Arfan Sharif.
I'm a technical marketing engineer at Crowdstrike
and I work in the Falcon
log scale team. And today I'm going to be covering it's
a log eat log world. Crucial log management skills
for devsecops.
Let's have a look at the agenda for today and what we'll
do is we'll start with Devsecops and talk about the fundamentals
around that area. We'll talk through the fundamentals
of logging and then we'll tie the two together.
So we'll look at what boxes can log management tick
for devsecops. We can then go into data
types and data sources which may be relevant for Devsecops.
We can then talk about best practice and we'll wrap
up on why log management is important for
Devsecops teams.
So just to start, let's talk about Devsecops fundamentals,
particularly about why do you need Devsecops?
So with the rise of cloud technology as well as containers
and microservices, this has really fundamentally changed the way
that software is developed. And in a DevOps culture,
APIs and configuration tools are needed to
break down the infrastructure as code, which can then
be adapted and revised by the development team.
So this allows developers to provision and scale the infrastructure
without involvement of a separate infrastructure team.
And there's been a growth of serverless functions,
microservices and containers by developers. And this
has introduced new security risks that now
need to be accounted for. So if you think about the architecture
of cloud native applications and it requiring
its own infrastructure, sorry, its own unique approach
to security in terms of policies and controls,
this additionally having to meet
the challenge of maintain a consistent security approach
across data center and public cloud environments where
the applications are being deployed.
And it often have to contend with lack
of maturity of tools for securing containers, API vulnerabilities
and other issues. And if you think about the VM or
virtual machine based cloud deployments, security tools and best
practices are a bit more mature and they offer more full
feature detection and visibility into threats and performance issues.
So at the moment we can't say the same about cloud native environments
that are leveraging microservices and containers. And despite these challenges,
cloud native approaches offer an opportunity for businesses
to transform the security alongside digital initiatives
to support the organization and to reach the
peak of DevOps organizations.
So to reach that peak, organizations need to find a way to
embrace cloud native application development securely and
making security an equal consideration alongside
the development and operations. It's really
another important aspect. So coming
back to how does Devsecops work?
So, in a DevsecOps approach, security is
built into every part of the DevOps lifecycle
and the key tactics they involve,
incorporating infosec professionals
or security experts within the DevOps team to oversee
the security agenda within the development lifecycle.
Also elevating the security skill
set of the it team so to understand cyber risks
and best practice so that each member can consider implications
during the developers process and writing code with
security in mind, and then also automating
security processes and tasks such as
testing for security exploits to enable an
agile workflow and developing security processes
and tools that are specifically designed to
support agile technologies such as cloud containers and microservices.
In a traditional DevOps approach, security testing is often
done near the end of the development process and
typically once the application has been deployed to production.
And this is because security related tasks such
as secure configuration and management, and also vulnerability scanning,
they historically have been known to be fairly time
intensive and essentially they slow down the development process.
Let's talk about logs management fundamentals.
So if you're not familiar with log management itself, essentially,
if you think about a log file, it is a text file where
applications, including operating systems, write events and logs
show you what happened behind the scenes when it happened.
So if something should go wrong with your systems, you've got a detailed
record of every action prior to the anomaly.
Therefore, log files make it easier for developers, DevOps,
sysadmins and secops to get insights and identify the root
cause of an issue with applications and infrastructure.
And logs are also useful when systems behave normally.
You can get insights into how your applications react and perform
in order to improve them. And there are many different sources of
logs as well as log types, and we can
talk about some of them as we go through the session.
So now we've had an overview of both what boxes can log management
tick for devsecops. So log management provides insight into
the health and the compliance of your systems, platforms and applications.
Without it, you'd be stumbling around in the dark, hoping to pinpoint sources
of performance issues, bugs, unexpected behavior and other
similar issues, and you'd be forced to manually inspect multiple
log files while trying to troubleshoot production issues.
This can be a painful, slow, error prone and expensive process.
It's not often scalable either. Log management is especially important
for cloud native applications because of their dynamic, distributed and
ephemeral nature. So unlike traditional applications,
cloud native applications often run in containers.
They emit logs to standard output rather than writing them
to files. So this means you don't have the default option
for manually grepping logs. Typically, you'd capture the logs
and ship them to a centralized log management solution.
Essentially in a nutshell, log management enables applications and
infrastructure operations to troubleshoot problems and allow
business stakeholders to derive insights from data
embedded in log events. And logs are also known as the key
sources of data for many use cases,
whether it be it operations,
DevOps and security analytics.
And log management solutions bring
in data from many different areas behind the
use cases we've just discussed. So let's just touch on
some of the areas that log
management will help devsecops with. So firstly,
let's talk about monitoring and troubleshooting. So if you think about the most
common and core log management use case is a software application
and infrastructure troubleshooting. So this is one of the most popular historically,
and log events go hand in hand with application monitoring and server monitoring
developers devsecops, sysadmins and devsecops. They utilize
both metrics and logs, so they're alerted
about application and infrastructure performance and health issues,
but also to find the root cause of those issues. Having a good
log management tool really helps to reduce the meantime to recovery,
which in turn improves the user experience and
long downtimes. Or even applications and infrastructure that perform
poorly can also be an impact on the
organization and the business.
Therefore, log management plays a critical role in reducing
the meantime to recovery. Logs provide value beyond
troubleshooting though. So if you have structured logs, either from the source or parsed
in the pipeline, you can extract interesting metadata.
For example, we often look at slow queries as an example,
and we can answer lots of questions depending
on how we query the data.
So as
touched on, there's a vast amount of data that
can be brought into these platforms and you have the ability to query them based
on your requirements and your use cases. And it can be
across use cases. So it doesn't have to be structured logs,
they can be unstructured logs too, and then you can structure them as you go
along. Now, if you think
about improving operations as applications and systems become more
and more complex, so does the size and the difficulty of the operation.
Secops, sysadmins and devsecops would have a harder
time monitoring everything manually, thus requiring more
and more financial resources. And by logging, you can identify
trends across your company's infrastructure,
allowing you to adapt early and come up with solutions that prevent fires
versus having to put them out. Another aspect
is actually better resource usage. So when it comes to system performance and
system overload is also like a dark cloud looming over
an organization. And you need to keep in mind that
it's not always the software at fault, but rather the requests that
are going to the server or the environment.
Whether there's too many requests or whether they're too complex,
your system can have difficulties dealing with them.
And in this case, log management helps you track resource usage.
And you can see when your system is close to being overloaded, so you can
allocate enough resources for it to cope.
Performance monitoring can let you know if there's any performance
issues, for example, if the nintieth percentile
queries are slow and they may also reveal bottlenecks.
So if you think about many requests going
to a particular node or a particular server, this can cause some
issues. And essentially log management will help
you identify the issue and
be a step in addressing the problem that you're facing.
Now, most of the above actually ties up with user experience,
but this is one of the biggest headaches people report is
with applications, long response time to query or
not getting a response at all is a major challenge. And log management really
allows you to monitor requests at any level, whether it's at API
level, whether it's at database level, to see what's actually underperforming.
And this enables you to step in and understand why
something occurred and helps you keep in control of your user
experience. And last
but not least, security and compliance. So there's
no such thing as too much protection when it comes to it. Security and
log analysis is really at the heart of any log management
or SIEM solution. So from network system and audit to
application logs, anomalies may
signal an attack. And logs really help security administrators diagnose
anomalies in real time. So they provide a live stream
of log events. So whenever someone's attempting
to breach,
to carry out a breach or impact the environment, whether it's from the inside or
an external threat, you'll have more insight into what actually happened.
And if you have enough data, you can go back in time
and look at the trail the adversary may
have left as they went through the environment and
then compliance the best way to ensure compliance and security and audit
requirements is to create a logging and monitoring policy. And a log management
policy sets security standards for audit logs,
including system logs, network access logs, authentication logs,
and any other data that correlates a network or
system event with a user's activity. And more
specifically, it provides guidelines as to what to log, where to store the
logs, how long you keep this data, how often it should be
reviewed. So compliance is a really key
area when it comes to log management itself.
Now let's go into a bit more detail and just talk about
some of the logs which are relevant for devsecops.
So in this example here, on the left hand side, we've got many different
areas of it which would generate data,
and some of these are much more relevant to devsecops than others.
On the right hand side we've got the more relevant ones. So we've got things
like network data. And as we interact with mobile
apps and web apps, websites, we generate a lot of network traffic.
And this could be network routers or switches and so on,
they can generate lots of data.
And unlike servers and application logs, even cloud logs
which are in more modern formats,
network data historically has been based on
Syslog in terms of the format and the transmission.
So that's a common method of working with network data.
You also have server and application logs. So traditional sources of logs
like servers and applications running on those servers. The kernel
limits log messages such as which drivers it loads,
and then there could be system services.
It will help to show which services are up and available and which
ones have been stopped. And then you can have information and context
around when a user logged in. And this information really
helps you diagnose stability and security issues.
As for applications, you can have, let's say
you've got NgInX web server, or a Java web app running
on a Apache Tomcat, or a PHP application running in Apache
web server. They'll emit various information, whether it's
errors or debug logs events, or whether it's HTTP status
codes. And some of the logs use standard formats.
It could be like a common log format, while others use various
custom formats including structured logging. So you typically would
have like key and value logging as well as JSON
logs as examples. If you write your own application,
it's often suggested to use a structured logging method,
which is easier to case down the pipeline.
One area which is really relevant devsecops would be container
logs. And nowadays more and more applications are
deployed in containers, containers and applications running inside
them. They're a big source of logs, and unlike
traditional applications and servers,
they're quite promiscuous. So a container orchestration framework
like Kubernetes moves containers from host to host,
adapting to demand and resource availability. And an average
container's lifespan can be really short. On top of
that, you don't have the practice to SSH in
and tail and grep the logs to troubleshoot.
This was deemed a bad practice in the cloud native world and
hence it's more important to have log management solution where
all of this ephemeral data can reside
and be available. Should you need to troubleshoot or
carry out an investigation, then beyond that
you have mobile devices which are ubiquitous, so you might not think of them
as sources of logs because you can't easily access system or application
logs on an iOS or an Android device.
So there's often limited disk space and unreliable network means you can't log
verbose messages locally and you can't
assume that you'll ship the logs to a central location
in real time. In spite of those challenges, there are ways to
get that data in and move them
into a central log management solution.
Now, security has a large role to play in all of
this data and it really depends on the
use case and what lens you're using, even if you go
beyond security. So you could be interested in performance
and uptime and availability, or you could be interested in
getting security context from that
data. So logging is quite unique from that perspective as
you can look at it from the lens you choose to,
there's a variety of data, you can look at it from many different aspects.
Now let's just touch on some Devsecops best practices
and organizations they want to unify
it operations the security team and application developers need
to make security a core component of the software
development workflow. So in order to enable devsecops,
the organization should do some basic things.
Firstly, they should ensure that security testing is incorporated throughout
the development cycle and completed by the development team.
So this was often something that was left right to the end, so it really
should be incorporated into the full process. They should enable
the development team to manage and solve issues found during
the testing. And to that end,
there's a few Devsecops best practices that
help ensure that the organization can shift to this
new agile method. Essentially, it would be good to dedicate
an info security leader within the Devsecops team, and many teams enable
a devsecops mindset by including a security champion within their development
teams. This is someone who has expertise in application security
and has taken a more advanced training in this field
than most of the team, and this person can review security fixes
to make sure they're correct. So if you involve your security
champion or team early in the development
process, integrating best practice from the initial phases of development,
and really being able to upskill
the IT team to ensure security is infused throughout every aspect
of the development lifecycle itself. So this
is really essential. And given that
this wasn't a core responsibility of a DevOps engineer in
the past, it might be necessary for the organization to upskill staff
to support these new requirements. Organizations can work with
their cybersecurity partners to develop a curriculum or training
to really advance with this process.
Now, some of the other key aspects that should be
considered is really automation and recurring security processes
should be automated logs analysis is really
the next part of the process. So from a security viewpoint,
it's vital that devsecops engineers in charge of the production environment
understand how to read and analyze logs.
DevOps teams usually lack the knowledge and the ability to identify security
breaches or hacking attempts from log data.
And having a log management tool capable of reading and parsing logs and
distinguishing between permitted and unauthorized activities is really
crucial for both tracking each action within the system
and creating confidence in the application and the devsecops process.
And essentially, you want to make sure that you ensure
you log data from all the relevant data sources that
you have to give you context over both
devsecops and secops.
So let's just wrap up on this particular subject
and talk about why log management is so important.
So logging and log analysis are really essential factors in achieving
and maintaining application security. They're also essential for
the success of a Devsecops organization as a whole.
One of the biggest concepts in agile development is the idea of continuously
evaluating the application, and examples include
continuously testing the application to catch errors at the earliest possible moment
in the development cycle, or continuously integrating
code into a common code base to allow for detection of code
integration issues at the earliest viewpoint
possible. Now, there's no different for logging and log analysis
as it relates to application security. While developing the software, the engineer
should be sure to write code that will log information regarding any
relevant security events, such as authorization
failures, maybe even successes and input validation
issues. In doing so, the developers will
help build the foundation for a secure application
as they integrate their code in a common code base to be deployed to
test environments that mimic the specifications of production environments.
Logs provide excellent visibility into
potential security considerations and related
to newly developers software. So most importantly, logs come
from every system in your pipeline. A CI server could
be used to identify anomalous code and operations,
and log files from application tests and builds provide an opportunity to evaluate
how software runs and find potential vulnerabilities before deployment.
And logs from production environments can help in the detection of
security issues that may arise from a running application.
The other aspect is really about faster processes and investigation.
So if we think about when a security issue arises
in production developers, IT engineers, and security engineers,
they need to react quickly and efficiently to resolve problems.
And logging is critical for enabling fast and coordinated responses.
Waiting on manual sharing of sensitive data can slow down the
reaction times. But when every stakeholders can
get the data they need from logs, access to the information
is no longer the weakest link in the security incident remediation process.
And I guess lastly, to touch on the final aspect,
which is better collaboration, you can't practice
devsecops if your developers, IT engineers and security
engineers lack shared visibility into the state of each application
release, in which features are coming next and
which features are actually coming next and therefore need to be secured.
So you could try to gain this shared visibility by asking
various stakeholders to collaborate manually. They could
hold meetings, talk on Slack, or so on. Yet having
some live collaboration is always helpful, so you're unlikely to
achieve complete shared visibility through manual collaboration alone. So that's
why it's critical to leverage logs as a single source of truth
to provide visibility into the pipeline. When security engineers,
developers and IT engineers have access to log data from across the pipeline,
they can use that data to assess its state,
and as a result,
they can find security issues better.
And these may be overlooked
if a centralized solution isn't used where
multiple teams
or people within a team are having
the same access.
Now, I just like to talk about
Falcon log scale. So this is CrowdStrike's log management
solution, and essentially what this
allows you to do is bring in data from your entire estate.
So if you think about cloud
data as an example, it allows you to bring
in that type of data, as well as other telemetry multicloud
tools from your data center, from your network, from your applications,
and then it allows you to work against that data, correlate that data,
and you have the ability to configure alerts
for any errors or issues. And on the right
hand side, you can see the number of use cases that you can work with
Falcon log case. So it helps across use cases such
as DevOps, it operations, security and compliance, as well as business
analytics.
Now, Crowdstrike also offers an all in one
cloud native platform that simplifies monitoring,
detecting and acting on potential cloud security threats and vulnerabilities.
As an increasing number of organizations adopt devsecops,
they're looking for ways to ensure cloud native application security,
protect business critical workloads and streamline operations.
And the solution combines multiple tools and capabilities into a single
software solution to minimize complexity and facilitate DevOps and
devsecops team operations. Further, it offers an
end to end cloud and application security
through the whole CI CD application
lifecycle. I'd like to thank you very
much for joining this session, and if you
have any further queries or you'd like to learn more about
Falcon log scale or any of Crowdstrike's
other solutions which help with challenges
that devsecops teams face, please have a look on
our website or reach out. Thank you again.