Hello and welcome to my talk about securing your pipes with the taco.
This is all about automating governance. When we work in these highly regulated,
complex organizations, or even when you're just working in an organization that's
trying to work out, how do I properly manage changes to regulation,
changes to security standards, changes to how I
govern my organization and how do I align those into the way I operate.
So this is all about those kind of things. So stay tuned and I hopefully
we'll have some good advice and guidance for you. So,
to get us started, I like to run things through in terms of
a talk map. Now, these talk maps are basically a way for me
to communicate with you, like what's going to happen in the talk and
where we're going to be going with it. We'll start off with an introduction.
We'll talk a bit about risk and where some of this comes from. We'll talk
about how you can go about automation governance, and we'll have some conversations
about why and how a taco can be helpful in
these circumstances. And after all that, we can
wrap up and have some q a so who am I? I'm Peter
Maddison. I'm a coach, a consultant, and a founder of a consulting
organization called Zodiac. We help organizations adopting
new ways of working. My particular speciality is
around DevOps strategy and in particular around lean controls and working
with senior executives around understanding how do we
marry up the need to go fast with the need to understand how
to do that safely. And so
we'll start this off with the idea that in this fast
paced world, our customers are demanding instant gratification. We have these little black
rectangles, and if we don't get what we need, we'll immediately go
somewhere else. It's very easy for us to change where our providers of
services are, and it's very different from the past where we started.
In a world where technology was very expensive, we had to spend a lot
of money on it, and it was a case of having to make
some very strategic decisions around how that money was spent to
really now we went through a period where it was about investing
in the capabilities, the networking of the capabilities, how we can then put different
parts together to create these more distributed systems into one now where
the customers really drives the story. It's all about how do we generate
customer value? How do we focus on the customer ensure that we're building
organizations and systems that are able to accelerate
this delivery of value.
And there's lots of tools that will help accelerate value delivery there's
all sorts of ones that I'm sure we'll be talking about a lot in this
conference. But one of the problems that we often see is that
efforts to adopt these tools fails from a lack of clarity.
It fails because the organization itself isn't
easily able to adopt these practices that go with those tools
and bring them in and start to change the way that they operate.
There's a lot of complexity in these environments. There's a lot of moving parts.
We've got a system that works. That system generates revenue, it generates value,
and it works as it is. So when we come
in and start to introduce new ways of working, it can be very disruptive
to the organization. And as we start to pull on the different threads,
it can be very hard to see what is happening and what the impact of
this is going to be. So that's all about the introduction,
talking about complexity and risk and value delivery, and how do we help start to
manage this in a fast moving environment. So where to begin?
So a lot of this work came out of consulting work I've done into
some large banks where we've gone in and they've started
on a DevOps journey. They've been wondering, how do we go faster? How do we
go further? How do we start to take the learnings we've
initially got and start to move those out into the
rest of the organizations? Because when we
start to introduce these new ways of working, we realize that it brings
in an awful lot of other types of risk. And risk
is something that as human beings, we tend to be
a little allergic to. So we need ways of being able to introduce
change more rapidly, get used to change. Change is the norm. We want to make
that something that we're able to deal with. And we spend a lot of time
focusing on how to do this in the software delivery space.
But we sometimes forget that we also need to apply this to the other
external dependencies, which may influence that. As we look at
the different things that are coming in, both from a regulatory, a compliance
and architectural design perspective, looking at new ways of doing things,
how do we see these
things changing the way that we do our delivery practices?
So when we look at devsecops, one of the key things that
we see is that there's a lot of focus on the loops that
we can bring to the table. And sometimes we remember
to talk about how these tools will modify the processes and how we do
our delivery practices. And quite often we forget about people,
and people are often the piece that's causing a lot of the complexity
unintentionally, a lot of the time. But as human beings,
as we interact and we look for different ways of finding solve problems,
when we look at something like DevOps, we can sometimes, especially from
a technology perspective, get far too focused on the tools and the processes
and the practices and forget that we need to work with each
other to make all of this work.
And all of this is easy, right? It's easy to adopt change, it's easy to
bring new things to the table. I mean,
that's why we have these conversations. And in my
experience we've managed to deliver some amazing results,
but it's certainly not been easy. There's work to be done
here as we look at how do we need to change the
way we think about the work that we do and how we interact with each
other in order to make this successful,
because we're adopting new paradigms, new ways of working where
we have to bring in new knowledge, new ideas, and all of
this while we're meeting the same obligations and existing commitments
that we've always had to meet. And as humans go through change,
they go through this cycle, they go through this cycle of saying, hey, that's not
going to apply to me. We're not going to be able to put devsecops onto
the mainframe. We've got too many regulations
that we need to make sure that we comply to. We can't possibly do that
here. It's not going to happen. I can ignore that. It's not my
fault to complaining like why are you doing this? This is terrible. You're going to
break everything if you do that. Everything's going to be horrible. You're going
to expose all our data, you're going to crash everything to,
please don't do that. Please don't do that to me. To sulking about,
God, this is terrible, it's awful. I can't believe you did
that anyway. And to finally accepting the change and
as change agents, one of the things that we're looking to do here is we're
looking to bring down this change curve. How can we make this easier
for people to adopt? How can we make it easier for people to
look at the processes that they have today and all of
the things that they know that they're dependent on all of these requirements that they
have to ensure, get embedded in the way that they do delivery and make this
easier for them to deal with. So working
with organizations, we come up with these different models, these different practices,
and we draw all sorts of different ways of doing this, from champions programs to
understanding how do we integrate these different tools together to start to build
out these pipelines that will already have some of the
capabilities and regulation baked into them, to understanding how do we
create, go from this small organization that's
trying to bring in more change and accelerate the change in the organizations to
being able to create the snowball effect of accelerating that beyond
the initial successes that we see.
And one of the things that we found when we were working with these banks
was that we keep hitting this wall, we keep hitting this wall where we
run into regulation and compliance and audit,
and where it's not enough to be able to say,
yes, we know that by adopting these practices, we can deliver faster and better
and safer, and it's better for our customers, and we know we can actually make
things more secure. We also need to ensure that we're bringing those practices
into the entire system, into other parts of the system that
also we need to consider around security,
compliance and regulation.
And one of the things that we found is that when we look across all
these different areas of the organization, we find that
things get lost in translation, as the Rosetta stone here
shows the translation between hieroglyphics through
ancient Latin to help us understand these things. So developers,
for example, are speaking one language. They're talking about how do we
make sure that we don't build the wrong things, that we're able to understand
what's happening there. The testing is
ensuring that we don't find the wrong things wrong, that we don't waste
our time chasing after ghosts, that we've actually got effective
quality built into our systems. We've got operations
trying to manage and ensuring that we're meeting any external
slas that we may have, and ensuring that the systems are
operating the way that we want them to operate. We've got security who's
concerned about making sure that we're properly identifying
problems and they can often get in the way of what we need to do.
We got compliance, who's saying, well, we've got these external
regulators, and we need to make sure this is broken in. How do we ensure
that we're properly identifying and demonstrating that
we are compliant? And we got architecture that's saying,
well, we can't do everything, and if everybody runs off in a million different directions,
then everything will start to fall apart. So you've got all
of these groups who are all trying to ensure that we
create a safe delivery environment and that we
reduce the risk to the organization as we accelerate
our value delivery practices. But they're all talking different languages.
They're all talking using different terms, different terminology,
different concepts, different models and visions of the
way that things should be done.
So in order to create alignment across these groups, we need to
find ways of coming to some common understanding about
what is it that all of us mean when we talk about
delivering safety and creating safety in the way that we deliver.
You can have the best security team and the best delivery team and still
fail at being able to deliver securely.
And this is because if we're not aligned in our vision and aligned in
how we go about creating value for our customers,
then we'll very often end up standing on each other's feet and not actually
accelerating the way that we deliver. So we have to move from this idea of
being the department of no to the department of yes. And this
is how you do it. How do we get from the point of view that
we as security, our job is to make sure you don't do the wrong thing
to we as security are here to make sure you can deliver securely.
So the other side of this as well is we need to
ensure that we're measuring correctly, that we're looking for incremental
improvements, that we're, as we set out on this journey,
as we look for, how are we going to go about making the
right changes to the organizations to ensure that we're embedding safety into
the delivery system, that we're quantifying what
it is that we're doing, that we're not just saying, hey, we want
to be safer, but we're saying this is how we're going to determine that we
are safer. This is how we're going to determine that we are
actually doing a better job of managing risk in our environment, and that
the practices that we're introducing through all of these different areas are actually
helping and not hindering our ability to create value
for our customers in a safe manner.
So we've talked about the introduction, talking about value delivery and how that can be
accelerated, and we've talked about risk and the different things
in the environment that cause risk and how some of the things we need to
start to capture and come of the problems that cause it and the
friction across the organization. So now let's talk a little bit
about how you can go about automating governance.
So one of the big problems we see, especially in these
large organizations which are regulated, is that the
parts of the organization that are responsible for ensuring the
safety of the organizations are very often not aligned to the
delivery teams that are looking to adopt DevOps practices and accelerate
the way that they deliver. Very often they're sitting off in their own silos
trying to interpret what's required from a government regulation
and try and translate that through to ensure that delivery teams
have the right compliance standards. But often those delivery teams have very
little visibility or understanding. And even when they do,
they had call up somebody in this much smaller department who's looking
at all of these standards, and they get told, well, here's a book
of standards. There's 300 pages. You got to go through these
other 200 pipes which are referenced over here. And if you can find the section
that applies to the problem you're looking to solve, then good luck.
And then if you call back, you may not even get the same person because
you may be dealing with somebody else. And it's very, very hard to
find the thing that is applicable to your
particular problem that you're looking to solve. How do I find the
standard, the control objectives that are actually
going to apply, and how do I then interpret those into my
team, into what I need to do in order to ensure that I can deliver
value without having to go through massive committees and
all sorts of other frameworks to do this? Common examples being things like
ARB. And there's another organizations I
was working with, TRDs, and then followed by ARP,
where you've got a technical review board, which will then take you up
to a larger architecture review board, which means that it could take
three months, or it could take six months, or it could take nine months,
or it could take twelve months to even come to a decision about,
are we allowed to try and do this?
Is this the right way to go? Is it okay if we do this?
So we need to come up with better ways of being able to understand
and apply these rules into
our delivery teams in a much faster manner in order to
be able to operations in the modern world.
So let's start with the pipelines, because if we want
to take a look at DevOps, this is a good place to start.
And this is a generalized pipeline that comes from some it revolution
white paper that I highly recommend reading, and there's a link to
later on in the talk. So if we look at these as some of
the primary parts of
the pipeline where we could start to introduce controls,
if we only put our controls in, in the production deployment,
then we're never going to be able to understand how secure
we need to make sure that we're introducing controls all along the pipeline,
that we're properly introducing and managing our delivery practices.
And there are lots of things that we can do at each stage in order
to be able to manage and secure the pipeline.
We can introduce even things like linting and SCA
into our source code repositories. We can look at dependency managing
using artifact repositories, using scanning for open source
vulnerabilities. We can look at tools
inside of our building, look at SAS and dast capabilities as
we move through the pipeline. All of these enable us to gather more and more
information about the state of our code and feed it back into delivery
team to help them understand what changes they need to make to become more secure
in the way that they do delivery. And when
we're looking at running the pipe, we can think about what
are the different stages we can do. We can talk about as
we define what we're going to do.
We can turn that into code and everything needs to be written in this code.
We can then use our CI systems, create build results
which we review. We can look at our quality tests, we can look at artifacts,
and then we can run another CI run, perhaps to run our organizational tests.
We'll start with doing peer reviews, but as we look to move forward,
we'd look to say, hey, how can we remove any other manual steps
that we have, if we have manual steps around the build results,
can we look at pair programming and other capabilities to start to think about
other ways to satisfy these requirements, to reduce the number of
manual touch points there are as we deliver? Because what we really want
to do here is we want to reduce the cycle time. But in
order to do that, we've got a couple of dependencies here
we need to be able to look at how do we reduce
what we're delivering to a small enough component piece that it's easy enough for us
to test? A good example here is that doing
peer reviews or code reviews,
although it's a great idea, it's one of these things that
in order to do it well, you've got to have a small enough amount of
code to review at any one time. If somebody only submits
their code every two weeks, they might have a few
thousand lines to review. And then it becomes very, very easy for things to get
missed. It becomes very easy for things to get rubber stamped as they move through
the pipelines. Far better if you're deploying
on a daily banks or less than a few hours, so that
there's less to review and it's faster to get
through the process.
And as we look to move forward, we can start to say, okay,
well, how will we audit all of this? And one of the values of being
able to automated pipelines is we can pull information out and we
can make it visible. When we did this at one of the banks,
we started with hygiea, but then found that keeping
hygiea up to date with the various other tools
that it needed to feed from was a lot of work in and of itself.
As the tools upgraded, hygiea needed to be upgraded and that took
time. So we switched to pulling logs out of each of the different tools
and using that to build dashboards, which we could then radiate
useful information back to the organization to help say,
hey look, we went from an average deployment time of
once every six months down to one of once every month, and we did that
in a six month period. So this is the kind
of automation you can pull out and radiate to help guide
and improve the automation within the organization.
So it's not just for the auditors, it's also very powerful tool
to help with the adoption of new practices in the organization.
One thing to realize here is that even as you build out these new
capabilities and building a paved road
and an automated pipelines is great, but you also need to consider that
it's not going to be for everyone in the organization. It becomes an easy button
for those parts of the organization that are struggling to see how
to adopt these new practices, and it can make it very,
very easy for them to start to get started. But your faster moving
groups are going to want to accelerate far beyond anything that
you could build out as a pipeline. So what we
do here is we can provide them with a set of guidelines and I'll
talk about these in the next section. But if we give them a set of
this is what you need to be able to do in order to build can
appropriate pipeline. These are the things that need to be embedded so that you can
do continuous delivery. If you don't do these
pieces, if you don't want to come and use ours, which has all of that
embedded, then go ahead and build this out yourself. You want to try other
tools, other capabilities. We're here to help, but it's
an invitation we're not going to inflict on you. We're not going to tell you
to come and do it our way. It's a paved road, but you
do have the option to try and do it. There's some other way if you
want to.
This is important too, because we know that we don't want
to provide just one way to go places. We need to create the ability to
innovate. We need to decide that hey, maybe we want to go in a different
direction, maybe we want to go on a longer route because we know that we
could possibly discover something of value in the process of doing it. We want
it to behave more like ways and help
us direct us in the right directions. But we want it to be something that
is not just singly controlled by come centralized team.
If you try to do it that way, then you will almost certainly fail
as you try to bring in these new practices.
So automating governance. There's a lot
of pieces that I'm touching on there as I'm pulling the threads out
and I'm happy to talk about them in more depth as we move forward.
It's always hard to cram so much into a talk like this.
It does sound like a lot of work and there is a lot of work
to be done, but here are some good pointers to get you started.
Think about it as not getting. It's not about keeping considered off your back.
It's not about satisfying a checklist. Think about it about
collaborating to create safety in your delivery practices.
Think about how do we make the safety parts of
the organization, all of these governance parts of the organizations,
a part of the solution, not a part of the problem. How do we get
them to be the departments of enabling safe delivery and
do that using come of the practices that I'm talking about?
Don't try and boil the ocean. Start small, get one team working
and then grow from there. Don't try and do all of this all at once.
Find one team or one thread, one value stream where
you can start to align your safety teams to that
value stream and start to understand what are their needs, what are their
controls. How can we start to create an understanding of
risk management for that particular value stream and align
on that and then grow from there? And three
is focus on the conversation. Make sure you're engaging
leaders in this conversation. Focus on needs to be,
not on the tooling. It's not about have I got the next greatest product embedded
into how I do this. One of the common mistakes that I see organizations
make is they bring in a new piece of tooling that generates
a whole bunch of reporting, but it also generates an
awful lot of false positives and lots of other information
and lots of other reports. But it's not being fed back into the delivery
teams in a meaningful way. So it doesn't really add any value.
It doesn't actually help with the intended
purpose of helping the organizations properly
secure their pipelines. The tools can be extremely valuable and
they are necessary. It's just bringing them in in such a way that we understand
and see that benefit. And we create the appropriate feedback loops into
delivery teams so they know how to respond to the information that they're being given.
So we've talked about a bit of an introduction about the
context of the world that we're living in today. We've gone through risk and
DevOps and how we look to try and reduce the change cycle to
make it easier for people to adopt these practices into heavily regulated organizations.
We talked a lot about automating governance and the different kind of
things that you can do and things you can embed into a pipeline and some
of the things you should avoid when you're starting along
this journey. And what sort of things are helpful as you go
through automating your governance practices. Now we're going to move into a
little bit about what taco is and how that was one of the
things that we brought in that was quite useful.
So when we look at how do we model
or create a model for us to be able to understand
and give to the delivery team so they know what it is they need to
do, we need to find a way of
communicating this, creating that common language as to what
does a safe set of delivery practices mean so
that I as a delivery team can understand
and apply it to my context without necessarily having to wade through 300
pages of documentation. And there's multiple elements to this. One is
this taco piece, which is on the tactical how do I understand
what I need to do? And then there's the
control piece of how do I make sure that as controls
change, I have a pipeline for those controls and that they
are also being embedded and fed into delivery teams, and that they
are being translated into the context of the team's need.
So this is in that lean control space, and we'll talk a little bit about
that, too. So the elements of taco are traceability,
like identifying what happens in the pipeline. This is critical both
from an operational perspective and from a security perspective and a compliance
perspective. So it's something we want to do. So looking for chain of custody
of code as it moves through the pipeline, which we can do in a number
of different ways. Looking for tagging things back to a Jira
ticket is one way that ive done this in the past. Other ways is
by if you've got consistent tagging and you can pull things with the logging
layer that can also be a great way to be able to start to create
that test results. All is about ensuring that
test results are visible and that we're not hiding them off in a separate repository
that nobody else gets to look at, that we're properly collaborating to bring
quality into the delivery teams.
Deployed version is in fact tracked. So we're looking at what is the version of
thing we deploy and making sure that changes are properly recorded,
which we also need both from a security and operations perspective,
securing the delivery process, looking at the access, who has access to code?
Who is managing that code? Looking at is the source code properly accessed
and managed? Are we tracking the creator? Are we signing code
so that we actually can trace who it was that did what in a
particular pull, request, build once, deploy many,
ensuring that we are creating immutable artifacts and deploying them out,
and only allowing pipelines to then do those deployments and
compliance. Looking at validating the payload in the pipeline,
are we properly doing managing peer review? Is that properly being birded
into the way that we do things? Are we scanning the code? Are we scanning
the artifacts? Are we managing the data and the way that it's delivered and
operations monitoring and securing after the fact, looking at validating the target
of where we're deploying, validating the quality and checking
it works and watching it live. And all of these tie
nicely back into the compliance standards that we're looking to map.
So this works very well with other compliance frameworks
and allows us to create a straw man that we could then marry
into the organization. So what we did from here, and we created a set
of auditing ones to validate that it was working,
is we said, okay, so if we had this set of standards, what else
do we need? What else is missing? What else could we
embed? And then we embedded this into the standards within the organization
to ensure that if somebody meets the set
of standards that we've defined on taco vendor and the
risk profile is correct, then we
can properly believe that the pipelines is doing what it's supposed to
do and that we know how to measure for safety in
that pipeline. And my daughter drew a lovely
picture that I like to include here. So the first version
of this was this spreadsheet where we said, okay, we want to understand, what is
the purpose of this? Why are we actually introducing this
as a control at all? What would the control be?
Where would the artifact be? Where would it be stored? What happens when that
control is passed? What happens when it's failed? And who's going to own this.
We could then map that because out of the spreadsheet and create the picture.
And I will end. If you sign up at the end, I'll send you a
copy of the spreadsheet. We then could also design
and run workshops up this. We like looking at
how do we help people understand where there might be risks in how they're doing
things today, and what might possibly be ways of overcoming that
and introducing controls that might mitigate some of the risks that they
have in their delivery systems today.
The ultimate result was a wonderfully complex diagram that
looks like this, but simplifying this out, it would
look like build, validate, test and deploy. And not as in
the terms of SCLC. There's no gates here. This is more about identifying
where are the areas that we can appropriately apply controls
so that we know what to do and identify them. So this is
more about understanding the phases that a software delivery system
goes through and then being able to identify what controls
we apply into each of those areas. And when
something goes wrong, what do we do when that happens?
One example of this is Capital one has a very similar sort of
sets of controls which they applied say, hey, if you
want to be able to get to controls, delivery and deploy through our pipelines,
these are the sets of things that you need to be able to do.
When we look at things at scale, across large teams with 20,000
developers or large deployments,
you've got every version of every type of software in there. It's impossible to
say, hey, everybody, do things this way. You'll never get to
that utopian version of complete compliance. So you
need to provide instead frameworks which work
for people to be able to adapt to their needs
while being able to provide this understanding
of how do we make sure things are operating the way that we want
them to. Nationwide also has some
great practices around this, applying lean control into the way that they do delivery.
And I'd highly encourage reading through some of their things and looking
up some of the talks that they've done on the topic. They've also created some
great dashboards on the way.
You can pull out information about how they've moved to
a model where you can put these control tickets into the delivery
team's backlog, so they could then solve those, and you can see how many of
them being dealt with so that, you know,
are we appropriately adapting to managing risk
in our delivery teams? So,
to sum this up, it's not about DevOps on its own,
and it's really not about devsecops. Either.
It's really, and John Smart put this very well about risk,
dev risk, ops risk. We're talking about how do you embed risk
into the DevOps practices and just make it a part of what we do.
I mean, we can't really come up with another term for
this. It's about how do we make sure that these
safety elements, these governance elements within the organizations
are properly aligned and enabling our delivery practices.
So we talked about an introduction, we talked about value delivery
and all of the way the world is changing and complexity.
We talked about risk. We talked about how Devsecops
aims to help, but it also introduces change. And change
in itself is risk. And we've talked about the problems with
communication you see across different parts of the organization. We've talked about automating
governance. We've talked about the different things and practices that we can introduce to
help with automating governance. And we've talked about why and
how to make a taco and how a taco is a minnow to help you
understand how you can start
to marry these and scale them out across your organization to
understand what is a good safety pipelines,
what does that look like? What are the things we want to see in there?
What do we as an organization agree is necessary in order for us
to be able to allow a delivery team to deliver software?
So to wrap up, it's really about not
using the same thinking we've always used around securing our delivery
pipelines. It's about how do we create a common understanding of
what good looks like and start to move from a model where
the compliance teams and the security teams
and architecture teams are sitting outside of the delivery teams
and are trying to dictate to them how they should do things, because that just
creates confusion, because they're talking a different language, they've got a different set of
priorities, a different set of goals. So we need to create tighter
alignment into the way that they operate. Safety teams
is a great way to do this, like looking at how do we start to
align small safety teams to value streams which
exist with delivery teams embedded in them, where they can develop
a stronger understanding of the context of that delivery.
How do we create that common understanding of what good looks
like? And this is where things like taco is a good model for
that, in that you can use that as a way of creating that common
language, that common way of talking about what do we mean when
we say that we are creating secure
and compliant pipelines in our organization.
Here's some great references. I'd highly recommend looking
these up if you're interested in this space and how to take and apply
some of these to your organization.
And so let's review. Let's go
from talking about apples, oranges and bananas to talking about tacos.
And this is the idea here is it's
really about, let's go from talking about all of these different terms
and terminologies and start to talking about a
common way of talking about what we mean by safety in our delivery.
So you should hopefully now have a common
understanding of how we get to a good pipeline,
if not what that good pipeline looks like yet. That's a longer conversation.
Safety is about behavior, not just tools. To truly get to
safety in your organization, you also need to be creating a culture
where it's okay to say that, whoops, something went wrong, that it's
okay to admit that there was a fault or there was a mistake, and that
it isn't necessary to get 300 approvals before you can do anything or move
anything forward. Ways to automate
your software delivery compliance so when we look at how we
can pull information out and create reports which are
aligned to compliance, that's one way. But when we also think about,
as we look to take and understand what we
have to do from a compliance perspective and translate it into
the context of the delivery teams, this means we can also now
measure and quantify what that looks like, which will allow us
to not only be more compliant in the way that we do delivery,
but make it easier to be compliant with what we do.
And I'll leave you with the Rosetta stone and a quick
thank you to everybody for attending. I hope you enjoyed it. There's only one
question required on the survey, which is, hey, did you like this?
And if you want to, you can leave your email there and it will
send you a copy of the taco spreadsheet and some
useful links as well. Okay. With that,
I'll sign off and say thank you very much.
It's been a pleasure and hope to see you all soon.