Hi everyone, my name is Josh Stella. I'm the CEO CTO
of Fug. Fug is a company that secures cloud
infrastructure structure toand checks it for compliance. For the last ten
years, I've been living purely cloud security,
both at Fugue as a co founder, also at AWS,
where I was a principal solutions architect focused on national
security. So that's a little of my background. Oh, I'm primarily
a software developer and software architect prior to being a
founder. Okay, today we're going to be talking about locking
down the security of IAM. I'm going to pull my
slides up here. Locking down the security of IAM in the
AWS cloud. The focus today is purely on the AWS
cloud. If you are new to IAM, this is actually
going to be a pretty good introduction because we need to establish
a mental model, an understand of what IAM
is and how you use it if you're more experienced.
I will be getting down into some details and hopefully
this will be a really useful session. Okay. It's mostly
going to be interactive session. Our whole agenda.
I have five slides. Most of this is going to be hands on at the
whiteboard, hands on at the console. Okay.
But I do have five slides and they're really. But why
cloud security is different than traditional data center
security. We're going to do that deep dive into securing
IAM, and there will be, of course, Q A.
All right, so why cloud security is different? For lots
of reasons. I'm going to really focus on a couple of these as they relate
to this topic we're discussing today.
So the way hackers approach
kind of the attack surface of the Internet has changed
over time. In the old days, sort of the Hollywood version
of hacking, which, by the way, does still happen. The hackers
pick but an organization and then find a way in, right? So they
identify the target and they search for vulnerabilities, or create
vulnerabilities through things like social engineering. This does still
happen. Some famous examples of this are
the north korean breach of Sony's network, Sony motion
Pictures. They made a movie they didn't like and so they went after them.
But far more often, it is what we're calling
here the cloud exploit strategy, which is the hackers are using automation
to just look at every single object they can reach via
the Internet and looking for misconfigurations very often on
cloud, looking for things like IAM and s. Three misconfigurations,
IAM being the permissions that are granted, but also bucket policies.
There's a lot of things they're looking for. And then their automated
tools essentially give them a shopping list that they
can then use to go pick, but who to attack from.
And some of the really high profile big attacks, like the capital
one breach, that's how that was done. She didn't target capital
one. Her automations discovered that. Now, John Breeden here
is saying that within a few hours of deployment,
these assets are being scanned by hackers and bad guys.
We think that is an extremely rosy estimate.
It is more like five to seven minutes. So what that means is
when you put an object, a resource, a cloud resource,
out onto the public cloud within a few minutes,
it has been examined by hackers who
intend to discover its vulnerabilities. And if it has vulnerabilities,
they've probably found them. So a whole lot of these breaches probably
go unknown and unpublished, or unpublished toand unknown in some of
the notable breaches we've seen in recent years. The only reason
the victims found out about the breach at all is because
the hacker bragged about it on social media or something like this,
even months after the actual breach occurred.
So it's a brave new world. All right, so the
main attack surface in the cloud is
not the operating system of servers that you have hosted in the
cloud. It's not the configuration of your applications or the
security of the applications that's much more relevant to the data center.
You still need to do it in the cloud, but you have this new attack
surface in cloud, which is the vast majority of hacks,
which is the misconfiguration of the cloud resources themselves.
And very often in the press, these things are portrayed
in overly simplified ways. I've been interviewed
with some frequency by journalists trying to get their head around how
a bunch of data was exfiltrated out of s three. And they
always go into it thinking, well, the s three bucket was left just open to
the wide world. Very often it wasn't. There was some combination,
usually using IAM,
misconfigurations. CTO, get to the s three data.
Okay? So at Fugue, we cover all these different compliance standards
for you more than anyone else, ISO, toand, NIST and
HIPAA, GDPR, CIs, et cetera, et cetera. And what we've learned is
that those compliance standards, even in their most conservative
interpretation, which is how we do it at very. I mentioned I
have a national security background. We are exceptionally paranoid
in our interpretations. In a good way. We're going to look for everything.
But even when you do that, a lot of the techniques that the
hackers are using are not caught by those compliance standards.
A lot of stuff is, and you want to use those, but a lot of
things aren't. So even if you're sitting there thinking, well, I know IAM
is secure because I've examined it against the best practices
and I've used the AWS IAM analyzer. IAM analyzer.
You probably still have highly vulnerable IAM configurations.
It's hard not to. And they're usually missed by security tools,
okay. Because they're not recognized as vulnerabilities. One example,
and I'll come back to this, is there is one action
in EC two. It's not even can IAM that allows an EC
two instance to change which IAM policy applies
to itself. A lot of people have this turned on by accident.
That is a massive breach potential to it,
okay? Same thing with things like s three list in these IAM permissions,
really, really dangerous in production environments, really dangerous,
but probably looks fine to your security tooling.
So what this means is, well, also they're only apparent in the full context
of an environment. You can't just scan an Infrastructure's code file and
say, we're good. You have to look at when that terraform or cloudformation
script runs and does a deployment or whatever you're using, you're doing it
manually. The same thing is true. You have to look at it once it lands
in these overall misconfiguration of the account, the know
the whole combination, because that's what the hackers are
going for. And the primary network that they're using
is not the TCP IP network, it's the IAM network.
And I'm going to explain what I mean by that later. But IAM forms a
network in the cloud, okay? Because of all these issues,
these things are really easy to overlook, and that makes them incredibly
common. And here it says, increasingly exploited in major
breaches. I am not aware of any major breaches that were
not carried out through misconfiguration of cloud resources.
You look at some of them, I have a whole talk, I give on thinking
like a hacker and walking through details of breaches. But when you look at,
like, for example, the Uber breaches or the Imperva breach,
and sorry, I'm naming names because you have to be able to go, look,
these things know Imperva is a great company. These make a great product. They had
a great response to their breach where their CTO went and put a blog post
up saying exactly what happened. And guess what? It was poorly managed configuration
of IAM keys almost always is. So IAM is central
to getting cloud safe. All right, now that's
the slides we're going to go to actually digging in.
All right, let's do that. So we're going to start. You might feel like this
is kind of remedial, but I think it's actually going to be quite useful.
I'm going to start with just the AWS documentation on
understanding how IAM works I mentioned earlier. I believe
it is just absolutely essential for you to have a
functional mental model, a way to really understand what's going
on in IAM and in cloud security in general.
And to do that, well, we'll start with understanding how IAM works,
and then we're going to go to the whiteboard and iam going to show you
a simplified form of this.
All right. This diagram, to me is not super
helpful. It's literally correct. But that's not really
useful to forming a mental model on how to think about it. It does show
us a number of things, like principles, firing off requests,
needing to get authorized, and of course,
authenticated and authorized CTO perform actions on resources.
But this diagram is just really, really muddy and it's easy to
get confused with it if youll don't already know what they're talking about. But I
do want CTO talk some about the terms here because we're going to use these
as we go to the whiteboard. So the first term we're
going to focus on is principal. So iam a
principal toand in AWS, a principal
is an actor. If any of you used to do uml, it's an actor.
Okay? That can be a human, it can be an application, it can be
a component of infrastructure. All right. That principle are the only
things that can create requests. There's an asterisk
on that, but don't worry about it. Simple mental model. Right. Something we can work
with. So you got principals who do actions. They do them by
sending requests. Okay, so a request is what it sounds
like. I'm going to skip over those things because it's just
authentication and authorization, in that order.
Yeah, the authorization is where you're going to find
out if you can perform an action. So you've got a principal performing
an action on, typically a resource,
which is an object. Okay, let's switch to the whiteboard. I lost my whiteboard.
Let me get it back and let's switch to it.
Okay, cool. My whiteboard's working. Excellent. All right. You never know when
you've got these fancy, complex setups. Okay? So let's just
get some of what we just discussed onto this whiteboard.
So we have principles and we have actions that's
doing things in the cloud, and we have resources.
Okay, there's a reason I'm putting this on the whiteboard, because a
lot of the complexities in designing secure IAm are
not constrained to just the policy understanding. They're really
cases by the interactions of these things.
And there are lots of scenarios that you can get into where
you can overly compliance things, or worse, you can make them overly
permissive and therefore dangerous. So we're going to talk through really
two scenarios today. The first one is where the
principal is a human, okay? And this is what most people
think about. It's kind of a hunchback human. Sorry about that. I'll call him Josh,
since he's got a bum shoulder.
I don't have a bum, just, anyway. So human
actors are who most people immediately think about
when they think about IAM, identity and access management. They're thinking about know
active directory users with their authorizations. Right.
And that is one type, and we are going to cover that. But we're also
going to cover applications as principles,
or components as principles, resources as
principles. So for example, we can have an EC two instance
or a container or a lambda. I always get it backwards.
Let's see if I get it backwards this time. I hope not. Might have.
Anyway, you can have an EC two instance acting
as a principle to do things like read out
of s three. And the way you define that is through IAM.
So this is how IAm becomes a network. And the same with.
Same with our lambda function. Okay, so what are
actors? We have a kind of high level fuzzy idea of
that. Well, when you think about the cloud, what you really
have are APIs that you can use CTO,
manipulate infrastructure to create it, or at least
configure it and modify it over time,
et cetera. So creating an EC two instance would
be an example of an action. All the verbs you
can do in the cloud, read from s three, get object
from s three, list s three buckets. So your actions, and there's
a lot of them. For the purpose of IAM, understanding IAM,
I think it's best to not overly focus on
which service things are in, but to just understand that
for any given function that you want to perform in the
AWS cloud, there are a list of actions that
that principle needs access to, and very often those are
not constrained to a single AWS service.
So it's best to think of actions as just a big long
list out of which you're extracting the ones that are the minimum
needed to perform the function, the business function you're trying to do.
There's a feedback loop in architecture here, too, which I'll talk about a little bit.
But actions, let's say like getobject,
create instance list
buckets. Now you can go on the web
and search for AWS actions, and there are thousands
of these things. And that's actually really good design because
it gives you the ability to really scope your permissions down.
But what it does do is put a lot of burden on you to really
understand the actions. And there's a lot of these. That's where things like the analyzer
can be helpful, but it can also give you a false sense of security,
because if you've architected your system in a dangerous way.
So for example, your Ec two instance needs to list s three
buckets. Don't do that, by the way. Put it in a database, separate the
actors. These tools aren't going to find that. So you really
have to understand what the attack vectors are. And then resources are
named things in the cloud. Like there's a service s three,
right? But you have an individual s three bucket. What did I get up to?
Let's call it Baz. Or you have a container
or an RDS instance, a database instance.
Call it my data. What do we call our container? We'll call
it whale. All right, so we've
got our principles, we've got our actions, and we've got
our resources. Let's think about this from the perspective,
first of Josh here, of this guy.
If I'm a user, a human user, I mentioned I'm a developer, so I
need to do things like create instances. Create Ec, two instances.
Okay? So I want to be able to call create
instance. However, there is a
default AWS policy for
all of these actions, and it is deny.
And there are really two walls of
denial. There's the wall of denial between any
principle and any actors. So your default is you get none,
right, good design. And the Other is between the
actions toand the resources. So there's a wall over here
too. And so the mental model for IAM
is poking holes in these walls. Okay, youll need
to get from the left to the right on the diagram, and you need
to do that by poking holes in the walls. And that's what in IAM policy
are allows, or I call them allowances. I think that's the correct English
to poke through the walls of denial. Now,
any deny you can get. So for example,
let's use a different example. Let's use the, well, let's do a list
bucket, all right? Which is different than list buckets
because in list bucket I'm listing the controls
of one s three bucket. In list buckets, I'm looking at what are all
my s three buckets. So let's talk about list bucket
for a second. So this guy got blocked. If I need to poke a hole
through here for list bucket, I want to poke
a hole through here for list bucket. Right. So I can
do that with Iam. I can grant the action
to Josh using a policy to be able
to list bucket by default. You also
then have to say which buckets may Josh list. And very often people
just put star in there, which is actually often wise for
many use cases. We'll get into some complexity of
things like attribute based access control for scoping. But you can also,
in your IAM policy, just enumerate a list of buckets
Josh is allowed to list, and that's reasonable to do too.
So if Baz is one of those, then the
request, which is the thing that caused this whole chain of events to
take place, will work because it got allowances all the way through and
from Baz, will be returned CTO.
Josh, a list of the contents of the bucket.
Right. Seems pretty clear. Okay. So as you're doing
this, your goal has to be to have these
minimum number of these actions. Okay. And even
in the AWS documentation, they will tell you,
be as constrained as you can, least permissive. Right.
Well, let's take a look at that. I mean, that's great to say, but this
is one of the places where people really get burned with
Iam, and it's really easy to do. And every time somebody
gets burned and ends up in the news due to IAM exploits,
I feel bad for them because there is a lot to know and do when
you're dealing with IAM. Okay, I'm on the screen here for the IAM
service and I went to policies. Policies are where you're going to be
effectively defining the allowances
and the denials. Right. Toand you get a whole bunch of
these that are called AWS managed. That means AWS
put them in your account already because the AWS services
themselves need them in some way, shape or form because AWS
services talk to AWS services using policy too.
All right, so let's take a look at one of these policies.
All right, here we've got, you can see here at the top effect
is allow. Remember, everything's a deny. And then here's the
list of actions. Access analyzer, service role policy.
Okay, so this is a policy that's intended to be used by an
access analyzer tool that AWS has. So, what it
needs are these very specific EC two collection
here. These are describe calls. Those are similar to lists in other places.
So describing the addresses the VPC endpoints
describe vpcs. So, vpcs are actually
inside the EC two service. Just a weird thing, a side effect
of how AWS evolved. And then we see some for IAM.
Remember I said at the beginning, usually to perform
a necessary function, a business function, you're going to have more than
one service in your list of actions.
Okay, so here we've got some EC two, we've got some IAM, which is
just getting roles and listing roles. And then we've got kms,
right? For our keys, we've got lambda,
because Lambda is an alternative to EC two. I mean, fugue is
almost completely built out of lambdas, but lambdas are
computational actors. They're principles in here. So we got
that. And you also have a bunch of stuff for organizations, which describes,
obviously, how the topology of your organization, its permissions,
and so on, map out. And a bunch of stuff in s three.
Okay, so you can see here it's a fairly long list
of actions, but you notice in resources,
right, well, resource in this case is any. All right?
So that means any resource that these actions apply
to, it's not scoping down the list of resources here, it's saying any of
them, but these actions are the only ones that can
be called on them. I want you to notice here that this star
is the only star in this policy. Star means any.
Okay? And as you go up here, you're just not seeing big,
broad star cases, and you shouldn't use them yourself.
Iam looking at an AWS managed policy, because these generally,
or often anyway, contain a lot of best practices.
And you really do need, if you want secure iam to
fully understand which actors are truly necessary for
the business function. And limit to that. And I'm going CTO. Explain why here,
now. Okay, well, that sounds simple enough.
Just list the actions you need. Well, why do people very
commonly make the error to be overly permissive?
Let's take a look at this is a policy I'm building for
interacting with EC two. So remember, we're talking about Joshua
user. I needed the create instance. So that's
probably here in write somewhere, right? Well, I selected all of write
which would be write star. And I just said don't do star.
There are 289 write actions in
EC two alone. So somewhere will
be create instance, I hope, right? You would think
create Internet gateway, create image.
See, I don't remember the name of it off the top of my head.
So somewhere in here are the permissions I might need
to use the actions that are needed to meaningfully create an EC two
instance. It's not just going to be about creating the instance, whatever they've called it,
I'll go find it later. It's also probably about like creating an EBS volume
and attaching it and some other objects that other resources.
An EC two instance, practically configured, is a
collection of resources. Really? Okay. So when
you're designing these policies for your users, my strong recommendation,
and that of AWS as well, is to use roles,
not map what are called inline policies directly to josh
these user, but instead create a role like
developer or team a developer
and have in one place that list of permissions of allowances
that are really needed for that developer role. And then if you decide
to change that or evolve it, you can do that in one place and the
managing will be preserved. Another thing
I see that is usually an error in
securing IAM is just proliferating iam policies.
I mean, a lot of folks, I think, look at the fact that AWS sticks
like 700 of these things in your account already and
think, well, no harm in that. I could have another 700 or 1000.
Gets really hard to keep track of. So doing this
is star, okay, that's star. Now you could have star for everything.
Ec two star, right? But we're not doing that.
We're doing here. Ec two, write star. Still do not
do this. Enumerate the specific actions.
I'll give you a couple of reasons why. The reason why people do it
is they look at this 289 and they go,
this is going to be a lot of work. It is. It's going to be
a fair amount of work. And you really need to develop the expertise toand follow
best practices as they're available from places like AWS.
I'm going to argue that not all AWS managed policies are actually all
that securely designed, but it's work you have to do. And there are tools that
will help you. We can help you. There are tools in AWS like the access
analyzer and other things that can help you, but you really do need to develop
your own chops. Now,
missiveness that you do not want to use. Star. Like maybe for
example, the, oh yeah, ec two has a whole
lot of describe calls, too, 124 of those. That's not
a good example. How about read? How many are in read? Okay, 23 toand read.
So that's kind of a reasonable number, maybe. I think to myself,
well, that's fine, I'll just do read star.
Well, what happens when AWS adds a new action
into read? It gets inherited. Right? So I mentioned
earlier, there is a particularly dangerous. Here, I'll show you a
diagram of this. This is fugue. We automatically
do these diagrams so you can kind of go spelunking around your cloud
infrastructure to understand what's going on with it. But here I've got can EC
two instance right here, and it has this
IAM instance profile. Okay, we're getting into our second
use case. Instead of Josh as the principal here,
it's this EC two instance. That's the principal. And what we've done here
is we've given it a mapping to an IAM policy to
allow it to go read and write from s three, and hence the policy name
s three, read write. So it gets a policy, just like a
user through a role would get a policy. And that's a lot
of what goes on in AWS hacking is
people being overly permissive, or just having
the wrong configuration, or even the wrong application design,
which causes the policies that are
running in the actual environment to create huge,
exploitative, lateral movement data
exfiltration, illegitimate crypto mining, all that stuff is done
through these IAM configurations. Very often they're
not getting them from users. Sometimes they do. Very often they're getting them from
running infrastructure that has a policy. And so in this case,
we've got s three read write. That probably means that
EC two instance has the ability to do things like list
all these s three buckets over here and their contents.
So that'd probably be pretty attractive to a hacker.
Right? So, other point I was making though is, if I've given this
like s three list star,
right? Can s three read star? When new actions come
out on the services, iam going to inherit those because of the star. And the
one I wanted to point out that I spoke about earlier is there is one
permission in EC two that allows you to remap which IAM
instance profile you have, so you can create an EC
two instance, give it a nice safe IAM profile, but for one
error, which is the ability to perform the action,
which is kind of buried, that allows you to switch which IAM
profile these EC two instance has. So you can think of
it as lateral movement or permission escalation.
But if that's in there, then hackers are going to have a field day.
Now, that didn't always exist in EC two. In fact, when I
was at AWS, the beginning part, there was no feature like that.
There was no action like that. So if I had created a policy
in whatever it was seven, eight years ago where I
had, I believe it's in the rights. So if I
had given it right star, for example, and these were a much shorter list
of rights back then, I might not know, it might have been actually safe
for my use case then. But as that feature was added to EC
two, I might not even notice that.
How many services are there now? Hundreds. And the release notes are
great and everything, but it's hard to keep up. Well, all of those EC
two instances that had my once safe policy have now inherited
an incredibly dangerous action because I put a star in there.
So a couple of reasons to not use star. So that's
really how we get into trouble with IAM,
is through over permissiveness and also through things
like losing track of the number,
all the different IAM policies and resources that you've got in
them. I'm going to go back to my whiteboard here if I can. Okay,
so let's whiteboard a little more, because if you remember in that
example IAM policy, we had a very concretely
enumerated list of actors. The AWS example that I showed you for the access
analyzer, but then for resources, it said all, you don't
have to do that. So in that IAM policy, you can list resources.
You could say, like, if you wanted s three in this case,
list bucket permissions, but you only wanted Josh to be able to list bucket permissions
on Baz. Well, you could put that in the IAM policy instead
of saying resources star, you would spell, but Baz there using its
arm, okay, now, a lot of folks do this,
and you'll end up sometimes with policies that have a long list of resources
in that resource field, and they feel like, well, IAM getting this right,
that can get challenging at scale. A lot of our customers have
hundreds of thousands or more cloud resources.
We manage millions of cloud resources for our customers.
And when you see these really large deployments and you imagine, can every named
resource be encoded, hard coded
into these IAM policies toand kept track of? Because there's constant
churn in the environment and the answer is often no, that becomes very
challenging. Just to wrap up here, and we're doing kind of an abbreviated
form of this. There's lots to talk about in IAM, but let's talk about something
called attribute based access control.
Attribute based access control is where, instead of having to list
in the resources part of the policy, every resource that
principle may act upon, it's based on tags. And so you
can tag resources. If I'm on team a,
I build application a for my business, and there's a team
B-C-D-E-F et cetera. As long as those resources
that are relevant to team a are being tagged in some way, CTO team a,
I can then create new resources with those tags,
and suddenly team a will have access to them. Okay, well, that sounds
really great. Right, so let's give the tags, we'll make them blue.
So I've got these tags over here that know which resources.
So blue is a and I don't know. We'll do rainbow
is b. And so if Josh is on team
know we're on a here, we can only see the
team a stuff and operate on the team a stuff. Okay, well,
that makes sense, right? Here's the catch. If you do this, youll need
to really restrict access to writing tags, okay?
And even reading tags, maybe now that carries
its own set of architectural burdens. Put another way, if I'm limiting
resource access based on tagging and many different
products and functions in cloud use tags, and I
have to block tags access to writing them,
particularly because then any hacker who gets in who has
right tag permissions can open up whatever resources
they might want into different groups. Now,
obviously, you might say, well, isn't that going to be limited? If a
hacker gets in and has a team a set of policies and permissions,
will they be able to even see Team B stuff to retag it? No,
that is fair. But there are scenarios where a hacker gets
a more permissive set of roles and can retag things such that
they are appearing in places that you don't want to restrict. So you
really need to be careful about you're now including tag
management as part of your security boundaries. That said, with that
caveat, I think it's a really smart way to go for a lot of things.
Maybe not the only thing to do, certainly not the only thing to do,
but in a lot of use cases, it's really smart. Okay,
one other thing I want to talk about are these are so
IAM is thought of as like the method of security,
and it's critically important to it by many folks. But really,
it's a citizen among other citizens
who have policy expressions in AWS. And remember, I said at the beginning
that any request by a principal, if it
hits any, denies, the whole request is denied.
Well, IAm isn't the only place we can put allowances and
denials. In fact, it interacts with things like s three bucket
policies. Toand I recommend every s three bucket have
a bucket policy. So, for instance, there would be, oh,
let's go back. CTo the browser and my diagram,
for instance, would be that this VPC,
this EC two instance, because it's in this VPC virtual
private cloud network, is allowed to read write CTO,
this important records bucket. But I don't
want this EC two instance which has the same role
as this one down here. Just, it only can speak CTo
this other s three bucket. Okay. And they can't see each other's
s three buckets. Well, there's a couple of ways to do that,
right? One is you could put the resource, you could have two different IAM policies
with different resources enumerated, or those two s
three buckets cloud have their own what are called s three bucket
policies. So these are resource policies, not principal
connected policies, if that makes sense. So we've been talking so far about these
IAm policies that get attacks to the principles
column over here on the left. Now we're going to talk just briefly because
it's not IAm. The name on the tin here is IAm. But it's
important to understand you have options. You don't have
to solve everything through IAM. You have other places you can put policies and so
on. This resource right here, this Baz,
I can have what's called a resources policy. And the way I would do
the pattern I was just describing where the one EC two instance that's in the
correct VPC can get there is in that bucket policy.
I can restrict access based on the
VPC endpoint, which is this guy right here. And that's how
this EC two instance is going to come out through this endpoint. To talk to
this bucket, you can put in the bucket policy only allow
requests coming from that VPC endpoint.
So now if you've got two EC two instances that both think
they have permission to all the s three buckets,
you're okay, because your bucket policies have introduced another layer
of denial. So you can say, no, you're not getting
to me, I'm not the right s three bucket. I'm not the s three bucket
you're looking for. So there are a lot of ways to strategize
and to design your IAM policies and
your practices with IAM understand there is no one right way.
There are some general right things like being least permissive
that you want to do, but there's no one right strategy.
And you really have to think of IAM in these context of all
the other AWS services and how you intend to use them together.
So if you were looking for a silver bullet here, I can't give you
one, but I can at least tell you some best practices and
some ways to really get your head around the problem. The most
common error I see moving my whiteboard here with IAM and with
cloud resource configuration in general, but it's particularly true of IAM.
The biggest problem that I tend to see is people never
develop a mental model. They never develop a way to understand the
problem. Instead they look at examples alone.
Examples are great, but you can't imitate somebody else. You have
to understand this stuff to do it well and make decisions. There are a million
ways to do security well in AWS.
I'll give you one example of this. Here's my email address and
my twitter handle. I'm not a big Twitter guy, but reach out to me if
you want to talk about this stuff. I'll leave that up. The example I was
going to use of different ways to very capably
accomplish secure systems in the cloud is to talk a little bit about
how we've done it. And we've had two major iterations of
our software at Fuge. The first one we started working on back
before Lambda existed, and it used EC two as a runtime
environment. That itself, that decision itself had lots of
implications for how we would make things secure.
When we did version two of the product, we switched to basically only
lambdas. And we have obviously a database and other components,
but for computation, mostly lambdas. And that had
created a very different scenario in terms of how we would deal with IAM.
It caused us to automate a lot more of our role creation
for all those lambdas, because you don't want a lot of
sharing, you want to limit that blast radius. And so that caused engineering
work, right? So depending on the decisions you make in how
you're architecting on the cloud, it's using to affect how you're going to do it
securely, and it's going to affect how you're going to use IAM
and think about those features. Okay, well, that's what
I've got today. I hope you enjoyed it. I'm around to take questions. AWS,
we're were talking and you've got my contact info now so
thanks for attending, and good luck
on your secure AWS. You've got the mental model, you got the piece parts.
You can do it.