Everyone, I am thrilled to be here today to explore
the captivating world of leadership 20. And this
one's from a very unique vantage point, a lens of a senior
product manager buckle up as we navigate the intricacies of
product development and team leadership in this ever evolving
tech landscape. So, a quick introduction. About me my
name is Tanvi Mishra and I work as a senior product manager at Amazon.
I've been working with Amazon for over almost seven years and
I have worked on a range of different products from Amazon launches
in Netherlands, Sweden and Poland, and now working with Amazon trade.
So what does exactly a product
manager do? Or how do they drive success?
I think it's a combination of couple of key responsibilities,
number one being strategy. Product managers
are the architects of strategic initiatives. They steer the product
towards alignment with business goals. They specialize
in the ability to envision the future landscape,
understand what the customer needs, and formulate winning strategies.
The second one is vision. The product
leader acts as the torch bearer of the product's long term
vision. This entails not only foreseeing industry
trends, but also inspiring teams to innovate and constantly
create products that stand the test of time.
Roadmap planning is the third one. Crafting a roadmap
is the key to chartering a course through uncharted waters.
Product managers create a strategic plan or roadmap
for the development of evolution of products over time.
This roadmap outlines enhancements,
milestones, and that all of these steps are
being done by the product team to aim and achieve the key
metrics of any product development. Stakeholder management is
the fourth and the key important part of actually delivering any kind
of product. Successful product leaders recognize that any
product success is a result of actually successful partnerships
with diverse stakeholders. Effective communication,
collaboration and negotiation skills are vital to navigate
this intricate web of relationships.
So what does a product development looks
like? In my view, there are essentially
seven phases, the first one being idea generation.
At this stage, creative collaboration and identification of
potential concepts are looked at. What can be an
ideal solution? What does the customer want? What can we look
at? And everyone comes together to identify what can be the right
product. Then comes the second step, which is market research.
This step is essentially an in depth analysis to validate
market needs and assess competition. This is
identifying different customer touch points.
What are the pain points? What does a customer lack in the current
experience that can be potentially implemented by the
product team? The third one is conceptualization.
This is defining a very, very clear and a demanded
product concept, and it is supposed to be based on research
insights that was done at the market research stage. Here you
define minute and smaller parts
of the product. For example, a product needs to be red in
color because the preference of the customers was supposedly in
the red and the orange phase. So this is defining deeper
concept and requirements. The next one
is design and planning. At this stage, you develop
a comprehensive plan outlining the product features, the architecture
and the development roadmap. Then comes
prototyping, which is creating a preliminary version
of the product for testing and validation.
This can be a very initial phase of the product,
can be if it's a digital product, can be in gamma phases, can be in
beta phases. To identify is the prototype working fine?
Is it supposed to go? Absolutely. As is in production and
identifying issues with your product ahead of time.
Then there is testing and refinement via
the product and the prototype testing, you go back,
identify, test the multiple facets
that you've designed, do rigorous evaluation, identify processes
to feed in the user, feedback, incorporation,
and then from a forward looking roadmap,
you refine the product. And then comes the final step,
which is the launch and the post launch monitoring. At this stage,
when you're launching, you introduce the product to the market. But the
most important part is actually monitoring its performance even
after launch and ensuring that this performance
leads to further improvements or developing strategies
to ensure success. As an organization, my topic
which is leadership 2.0, what are the traits for success here?
I think as a product manager, there are
a couple of key things that you need to be very,
very successful at. The first one is visionary thinking,
the ability to anticipate the marketing trends, vision of product
managers, vision of what the landscapes are going to
be, and the ability to guide teams towards
innovation is going to be very, very important. The second one
is adaptability. Embracing change and
swiftly adapting and adapting existing strategies
to ensure success. In the long run, it is
imperative to thrive in this dynamic tech environment.
Imagine how many products have become obsolete, how many
products have changed, the requirements of the customers have
changed. Imagine the whole boom of technology at
this age. The next one is communication.
Clear and effective communication to articulate vision,
strategy expectations, fostering collaboration
across team is imperative. Here. The vision,
the documentation cannot be just in your head. It needs to be a
part of everyone's brain, everyone's collaboration.
Whoever is participating in this journey, then comes the next part,
which is a special one for me, which is empathy.
As a product manager, if you come with empathy,
understanding the customer needs and understanding
what their pain points are become easier. Also,
you become a winner in the team dynamics.
Understanding the market nuances and driving products
to resonate with users to actually develop truly
a winning product becomes easier. So empathy definitely is a
key. Now the challenges of
developing and managing product lifecycles
I think in my view there are three key challenges,
the first one being communication challenges.
Communication challenges can happen between multiple stakeholders
because there are a lot of stakeholders in this journey. Development teams,
key stakeholders like leadership, cross functional
teams can be a big challenge. Then the second one is time
and pressures. While everyone has the time
to develop the product, we also need to balance the need
for speedy development and ensuring that the quality of
the product is what it is supposed to be and
at the same time that the customers actually require the solution. While you can
develop an amazing product ten years down the line, that the customer do they really
need it? Also, the fact that you might not have the luxury of
everything tech from tech investment at
your luxury in your organization. So you need to balance out
timeline pressures are often at crunch resource allocations,
efficiency and managing resources is
one of the key challenges that I go through as a product manager.
Managing conflicting priorities within the team can be absolutely complex.
Strategies that I use often to overcome these challenges
are collaborative tools. For example,
using Asana Slack confluence to bring everyone together
in the team and define clear timelines, define clear ownership
doing product tracking documentation on an ongoing basis
becomes imperative to not just keep a track
for yourself, but communicate to the stakeholders on what is happening.
The second one is agile methodologies.
Embracing agile methodologies like scrum promotes iterative
development, adaptability and continuous improvement.
Then fostering a culture of innovation,
product development and product launches is not
a one time thing. I think it's a culture that is important. So cultivating
an environment that encourages creativity, problem solving
is crucial for sustained development of not just yourself,
but your team. Like any other
team in Appison, what I've learned is the classic
two pizza team in which there is a smaller team
and these are key contributors that are absolutely required to deliver
a successful product. And it
is enough to share two pizzas within the team
and everyone has their appetite satiated. But at the same
time it is successful,
timeline driven and it is also ensured to
reduce any kind of bureaucracy that can potentially happen in the
process. It is a very, very common concept in Amazon.
Then as a product manager,
developing teams and managing development roadmaps
can be absolutely tricky in this case.
If you see there are three key challenges
that I always come across and
I use key strategies to always
come back and get my anchor back
to my journey. I think it starts with business impact
assessment often when product managers are confused
as to what to look at, what to prioritize,
it is necessary to evaluate whether the product and its features
have the potential to drive the key goals for business. For example,
it can be revenue, it can be growth, it can be any kind of
custom account, it can be profits. Depending on what the business is actually
aimed at, the product should deliver in line with that.
The second one is strategic alignment. So ensuring
that the product roadmap and the vision is aligned with the business
objectives, not just for now, but in the long term.
It cannot be that your product is conflicting with what
the organization wants in the long run. So pivoting and adapting to the
strategic vision is absolutely important.
The next one is user feedback. Analysis qualifies.
Incorporate any kind of user feedback to identify which features
are priority zero. Absolutely. Which are non negotiable,
priority one which are important but can be deprioritized,
for example, in the next six to twelve months. This is imperative
to balance any kind of resource utilization and at the
same time ensuring maximum success.
If I tell you Amazon works on a very customer centric
approach and we often prioritize features, for example,
which enhances user experience over a lot of times
just driving profitability, for example.
This helps us always go back and pivot our approach whenever
required. And whenever there is a conflicting view on product development,
the next one is I want to talk about is
the data driven approach. I think one thing that Amazon has absolutely
taught me is relying on data
for 100% of decision making. As a product manager,
data is the coolest tool and absolutely it is a non
negotiable tool for developing great products.
As a product manager,
I, and for that matter, everyone uses
and measures success through key metrics which are absolutely
business relevant. For example,
user engagement, tracking any kind of interactions that
the users have had with your product,
such as time spent on the app or features
that were absolutely used or click through rate to gauge
is the product actually relevant to the end customer?
The second one can be conversion rates. For example,
is the product actually resulting in any kind of conversion?
Is it resulting in any kind of sale? Then a
very key important one can be customer satisfaction. In this
case, identifying while the customer is actually using it.
Are they truly happy with the product or not? And then the
fourth one being retention rate. Yes,
the customer can be unhappy, but sometimes they don't leave the product.
Retention rate is the key to identify what is that ticking point that the customer
refuses to use your product, ideally on a
standard basis. Retention shouldn't be like retention
should be less than 2%, and most
customers and most products should not reach to that point. But retention rate is still
an imperative metric, and tracking these metrics,
not just these, but any kind of business relevant metrics, are absolutely
important to go back and identify if you're going on
the right direction or not as a part of
the product journey. Once the product
lifecycle has started, it just doesn't end
at launching the product and post launch.
Once the launch has been completed, there are multiple techniques for
managing the product lifecycle, the first one being sunsetting.
It is almost like strategically retiring products that are no
longer relevant or aligned with the marketing trends
or even organizational goals. For example,
Amazon actually discontinued Kindle Voyage,
which was an e reader, in response to changing customer
preferences and advancement in the Kindle technology.
The second one can be pivoting. Yes, the product can be a successful
product at launch, but adapting the product strategy based on market
feedback or shift in the industry trend is really important.
In case of Amazon, Amazon Echo actually
started as a voice activated assistant, which then
evolved to evolving like a complete smart
home hub as a one spot,
one size fits all kind of a product. The last one
is continuous iteration. Implementing any kind of
ongoing improvements and updates to enhance product value and competitiveness
is an absolute must for long term success.
For example, in case of Amazon,
Amazon prime membership program keeps adding these new features,
some kind of new benefits. There are always while
there is a standalone app, there are for example,
wine program that got launched or you as an
end customer keep getting better updates on more
products to try based on your
purchase history. Right? All of these
strategies revolve around developing and evolving products
post launch as well. I have listed
down some key resources
which can be utilized for enhancing your knowledge.
Not just knowledge, but actually skills and understanding
deeper details of product management here.
Thank you you so much for your time. If there are any questions, I'm absolutely
available. You can reach out to me on LinkedIn.
Thank you so much.