Hi, everyone. I'm Kareen. I'm going to do my introduction now just because I'm going
to do my portion of the talk now. So nice to meet you
guys. Let me share my screen so that way you can actually see a picture
of me so you know what I look like. That's me.
I'm Kareem Wallach. I have a consulting company called Project
Elevate. I do developer relations, community stuff.
It's basically all things that work with developer
tools and the community. Fun people like you
and. Yeah, I'm just going to talk about a portion of some of our presentation
with Tim. So just to take it off, I'm just going to give some background
about what is stream processing, because I don't know what people's
experiences are, if they're aware of stream processing or streaming
technologies in general. So I'm just going to give a quick overview.
So stream processing is basically
a approach dealing with data where you're.
Well, there's two parts to it. The first is a streaming ingestion part.
So streaming technologies, things like Kafka or red panda,
where you are ingesting data as it's happening,
instead of like batch or like more
like batch kind of processing. Batch ingestion,
this is more of like a continuous flow. So as the events happen, you are
constantly ingesting the data. And then the processing side is you're doing something
with that data as you're ingesting it. So it's kind of as real time
as you can get. So this process
of stream processing, there's a lot of processes of stream processing
and processing. The data process of stream processing.
So the process of bringing
the data in as it's happening and then streaming kind of allows
you to be able to do real time analysis on the data
as you're bringing it in, and then transformations and computation
before you're actually storing the data. So if you're almost
thinking about it kind of in a philosophical way, the data
is, as it's being ingested, you're able to make those transformations
while it's in flight and then storing it
or putting it into another stream processing system or something like that.
But then there's a downstream side,
too. So basically,
stream processing is used to extract valuable insights in real
time, things like detecting anomalies and trigger
actions based on incoming data.
I do go over some brief use cases here. There is a
lot you can do with stream processing and real time
kind of analytics and capabilities, including enabling your
users to do more by providing them actionable
insights, which is basically real time insights that then they can take action on.
If you think about LinkedIn,
for example, some of the real time stuff that they have implemented
into their systems is if someone views your profile,
a user of LinkedIn can then go in and take action.
They can message that person, they can view their profile,
whatever. They can take action based on that insight that they now
have. There's a lot of cases like this where people are exposing
real time insights and real
time analytics. The insights are a little bit different. It's more of like a decision
making capability. But a lot of organizations are doing this now too. So that's something
to keep in mind. So there's different kinds of queries
you can do inside stream processing. So we kind of talked about the streaming technologies
first, where you're ingesting the data and you're able to do these transformations
on it as it's in flight. Then you have the type of queries
that you're able to do inside of stream processing as
the data is in flight. So just to give a couple of examples, I'm going
to give some examples of each. These are all listed here, so you can read
along if you'd like. So the first one is filtering.
This involves a selection of specific
data from a stream based on predefined conditions.
So an example of that is like filtering out log entries
that contain errors that are needed for immediate attention.
That's like a filtering example. So this is an example of queries and stream
processing. Aggregation is
involving of summarizing or reducing data over a
certain time window or key. Some of these might be kind
of straightforward. You might be already familiar with these types of queries,
but this is all stuff that you can do in stream processing in a very
real time kind of capability. This allows you to calculate the average temperature
over the last ten minutes in a sensor stream joining
streams. This one I think is just really cool.
Like you're able to basically ingest streams from multiple sources
and bring them together to kind of have a little bit more of
a dimensional analyzed.
So one of these examples is like combining user click data with
product data to analyze user behavior.
Windowing,
they group data into fixed time intervals
or Windows for analysis. It's windowing. I think it's
pretty straightforward. So example of that is analyzed the total sales
for each hour of the day over a week.
So that's what an example of windowing would be.
Pattern recognition. This is used a lot like with anomaly
detection related stuff. It's like identifying a sequence or pattern of events
in a data stream. This is where you can find anomalies
and things like that. So example of this is detecting
a series of login failures as a security breach.
Attempt stateful processing.
Maintain state information to analyze data over time, such as tracking user
sessions. So example, this is monitoring user behavior and
detecting when a user session is idle. So I'm going to talk a
little bit about rising wave. This is a stream processing
database. Rising wave, it's open source.
It's a SQL distributed stream processing
database. So essentially what it does, this is
like a lot of just jargon, but I'll just explain it to you guys.
All right, so basically it allows you to be able to pull in data as
you're ingesting the stream. So it works with streaming technologies,
which I'll show you, kind of dig a little bit deeper into this in a
second, but you're able to pull this data in and then you
can perform incremental computations as the data comes in
and then update the results dynamically. So ingesting
the data and doing transformations and queries
on this data as you're bringing it in and then storing it
in a downstream kind of capacity.
So there's a downstream side.
So it does have its own storage. So you can
access the data in rising wave.
Specifically the storage and the
computation side of things are separate, so you can actually scale them out separately
if you want. And you can also do downstream in another database or
data warehouse or whatever if you want to do that.
The benefits of having this downstream thing with rising wave is easily accessing
this data that you just perform these transformations on.
It is SQL based, which is really nice. If you know SQL, it's pretty easy
to pick up. It's postgres compatible,
which is also pretty great. It's like very
easy. If you've ever dug into stream processing,
there's some technologies out there that are pretty
big builds. Like the learning curve is
pretty challenging. So this kind of serves as really
easy learning curve because it's all SQL and postgres. So if you know
SQL and you're working with any kind of postgres compatible
type of data stores or anything like that, then it's
pretty straightforward to use. I mentioned the storage
and computation are separate. It has incremental
updates on materialized views. I didn't put
that last part in there, but I think it's important. It's also built with rust.
A lot of people love that because it's very performant.
Okay, so the data stream process, this is kind of what I was
like making jokes about the stream processing, the data stream process, the process of
the data streaming and the data stream process is like this.
So as I mentioned, rising wave allows
you and this just stream processing systems in general.
But I'm specifically speaking about rising wave. In this case, it allows you to
accept data from a
streaming source. So you do have to have something that
allows you to be able to ingest this data in a real time fashion.
So as an event happens, it's pulling into the data into rising
wave. So you can use any like, so these are a bunch of popular
streaming technologies like Kafka and Pulsar.
There's also red panda. It's not listed on here, but that's also another really popular
one, too, Amazon kinesis. So you can pull these
streams and these pieces of data into
rising wave, and then inside it has
the ability to ingest it. You can do kind of a lot of those different
kind of queries that I mentioned in the earlier slides of joining
streams, filtering, aggregation transformations, whatever, and then have
the downstream side where you can store it
to either rising wave or other kind of data
warehouses or data lakes or whatever kind of processing you're looking for.
So here are some use cases and examples. I'm going to run through these really
quickly just because I know there's a lot of material in this talk.
But streaming ETL is basically the practice of extracting,
transforming, and moving data within different systems.
So it allows you to ingest the data from a wide range of data sources
and transform that data in real time and
then sync the process data to downstream systems.
Real time analysis, this is kind of a popular
trend now everyone's doing real time analytics. So real time
analytics is basically the practice of analyzing data
as it's generated. So as soon as something happens, you're analyzing
it, you're running some kind of transformation before it's even stored. And that offers
you the ability to be as real time as possible because you're literally transforming the
data. One thing that I think
that's just important to keep in mind is a lot of times, and I know
this happened for me, and this is why I kind of said this. I said
this before, I'm going to say it again, because when I first kind
of learned about real time analytics in general, I think a
lot of us just think about the generalized uses
of analytics systems where it's like dashboards
and things like that. The capabilities of what you can do with real
time analytics go way beyond dashboards.
And this is kind of what I was talking about those actionable insights before,
that's like when you're offering your users
insights or real time analytics to be able to make smarter
or more effective decisions in real time. So things that
have that need to know of what's happening right this very second,
you can either use it internally and have a system process it like
a machine that's like a llamalay detection related stuff. You can have a
human process it or you could give it to
your end users. And then people productize these things too,
where they literally, people pay for premium services either for an
entire software or for
just certain real time analytic capabilities and things like that.
So that's just something that I think is really important to keep in mind
in terms of real time analytics. It provides business with
valuable insights and actionable information real time.
And it does provide competitive advantages by enabling business to
respond quickly and changing market conditions. It also offers competitive
advantages because if you use it for the actionable insights that
I was kind of mentioning with your users, you can make your users
happier and they could have a more positive experience using your technology if
they have a more real time, insightful experience.
I mean, everybody knows we don't have patients, and as
time goes, we have less and less and less patients. Okay.
And it could also be used to improve operational efficiency and reduce costs
so you can use it internally as well. Another example,
event driven applications, enables continuous
event ingestion and processing, maintains context
across multiple events, and performs sophisticated processing,
and then detects complex patterns and correlations within
a stream of events, and provides direct integration with
a variety of upstream and downstream systems.
So really quick rising wave architecture,
kind of what it looks like. So first is you have a serving layer.
This parses SQL queries and performs the planning and optimizations
of the query jobs. Then you have a processing layer
which performs all your computation.
Then you have, I think I clicked too quickly, but it doesn't matter. Metadata management
service. This manages the metadata of
different nodes and then coordinates operations amongst these nodes.
And then you have the storage layer that stores and retrieves data
from object stores like storage like s three.
And I think that's it. And then, Tim, I'll let you.
Thanks. That was a really good introduction to a lot
of complex topics there. And I'll take
over from here. So we saw some really
important things to see on how you're going to
be general topics, how you can query it with
something like rising wave. But let's cover a little
bit more. I'm Tim Spann. I do
a lot of streaming stuff I have some virtual meetups around the
world. Put a newsletter out, you'll get all these slides.
I don't want to spend too much time giving you 10,000
overview things. I think the new thing to mention
though is with generative AI,
with these large language models and some of the smaller and
mid sized language models, now you need a lot of data.
You get that processed things like Apache,
Nifi and Python let you get a lot of that data into
the pipeline, whether it's going right to a model or
using to a vector store. And then once you have it cleaned up,
maybe I get the results from stock feeds,
maybe I get it back from the model
or some things stored in a vector store. I get that into
something like Apache Kafka, which we have at Cloudera. And then
I could share that with rising wave so they could do some real time
analytic decisions on there. And maybe they
put it into another Kafka topic which I could read later,
run some additional processing.
There is multiple levels of
all of this, and a lot of it's enabled by Python.
Python fits into many layers of this process,
whether that's getting data into Kafka, and I'll show you that real quick,
or it's being called by Nifi to do
different processing for chunking up data,
getting it into a vector store, running at the
edge, working with different databases,
lots out there. I have a number of articles on
how to use that. Now we mentioned Apache Iceberg,
again getting a lot into this one talk.
But Iceberg is a very interesting table format
that sits on top of usually apache parquet,
could be another file format like Orc, but let's just keep it
easy and say parquet. And there's tools built
into the cloud to get data into these formats.
And what's nice is having things in iceberg tables means
everybody in every data store,
any kind of query engine can access it.
So it's very helpful. And I'll show you how to do that on
the simple. So you could do that on your laptop just to try out.
How can I get stuff into iceberg tables, into Kafka?
Just using Python show you how easy that is. And then
when you get into the enterprise level, all the governance and
all the tools and encryption that you need in there are available.
Don't have to learn anything new. Really easy
to do that. Apache Nifi
again, you can run it on your laptop or in
production. Cloudera from Cloudera makes it easy and scalable
and it's been around forever. So what's nice is
it just doesn't die. It just keeps getting better and better.
I've left servers running for months on an old laptop
sitting somewhere. It just keeps running. And I show you a
quick bit of that. And with the new version, which I have another
talk on, we show you how we've made it so you can expand the
tool and add your pipelines with Python. I show you
a little bit of that today. Providence is important.
So everything I run I know what happens. So if people
go, how did I load this data? I could show you has
a lot of pre built components to handle,
lots of different formats for processing. This comes in really
handy when you don't want to write your own boilerplate
code to do everything. So do Python for the important
stuff, complex processing,
using some of the amazing libraries for vector stores and
LLM, and all the easy stuff you could do with stocks.
I'll show you some example code I have here so you could
do that yourself really easy. We mentioned
Kafka. Think of it as just an
infinitely sized pipeline that I can put
any data I want into, usually structured Json,
avro protobuff, things like that.
Get that in there and distribute to as many people who want it,
which is really nice. I just have to get it in there.
Then anyone who wants to subscribe to and can get to it and
it scales out as big as you need to go. It is a
nice buffer and pipeline to get my data to where it needs
to go. But let's show you stuff actually running.
You don't want to just see awesome looking generated
graphics, but I'll show you one where I'm taking stuff
from the fin hub stock API
with Python. And what's nice there is it
grabs websockets, push it to Kafka and
do what I need to do with it. I can also
process things like documents and different stock APIs,
and I've got links to all the code here,
so you can try that out on your own.
But let's go through a couple of quick
passes here and I'll first show you where the source code is.
I've got a new one on grabbing
stock data from Yahoo. Using the Yahoo finance
library for Python. I am
reading that and then as you can see here, I'm using Py
iceberg to set up an iceberg catalog.
Again, this is a small one, runs on your
laptop using SQL lite, so you don't need a giant
catalog or meta store out there, obviously not for production.
And I've got a little mini instance
running. So again, I don't have to pay for s three. Something to
think about while you're learning, trying things out. Especially if you're
coming from the Python world where you may not have
access to a large data platform like Cloudera and you might have
to just start learning on a laptop or whatever
you have. So I'm just going through just
calling as many of
stock prices as I want, getting them back and
sending them to Kafka. That's how easy it is to send from
Python to Kafka. You set up a producer pointing
to whatever servers you have. Again, for me, that's running in Docker.
And then I send the message, give it a key that's
gone, that's into Kafka. We'll show you that. And then over here
I'm grabbing bunches of 1000 of those records
and putting them into an iceberg table,
appending that got a short sleep there.
And every 1000 we refresh that just so
the files aren't too small. They're still pretty small, but it's
nice to keep them smaller than zero
here. And then this is the data that's getting written to
Kafka. It's Json, pretty straightforward
and I can put as many as I want here and I could share
it with whoever wants it. It could be a python user, a Java
user, spark, rising wave,
flink, nifi. Almost anybody can read
Kafka, which is really nice. So we got that data in
and on the other end I've got it into iceberg.
This is the data. It's in parquet. The amazing
part for iceberg is it creates this metadata
that lets me do some amazing things like append,
like change data, change field, do time travel.
So I could say, what did the data look like two days
ago, an hour ago? That is really cool.
And that might be a feature you want.
I'm going to send some more data into there. Let me show you
some of this running. And I'm just running this like
you saw in the code, just printing it out just to see that it's
running. And then that is sending each record
as it comes in into Kafka, which makes sense for Kafka.
Kafka likes that sort of thing. As you get more
and more data there and every thousand,
I'm writing that to Parquet, which we
can take a look at. There's the head.
Just so we don't need a full query engine. I could just use the parquet
tools to make sure those files look okay.
And I could look at the header for that. You do whatever I
want with those files, get a sample,
query them, convert them. The command line tools
are pretty good for that. And you can see, make sure the data
is coming in and you can see we're pushing data
out. We've got a couple of other ones. I mentioned
that finance one, that is pretty easy for me to
just run that and if
I could spell properly and then I'd open websockets.
You can see this one is super fast, python to websockets
to Kafka, amazingly fast. And we
just send that here and you can see that just the amount
of rows just keeps piling up, really straightforward.
And that one is documented here with the source codes.
You can give that a try. And then another one I have is
the same as that Iceberg one, but it is just sending it to
Kafka, really straightforward there. And you can see that
coming in last. I want to show you a couple of different things in Nifi,
and one of them is I could read data from
Slack. So here I put a slack message
asking for the current stock price of IBM,
and I've got a listener that's pushing it to Kafka.
And then here if it is in the right
channel, then I'm going to see if it actually
asks about stocks. This one did. I'm going
to use Python. I have a Python process
to pull out the company name, and this is mentioned in that other
talk. And then I'm going to use that to
call Alpha Vantage to convert it into a stock title
because your company name and your stock symbol usually
not the same. And then if we got data back from that,
I'm going to use Nifi to pull out the company name.
And if there's multiple records, parse them, clean them up.
Then I'm going to grab stock from twelve data for that,
clean it up, add a timestamp and then
push that to Kafka over here. Put that in
a cache as well if we want to, and also trying to see if
there's any wiki data for it. This is also a
Python processor. If there's a wiki page for it, I download
that as well. And we could push the results
to slack, which again is nice. I can have Python
do something, push it to Kafka, and then if I push it to slack,
and then if I read it from Slack, maybe push it,
execute some python,
a cycle of what's going on. And you can see here
I got some data back on this, there's some
wiki information, plus the stock current
value pretty easy to do that.
There's a lot of different things I could do within Nifi
with Python. Pretty easy.
But just wanted to give you a short sample of that with
stocks as well as over here, we've got stock
news, but I've got a lot of records
here. We could be sitting a while as it goes through all the news,
but just to give you an example there,
thank you for sitting through this talk.
I hope you enjoy things. I know there was a
lot in there. The source code is there. There's another talk. I have
a little more in depth on Nifi and working with
the various Python processors, so definitely check that
one out. That is in this current list
of comp 42 Python talks.
So definitely check that out. Thank you for
listening to my talk. If you have any questions, I'm on medium.
I'm on GitHub, I'm on Twitter.
You will find me. I am posting stuff everywhere.
But thanks a lot for coming
to our talk today. And Karen
and me say thank you and we will talk to you again.
Thank you.