Hello everyone, I'm Karan and today I will be
taking you on a journey into the world of serverless. With Kubernetes
we will be diving deep into what is serverless,
what is knative and how we can leverage this tool
to create serverless applications right within a Kubernetes setup.
Before getting into what is a native and how
we can leverage this tool to create our very own serverless
infrastructure. I would first like to cover what is
serverless in the first place, but before
getting into that we first need to understand what is the
with server architecture. In the traditional
with server architecture you first have to set
up a virtual machine on whatever cloud provider you may be using.
Then once that is set up, you have to deal with the configuration
of that virtual machine, whether it is fitting your
needs and requirements or not. Once that is done, you have to
set up your application and not to mention that you
have to install all the necessary tools, the configuration required
for that application to run. And once it is up
and running, your job is not done. You still have to maintain
this entire setup. So over time if you start seeing
more users using your application, you have to
deal with the scaling of this application as well.
So these are some of the problems that are associated
with the with server architecture and these
problems are addressed by the serverless architecture.
Contrary to popular belief,
serverless is actually a misnomer.
So it's not like a server is not involved,
it is, but it is involved behind the scenes.
So whatever cloud provider you may be using and if they offer
any serverless functionality,
then basically they are dealing with all
the problems that I mentioned in the previous slide.
And you as a developer just have to deal with the
business logic, the coding aspect of building applications.
So that makes it very easy to maintain and scale in the long
run. Because you are not dealing with the configuration the
cloud provider is dealing with, that you are only dealing with the
business aspect of development.
These are some of the cloud providers and their serverless
offerings. So you have lambda for AWS,
cloud functions for GCP, and serverless functions
for Versaille and Azure. These are just some of
the cloud providers that I wanted to mention. So you are familiar with
the offerings that are out there. I'm sure there are a
lot more other offerings, but these are just a few that I wanted to mention.
All right, so next I wanted to cover some
of the basic concepts of kubernetes. I am sure that in
this conference a lot of great folks will be covering
the introduction to Kubernetes fundamentals of kubernetes the core
components and all that jazz. I will not be going deep into
the entire Kubernetes architecture. I will just
be covering some of the core building blocks
that we would be using in the demo part of
this talk. So stick around till the end, because towards the end
we will be exploring how to use knative and
how we can create our very own serverless infrastructure right within
a Kubernetes cluster. So just
some high level overview for
the components or the building blocks that we would be
using or working with in the later part of this talk for
Kubernetes. So first I would like to cover what is
a node. So node is basically a virtual machine.
You can think of it as a physical server located somewhere
where your applications are hosted and
managed by kubernetes. Then next comes the
deployment. So deployment is, you can say
a configuration that is related to your
pods. So it has a lot of things you can configure.
I won't be getting too much into that.
Then next comes the pod itself. So pod
is the smallest unit of abstraction that is created
by kubernetes. Basically you can host
one or multiple containers within a pod that is
related to your application. Then next
comes the replica set. This is also managed by the deployment,
and replica set is nothing but a unit
which ensures that you have n
number of pods, whatever you may have defined up and running at
all times. Then last but not the least,
service. So service is you can think of it as a
logical interface which exposes your pods
to the outside world. So there are a lot of different types of
services which I won't be diving deep into. I'm sure there are
a lot of great folks who would be talking about all this in
depth in this conference. So I won't be diving deep into that.
These are some of the concepts that I wanted to cover
so that it's easier for you to keep up with me in the
later part of this talk where we would be covering the demo of knative.
All right, so it's finally time. We would now
be looking at the knative tool. What are some
of the features provided by this tool, what are the core components
and why? In some cases using this
tool may be better for you than using a serverless
offering provided by your cloud provider. So yeah,
we would be diving deep into what is knative now.
So knative is an open source serverless computing
platform written in Go for kubernetes.
Essentially you can create your very own serverless infrastructure
right within your Kubernetes setup and by using this
tool, you get the advantage of having the control over the configuration
of how your serverless infrastructure should work.
So earlier on in this talk, I discussed that
why a serverless offering may be beneficial because
you don't have to deal with the configuration that is associated
with managing an application, you just have to deal with the business logic.
But in some cases that may be a disadvantage
because you don't have the control over how it works,
and sometimes it can get out of hand. So if
you want the control over your serverless configuration,
this is the tool to go ahead with.
So knative has two different offerings for
managing modern serverless workloads. One is
the serving component and another is the eventing
component. So in the scope of this talk, we would
only be covering the serving component and not the eventing component.
So knative comes with various features.
Some of them are first and foremost the scale
down to zero, which is the flagship feature of knative.
Basically, if your deployment does not
have to deal with any messages or requests,
then it can scale down to zero, and then again
scale back up from zero. If there are any messages later
down the line, then next comes yaml based configuration.
So similarly, how you define objects in Kubernetes,
you can define objects for knative as well using YAmL
files itself. Then next comes the rollout
strategies. So similar to how you can define different
types of rollout strategies for your deployment in Kubernetes, you can
define those same rollout strategies for a knative
deployment as well. Then last but not the least,
easy integration with tools and services. So like
service meshes, monitoring tools, tracing tools,
logging tools, knative is very easy to integrate with.
Knative provides two components to work with
in order to create serverless infrastructures. One is serving
and another is eventing. In this talk, I will not
be covering the eventing aspect of knative, I will only
be covering the serving aspect. If you want me to cover eventing
in the future, you can let me know and reach out to me
through my social media platforms. I will be mentioning those
at the end of this talk. So in this talk
we will be covering only the serving aspect. So in serving there
is a service, there is a revision
and a route associated to that service, and a
URL that points to that route which allows us to
communicate with the service. And revisions are
basically a version of your application.
So essentially you can have multiple revisions
of your application as well if you want. So you can split
the traffic between those revisions, let's say 80% to
revision one and 20% traffic to revision two. So it is
very easy to create sort of an A B test environment with
knative as well. All right, so I have
covered all the theoretical aspects of knative and now
it is time to jump into the demo. Before we do that, I would like
to mention some of the prerequisites that are required for this
demo. So first is Docker, then the next tool
required is kind, which is basically Kubernetes in Docker.
And the last tool that is required is the
knative client. I'll be going over the installation instructions
for the knative client in the demo part for
a macOS operating system. But if you are on a different system,
I have provided a QR code on the slide
right now. So you can scan the QR code. You will be directed to a
GitHub repository. In this repository you can find all the
files that I would be working within the demo and the instructions associated
to the demo. So you can find everything over there
and yeah, let's get started.
Okay, so we are in the demo part of the talk, I would
say the most exciting part and we are inside the
terminal, the home for every DevOps engineer.
So earlier, as I mentioned, we would need
three tools. One is Docker, second is kind,
and third is knative client. So I
hope you already have Docker and kind installed on your system.
I'll be going over how you can install the knative client on
Mac operating system. Don't worry if you are on
a different system. As I mentioned earlier, the QR
code that I provided, if you go to the link provided in that
you can get the installation links and those links
will direct you to a page where you can install
the knative client for your particular operating
system. So for Mac you can use the brew command.
So brew install knative client
kn so I won't be
going ahead and running this command because I already have the
knative client installed on my system, but we are not done
yet. We can also install a quick
start plugin that the knative client has
offered. So basically in production, if you
want to set up knative, you would manually have to install various
tools and custom resource definitions for knative
to work in your Kubernetes cluster. So we don't have
to do that. There is a quick start plugin that we can use and
get started with using knative quickly.
So again I won't be running this command because I already
have the plugin installed. Once both
of these commands have successfully executed on your system,
you can run the following command which is kn quickstart
kind. So I'll go ahead and run this.
This is a command that takes a few
minutes to complete its execution,
so I won't be making you wait for this command
to complete. I'll cut straight to where it has finished execution.
All right, so it seems like the
command has finished its execution and
this is the type of output you may also be seeing
on your screen if you are following along. So let's
go over what this quick start command
has done. So first it installed
the Kubernetes version 1.25.3.
Essentially it installed the entire Kubernetes control plane
in a single docker container. Then once
kind was installed, the knative serving
component was installed, so you can see all the steps
related to that. Then next the courier networking
layer was installed. So courier is nothing but a lightweight
service mesh which was adopted by Knative
in the recent years. Service mesh this particular
service mesh is used for exposing the service
that we would be creating as a serverless application
to expose that to the outside world,
outside of the Kubernetes network. Then it went ahead and
installed the knative eventing component, which we won't be going
over in this talk. And yeah, it finished its
execution and seems like it has successfully installed knative
on our kind cluster.
Just to see what cluster has been created by
the knative client in the previous command we can run
this command kind get clusters.
So as you can see it has created this cluster called
knative. So usually what I like to do is
run the Kubectx command.
Basically this just ensures that I am on the correct context.
For those of you who aren't familiar with Kubectx, this is
a very helpful tool that enables
you to switch between different contexts that you may be working with
in Kubernetes. So yeah, that's what I did. I just ensured that I am
on the correct context. I am sure that the
command that we ran earlier, the quick start command, switches to
this context, but it never hurts to run the command
again. So yeah, now that we are sure
we are on the correct context, the first thing that I like
to do in order to see what all has been installed in my
cluster is to get all the namespaces. So we can do that by
kget namespaces.
K is just an alias that I have set in my system for the Kubectl
command. These are the namespaces present
in our kubernetes cluster and I believe default kubernetes,
lease cube, public cube system and local path storage are the namespaces
that come out of the box with the kind cluster,
but these are the three namespaces
that I can see which has been installed by the knative client.
So eventing, serving and courier system, as I'd
mentioned earlier, we would only be going over the serving component.
So this is the namespace that I would first like to look at.
So the next thing that I'll do is get the resources
present in the knative serving namespace.
So this command that I ran, kget all namespace,
knative serving basically gets all the resources present
inside this particular namespace. And as you can
see there is a lot of information on the screen. Not to worry, we are
just going over what all has been installed in our cluster.
So as we can see there are a bunch of pods, bunch of services associated
to those pods, deployments for those pods and replica sets.
So these are the pods
which help knitting manage all the
serverless workloads. And you can see that there are a
few horizontal pod auto scalers as well. So yeah,
these are the resources that have been installed in our Kubernetes
cluster and now we can jump into installing our
first serverless application. So yeah, let's get into that.
All right, so we are in vs code now,
this is the id of my preference,
and here is a Yaml file that I have named as hello
World Yaml. And this is using the API
version serving knative dev v one. So this is
a custom resource definition that was installed by the knative client
which we would be leveraging to create our very first serverless
application. So the name for the
application would be hello. And here are a few annotations
that I have mentioned. I won't be covering this right now,
I'll get into this later. Then we have the spec containers
image provided for the container, the container port and
env variable that we have mentioned with the value world.
So as you can see that this Yaml file seems very familiar,
right? This is a very similar file that
we would be creating for normal Kubernetes applications.
So yeah, essentially you create your serverless
applications using YAML files itself and it's very similar to
Kubernetes. So let's jump back
to the terminal and apply this yaml file.
Before applying any YAml files, I like to first
do a diff on that Yaml file. So we can do that by running k
diff hello world Yaml.
Yes, so as you can see it is going to be
creating a service named hello and it has
a few annotations defined. It is creating
the image that we had mentioned, and also it is specifying some of the
default values that we did not mention in the YAml file, like the readiness probe,
the traffic with the latest revision and the percentage
split between those revisions. So 100% because
we are going to be creating our first revision. As I
had mentioned earlier, you have the ability to create multiple revisions
in knative and split the traffic between those revisions.
So yeah, this file seems good to me. Let's go ahead and
apply hello world Yaml.
Okay, so it seems like the command ran without any errors.
So what we can do next is get the pods in the default namespace.
Because we did not specify any namespace, it would be created in the default namespace.
As you can see, there is a pod named hello
and it is in the running state. So if I run the command
again, instead of running it again and again,
we can go in the watch mode.
So let's wait for a few seconds, and as you
can see, it has started terminating the pod.
The reason for that is because of the scale to zero functionality
provided by knative. So essentially right now this pod
is not serving any traffic or any messages.
So knative is smart enough to understand that and
scale the deployment down to zero. So that is what
it is doing. Right now it is terminating the multiple containers.
We'll go into that later. As to why there are two containers
instead of one, because we specified only one container. We'll get into that later,
but for now understand that if I run the command again,
there are no resources present, although it was present before.
So it has scaled the deployment down to zero.
Next command that we can run is the
KgetksVC command.
Basically KSVC is short for knative
service. It is a custom resource definition created by the knative
client. And as you can see, this is the service that we
created. So hello, it has a URL, and this
URL points to the route which points to the
revision of our service. So this is a URL
that is created by the courier networking layer,
basically exposing the knative service
from the Kubernetes network outside and
exposing it to us on our local network. So if you
may know that Kubernetes runs its own network and our local network is
different from the Kubernetes network. So this essentially
allows us to communicate with the services present
in the Kubernetes network. So the knative Quickstart
command has set all of this up for us very nicely.
We don't have to deal with the configuration. So I'll just copy
this link and run a simple curl on this. I got
a response. Hello world. If I get the pods again, you can
see that there was a deployment, there was a pod created.
So essentially what it did was it scaled back
from zero to one to serve our request.
So this is how the knative serving
platform works and this is how the scale to zero functionality works.
So the next thing that I would like to go over is how you can
load test your serverless application. So there
is this neat tool called as hay, and this
tool essentially allows you to load test any application for that
matter. So this is the command, I will run this.
Basically what it is doing is it will load test our application for
roughly 10 seconds and it will concurrently try to send 100 requests
at a time on the URL, which would
be the URL of our service. So the URL
that we ran the curl command on, that is what it
will be getting through this. And once it
has finished its execution, it will run the get
pods command. So as we can see, it ran successfully.
And these were the pods at the end of this
lotus. And this was the report generated
by the hay command. So it ran for about 10 seconds roughly.
Slowest request was 1.6 seconds,
fastest was for this long, average was this
much. And in total it was able to
run 4390 requests per second.
So yeah, the next thing that I will be covering is
how we can specify a minimum
number of pod for our serverless
application in order to avoid the cold start problem.
So if you are familiar with this problem, basically what
happens is that if there are sudden requests
that come into your serverless application, so it takes some
time to scale up from zero. So the
first request or the first few requests can take
some time to be responded to rather than having
a consistent experience. So this is a well known problem in the serverless
ecosystem and how we can solve this problem
using the inative client. We'll look at
that by jumping into the vs code id again.
So we are back into the vs code id and as you can see
this is a different file, minscale Yaml.
But it is pretty similar to the hello world Yaml file that we
saw earlier with a few differences here I have
defined a few more annotations for this particular service.
So here we are mentioning a target of ten.
Essentially this tells knative that a
single pod should be handling ten concurrent requests at a time,
then target utilization percentage, so 80%.
So if the target utilization of
the pod has reached 80%, which would be eight in this
case, then scale up to the next pod.
So that we can specify. And next is min scale.
So min scale we have set to two. So keep a minimum of
two pods running at all times. So don't scale down to zero,
basically. And next, we have defined a panic window percentage
and a panic threshold percentage just in case if things go
wrong. So this is how you can customize
your knative service. There are a lot more things you can do,
and I just wanted to show you how you can customize
your serverless application. So let's jump back
to the terminal again and apply this new Yaml file before
applying any new Yaml file. As always, I like to do a diff on that
first. So get the diff. Minscale Yaml.
And since we did not change the service name in the
new Yaml file as well, we have kept it to hello itself. So it is
going to be making changes to the original service that we
created through hello World Yaml file. So as you can
see, it is only making a few additions, which were the annotations
that we had provided in the min scale Yaml file.
So everything good looks good to me. Let's go ahead and
apply so we can do that.
Minscale Yaml seems
like the command ran successfully without running into any errors.
And we can get the pods now.
Kubectl get pods. And as you can see
that this is revision two and there are
two pods running. Let me tell you that there will always be
two pods running at a time because we have set the min scale to
two, and essentially it won't
scale back down to zero. So now that we
have two pods running, I want to do a describe
on one particular pod. I'll do it on this pod.
I just want to show you as to why we have two
containers running for each pod. So one is the
container that we created which knative specifies as user
container. This is the image that we had mentioned.
And if we scroll down a bit, you can see
that there is another container called qproxy. So this
is a sidecar container that knative installs
in every pod so that it can communicate with the outside
world. So yes,
let's run the load testing command again and see if there are any changes,
since we now have minimum of two pods running at all times.
So I'll paste the same command that we ran before.
Again, it will run for roughly 10 seconds, send about 100 concurrent requests
at a time, and send those requests to the service URL
that we have created. So yes, it has
finished its execution and given us
this report. So as you can see, it roughly ran
for about 10 seconds. Slowest was this much.
You can see that the slowest request time has been reduced
drastically because now we have minimum of two pods running. So essentially
we have solved the cold start problem and the
fastest I believe is about the same average. Also I think got
reduced by a bit because of the cold start problem.
And average requests per second has also improved.
So yes, this was it. These were all
the things that I wanted to cover. And yeah, this is
the end of the demo and we can now jump back into
the slides. All right, so we are towards the
end of this talk. Before we conclude, I would like to recap all
the things that we covered in this talk.
So initially we started off with learning about the with
server architecture and the problems associated with it.
Next we looked at the serverless architecture and how those
problems can be addressed. Next we looked at
the conceptual overview of Kubernetes and the
building blocks that were required for the demo presented in this
talk. Then next we saw what is knative,
the features of knative and the components that are
provided by knative. And lastly, we jumped into the demo
where we saw knative in action and how we can
create our very own serverless infrastructure right within our
Kubernetes cluster. So yes, these were the points
that we covered. Before ending this talk, I would like
to mention my social media profiles so that you can
reach out to me if you stuck around till this point.
I would like to thank you and I hope that
you learned something new today. If you want to reach
out to me, if you have any questions, if you want to discuss anything
related to DevOps or anything related to tech in general, you can
do so by reaching out to me through the links provided on the slide
here. There are two QR codes. Also I have
provided for your convenience. So the first QR code will take you to a page
where all of my links would be present, and the second
QR code will take you to a GitHub repository where the file
that I worked with, instructions, the commands that I karan,
installation procedures, everything is mentioned in that GitHub repository.
And I would like to thank Conf 42 for having me
here and giving me this platform to talk about the things I love.
So yes, thank you. Thanks a lot.