Hello and welcome to this talk titled Kubernetes security jumpstart.
Like a real jumpstart. The goal of this talk is to start our
security journey in kubernetes. After this talk, hopefully you
will know all the different aspects of kubernetes that you need to secure and
what security really means in the scope of kubernetes or
in general. This is not an in depth tutorial on how to secure your Kubernetes
cluster. This is collection of bunch of different tools and techniques and ideas you
have to be careful about when you're trying to secure your Kubernetes cluster.
The slides to this talk are in this link at tiny cc k
eight s security. If you need to follow along and if you want to find
these slides, you can find it there. So I'll start with the question,
are computers less secure than real life? By real life
I mean you and I, our daily day to day life, when we think about
computers, we think of a lot of different things. But what I'm trying
to ask here is our computers less secure than real life?
So let's take some example. Is this secure? This door
with the door code on the top and on the handle? You could say
this is secure because you don't know what this door is.
Or how about this? Is this secure things?
Turnstile is trying to stop people from going into this space,
but as you can see, there's a wide gap next to it.
How about this? This is a door that has a push to exit, but that
you can kind of slide your hand through and kind of open the door from
outside. Hidden camera. This camera is trying to monitor things,
but it is blocked by a sign. Well, how about these
locks? These are padlocks, standard issue masters padlock
you can buy from any store and people use that to lock their gym
doors or something, some small locker. So one on the left is a
master lock, it's fairly common. One on the right
is a padlock makes by squire. It's a british company that
makes some of the strongest padlocks in the world. The one here,
it's a one could lock. And when it was created, it was declared
the strongest padlock in the world. So the year after that they decided,
you know what, that wasn't strong enough. We're going to make a stronger version of
that. We're going to make like a two could version of the same lock.
So that year, this lock was the strongest lock of the year.
Well, they thought, you know what, that's not good enough either. We're going to go
higher. We're going to have to make it stronger. So they made a five pound
version of the same lock, and that was, I mean, this is one of
the strongest padlock you can probably buy if you're not custom making it.
So what's the point of all this? What's the point of you showing you real
life scenarios or actual logs or like, security things people use in
day to day life? Security is a spectrum. Security is not a thing that,
oh, it's something is secure or not secure. Things can be
more secure or less secure. Never just secure. You can't have
something that is just secure. Well, in software,
you can probably have security in software that you didn't write. Only secure software
is where you have no code. But the moment you write code, the moment you
have infrastructure involved, you have a spectrum of security. Well, remember this
lock, the five pound lock? That is probably the strongest lock that you
can buy in the hand of lock picking lawyer. It's a YouTube
channel that deals with, like, lock picking. It took him four minutes to dismantle
the entire lock with some tools. So security is hard.
It is a spectrum. It is hard to get right, because attacking
computer is easier. We can attack a computer by hundreds of
other computers at the same time. In real life, we have a lot of assumptions
that you can make right. For example, most, many of us drive
here. How many times when you are driving, you have to worry about this scenario
happening. I'm going to assume and hope it's not. All of
us have to worry about this situation happening day to day. But when you
are a computer, software, everything is an adversary on the Internet. The moment your
application touches the Internet, everything on the Internet is trying to attack it
and exploit it. Trust no one. This is the agenda for the
talk today. We're going to talk about security and us, which we just touched upon
a little bit. We're going to talk about security in Kubernetes context. And finally we're
going to get started with Kubernetes security. Things talk in no way, shape or form
a full, complete tutorial on Kubernetes security. Security, as I
said, is a large spectrum and a lot of things is involved. But hopefully this
talk will give you ideas on things you need to worry about when you're building
your Kubernetes cluster or maintaining your Kubernetes cluster. My name is
Mophi. I'm a software engineer and a developer advocate at IBM. I mostly do container
stuff, write go code and collect stickers. If you need to find me in the
social media you can find me at Mufi codes in any of the social platforms
up above. So let's started talking about Kubernetes security.
Kubernetes security has few different aspects to it. Number one is
application security. The application you run on Kubernetes next is container
security, next image security, next infrastructure,
then network security. And finally we're going to talk about runtime kubernetes security.
Let's talk about application security a little bit. For application security use
best practices for application security. And this may sound a
little counterintuitive because I'm not really giving any proper advice because it
is quite hard to give you advice or information
about application security because it depends on the application you're writing, the runtime you're
using, the language you're using and everything around your runtime.
So just use the best practices for the language runtime
and the environment you're using it for. As Gordon Ramsey could
put it, I can't teach you that because that's common sense, although a
lot of this common sense information are not common at all. But again,
try to use the best practices. So let's talk about container security.
No unknown base image. So between the two
here, pop quiz, which one do you use? We have on one side we have
movie code, Golang Super Secret 116 and
Golang latest. Some of you may answer it's the right one
because the left one is an unknown base image. You are right, but you're also
wrong because none of things why? Because you have to lock
down versions you can't guarantee. Just because the Golang
latest is an official base image, you can't really guarantee this. Golang latest
is the Golang you build your application on top of this latest image
tag is a terrible image tag to use because that latest keeps
changing with every new version that comes around. So if you build your application for
Golang 112 and latest Golang 116,
117, 118, whatever comes out next might have some breaking changes
that now breaks your application. So never use latest.
So let's look at two Golang versions. So one of
them is Golang 116 three Alpine 313 which is
very specific. It's a tag that is pretty good.
It's not necessarily the best, but it's still pretty good.
But the best way to lock down version is by using digest Sha
you have like the image itself and the Shia is built using
the image content. So every time you use this image you
are guaranteeing that you are building things image on the version that
you tested and have verified. Your application works so use digest
Shah when possible. And it's pretty much if you're using any kind of like image
registry, it's almost always possible to use digest Sha. So make sure
you use it. Next update for vulnerability remediation. So if
you're using something like node and NPM packages,
every once in a while you would see that your NPM packages have some vulnerabilities
and you need to update your images. So there are tools we're going to talk
about later that lets you kind of look at your images
and find out if there's any vulnerability in them. Next is limited
attack vector. What does this mean? So this basically means
you should try to use smaller base images. So if you
have a choice between Alpine and Debian, you should probably go with alpine because it
is a smaller image with less things in it. So you have a less chance
of exposing something that you didn't want to expose. And if you
have a compiled language that can take binary, definitely look
into scratch images. So scratch are empty container
based images that only can run compiled binary.
So if you're using languages like Go, C, C Plus plus or rust,
or using Java with GralvM, you could take advantage of
this container base image that has nothing other than the binary. So your attacker doesn't
have anything to attack your container images on. So let's talk about image security
a little bit. So for image security, the best practice here is least
privileged access. If your user doesn't need to be root,
make sure you're never root. Always use some user creation within the
container image so that you're running as user 5000, which a
random user who doesn't have any special permission in the container
image. One thing I always like to say is root is the root of all
evil. If your container image, if you're running as root, if somehow that
image escapes now in the host, that user is now
root as well and can wreak havoc. So you want to make sure your container
image is running as non root users. It's kind of like things situation,
right? Like your container is that small rhino
inside the enclosure, but somehow it kept
in gap. Now this rhino is out in the world, but now this rhino is
also a root user. So outside and out in the world
that this rhino can do anything they want. So you have to make sure the
cage you're building for your container is really secure. Also,
if it by mistake does go out, it doesn't have any permission to do anything
extra. Let's talk a little bit about infrastructure security at this point. So again,
Kubernetes is abstracting away a lot of the infrastructure,
but underneath all of it, it's still, there are bare metals or
vms or what have you. So we have to make sure that our underlying infrastructure
is secure to make sure our application is secure. So don't expose
underlying infrastructure. That kind of seems like common sense,
but like in the last few years there have been a number of these exploits
where hackers have attacked the master node or the worker
node itself. So where Kubernetes security was not broken, but they broke into
the underlying vms and master nodes and got access to it.
Famously we had the cryptojacking of the Tesla Kubernetes servers
where their master node, the Kubernetes dashboard,
was actually insecure without any password. So they found the master node
IP and just like accessed it directly from their computer and
now then had AWS s three secrets exposed.
Metadata is more valuable than you think. So when you're a Kubernetes cluster,
information you get to yourself. You have information
like your master node IP. When you're using Kubectl to connect to it.
This information might not seem like without the secret it might not seem
super valuable, but the moment someone knows your node IP,
then they can started even start doing some DDoS attacks on
the node. So if your node is too busy like just serving random
requests, your Kubernetes cluster might go down because it can't reserve your network traffic
hardened nodes. So you should make sure that your node doesn't
have SSH enabled. That's just like security 101. At this point
you could make sure that there is no other way to access your
nodes. Don't expose the node IPS if you can,
and all of these good practices you can start doing. So. Make sure your
node underlying infrastructure itself is following the best security
policies. Update regularly. So every once in a while under Linux
like Ubuntu or like a red hat Enterprise Linux, whatever underlying node
Linux environment you're using might have some vulnerability that leaks
something or just something is vulnerable. So you have to make sure the underlying
infrastructure is updating as well as update the Kubernetes version
when the new version comes out after some testing. Because if you have a too
old of a version, you might just open yourself up for some
vulnerability that was fixed in a later patch. And just by not fixing
the zero day vulnerabilities you're just opening yourself up for these kind of attacks.
So let's talk a little bit about now. Network security. So Kubernetes is
environments for microservice applications. So you have a lot of network traffic,
both internally from service to service and externally from service
to other applications. You have to be very careful about making sure
your network security is up to date and working to keep
everything secure. So network segmentation. So this is the idea of making sure internally,
within the same Kubernetes cluster, you have segments where your application
is isolated to talk to, only the application they need to talk to,
rather than opening it up to everything in the cluster. So by default,
any pod in any namespace in Kubernetes can talk to any other pod in
any node. But that is not the best system for security. So what you
want to do is make sure that you are locking it up so that
it can only talk to things they have to talk to.
For example, you can use network policy, and here we are
only allowing incoming traffic from front end to go
to back end and nowhere else. So that my back end pod selectors will
only allow traffic to come in from front end. So if someone gets
access to a random pod in your cluster and someone
just hijacks that pod, they won't be able to make network traffic calls
to your back end if this policy is in place.
So some runtime Kubernetes security practices that you can use
is use RBaC. RBAC stands for role based access control.
So RBaC tries to answer this question, can subject
verb object. One of the example this could be can user
list pods. So every time you set up an RBaC rule, this is the rule
you're trying to set. You could also set RBaC rules to
individual namespaces. So then the question becomes, can user list pod in
namespace? So you could have RBaC rules that are either specific
to entire cluster or specific to single namespaces.
So one of the examples, so this right here is example of
a role that is bound to a namespace. So in this case, namespace default,
we're creating a role that allows our user to
list pods. So get watch and list pods. And we're doing
a role binding to connect that role to a subject. So in this case,
our subject is a user username is Jane, and role
is then is going to be a read pod reader role. So things user
Jane now will be able to get watch or list pod.
So the command kubectl get pods will succeed.
But if they try to do something like kubectural delete pod, that would fail because
this user Jane does not have permission to delete pods.
Define quotas. So every resource you create, you can define some sort
of quota. In this example we're creating a resource quota and adding
some sort of limit like how much memory you want to give, how much cpu
you want to give, or in
every single pod you can also create some sort of resource coder by saying we
want to use 00:25 cpu, 128 megs of ram and
also limit that kind of like different limits as well. So why is
using resource code a security mechanism? So the ways resource
coder help is limit attack surface and damage. So let's
say one of your pod gets compromised and someone gets access to
your pod if there is a limit, if the pod
tries to access too much resource, kubernetes API can
then kill that pod if it's asking for too much resource. If you don't have
a resource limit, that pod in theory can just
request too much resource and block out all other application
that's running on your cluster. Also with resource coda. Another side effect
or the main reason you want to use resource coda, that is you can get
better resource utilization. If the scheduler knows upfront how
much resource things applications is asking for, it can schedule it
in a location that has exactly that much resource available and thus you
can reach over like 70% to 80% cluster utilization.
So that's why resource quotas are great. Finally, when you actually put a
resource quota in your applications on your pod and deployment,
Kubernetes actually marks these pods and application with a higher priority.
So if you have limit and requests both set and are equal,
your application is quality of service is rated as guaranteed.
That means this is the last thing Kubernetes will delete
and usually won't delete ever. And if you don't have any limit or
request set, what happens is your quality of service is listed as best effort.
So if something more priority comes along, Kubernetes API might
actually delete this particular application. So putting resource quota is
not only useful for security, it's also useful for your application so the application
doesn't get booted when there is more resource needed. Monitor and log and this
is not necessarily anything specific to Kubernetes. Anytime you have application and
runtime, you want to make sure that you're monitoring and logging those information into some
location, and so that if something does go wrong, you can immediately
find it. And even if you immediately can find it, you can have a location
where you can go find information later. Pods are ephemeral. So if you have
pod logs just printed out on the pod itself, when the pod
dies, something goes wrong. Those logs will be gone as well. So you'll have no
way of knowing why a pod died. So I have some sort of central logging
mechanism, hopefully outside the cluster that is constantly
adding these logs into so that you can go back and trace
why something went down. If some bad actor tried to make
too many requests too quickly, you can then look at it and have
some mechanism, have some way to alert or have some way to
kill that thing. But you can't do that without having a location where you're collecting
and aggregating this information. Admission controllers so admission controllers in
Kubernetes is a way where every time you make a request
or every time you try to create some new resource on Kubernetes,
you can run those resources requests through this admission
controller. So admission controller kind of looks like this. When you make an API request
using Kubectl or directly using the Kubernetes API,
it takes the authentication, all that is done.
Then it goes to mutating admission and this webhook
can mutate your request. And then after the request
has been mutated you can then go through validation and validation
can stop a deployment if it doesn't follow the validation
webhook. And finally it gets persisted to etCD.
And then at some point the reconciler takes that information and make your cluster
state that. So why is admission webhooks useful?
So you can use admission webhooks for pretty much anything. But one of the
key security features they can do is look at some policy that
you have in your company and make sure each of the resource
that you are applying or deploying to your Kubernetes cluster follows those things.
For example, if you want to make sure that you have quotas defined on
all resources, you can put that in a webhook. And every time a new resource
is being created, if it doesn't have a quota specified, either you can have
a mutating webhook that adds a quota automatically, some default
quota, or have a validating webhook. If it doesn't have a quota defined,
it can just reject the application of that particular deployment.
And it could be for a number of things. If you're trying to add privilege
escalation, if you don't have AC Linux profile set and any number of
things in between, you could do that using admission webhooks encrypt at
rest. So by default the HCD database that where Kubernetes
stores all its states is not encrypted. So to secure
your information like secrets and other things, you need to make sure that your ETCD
database is encrypted at rest so that no bad actor
can access that information. Well, as Gandalf would say,
keep it secret, keep it safe. So now let's talk
tools. We talked about all the different things we need to worry about. Now let's
see what are the tools in the ecosystem that we have to our disposal to
make that job easier for us. Always be careful with your tools
because it's very easy to burn ourselves when we are trying to
use a new tool that we don't really take into consideration, what are the
effects that could happen? But with that in mind, I'm going to talk about some
of the different tools that touch upon different aspects of security.
Most of them are open source. There are some paid products. None of them are
endorsement. I have tried some of them out, I have found many of
them in the ecosystem. So none of these listed here
are like, and they are not listed in a particular order. So don't take
this listing as any recommendation or kind of a vote
of confidence. The ones I have tried and the ones I have kind
of played around with, I can say if they are good and decent
at what they do. But again, when you are trying to do that for your
application, your company, please do some more research into them to find.
But if they fit the need that you have. So let's first
talk about image scanning and analysis. So when you are building container
images or you have a container image, you want to make sure that this image
doesn't have any vulnerability. There are a number of image scanning tools
both in open source and paid. Some of them would be encore,
Claire Dockle, Cubexray, sneak, trivi these are
all tools. Some of them are free Apache MIT
licenses and some of them has commercial offering
tied to them. So they are part of a larger commercial offering.
Let's look at a demo of a couple of these tools here in
the list. Dockle good with tech test
image v one. So guru tech is the creator of this
tool dockle and they have a test image that you can run this against.
So you're going to run that against this guru tech and this
will just like download the image and scan the image,
all the contents there and you'll see that we have some fatal things that are
coming out of this. Talking about instead of copy we should use add
do not store credential environments, clear app get
caches. That is to make sure our image size is smaller.
We're using avoid empty's password. There are a bunch of things that are bad and
you can actually put this in between your CI when
you're trying to build your image to make sure your image doesn't have any problems.
So if you see any of the fatal errors you could stop your
CI build and fail the CI build. Another image that does similar thing
is called three v. With three v we can point it to
one of our Golang latest image and it will look at
the image and it will find bunch of things and many of these things
are from the CVE. So these are list of container vulnerability that are
found for Linux and it can list bunch of these things, right? And based
on these issues either we can update our image or we can
fail this build depending on if the error is something that
we need to update. You can use both dockle and trivia in your CI
and in their documentation. They have documentation for how to use them in your
CI pipeline and make sure that you are taking into consideration that your image
scan like whatever value you get from your image scan. So let's move on.
So let's talk about runtime security a little bit. So for runtime
security in Kubernetes what we are talking about is your cluster
is ready, your cluster is running. We want to learn things about that cluster,
whether or not the cluster is set up properly or the things you deploy
to things cluster. So again these
are a little bit more involved to set up. So we're not going to look
at a demo, but there are some really big hitters here.
For example Falco is a sysdig project. They do a lot of these security things
that you inject into your Kubernetes cluster. They monitor the cluster real time
and every time something bad is happening someone is trying to access the cluster
in a way that is not allowed. It can create this
monitoring alerts that you can look at. You can also set up SC,
Linux and Seccomp to make sure that you are limiting the
amount of things a container could do within the cluster. And these
are definitely like each of them demand their
own talk in their own rights. But you could set up these kind of rules
to make sure that your container has the most least
amount of access to do things in your cluster as possible.
So let's look at the network security a little bit. So for network security
there are a bunch of network overlays in Kubernetes and
each of them aside from the network policy that is based on
Kubernetes itself, if you are using any of these other things as your
network overlay, for example in IBM cloud, Kubernetes we use Calico
as a network overlay, and Calico has things you could do as well in
terms of network policy that can go even more fine grained compared to
the general Kubernetes network policy. So if you find out exactly
which network overlay your Kubernetes cluster is using, you can make use
of the particular network policy rules
from your provider to make sure that your cluster network policy
is really secure. Secrets management and this one is a tough one,
because by default kubernetes secrets are not necessarily secret,
they are just base 64 encoded. Although you could encrypt your HTTP
cluster at best, even then your secret anyone who has access
to the cluster can be read by and then converted
base 64 from regular text. So creating secret in
kubernetes is not probably the best idea. So the way you want to create secret
is probably using some sort of secrets management, either using
some kms from your cloud provider where your Kubernetes cluster is,
or using tools like vault where you have either deployed
yourself or managed from Hashicorp. Get vault
that you can store secrets and inject secrets at runtime directly to your application
for image distribution. There are a number of tools. You have
grapheus in Toto Portieris and each of them does something
a little bit different. But all of them has the idea that if your image,
when you're distributing an image, how do you make sure that
image is coming from the right place? Especially portiers
has admission webhook that can look at an image and make sure
this image is coming from a whitelisted source. So each of the
tools, they are open source so you can deploy your own version of it.
They're dealing with the idea how you can distribute an image from
a secure source and securely to your end user.
Security audit so for your kubernetes, there are ways to audit
both the deployment yamls and the cluster itself.
For example, tools like Kubebench or
kubernetes, they're both from Aqua security. You can run it against a running
cluster and that can check against some fixed rules to see if
your cluster is set up properly. Kube audit is pretty
cool. It can look at a YAML file that you have about
to deploy to your cluster and check against the YAML
file to see if the YAML file is following proper Kubernetes
guidelines, and it can also fail your continuous delivery
pipeline. If the YAML file you're about to deploy is not up to
mark, you have Kubesec does something very similar.
It can give you a scoring and it can fail your build. And finally,
open policy agent in this scenario is probably one of the best tool that
is out there for auditing your running Kubernetes cluster deployment
where can define any kind of rule. So all the things we could do
with admission webhook it is quite difficult to write your admission webhook from
scratch with open policy agent you can define all that and more
using very simple rules and logic. And every time
you try to deploy something new it gets validated against the open policy
agent webhook and you can then stop deployment because it doesn't
match the set security rules that you have in your company. Let's look
at a couple more demos that showcases a couple of the
tools. We're not going to talk about open policy agent in this one in terms
of demo because again that's a much more in depth demo and definitely deserves in
its own talk to cover all the different things you could do with open policy
agent. So we are running a Kube audit against the deployment
that I have and this is checking for all the different things
that we have. So if I run this against my deployment Yaml,
you will see that we are getting a lot of errors. So one of them
here is app armor settings is not set up,
automount service account, token true and default service account.
So in this deployment YAmL, we are not using like
a special service account, we are using the default service account for the namespace
which is not best security practices capability or security context
missing. We are not adding any specific security context.
We are not doing run as non root. So run as non root
is not set to true allow privilege escalation neil so
we are not also stopping our container to privilege escalate
to root here either. So all these things we should set but we are not
in this yAml. And so this cube audit tool is
failing this particular YAML file. So if we set it up in our CD
and run cube audit when you are about to deploy our YAML file,
we could fail the build because our deployment YAML
is not up to mark. We can also do something similar with Cubesec.
Cubesec also can scan our YAML file and in this case
we are looking at some, we get a score of
four. So we got a passed because we have a limit set,
we have a memory set, we have cpu set as well as request
memory is also set. Some of that they also give some advice in
terms of not directly errors, but give some advice like set app
armor use service account, seccom root file system non root and run
as user. So all these things, as you can see, both Cubesec and Cube audit
does a very similar thing. So you can choose either of them in your
pipeline to make sure that you are failing builds that doesn't
follow the best security policies. Now finally, let's talk about some of
the end to end commercial security products that are out there. So the ones I
talked about, most of them are open source, but some of them are tied to
some bigger commercial offering. With commercial offering we get
enterprise support as well as probably a nice dashboard
that can constantly be scanning your kubernetes cluster and updating you
with the vulnerability that it found. So there are a number of them obviously,
because again this industry have a lot of choices for almost everything. I list
some of them here. This is in no way shape or form a complete
list. So when you're doing your security you may come across something newer
or something even better than this. But there are some of them I'm going to
talk about. You definitely have aqua security. They put out a lot of open
source tools in the community as well. There are a bunch of them in the
list like sysdig as well, twist lock and a number of them.
And there's like a quick comparison between some of them.
And each of those tools have these different capabilities.
And just because something has more capability, that doesn't necessarily mean
they are better or worse than the other tools. It just means as of
now and they are claiming to have all these different tools. It might be
possible for you to look at these tools when you are
trying to use one of them, that you may not need all kind of
all of these capabilities. So for your application you might look
at one of these tools and see that the capability they offer is all
we actually need. So definitely keep this list in mind.
Look at this and look at all the features each of them provide. But also
keep in mind that just because having a huge list of
different things some of these tools has to offer doesn't necessarily
mean how good each of those tools are. So again, I would implore you to
kind of do your own exploration, try them out,
use the trial and see which application here fits your
need the most. Finally, let's talk but service meshes.
Service mesh, there are quite many of them now. The notable ones would be
istio Linkerd one and two kuma mesh. So service
mesh are a collection of best in class solutions that
brings in bunch of things that right now is quite
difficult to do just in kubernetes. And you have to do a lot of these
things yourself to do them well. So service meshes control and
monitor service traffic. They are invisible to dev team,
which is a great thing. Your development teams won't have to worry about where your
application runs to build really cool applications. And finally,
they can enable mtls between service to service traffic.
So when you have mutual TLS enabled between service, what you
can achieve from it is if by any chance one of your pods
gets compromised without the proper TLS certificate, that pod
won't be able to talk to some other pod it is not allowed to talk
to in the first place. So you can really limit the amount of things a
bad actor can do. Even if they get access to your application?
Even if they get access to the application pod. It also lets transparent
monitoring of network traffic. So you'll automatically collect these metrics
from the network traffic as they're passing through. Can kind of look at what exactly
is happening in your cluster if one of their pod all of a sudden
starts to make too many requests. You can monitor that, set up some alerts and
take action based on that to make sure that your cluster is
not going crazy. So let me ask this question again,
right? We talked about a lot of these things and after talking about
this for about the last 2025 minutes, are computers less secure than real
life? Right? Like we have a lot of problems in computer security.
At the same time, we have a lot more tools too to make sure that
this security vulnerability doesn't affect us directly. As I said,
and I'm going to say it over and over again, security is a spectrum.
Nothing is like secure. It could be more secure or less secure.
Never just secure. When I think of kubernetes security or security in general,
this picture comes to my mind. Let's say our bike is the application and
we want to make sure this application is secure. So all we are trying to
do is put more and more and more locks on things bike,
so that at the end of the day it's not worth for the thief to
try to get rid of all these locks to steal our bike in
terms our data and application. So when we try to secure our application,
all we are trying to do is to make sure that sealing the
data, stealing the information, breaking into this application
is not worth the time. With that, go out there
and secure your kubernetes and your applications in general.
Hopefully I have managed to show you what are the
different things you need to worry about when you're trying to secure your kubernetes cluster.
And I'm trying to free your mind, but I can only show you the door.
You are the one that has to walk through it. Great. DevOps Admin Morpheus
said that to Neo once and I'm saying that to you now. With that.
That is the end of the talk. Thank you so much for spending the last
30 odd minutes with me and listening to me about kubernetes
security. I'd love to hear your stories, comments, questions and
any cool security stories that you have. You can find me at movie
codes and if you have any questions, feel free to drop by and ask me
on Twitter. Thank you.