Hello and welcome to my talk. I'm going to be sharing a bunch of anecdotes
that encouraged during my last decade of development.
And there has been a bunch of crazy stuff, mostly due
to myself. First anecdotes in
the series that I chose based on no order whatsoever
is how I learned to do Linux administration.
Basically it was the middle of the night, which is a perfect time for doing
any sort of administration Linux production servers.
So I wanted to delete some stuff. It was in a
separate directory and normally I'm going to delete it
with using pseudo privileges. So pseudo
remove recursively everything under slash.
Now for those not so versed into Linux as I was
that moment that deletes everything from hard drive.
And good thing is some things stay in memory. So there exists
at a brief moment in time there was absolutely nothing on
the hard drive, but website was working after 30 seconds.
Once the realization hit me about what I just did,
I had to boot up the new server, install all
the requirements, do got deployment, set up
all permission, check if everything is working correctly,
and dont DNS server to that. Now that
woke me up very fast. If you want to switch from Red
Bull or coffee, I warmly recommend deleting
production servers. That's going to wake you up very quickly. And I remembered
almost everything from stack orderflow that I googled
in that panicked moment. So that's how you should
start your morning now. Another crazy stuff that I
did was basically using text editor
for the development. I know there are some super smart people,
they can do text editor for development of complex
programs, but myself am got among them.
I love my autocomplete, I love syntax checking,
all that stuff. So using Notepad,
notepad Plus, but just notepad for
the first two or three weeks of my career was
not a good choice. To make it even better, I was
doing basically had one file would write into it,
then FTP uploads to the production server because what
else? And if I managed to mess
up the PHP syntax production site would crash. But that
was okay because client was in USA and you would
not notice that. So develop in the completely opposite time
zone of your clients. That's a very good lesson if you're going to use
production server for your testing purposes later. I did realize how
you can create your local environment and why you should have a staging
environment and dev environment when it comes to that.
Things that I learned after that is version control.
That was super amazing stuff that I discovered before entire
mankind. Since what I was doing is
every time I would upload a file to production server
using FTTP. I would just make
copy of that file with a timestamp and that way I could return
to it later if there was need for that. I was watching YouTube at
the time and I saw somebody talking about version control and
I realized this cool, be good. I started using it and
it was super fun. Then I think it was two years
after I realized that branches existed in git and after that
everything was super awesome. Another thing that is super useful
is you should always try to be the smartest person in
the room. That way everything you say is absolutely correct,
no matter how insane it is. Since we were working at the startup in the
first company we didn't have lots of resources, so we hired a bunch of juniors
and me with my six months of experience was leading them technical
disaster in all the possible ways. Seniors are
expensive, but they are less expensive than juniors. Try to have
a mix of them and company culture is important.
Also, I realize I can be pretty stupid at
the time, so I need somebody smarter to tell me when I'm making crazy stuff.
Now that first startup was done, I realized,
okay, in the end we managed to create something good because it was a
search engine, it had some super good performances
and you could get the listing from million track articles
in less than 15 milliseconds. With the solar that's super good.
Now design was created by me in the first version,
which means that everybody who visited that website started
bleeding from the iris. But later I hired a designer.
That's probably smartest thing I did at that point, and website looked
pretty good. Now why did that website or startup
failed? Well, after one and a half year we realized
we do not have any sorts of monetization plan.
So before you start working on a project or a startup,
figure out how you're going to make money. That's one of the things that's
pretty crazy to me today because for most of the Silicon Valley
companies, their business plan is we're going to get
zillion users, then we're going to get funding, then we're
going to got acquired. Myself, based on my lessons, I love
to get business plan early, see how I'm going to
monetize this project. It doesn't mean writing 50 pages of business plan,
but I need to know how this thing is going to make money and focus
on that. So with that in mind, I decided we should
start the second startup. Now we are all smarter and super good.
Same team and me. We decided we're going to make social
network because it was 2012 2015.
You can check on my LinkedIn profile. I do not remember the years,
but social network movie came up and our main investor
really wanted to make social network and we were
all very excited. Now since social network was very hype at the
moment, there was also another technology that was super
hyped and you know what? That was NoSQL.
Normally we started the project with MongoDB and everything
was super good because we were ready for a web scale.
Two years later, I did realize that majority of the code
I have written related to communication with database
was to turn it into relational database. So that's
my lesson to you. In 95% of the cases,
relational database is perfectly fine for you. You do not need to
jump straight into NoSQL. And when you do, you need to know why are
you jumping into NoSQL database. Do not be afraid. Relational databases
are good. I can assure you I've been working with them after I learned
my lesson. The second lesson that I learned during that
whole trip is dont get hype driven. That second
startup was pretty amazing to multiple factors,
mostly because I learned how not to do things.
Our main investor, he loved having meetings
because those would inspire us. So every day we had
hour and a half meeting where we would listen to speeches
and get super inspired and get motivated to work
whole day. This is not me making fun of my clients.
This is me telling you how I failed to communicate
and manage that project. Today, I would not allow client
to hold that many unproductive meetings that had absolutely
no point. I would communicate better. At least I hope
I would communicate better to a client that his time can be spent in
much more productive way. At that point in time, I did not know how
to say no to the clients, because sometimes you need to say, this is not
working. Also, we worked on that project for a year and a
half before actually getting to our users. Now that's
another lesson that's very well done, because once
we release it, we release. Nobody's going to use this stuff.
And always talk to your users,
see if they want to use that crazy thing you're building. They may want
to, they may not want to, but talk to them because you
want to fail fast as possible. Less money spent and
more you can focus on something else. And another thing is talk
to your team. I did not communicate very well with my team.
One time I decided to speak with each of the team members,
15 of us. And what happened is I just asked him a
simple stuff, what are we making? I got 15 different answers,
myself included in those, they were not even the similar. Everybody thought
we were building the different thing. And I can assure you that product
looked absolutely schizophrenic and was
unusable. Now, after that, I started doing consulting
because it should be less stressful than developing your
own product. And I had plenty of python architecture skills.
I encountered some very interesting clients. Sometimes it
would be nontechnical client. Those are very difficult to work with
because what you need to do is establish the trust between
you and them. Basically assure them that you are
not trying to steal money from them and that you know how to do your
work. Almost all of the time you're going to be asked to send a proposal,
and that proposal is going to be beautiful. I know
that because I believe in each and one of you. You make
beautiful proposals. Client is going to go over 20 pages of that proposal.
It's going to ignore completely everything else. So what
I learned during that is that you need to talk with your clients before sending
them proposal to figure out what's important to them. Is it just the pricing?
Is it quality of the work? What are their biggest
fear? What problems are they trying to solve? Because sometimes clients
just want to try making something and sometimes the
project they're wanting to build actually requires bunch
of expertise from their side and is critical to their business.
You need to differentiate between those two. Based on that, you can
make your proposal. I can guarantee your proposal is going to
stand out once you've done your research and figure out what exactly client
wants, than if you just send them the proposal. If you just send them
the proposal, it's going to get ignored. Because if you got
your job or contract just based on the price, there's always
going to be somebody who can do it cheaper. Now,
another anecdotes. One time we were building a simple
video player and client was pretty successful in his business,
decided to bring more innovation into
our product. So I asked him, okay, what sort of innovation?
He said, don't you think that majority of
players are just one dimensional? I said,
okay, what do you mean exactly? You can move
backwards and forward in the video. How about we make it
three dimensional? Okay, so you
can go backwards and forwards in the video, up and down,
could handle the volume. And what's
the third dimension? You can go backwards and forwards.
So I thought to myself, what's the third dimension?
You can control videos. Would that be something else?
However, client had very much confidence into me and told me,
you can figure it out. Now, I spent about
two weeks trying to figure but how to
create the player controls that would work in three dimensions.
And when I figured something out, I talked with clients and he already
forgot. So don't be afraid to
tell clients that they can be a bit crazy or let
idea slip for a bit, because that can happen.
Now, the most interesting type of clients that
I encounter are clients that have friends that
know something. Basically, they would
get friends to tell them what's good or not. In my
case, since I love doing things with Python, I would make
a proposal for writing entire website in Python because I
know that stuff. The client would ask their friend and they would tell me,
yeah, but their friend says they're using Java in their company,
so Python is no good. And I was like, okay, but you can write website
in. No, no, they're not using Python.
Well then you need to find, no, no, no, we want
you to write in Java. So after back and forth asked to
speak with their friend and they told me, yeah, you can write stuff
in Python as well. Sometimes it
pays to talk to the friends of the clients that are giving them awesome advice.
Sometimes it just pays to pass on the
project. And one anecdote that every designer is going to
tell you is the moment when their client's child told them that a logo
design is not nice and they need to change it.
Luckily, since I'm backend developer, nobody ever gave me
a compliment and told me, oh my gosh, your backend code
is so beautiful. Most of the time what they tell me is,
okay, it's working or it's not working, fix it right away.
So that's what I do. Ash, I'm sure most of you have come to
hear the story about nuclear silo and Python development.
Well, at the peak of 218,
when blockchain was all decraised as it is now,
client decided to create a new blockchain and they invested
a bunch of money into that blockchain. So one time,
since I was a contractor and I was the most expendable person
on the team, but sadly, I was the only person
who knew the entire back end because I built it. I was
also the person who could not be easily fired. So they put me
as a sacrificial lamp to hear an idea from the CEO
because nobody else could say no to him because they would
get fired. I said, okay, I know something crazy is going
to happen, but let's hear it. CEO starts telling
me, okay, since we are developing this blockchain and
it's going to got super popular, what we should do
is basically buy a nuclear silo and
put our servers there move everything from AWS to
nuclear silo, and that's going to be super secure.
And I was thinking back a little, because my first question
is, you can buy nuclear silos.
To which my response I got,
yes, they're selling decommissioned nuclear silo for
just 800,000. For me, that's a super good
deal. I don't have that kind of money, but if I ever wanted to buy
decommissioned nuclear silo, that's a super good price. So I
tried to explain to a client that that's not how computer security
works. AWS has a good security system.
You just need to configure it. And we had a bunch of back and
forth, and then I realized I'm using technical language.
So I explained to him that using nuclear
silos to secure your blockchain servers is the same thing
as buying a dog and putting it next to your computer
to ward off the hackers. And that worked.
That metaphor solved everything. We did not buy the nuclear silo,
which is super sad because I cool have worked on nuclear silo
project, but can't have everything. And what he didn't
mention that meeting, which I probably should, is that security
and nuclear silos were not the biggest problem on that project.
Problem was that nobody was using that blockchain. It was
pretty much useless. So, lesson for everybody.
Focus on project market fit, get some users,
then try to solve problems in that area.
And another client wanted us to write a file system
for a website that was basically a marketplace. And I
asked him why, and he said, well,
Google and Facebook, they all have proprietary technology. So that's
AWS. We should have our own proprietary technology. So let's write everything
from the start. When client asks you something like that,
then you know you're going to lose a bunch of times.
So what they did is just make an estimate how much it would
cost to reinvent a file system,
how much it would cost to rewrite entire database
from zero and stuff like that. And he realized that for
his $10,000 web store, he did not need custom
file system and database, and all was good.
One thing I realized pretty quickly is that I have no
idea how to do design. Because this goes way back
into the time when I thought I actually can do design.
Now, I'm not sure if you remember, but in the time of dial
up days, Flash was all the craze. So I created a
website that had five megabytes of Flash file
that was always playing music and animation on a web page.
And you could not stop that music. And I was super impressed because I was
16 and that was my first website. What was crazy
to me is while I was getting so little visitors,
oh my gosh, this works super fast on my local machine,
but when I tried to visit it from my friend's house, it turns out it
takes 20 minutes to load it up. Yeah,
I would like to say that I learned the lesson, but as you already
know me, I did not. I just left that website
because fault was my friend's computer, not his Internet
connection, so it was just him. I did try to find that website
several years ago, but it's gone. Probably for the
best. Also, one of the good things I learned is that
I have no idea how front end works because
in the olden days before the Javascript alien had a debugger,
all the synchronous stuff, all the craziness that was happening there.
Internet explorer six, that's all I'm going to say. That was
super crazy to me because I love deterministic behavior as
people say. I don't hate front end, some of my best
friends do front end and my younger brother, he does front end
and he's super good and he writes tests for
front end. I'm probably only thing I can write
in front end is background red in CSS.
So learn your limitations.
Learn what you want to do and what you don't want to do. Because at
the end of the day at this job, you're going to be working it hopefully
just 8 hours per day. And spending all that time on something you
do not like and do not enjoy is not worth it in the end.
Also, let's see, I probably have some bunch of cool anecdotes.
Oh yeah. When I had a cool idea about got having a
set work time, like when I said to my team, you know,
we are super organized and we were all junior developers,
we can work as much as we want as long as we finish
our tasks. So if you want to work 2 hours per day it's perfectly
fine. If you don't want to work Monday or stuff like that,
perfectly fine. What happened was utter chaos
because fronted was waiting on design, back end was
working on something that was obsolete and stuff like that.
What happened after that is at one point I realized we were
working 14 12 hours per day. I don't know if you ever
done that, but that's soul crushing to say
the least. So after that I went back to hang regular hours.
It worked fine. Like you don't need to reinvent the wheel.
I'm hoping you can get it below 40 hours because I'm
going to say this on the programming conference, but personal life
is more important than your programming skills.
I spent last decade programming, and most of the stuff I remember happened
outside of programming. You deserve to have a life. Yeah, life tip
and I think that's all the wisdom I have to show
for at the moment. What I would like to do is had something
super crazy and super amazing happen to you. Please share
with me. You can reach me on LinkedIn. There's probably going to be
link in the description or somewhere else. I also love having virtual
coffee with people. I met all sorts of amazing people on
Internet. So unlike what most people tell you,
Internet is full of nice people. Thank you very much for listening my talk.
I hope you enjoy it.