Welcome to the conf session on advanced mixing port of warfare.
So this talk will be about how different quantum technologies can assist
modern warfare in improvising their performance.
So this will be the slow of this talk. I will start with the definition
followed by the main components of the quantum technology. Then I will discuss
different warfare mechanisms followed by later section on
global progress. Then I will go through the challenges in concluding revamps.
Let's start with the down quantum workfare in simple perks.
It refers to the utilization of quantum technologies for military strategies,
operations and weapon systems. It uses the superior cover bridges
of quantum advancements, which surpass traditional methods in encryption
data processing. In environmental sciences, these innovations can
connectively optimize logistics, improve the decision making processes,
and enhance the performance of autonomous systems.
The foundational principles of quantum mechanics were established in
the early 20th century, with the contribution by Max Planck, Albert Einstein,
Nielsburg, etcetera. These early developments were purely
theoretical and not connected to webpage. Then, during the Cold War era,
both the United States and the Soviet Union invested heavily
in scientific research, including quantum mechanics. So while the
primary focus was on nuclear and conventional arms, there was also some
theoretical research into quantum effects in various other technologies
like radar, cryptography, etcetera. Following that, in the 1980s,
quantum gate distribution was proposed, which laid the groundwork for secure communication
methods, and this could theoretically be applied to military communications as
well. Then, in the 21st century, advancements in quantum computing
and sensing technologies started showing potential military applications.
Governments and defense organizations began exploring these technologies
for secure communication, advanced sensing and navigation systems.
Today, countries like the united states, China,
etc. Are heavily investing in quantum technology research,
military applications, and this includes quantum radar,
quantum sensing for submarines, quantum communication satellites, and so on.
The current research on the quantum technology can be classified into three main components,
quantum computing, quantum communication, and quantum sensing.
Let's start with the quantum computing part. It's when you use the
principles of quantum mechanics for performing operations and computation.
This is done with the help of a quantum quantum computer uses qubits instead of
classical bits. So these quantum computers come in various types,
each based on different principles and technologies. For example,
IBM and Google use superconducting qubit based quantum computers.
Then we have ironq and Honeywell, which uses trapped irons, quantum annealers by
d five, and so on. Each type of quantum computer has
its own strengths and challenges. They are specifically used to solve complex
problems. So these quantum computers usually function as subroutines
within classical computer programs, with classical systems managing
the main control and performing tasks less efficient for quantum processing.
Due to their size and need for cryogenics, quantum computers
are unlikely to be personal devices in the near future. Instead,
they are accessed by cloud services offered by platforms such
as Microsoft and Amazon Prickett, which integrate quantum computing
resources from various manufacturers into a unified ecosystem.
Now let's see some aspects of quantum computing. The first one
is quantum machine learning and artificial intelligence. Quantum computing's
properties like superposition, parallel computation, and integral
wind have garnered significant interest across various scientific
and engineering fields, which has led efforts to adapt classical machine learning
algorithms for quantum computing, particularly during the NISC
era. Quantum operating's probabilistic nature and parallelism promise
advancement and semi supervised approaches such as reinforcement
learning and vision networks. Another one is quantum enhanced MLAI,
so they enhance specific machine learning tasks like quantum sampling,
linear algebra operations, and quantum neural networks. The quantum
memory and algorithms are still in the development phase.
Now let's see the role of quantum ML and AI for mimicry.
Quantum enhanced pattern recognition can identify objects,
patterns and anomalies in data the classical algorithms
might miss. This is valuable for tasks such as detecting hidden
terrorist networks, predicting enemy movements, recognizing threats,
etcetera. It can be also useful for accurately predicting potential
future conflicts and scenarios, which enables military planners to
develop proactive strategies and plans. Also, QML can process massive
datasets much faster than classical machine learning algorithms. This capability
is crucial for analyzing intelligence data from various resources such
as satellite images, communication intercepts, and social media.
Then, with the assistance of quantum ML and AI, they can
significantly improve the performance of the automated defense mechanisms
that respond to cyber threats in real time. This is by reducing response
times and reducing damage from cyberattacks, which includes UAV's
autonomous drone vehicles and maritime drones.
It can also enhance military wargaming and simulation by providing more
accurate and realistic models of combat scenarios, which allows for
better training and preparation as well as the development of more effective
strategies. So there are still some major challenges.
Quantum computers are highly prone to errors due to their delicate
quantum screens. Error correction is a significant challenge as it requires
quantum error correcting codes to to detect incorrect errors
without disturbing the quantum information and developing these
codes and implementing them efficiently remains a major hurdle.
Next is developing quantum algorithms, which can actually show
improvement over classical algorithms. So also,
classical machine learning algorithms do not have straightforward quantum
equivalency in general. So developing new quantum algorithms
that can handle the ML task while being practically implementable on quantum
hardware is an ongoing area of research. Coming to the data
part. Classical data needs to be encoded into quantum stage for implementation
of quantum computers. This encoding process can be challenging
limiting the practical application of QML. Next, we have quantum
memory, which is essential for storing quantum information reliably
over time. However, creating stable and long lasting quantum memory
is challenging due to decolons and noise which have corrupt
stored quantum information. It is also an important ongoing
area of research as it would enable the retention and retrieval of quantum
data necessary for storing complex competition
and long term projects.
Another important aspect is quantum optimization. The optimization
is in the quite important for balanced functioning of large systems
and resources, and quantum optimization provides techniques
to solve these complex problems.
They are particularly useful for np hard problems which become impractical to
solve otherwise. The brute force has complexity increases.
One such algorithm is QAOA, which combines quantum operations with
classical optimization techniques to find approximate solutions to
optimization problems. Cuba is another approach
used in quantum optimization, particularly suitable for analog quantum
computers. It involves transforming your optimization problem into
a form that can be tackled by quantum annealers or other quantum devices.
Quantum inspired classical algorithms derived from quantum methods like
QAO may also provide performance improvements without requiring
quantum. Various demonstrations and
proof of concept applications in sectors like traffic,
logistics, and finance highlight the practical utility of quantum optimization,
especially using analog quantum computing.
Now we see its role in military. So first application we have
is in mission planning and scheduling, which includes determining the sequence
of operations to optimize the effectiveness of the mission.
Effective planning and scheduling are crucial for coordinating multiple
games and assets, minimizing risk, and adapting to changing
rotations. Next is the resource allocation, which refers to the optimal
distribution of limited resources to various tasks projects.
In a military context, this involves assigning personnel, equipment,
and funding to operations where the impact can be maximized.
Then we have another decision making process, like all
general decision making processes, which involve gathering and
analyzing relevant data, considering various alternatives,
and choosing the best course of action. And it is necessary for making
well informed, timely decisions that maximize mission effectiveness
and minimize risk. Then, one of the well known applications,
logistics and supply chain management, which is coordinating
and managing the flow of goods, services, and information from origin
to destination. In a military context, this ensures that troops have
the necessary supplies, equipment, and support to carry out their missions.
Here are some challenges as well. The first one is converting classical
optimization problems into quantum formats that can be effectively
processed by quantum assets algorithms. Then, creating systems that integrate
quantum and classical computing to leverage the strengths of both is necessary but
challenging due to differences in computational paradigms and architectures.
Next is scalability. Scaling quantum computational solutions to
handle large military operations and logistics is a complex
task that requires significant computational resources and
infrastructure. Apart from this, there are several other algorithms.
Quantum searching algorithms such as Grover's algorithm and quantum random
work mechanisms, offer significant speedup for unstructured data
analysis. The HHL algorithm shows potential for
superpolina will speed up in solving linear equations beneficial
for fields requiring large scale numerical simulations despite
practical resource constraints. Some other examples are
quantum phase estimation and variational techniques like VQe,
which are dominant approaches for quantum stimulation.
Now, let's look at the timeline of the future progress. Quantum computing
is advancing rapidly. Current quantum computers, such as
those developed by IBM, Google, etc. Have demonstrated the capability to
perform specific computations faster than classical computers for
particular tasks, which is known as quantum supremacy.
However, these systems are still in the Nisk era,
characterized by noisy qubits and limited error correction.
So in the next five years, improvements in quantum error correction and
qubit coherence times are expected. Quantum computing will be
increasingly used for specialized applications such as optimization problems,
complex simulations, and machine learning in academia industry.
In next ten years, quantum computers with hundreds to thousands of
qubits could emerge and are being more complex. In practical applications.
We may see more robust, error corrected quantum computers that can outperform
classical systems in a wider range of tasks. Then in
the next ten to 20 years, fully fault tolerate quantum computers
could become a reality, revolutionizing fields such as cryptography,
material science, and drug discovery. Practical, large scale
quantum computers with millions of qubits could solve problems currently intractable
for practical computers.
The next component is quantum communication. It is transmitting quantum
information using fibers of three space channels with quantum communication
protocols. Quantum communication protocols suggest quantum key
distribution enable the exchange of cryptographic keys with
theoretically unconditional security, as any attempted eavesdropping
can be detected due to the disturbance it causes to the quantum states
being transmitted. Quantum communication and cryptography research
focuses on developing quantum safe cryptographic algorithms to
secure data against potential threats from quantum computers,
ensuring long term data security and privacy.
Slide the first aspect of quantum communication, which is
quantum key distribution or key QK did so.
QKIt is designed to securely distribute a secret key between parties
for encrypting data over classical channels. It uses the
no cloning theorem to ensure that any eavesdropper is detectable
due to the disturbance caused by measurement. Unlike classical
encryption, which can be potentially broken with powerful quantum
computing computers, QKD uses quantum bits or qubits that change
state when observed and hence preventing eavesdropping without detection.
So there are two main protocols, BB 84 and E 91.
The BB 84 protocol, which requires pre distributed quiz and
quantum random number generation, is simpler technically. In contrast,
the E 91 protocol uses quantum entanglement to generate
keys during distribution, which makes it more complex with not
requiring pre generated randomness numbers. And so some of
these products are commercially available in the market, and further research
is also going on. So now let's see the
role in military QKD provides theoretically unbreakable encryption.
When using the principle of quantum mechanics,
maintaining the confidentiality of sensitive information is paramount in military
operations. QKD ensures that communications between command
centers, troops, and other military assets remain confidential
and secure from interception by adversaries. Next is secure satellite
based communication satellites equipped with QKD technology can
establish secure communication links over long distances,
overcoming the range limitations of terrestrial QKD systems,
and this is particularly important for global military operations and coordination
between geographically dispersed units.
QKT can facilitate real time secure communication
between military satellites and ground stations,
ensuring that commands and intelligence are transmitted securely
and without any delay. Military networks that control critical
infrastructure, such as missile defense systems and surveillance
networks, can use QKD to protect against cyber attacks
and unauthorized access. Here are some challenges as well.
Implementing QKD on a large scale, such as across an entire military
network, is difficult due to the need for point to point connections and
the lack of efficient quantum repeaters. This limitation makes it
terrain challenging to deploy QKD broadly without significant
advancements in network architecture. Integrating QKD with existing
military communication infrastructures poses significant challenges.
Current systems are based on classical technologies, and transitioning
to QPT would require substantial upgrades and potentially a
complete overhaul of existing networks. QPT systems require
specific and often expensive hardware, such as single photon detectors and
sources, quantum repeaters, and high precision synchronization tools.
This specialized infrastructure is not readily available in
many existing military communication networks. QCD is
highly effective over short distances but faces significant
challenges over long distances due to photon loss and decoherence.
While optical fibers can transmit QKD signals over tens to
hundreds of kilometers, extending this range requires
complex and cost free solutions, such as quantum repeaters,
which are still in development stages.
While QGIT is theoretically secure, practical implementations must account
for potential side channel attacks and physical tampering.
Ensuring that the entire QK systems, from hardware to software,
is secure against all possible attacks is complex and requires constant
vigilance. The sensitivity can cause signal loss,
breaking reliable operation in often harsh military environments.
Challenging the next
aspect is a quantum network, which is designed to
transmit qubits between spatially separated quantum processors.
The structure of quantum networks mirrors classical networks comprising end
nodes like quantum resizes communication lines,
optical switches, and quantum repeaters. Quantum networks
enable secure and direct communication between quantum computers, allowing the
exchange of quantum data. This capability is crucial for the efficient redistribution
of computational tasks based on the performance of individual quantum
computers. It facilitates the division of large computational
tasks into smaller ones that can be processed simultaneously by multiple
quantum computers. Undistributed quantum computing, when numerous quantum
computers are networked together is likely to be the practical realization of scalable
quantum computing systems. And now we
see the role in military quantum position verification technique
can be used to verify the location of military assets and personnel without
revealing the
integration of quantum networks allows for distributed quantum computing
where multiple quantum computers can work together to solve complex problems.
This can be particularly useful for military applications that require significant
computational power, such as cryptography, simulations and
data analysis. Quantum networks are inherently resilient to
tampering and eavesdropping due to the principles of quantum mechanics mechanics.
Any attempt to intercept or alter the quantum information transmitted
over the network would be detected, ensuring the reliability and integrity of
military communications and data transfer. Some of the challenges
are listed here. The first one is development and maintenance of
components like optical switches, so maintaining quantum components
is crucial. Quantum repeaters are necessary for long distance quantum
communication, but are still in the experimental system stage and developing practical,
efficient quantum repeaters that can be deployed in military
networks as a significant hurdle. Depending on the application,
end nodes might need to handle single or multiple qubits.
They may also require quantum memory to store quantum information
temporarily, so this is also a challenge.
Next important aspect is post quantum cryptography PQC
so post quantum cryptography bears encryption techniques designed
to withstand future quantum computer attacks. While current asymmetric
encryption methods are vulnerable, symmetric cryptography algorithms
and hash functions are generally considered secure against quantum attacks.
Most current symmetric cryptographic algorithms and hash functions are
still secure against quantum attacks, and increasing key size can
mitigate risk posed by quantum algorithms. With growers,
algorithm cryptographers are creating new algorithms in anticipation
of q t, when current cryptographic methods will become vulnerable to quantum
liquidity. This can safeguard the integrity and authenticity
of relative data. One of the main challenges in post quantum cryptography
is considered to be the implementation of potentially quantum safe algorithms
into existing systems. So there are tests done,
for example, by Google, Microsoft, and Apple to ensure the security.
Here is the timeline for CTF. Quantum communication,
particularly quantum key distribution, is already being implemented in pilot
projects and limited commercial applications. Quantum communication networks
like the quantum Science satellite launched by China, have successfully
demonstrated long distance quantum entanglement and secure communication
over hundreds of kilometers. So next five years we can see
expansion of jukery networks in urban and metropolitan areas for
secure communication and continued development of satellite
based quantum communication for long distance secure communication.
In next five to ten years, we can see the integration of quantum
communication protocols with classical Internet infrastructure
to create hybrid quantum classical networks and development
of quantum repeaters to extend the range of quantum communication.
In next ten to 20 years, there can be realization of a global quantum
Internet allowing secure communication across
continents. This will involve robust quantum repeaters and
satellite constellations to maintain quantum entanglement over long distances.
Let's move on to our next component, quantum sensei, which is one
of the replica advance in quantum technology and making it to the real
world. From laboratories, it refers to the use of quantum
properties to measure the physical quantities like magnetic and electrical
fields, temperature, pressure, time, frequency,
etcetera. So its strength lies in the inherent weakness of the quantum
systems, which is their instability against the external
environment. Using this, the quantum sensors offer unparalleled sensitivity
and precision in measuring, providing better stability and superior
performance compared to the conventional sensors.
The first aspect is quantum clock. Quantum clocks have highly precise
time keeping devices which utilize laser cooled single
ions confined in an electromagnetic track to achieve unprecedented
accuracy. State of the art chip sized atomic clocks
achieve an uncertainty of two into ten to the power minus twelve.
By quantum logic. Single ion clocks have uncertainties as low
as nine into ten to the power -18 so this level of precision
allows quantum clocks to perform new types of measurements,
including the ability to measure height differences between points on earth
with an accuracy of 1 cm. This opens up possibilities for
highly accurate gravitational potential measurements and other applications
where precision timing is crucial, such as satellite navigation,
network and finance. OVC role
in military quantum clocks provide unprecedented accuracy in
time measurement, essential for navigation systems such as gps.
Precise timing ensures more accurate positioning,
crucial for military operations. Quantum clocks enable more accurate
timing in missile guidance systems, increasing the precision of
targeting and reducing the likelihood of collateral damage.
Precise timing is critical for the coordination of complex military
maneuvers and the synchronization of multi phase attacks. Also,
synchronization of communication networks ensures secure data transfer
between military units and command centers. Now we see some
challenges for military applications, the reliability and longevity of
quantum clocks are paramount. Ensuring long term stability
and minimal downtime is a critical challenge that must be addressed.
The power consumption of quantum clocks, especially those requiring cryogenic
cooling, is a critical concern. Developing energy efficient motors
that can operate autonomously in the field that frequent
maintenance is essential for practical deployment. Quantum clocks
involve complexity that is currently not as compact
or portable as needed for various military
platforms. Achieving miniaturization while maintaining accuracy and
stability is a significant technical work done.
The next aspect we have is quantum radar. The quantum radar operates
similarly to classical radar by sending a signal towards
a target and waiting for the reflected signal. It utilizes
quantum features in both the radiation source and output detection to
outperform classical return resistance, and for this it
leverages quantum mechanical effects such as the uncertainty principle and quantum entanglement.
Quantum radar can effectively counteract conventional retarding techniques,
so spoofing signals cannot match the original quantum state
of the radar's internal signal, allowing the system to filter out
these and other environmental sources and hence enhancing detection accuracy.
Quantum radar shares properties with noise radars, including preparative
detection and efficient spectrum sharing.
Various protocols currently exist, such as interferometric quantum radar,
quantum illumination, hybrid quantum radar, three dimensional enhancement,
each having its own requirements, strengths, and limitations.
Now we see the ruling military a quantum radar can potentially
detect stealth aircraft and submarines that are designed to be invisible
to conventional radar systems. The higher sensitivity
and ability to distinguish signals from noise allows quantum
radar to identify stealth targets more effectively
then in electronic warfare. So quantum radar is less susceptible to jamming
and interference compared to traditional radar systems.
Its use of entangled photons and quantum illumination
techniques can maintain signal integrity even in environments with significant
electronic countermeasures. Then, in maritime
applications, quantum radar can enhance the detection of submarines
and underwater mines. The increased sensitivity and resolution of
quantum radar systems can help in identifying objects beneath
the water surface, which are typically challenging for conventional radar.
This was particularly important important for maintaining the safety of satellites
and other space assists in an increasingly crowded space environment.
Now we see some challenges. So quantum radar systems
currently have limitations in range and power. The efficiency of quantum radar
declines over long distances and achieving high power outputs while
maintaining quantum properties, is technologically challenging.
This limits the practical development of quantum radar in extensive military
operations and applications. Its dependence on other quantum
sources, like high entangled photon generation sources and quantum memory
makes it less reliable in current scenario.
Quantum radar protocols, such as interferometric quantum radar,
are highly sensitive to noise and require the preservation of quantum entanglement,
which is difficult in practical real world environments. Quantum decoherence,
where quantum states lows their coherence due to environmental interactions,
also remain of ethnic and health.
Next, we have quantum imaging. Quantum imaging uses
quantum optic principles to enhance imaging capabilities beyond the limits of
classical systems. So key components and techniques in quantum imaging
systems include sprite arrays, which are highly sensitive detectors that
measure time of flight of photons for 3d imaging. Quantum ghost
imaging, which uses entangled photons to create images from
correlations allowing for low light and non line
of sight imaging. Sub shot noise imaging, which utilizes correlated
photons to surpass classical noise limits and applicable detection of
weak absorption,
which employs entangled photon pairs for target detection in noisy
environments, maintaining advantages even when entanglement is decreasing.
These advancements allow quantum imaging systems to perform tasks
such as behind the corner imaging, low light level detection, and high resolution
3d mapping. In the future, it could be used to store patterns of data
in quantum computers and allow communication through highly
encrypted information. Now we see that rural
in military so quantum imaging allows for non line of sight
imaging, which is critical in urban and battlefield environments where
direct line of sight is often obstructed. Spider is
combined with advanced quantum protocols can detect objects hidden
behind corners or walls, providing tactical advantages by revealing
enemy positions and movements that are otherwise concealed.
Quantum imaging systems can operate effectively in low light and low
visibility predictions. Techniques like quantum ghost imaging utilize
entangled photons to produce high resolution images with minimal light,
allowing for surveillance missions to continue uninterrupted
during night operations or in other adverse weather conditions.
Quantum imaging offers a higher signal to noise ratio compared
to classical systems, making it possible to detect and image
objects with greater clarity and precision. This improved SNR
is crucial for applications such as monitoring the battlefield
environments, identifying threats, and guiding precision initiations.
It enables high resolution 3d imaging and mapping of
terrains and structures. This capability is essential for creating
accurate topographical maps, planning military operations,
and navigating complex environments. Now we see some
challenges. The quantum emerging systems, such as those using sprite areas
and entangled photons, involve sophisticated technology that is
complex to develop and maintain. The production and maintenance of
these advanced systems require substantial financial investment.
Also, these techniques are highly sensitive to environmental conditions.
This can pose significant challenges for development in diverse and
harsh military environments. The data generated by quantum imaging
systems are also vast and complex, so requiring
advanced algorithms and high performance computing resources for real
time processing and interpretation is also a challenge.
Ensuring the security and reliability of quantum images systems
is paramount for military use. Protecting these systems from
cyber threats, jamming, and other forms of electronic warfare is
crucial. Additionally, the systems must be reliable and resilient,
able to perform consistently under the stress of combat conditions
and potential adversarial actions.
So, in the next few years, prototyping and testing quantum sensors
in various environments will continue to take place.
This includes laboratory settings as well as field test in
more practical scenarios such as on drones and satellites.
Initial deployments of quantum sensing technologies for specific applications,
such as precision navigation and resource exploration, are anticipated.
After that as technology matures, we can expect more quantum
sensing devices to enter the commercial market. This period will
see increased integration of quantum sensors in industries like oil and
gas exploration, environmental monitoring and healthcare diagnostics.
Then we can expect more extensive use of quantum sensors in military applications,
particularly in US and China. Later on, quantum sensing
technologies are expected to have widespread adoption across various sectors.
It is also possible to have fully operational quantum radar systems
with long range capabilities and integration into space and naval
based back homes with non capabilities.
Now we see some examples of quantum technologies that can be used for attacking
and that for defending. So for attacking. So first we have Shor's
algorithm. So Shor's algorithm threatens public key encryption methods
like RSA, DH and ECC, potentially enabling decryption of
previously collected data. For example, ECC has shorter
keys so attack will be easier as this will require lesser qubits.
Then we have growers algorithms, so it provides speedup in searching
for the key which weakens symmetric key encryption but is currently
impractical due to quantum resource requirements. Simons algorithm
and superposition queries pose risk to wage and AAD
algorithms, and then finally the trivial attacking methods.
Classical hacking and physical attacks on quantum equipments or
other equipments. Until new softwares are not quite properly secure,
hacking will always remain a threat. Also, the quantum networks
are subjected to physical attacks by external
damage and external attack.
Now we see some defensive mechanisms. So although
with existence of vulnerabilities at hardware and software endpoints,
QKD still provides a secure method for encryption key exchange,
which is verified by mathematical proof. So PQC implementation
is also critical and should be prioritized to counter the risk of future
decryption by quantum computers. Next we have quantum crypto
agility. The current trend involves preparing existing
infrastructure for quantum crypto agility, waiting it for
the deployment of standardized PQC as soon as it becomes
available. Then we have emerging quantum resilient algorithms in
progress, and developing and designing them is crucial to withstand
quantum computing.
Moving on, let's see some scenarios on how some quantum technologies
can be utilized for space and underwater warfare. So let's see some
space warfare first. So first we have satellite based QPE.
So instead of ground to ground, satellites can be used as trusted repeaters.
This is because they facilitate secure long distance communication,
although they face security challenges similar to terrestrial systems.
Currently, advanced protocols like measurement device independent QKD
are being explored to enhance security and mitigate potential cyberattacks
on satellite control systems. Then quantum goes to
merging technology and satellites which provide superior surveillance capabilities,
particularly under adverse weather conditions or during nighttime.
This technology allows for high resolution imaging even in cloudier,
foggy environments, improving military and intelligence operations from space.
Next, we have quantum enhanced detectors like quantum radars or radars deployed
on satellites, which offer significantly improved protection and
tracking capabilities for other satellites, space one objects and space jabras.
These quantum sensors provide detection sensitivity
compared to classical radars, particularly for objects smaller than
ten centimeter. Then the weaponization of space,
which includes the development of satellites equipped with laser weapons
and satellites capable of attacking other satellites.
Quantum technologies enhance these capabilities by improving target detection
and precision. If we have underwater
sensitive quantum magnetometers and gravimeters can detect
and classify underwater hazards without active sonar
emissions, which helps to maintain the stealth of surveying
vessels. Then there are quantum enhanced sonars which offer
higher precision and sensitivity, allowing for better detection of
submarines undersea canyons without emitting detectable sonar
winners. Quantum inertial navigation systems provide precise navigation
for submarines and other underwater vehicles without the need for
external signals which can be disrupted or detected. So, large submarines
can incorporate these systems including necessary cryogenic cooling.
Quantum magnetometers such as quits can detect submarines
and underwater mines with significantly greater sensitivity and range combination.
Comparative classical magnetic and anomaly detectors squid
magnetometers have the potential to detect submarines from distance
up to 6 km for a surpassing in the current detection
range of a few hundred meters by classical detectors.
These errors work with enhanced noise separation,
making it difficult for submarines to avoid detection.
Additionally, unmanned underwater vehicles equipped with quantum
magnetometers can be used for mine detection and utilization.
Then, similar to ND satellite anti submarine warfare capabilities
can be also adopted.
Some other warfare capabilities also.
Quantum technologies significantly enhance positioning,
navigation and timing systems with quantum clocks, providing high time measurement
accuracy crucial for global navigation satellite systems.
Then, quantum sensing based on magnetometric gravimetry
and gravity gradiometry provides high precision data
for studying earth surface and underground structures.
These technologies can detect unit gravitational magnetic footprints
of natural and man made objects. Quantum technologies can also significantly
enhance classical electronic warfare systems. For example, the integration of
quantum computing in electronic warfare can optimize rf spectrum
analysis through quantum MLEi techniques. Then, other quantum
timing enhanced participants can improve other quantum various
electronic preference capabilities such as signal intelligence,
counter DRFM, and counter radar jamming. So overall, quantum tech
still significantly enhance eye star intelligence surveillance
target acquisition reconnaissance capabilities, which is helpful in strategic,
multiphase and multidisciplinary operations.
Moving on to the next section, these are some top countries investing
in quantum technologies. This includes India, USA,
Canada, China, Russia, Australia, Japan,
Israel, Singapore, South Korea, UK, European Union,
and so on. There are two front runners in the
current global market, which are China and US. So both China
and the United States are heavily invested in quantum technologies,
recognizing the potential to transform industries and enhance national
security. The first is the government structure. The US employs
a three pillars model for quantum research, dividing the federal
investment among civilian, defense, and intelligence sectors, while for
China substantial support comes from the People's Liberation army
and the big defense companies it recruits. China has
demonstrated satellite based QKD and this infrastructure could easily
be adapted for military use. While US army is currently working on
quantum television politician research while the US is integrating
quantum comprehensive into alliances such as NATO,
China is collaborating with Russia in various technological fields with potential
for closer cooperation in quantum technologies. The US has traditionally
led in quantum computing innovation. China has made significant strides
in, particularly in quantum communication and quantum sensing.
Let's see the budget. The US had increased its investment
in one technology from $500 million in 2015
to almost $2.1 billion in 2021.
However, China had no rise, with investments growing from $300 million
to an estimated $13 billion over the same period.
So this data clearly captures the magnitude of their commitment for this
cause. Apart from government r educational research
parties, 3000 key players in global quantum warfare market
contributing in one way or the other. So as of 2022, the quantum
warfare market was valued at approximately $134.66 million.
So this valuation reflects the early stage of technology adoption and the
ongoing research and development efforts in the field. The quantum Horford
market is expected to grow significantly over the next decade.
It is predicted to reach $540.91 million by the
year 2030, with a compound annual growth
rate of 16.8% during the forecast period from 2023
to 2031. This growth is driven by the increasing
investment in quantum technologies by defense organizations and
governance worldwide, as well as the potential disruptive capabilities
these technologies offer. In order to offer now,
we see green challenges. First, we have technical challenges.
In most of these we have already seen in the previous sections, so it will
always be a challenge to make the product actually deployable. So after
this, the developed prototype should be integrated with existing military
infrastructures such as communication networks, gps systems, etc.
To ensure seamless interoperability. This involves complex engineering
to ensure proper functioning of the quantum devices without any operational
disruptions. Apart from this, they must undergo rigorous decision and
validation to ensure they meet the standards required in military applications.
Another crucial challenge is related to the data handling part.
It's important to have efficient data handling protocols and systems that can
manage the high data throughput without compromising speech or security.
So these are some of the major challenges from the technical viewpoint as
we are talking about war. To determine the external nature of the war,
policies are the foremost thing. Each new technology in war comes
with its own level of effect. So with the quantum technology, also new policies
are needed. The first one is to obviously answer the ethical
questions. So these technologies may also challenge existing legal frameworks,
particularly concerning the laws of war and international treaties.
Also, this can alter the global security landscape, potentially leading
to new arms races or shifts in power dynamics. Hence,
policymakers must navigate these ethical and legal boundaries
to establish guidelines in compliance with international laws that
balance technological advancements with moral responsibility.
The next challenge is related to the standardization procedures,
so ensuring interoperability between quantum technologies from different
manufacturers and nations is essential for collaborative military
operations. Also, establishing reliable verification protocols
to authenticate the performance and security of quantum
technologies is crucial. And these protocols must be rigorous
enough to detect any anomalies or weaknesses, ensuring that the technologies meet
the required standards for military use. So achieving overall unification
in the standards and practices for quantum technologies across the
military sector is essential for its effective implementation.
Now, we have related to the manpower, the complexity,
chefs quantum technologies necessitates a specialized training program,
so military personnel, so developing comprehensive training modules
that govern both theoretical knowledge and practical skills is
essential to ensure that operators and technicians can effectively utilize and
maintain these advanced systems. And for this,
establishing dedicated courses and research programs is crucial for
building a skilled workforce. This also requires interdisciplinary
expertise as quantum technologies intersect with multiple fields,
including physics, engineering, cybersecurity,
etcetera. So collaborative programs need to be designed to foster
interdisciplinary expertise. Moving on this economical challenges
for the governing bodies, private organizations, and other stakeholders
directly or indirectly associated with this technology. So these players,
along with military organizations, must assess the long term financial impact,
balancing the cost with the anticipated benefit, and sustainable funding
for research and development. This calls for an efficient allocation of resources
to avoid redundancy and ensure that critical areas receive the
necessary support. Strategic planning and prioritization are
required to maximize the impact of investment in military applications.
Concluding the talk here are the key takeaways for
advancements in quantum website technology signify transformative shift
in military capabilities currently, many quantum technologies are still
in the experimental development stages, since we have seen
some technologists like QPT have already demonstrated their excellence
over classical methods. While other areas like quantum sensing are fast
growing and looks promising in some aspects.
So there are still some unanswered questions on whether certain quantum technologies like
quantum ratar will meet the practical requirements or not.
But overall, the next few decades will be critical for advancing
these technologies, from theoretical concepts and rebels laboratory
demonstrations to practical field developer systems.
Here are some references. And so that
brings us to the end. So if you want to reach out to me,
here's my email and LinkedIn. Feel free to connect. Thank you.