Thank you so much for coming to my talk today. I am super excited
to be part of comfort two cloud native 2024.
And today I'm going to be talking
about synthesizing threat informed defense when
cloud attack emulation meets detection engineering.
All right, a few words about me. I'm the CTO
and one of the founders at Mitigant. Mitigant is
a cloud security company. These I breathe in Berlin.
I have spent about twelve years in cybersecurity.
Within these years I've held different positions.
I've worked in academia doing academic research.
During my research, I was one of the
pioneers of the concept of security chaos engineering.
But I also worked in the industry, in different startups and
held different technical positions. And I am a
member of the AWS community builder program. All right,
so what are we going to be talking about today? We are going to be
looking at a few topics.
First we will look at trade informed defense and then
the three pillars that constitute this concept.
Then we will look at adversary emulation, and then we will
go and look at cloud attack emulation, which is actually
a subdomain under adversary emulation.
Then after that we're going to be looking at a use case where
we see how we can use cloud attack emulation to validate
cloud trade detection. And I will give you a very brief demo of the
mitigan cloud attack emulation platform.
So let's get started. So, cybersecurity,
the domain most of ours are,
it's a very noisy domain. It's noisy in
this sense because there are a lot of attacks,
and we hear of attacks virtually every day on
the news. We hear of different companies, we hear of different threat vectors,
and it sometimes gets a little bit challenges to be able to
sift these noise. To sift the signal from the
noise. And what I mean here by signals is kind
of how to know what part of this news
that is more important to you, what part of it is relevant for you,
relevant for your organization. And I
compare it in a way to the needle in the haystack
problem. So as you see in this picture here, you got a
needle and the needle is very little. And if you drop
a needle in these haystack, it's kind of challenging for you to kind of
identify the needle. So it's kind of the
problem we have in cybersecurity. Probably not as complex
as defending needle, but you get what I'm saying. And the ability
to be able to sift the signal from the noise
is very important because the signals
is what you want to be focused on the noise will
eventually distract you and reduce your proactively,
and if you're not careful, will be the very problem, or let's
say, will be the very reason for which you might be attacked.
So that leads straight to trade informed defense,
which is by definition, these systematic
application of a deep understanding of adversary
tradecraft and technology to improve defenses.
And this is the definition that has been provided
by the mitre ingenuity, which is basically the
center for trade informed Defense. It is a non for profit organization
in the United States. And they came up with this
idea which you can use as a strategy for
your company to ensure that your security architecture
is effective, it actually works and
is able to toward attacks.
So we're going to be looking deeper into what this means. We hear
about it every now and then, and I
took a look at what this informed
defense means, and that's what we're going to be exploring.
So there are these pillars of trade informed
defense, as we see in the symbol in the last page.
And the first one is defensive measures. So what is defensive
measures? So basically, the moment you begin to talk
about the defensive measures, you are basically looking at
the security controls, the security tools,
the security strategies that you're actually going to be implementing to help
you to stay ahead of attacks.
And one of the major reference points when it
comes to defenses is the Mitre attack
framework. And the Mitre attack framework itself,
which is also another program by
Mitre, which is also a US government
agency or non for profit agency.
It is basically a globally accessible
knowledge base of adversary tactics and techniques that
is based on real world observations. And here it's very
important for you to take note of adversary
tactics, which is basically the way attackers
compromise systems. And also, it's important for you to take
note of real world observations. So these are based
on real attacks that are happening and not theory.
So they try to kind of focus
on real attacks rather than theoretical attacks,
rather than attacks that people are thinking that will occur. These are
actually based on different companies that are part of this program.
They monitor devices, these monitor, they're being used by
different companies and they're gathering this information. And they are basically
kind of using this to understand how attackers compromise
systems, how these compromise organizations, and they classify
these under different tactics,
and also under these tactics also have
techniques. And we're going to be looking deeper into these in the next
slides. So the Mitra attack
framework itself is divided into,
let's say, technological categories in
the form of the enterprise matrix, which basically
looks at most systems, whether web applications,
cloud systems, software as a service
systems and so forth. We also have the mobile matrix,
rooks and mobile applications, mobile technologies,
and we have the ICs, which is the industrial control systems.
But today we are going to be focusing more on the enterprise matrix,
which has us at version 14, which is the
most recent version. It has 14 tactics and 234
techniques. That's a whole
lot of, let's say it's a lot.
And most companies cannot. Even if you use a tool that
implements all of these techniques,
it is very difficult for you as a company to
focus on all of that. Right. It's going to be overcoming the
idea. These, which I want to really state
is the idea is not to cover the
entire tactics and techniques, but to kind of select which of
these that is more relevant to you.
All right. And this is kind of a larger view for you to see.
But ideally, you're not going to be covering every
of these techniques. What you will do eventually is
something like this. And this visualization is created
by van Vlad. He wrote a very nice
blog, which I will leave the link in the slides. And basically
here you see out of 14 tactics,
you have something around seven. And from there you see these
clusters represent techniques which
might be clustered. So under each tactic there are techniques and
there could also be subtechs. And you also see
this red line, which kind of shows how an attacker
will navigate through
an infrastructure. And this line most likely
kind of determines for you what is relevant
to you, what you have to really take care of what is important
for you. And you can see that in the end,
it really slings down the areas
that a company should actually be really concerned about.
All right. We just looked at the first pillar, which is kind of
looking at what you do, but that's not. All right. The second pillar
brings in more context. And the second pillar is
basically cyber threat intelligence. And what is cyber
threat intelligence is basically information that has been
aggregated, transformed, analyzed, interpreted or enriched to
provide the necessary context for decision making.
And you have to understand here, we always say in cybersecurity,
that context is king. Context is
what differentiates you from other organizations.
You got to know your context. And cyber threat
intelligence helps you to kind of fine
tune your context more. It helps you to further
sift the signal from the noise.
And again, the mitre actually
also has a section here, as you see here,
where they provide cyber trade intelligence,
which is here they actually talk about different trade actors, and they
describe who they are. They describe the campaigns that
they've noticed these trade actors to be involved in, in real life and
also talk about the map. They provide a mapping of these threat
actors to the tactics and techniques that they have
observed them using, and that narrows
down your focus as a company. So, for example, scattered spider has
been notorious in the last two years.
They were behind the ransomware attack against the MGM resorts
in the United States. And they're actually
interested in a specific sector in not all
verticals. I think they're interested in entertainment. They're interested in
telecommunications. They're interested in technology companies.
And this already gives a kind of definition
of these sectors that should be interested in implementing
defenses against scattered spider.
Right. And this is actually the mitre
attack navigator, and it's also free, and it
helps you, as I said before, it creates a mapping of
threat actors to tactics and techniques here.
These orange colored techniques are actually the
ones that scattered spider implements.
And you must understand that I already
kind of slimmed down this mitre
attack. The techniques slimmed it down to the ones that are related
to infrastructure as a service. And this is all
possible. You can actually sift and
just narrow down to the areas that are more relevant
for you. And in the end, you have a very minimal
techniques to be concerned about.
Okay, so let's go to the third pillar,
which is testing and evaluation. And this is a pillar
that is mostly not talked about,
right? Most of the time when people talk about the
miter, when people talk about a threatinformed
defense, they kind of talk about the defensive measures.
These talk about cyber threat intelligence.
Testing and evaluation is most of the time not discussed.
And I'm going to be talking more about this aspect
because you have to understand that these three pillars are
complementary of themselves, and they work together as a
feedback loop. So none of them is more important
than the other. And if actually want to have a very
robust and a very efficient security strategy,
you have to implement the three pillars and you
have to make sure that they work together in
synchrony. So testing and evaluation, Basically,
Mitre engineer recommends these use
of adversary emulation for testing and evaluating
your defenses. And why is that?
We will see a bunch of questions in the next slide. But adversary emulation,
simply put, allows you to mimic the behavior
of real world threat actors in a safe and in a repeatable
manner. This is very important because in cybersecurity,
we have different kinds of security testing. We got
penetration testing, we got vulnerability assessment.
There's a lot of security
testing methodologies. But when it comes to trade detection,
trade incident response, you want a testing methodology
that mimics the exact behavior
of how attackers behave in the real world. You want something that
is really close.
It's a very close semblance of attackers behavior,
and you want to do that in a safe way. And most importantly,
you want to do that in a way that's repeatable, meaning that you can do
it multiple times. And the reason for this repeatability
is because when you go through this process, you want
to test again your defenses and to be sure that
after hardening, after improving,
you see some progress. So that's the reason why it's important
that these testing methodologies are repeatable.
All right, now these five questions are actually questions
from the Mitre ingenuity website.
And I also left a link below here.
And these questions are very important because they
help you to kind of determine whether you need
adversary emulation. It kind of also provides
more context to the reason why adversary emulation
is, is kind of recommended
for testing trait detection and incident response.
So the first question is, how do we build a resilient defense that
is not static and is easily and easily evaded
and indicators of compromise. So how do
you have a defense that it's not static,
it's dynamic in nature, and it cannot
be easily evaded, and it gives you
a very clear indicator of compromise. So indicators of
compromise are events that are indicative of an actual
attack. Adversary emulation helps you to kind
of satisfy this requirement. These next one is how do we detect,
mitigate, respond to, or prevent against
threat actor X. Here you are talking, as we saw
in the last slide, we were looking at a specific threat actor,
scattered spider. And this is kind of the questions you ask yourself
if you are trying to defend your company against
specific threat actors, and there's a narrow
focus here, and you want to prepare that either
you can detect activities that indicate
these threat actors, or you can mitigate, or you can respond
to these activities, or you can actually prevent them from
occurring in the first place. Right. So let's move
forward to the next question. It says, are we collecting the
right data and run the right queries to
detect technique y. So we talked about
techniques. Techniques are basically how threat actors
behave, how they attack, the kind of tools they use,
and the way most threat detection systems
work is they collect data. These data are in the
form of log events, and then they perform some
kind of queries over this data. And from that they're
able to conclude that these are kind of indicators
of compromise. And oftentimes you might not have
the right data, oftentimes your queries might actually not be
correct. And for you to reduce problems like
false positives or alert fatigue, you have to
use the right data sets. You have to perform the right queries.
Otherwise, so it's kind of, in the beginning, it's like try and error,
and adversary emulation allows you to kind of
get this right. And we will see later in the next slides,
we're going to see much more, let's say
much more good examples. So next question
says, how do we build experience and skills on our team
to defend against real world trades? So I like this
part because you see these, that it's kind of
moving from actual technology, the technological
aspect of cybersecurity. It's moving to
the people aspect. So the people, when you talk about people,
you begin to talk about experience and skills. And this is
really important because oftentimes it's not just about technology,
right? We have this concept of people, processes and technology.
And you always have to think not just about these technology,
but the people, because the people are very important. Even if the
technology, if you have the best kind of the best products,
if the people are not able to know how to use them properly, it's still
going to be challenging, it's still going to be attacked.
And the last question says, how do we tune our tools and processes
to maximize efficacy against real
world threats? All right, so here we're talking again about tools and
processes. Remember, I talked about processes.
Processes are very important. Tools are also important,
but they have to be tuned. Right in the beginning, we started talking about
noise. And remember that one of the major reasons
behind trading from defense is to allow us to
be able to sift signals from noise.
And even the tools and processes, they might become noisy,
and you have to tune them, you have to customize them.
And adversary emulation actually helps to go
through this customization in a very efficient manner.
Okay, let's look at an example. Now,
this is a very interesting example of
a company that uses adversary emulation.
This is GitLab. And actually, this is all open.
So in the link here, if you go to this link, you will
see GitLab talking about their
purple team and red team operations. And they
actually call it stealth operations. So basically, they do this
attack emulation without telling the company. So they do it in
a clandestine manner. And just very few managers
and very few people are aware. And what
I wanted to point out here is just the process here. So you
see, there are three main phases of this attack emulation,
adversary emulation, attack emulation, actually the same thing. You got the
attack planning, you get the attack emulation. Itself. And you got a conclusion
and you see that it's color coded. So these purple
colored circles represents activities
that are shared between the red and the blue team,
and the blue colored ones are the blue team. And then you have the
red team owning these red colored circles.
And so you see that there's brainstorming,
there's logistics part, there's adversary profiling, which is actually where
they are doing research to understand the kind of
adversaries they should focus on. And they do some tabletop
exercises, and then they develop capabilities. Then they emulate attacks in
step six, so they don't just start emulating attacks right from the
beginning. Step seven is validate
detection and response, which is actually a function
of detection engineering to a very large extent. We're going to talk
more about that. And they write a report in
the eight step. And finally, there is a retrospective where they
come together and sit down and look at the learnings, what they've learned, and they
actually discuss with the
right team, could even be the DevOps. They talk about what
they learned from this exercise, what are the takeaways, how can they improve?
And things like that. All right, so now
we're going to talk a little bit about cloud attack emulation. So cloud attack
emulation, putting it in a very clear, straightforward way,
is adversary emulation for the cloud. And at
Mitigan, we actually, because our focus is cloud and
cloud native technologies, and we basically have taken
the whole idea, the concept of adversary emulation,
and we apply directly to the cloud. And the reason why
we do this is because the cloud comes with very specific
attacks, very specific problems, very specific challenges.
And the best way to tackle these challenges is
by narrowing down your focus to cloud, which is
actually a lot of things if you think about AWS and you begin to spread
to other cloud service providers like Azure, like Google Cloud,
and even Kubernetes. And so we
have designed this whole concept to be
really cloud specific.
Now we're going to be talking about detection engineering. So what
is detection engineering? So detection engineering is an aspect
of cybersecurity that focuses on developing, fine tuning and
maintaining systems designed to identify and alert
organizations to potential security threats,
breaches, malicious or suspicious activities.
And it's a very new, let's say,
division or subdomain of cybersecurity that appeared just
two or three years ago. And basically,
why do we have detection engineering? So,
like, a decade ago, most of our cybersecurity tools were
kind of focused on prevention. So we had firewalls,
we have web application firewalls,
conventional firewalls, identity and access management.
And all of these were basically on the front door,
more or less kind of trying to prevent attacks coming in,
inspecting traffic and all of that stuff. But as technology
improved or let's say, got more complicated and
things like cloud technologies appear on the scene,
attackers, these whole peripheral defense collapsed.
And now we have the cloud that has an open API that is exposed.
And all of this has led to a scenario we
find ourselves where attackers just jump into our system
straight off. And because of this,
the idea of detection and response, which before used
to be really not very, people weren't really putting
so much effort in detection and response. But now
it becomes more relevant because you can't
focus completely on prevention. You also have to take care of things that
happen when attackers are already in your
environment. And you have products like SIMs,
these have extended detection and response,
network detection, response, cloud detection, response. All these
products have appeared on the scene to take care of this
specific issue of detecting and responding to
attacks that kind of circumvent these
preventive controls.
Right? So what do detection engineers do? This is a detection
development lifecycle, which is highly inspired by the software
development lifecycle. And if you look at it and
compare with the software development lifecycle, you will see
a bunch of similarities. And basically detection
engineers and we will see some examples later, they basically
are doing a lot of things,
including trying to understand these way
that attackers compromise our systems, trying to see whether
our detection tools are able to identify
the correct attacker behavior and trying to
see improving that on the fly, which actually in
a lot of times requires some kind of software development or
some kind of bash writing, scripting and
things like that. And this is kind of the workflow
which most detection engineering teams kind of follow this
process where they develop detection logic
or detection algorithm. They push these, deploy it and they test
it. And it's basically very similar to software
development. And here we see
an example of a sigma rule, and this is actually written
in Yaml. And most of the detection response
systems are using some kind of,
let's say, format, which sigma actually
tries to make these various formats
to be interoperable. And basically this very
sigma rule is, if you see line 20,
21, 22, is basically it
detects when cloud trail is either stopped, it's updated
or deleted AWS cloud trail. And this can
be an indicator of compromise. It can mean that
attackers are in the system and are beginning to tamper with your
detection with cloud trail. And this very
rule basically detects it.
So this is a very good example, actually.
All right, so now let's look at an example. And in this
example we're going to be looking at how to validate threat detections
in the cloud. And we will go through these
three pillars that we discussed in the previous slides,
starting from the top right here under the cyber threat intelligence.
Let's say you kind of received intelligence
report or your threat intelligence
provider kind of told you about scattered spider trade actor,
which we already talked about before. And the next
thing you do here is let's say you have
implemented some threat detection
algorithms or you have a system that takes care
of, that basically tries to identify
scattered spider techniques. And here we are looking at this
technique which basically is about credential harvesting.
And these, the next thing here, which is the
third pillar is you're going to be emulating this
technique specifically to be sure that
your detection is able to capture it, is able to detect
it.
So that all of the three pillars are put
into.
So this is basically our use cases AWS.
And this diagram shows, kind of gives a very
clear high level,
there's an illustration of what we're going to be looking at. So on the left
here we have the emulation which is here pertaining
or let's say mimicking the attacker. And you have the AWS
secret manager which stores different
kinds of secrets, which could be API keys,
could be tokens, could be other kinds of
secrets. And just for
you to understand the implication of this attack, if it succeeds,
if it's a real attacker, if they are able to
compromise your AWS secret manager and they get
the keys, these, and let's say the keys are not encrypted, it means these
have access to all of this stuff which could be access to
your databases like RDS, redshift document database,
your other applications, maybe kubernetes clusters, it could be
whatever you're using the keys
here to protect. And on the other hand here
down below here we see cloud trail. So usually this is the setup
most threat detection systems have. They are basically
fetching logs from cloudtrail and basically cloud
trail, it kind of collects different kinds of logs
from different AWS services and they're fetching these logs.
And here we have just for example, for the sake of this
demonstration, we're going to be using datadog cloud
CM, which is actually kind of a threat detection system.
And on other hand here we have, let's say the
admin, maybe like the security engineer
who is basically in charge of this system.
So here we see that we are emulating the attack
and this is a screenshot from the mitigant attack
emulation. And there are actually two attacks that we are
emulating here. The first one is basically
a malicious secret retrieval, and this
is an implementation of the technique we saw before. There are two implementations.
The first implementation basically retrieves these
secrets.
It's kind of limited, it cannot retrieve a
bulk secrets and bulk, so it has to do one after the other.
And the second attack here actually is doing
batch secret retriever. And this is a feature that was
released by AWS just in November last year,
which allows you to say, hey, give me 20 secrets,
for example, or 100. And basically you can take it
with just one API call and
that's kind of bad. So here is
the cloud trail record that corresponds to these attack
emulation. We can see the name of this event and here
we're focusing on the batch meets secret value,
which is the attack where you are basically fetching a
whole lot of secrets. And you can see here that
this is the secret ID list. This is about ten secrets
that were fetched by this API call and
you have it registered in cloud trail. Then on
the other hand, remember I talked about Datadog and
cloud CM, and this is kind of the Datadog
investigator. So it kind of has this nice user
interface where it shows you on these left here
you have the mitigant role which
actually emulates these attacks.
And basically you see here the secret manager, which is
a service that is called,
and then this service basically has,
we have done different activities here. What we're interested here is
two. So basically there are 30 get secret
value API calls. So this basically gets
basically single, as I said before, single secrets.
Unfortunately, the get bad secret value, it's not detected
by this system, so it's not able to detect
that. Also, there were calls that allowed
here the emulation to be able to collect a
huge amount of secrets with just one API call. And this
is exactly what we are trying to say here, that the threat
detection systems might miss some detections,
either because the cloud
service provider kind of had new APIs
or they released new features, or even MIT attack framework had
some updates which have to be kind of integrated
into the threat detection system. So this is a very good example
of what could go wrong.
And what is the solution here. Again, we have gone back
to sigma rule, and although this is not exactly
what they use at Datadog, but this is just for the
sake of kind of an illustration.
We talked before, if you remember when we were talking about looking
at the questions why you should use attack emulation. We were
talking about whether we're getting the right data sets or
whether we are making the right queries. So you can see between
line 96 to actually 100 here that
actually these query is made
against cloud trail. And that is how this
event is actually more like
identified. This event of getting secrets
is identified and what you can see on this
line 98 is here a query
to fetch get secret value. And this
is basically here again we see that
there is just the old API that is put
into consideration. The API
that gets a batch amount of secrets is not
considered here and definitely that event will be missed.
So to correct this problem, this query has
to be updated and the correct get batch secret
value has to be added here. And as simple as that,
once that is added, you basically will be able to
identify their tracks where batch
secrets are collected.
All right, so we're coming to an end now. So these are the
resources that I want to leave. Most of them are blogs.
I have written about the whole
topic of threat informed defense
as well as Mitre tag cloud matrix
as well as threat led emulation, which I will just
give a quick demo right away.
So I just want to give a very quick demonstration of
mitigant cloud attack emulation.
And I am going to log in into my own account
using the Google SSO.
All right, so the platform has different products,
but let's go straight to the cloud attack emulation
and switch to this cloud
AWS account. So what you see here are
different statistics about attacks that have run
before. And you can see the attacks by
different metrics, for example by status, by service AWS
services. And here are these tactics that
have executed against different AWS services.
What's interesting here is if you scroll down, you will see that
we currently support up to title attack actions
and we also support different attack scenarios.
So the attack actions are things as simple
as for example, we got the very popular one
which s three, let me
search for it. So we have public s three bucket and this
one is very popular. And basically what this does, it basically
goes to the cloud, looks for buckets that are
private, and out of these private buckets makes one of
them public. And the aim is to see whether
the threat detection system is basically able to
identify that event and it's also mapped to the mitre
attack framework. We can see the tactic here is discovery and the
technique is cloud storage object discovery. But we
also have the idea of attack scenarios.
So for example,
different attack scenarios. We have ransomware for example.
We have also the s three object exfiltration
and the ransomware attack to
run an attack is pretty much simple. So you just hit the run
attack there and then you can select,
let's say once you just select the attacks,
they're queuing up there. So we've selected new Im
user, let's select another one,
disable s three login, which is basically going
to disable the login facility for an
S three bucket. And let's choose also public
s three bucket, the one we just talked about. And basically on the right
here you can see these attacks that I just selected.
And there's this slot for attack objectives.
So we say testing threat,
right? So that's going to be documented and you
can see the attack steps here, just kind of giving very brief
descriptions of what you expect to happen. And then you
can basically hit these start attack button. And this
happens really fast because we're
connecting over the AWS API, we don't
install agents at all. And that makes it super simple to
onboard your account and to also execute
this mean to execute attacks. And what
you can see already is the new im user attack is already completed
and you can begin to actually look at what occurred.
So we kind of print out some of the steps.
You see the name of the user that was created these
and it created a user. It created also
API keys for that user and
it also created a policy for the user. In this
case, the user has, a policy has been attached
to grant a user full access to s three.
And these are all kinds of activities that a
very robust system might not even permit it
to occur, or there's going to be some notification
being streamed to the tools at this
point in time. And we see the other attack also already completed,
disable s these bucket login. And what
does it do? Let's have a look. So basically
that attack. So basically it
goes into Aws s three.
It acquires the targets, it finds the buckets.
It looks whether there's any bucket that is exempted with tags.
So you can actually exempt some resources from being attacked using tags.
And then it selects a bucket that has
the login feature enabled. It disables it,
which is kind of malicious, which is what attackers will do.
And then it basically finishes.
So let's see the comprehensive attack report.
So here we see the comprehensive attack report steps
again, which we already looked at. And of course there's a
remediation section that we basically describe what
you should do as a defender. And the attack evidence is
being collected. So we're going to be getting some evidence from Cloudtreel where
you will see the exact cloud trail record
that was created due to these attacks. And we're going
to get it because cloud trail doesn't provide it in real time.
So it's going to take something around ten minutes for that to come
here. Interestingly, I want to talk
to you about this pain and recovery. So the cleanup is going
to be automated. So immediately, let's say about five
minutes after this attack has occurred,
there's going to be a rollback, which basically means,
for example, this new im user is going to be
deleted along with all the resources that were created during the
process of the attack so
that it's cleaned. It's kind of back to how it was before
the attack. Same team, this bucket that
had the login disabled will be re enabled,
exactly how we saw it. And the public bucket will
also be taken back to a private mode, exactly how it
was before the attack. So on the right
here, you can see we already had written our attack objective,
and you can also enter your observations here. So in this
case, you go to the cloud or you look
at your threat detection system and observe,
kind of look at whether it was able to detect these activities,
if it detected it, whether what it told you,
whatever will help you to make the system to become
more secure. You can note it here and you can always come back
to these reports. All right,
so I will switch back to the slide, and I
think we're almost at the end of the presentation already.
So that's actually the last slide. So thank you very much for
listening to me. Feel free to reach out to me.
That's my email here. I'm also on Twitter, and I'm always open
to talking to anyone who wants to ask questions.
Yes, thank you so much for staying this long for my talk,
and I wish you a very nice conference.