Hello everyone, let's talk about Azure Cloud for
the web front end developers.
Microsoft's global mission is to empower
every person and every organization on the planet to
achieve more. And the same is absolutely applicable to
what Azure cloud brings to web front end
developers achieve more with less app my
name is Maxim Salnikov. I work as a developer engagement lead at
Microsoft Norway and let's stay connected on
Twitter webmaxru. I fit mainly about
web technologies, web frontend end to be precise, and about cloud
technologies. I spent 20 plus years
in web development myself.
I'm big fan of the developer communities and technical
conferences and you'll often find me on
the stage, virtual or real, speaking about
cloud and web. And also I do lots
of training and blogging.
Also what I do another side of
my personality, I'm a hobby music producer and hobby
DJ. Why do I ever talk about this
side of my personality here at this technical session?
Because this is very connected to the project I want to
have as a demo for today. So as
DJ and music producer I
was missing one particular tool, counter of
BPM bits per minute for the audio
stream. When for example I produce some music on the fly and
I want to mix this with some existing track, I want to have
at least rough understanding of how fast this
music I produce and it counts in bits per
minute in this area. So I couldn't find
this tool and I created the one for myself.
And this one is purely based on
web technology. So it works in any modern browser,
on any operating system. There is no back
end for core functionality. So it analyzes audio
stream right in the browser. This is where I'm super
excited by power of current web frontend
technologies web APIs and what modern browsers
can do. So it captures audio stream, it applies
some filters and then it calculates peaks.
So this is how we get BPM
of the current track. And this is a progressive web
application so you can install it if you wish.
If you wish you can use it just as a website or
you can install it as an application on your device.
And of course it works offline because
it analyzes everything straight on the particular device.
And I even gave a name to this tool. I call this
BPM techno created this simple logotype and
I'm super happy with its
functionality. So I run it on my local
machine, localhost 3000. I do some home streaming
and producing and I decided actually
what's next? What's next for my tool? It works very good for me
and no doubt this will work very good for the global
dj and music producers community. So I want to share what I
created with everyone on our planet who does
similar activities like me.
Plus I have some extra features
on the roadmap. What I want to add to this
tool, maybe some simple
user account so you can track your
stats on what kind of music do you play,
how fast is your favorite music. So just these
nice additions. At the same time I
want to stay focused on what I can do,
what I can do very well and what I love to do. This is front
end web development. So it's Javascript frameworks,
it's HTML CSS and all things around
that. So to achieve my
goals from this what's next? Statement I definitely need some
help from the cloud providers and I decided
to create kind of wish list from me
as an individual web frontend developer
to the cloud provider. And I believe the points I
will mention now are very relevant to
many, many web frontend developers and teams
from small companies, medium companies and for enterprises.
Well, the requirements are pretty much the same.
What are these requirements? First, hosting itself.
No doubts. It should be the fastest, it should be super reliable,
it should just work 24/7 then if
you talk about global community djs
and music producers and consumers of your web frontend application
I believe are everywhere on the planet and it makes total sense
to have this application, my application, your application,
hosted as close as possible to these folks.
So we need to propagate
this application to multiple servers in multiple countries,
multiple continents. And that's really good idea.
Then it's not a secret that modern web frontend applications
are not simplest these days, right? Many of them
are single page applications and now there is a trend to
do server site rendering. It requires some extra configuration,
some extra possibilities from the web server and
it should be supported by my dream hoster
company. Next custom domains
definitely you want to provide custom domain for your tool.
I registered domain for myself.
Bpmtech no, in norwegian top
level domain zone. This is absolutely a must
have and the same must have is serving
under HTTPs and it's nice to get
free SSL certificate if
we talk about deployment.
Modern web front end applications are something
that you update quite often,
right? So many companies have daily
deployments or even multiple times per day. This is how
modern flow works, right? And I as a web frontend
developer would like to spend less efforts
on these parts. Maybe later I will learn deeper
about DevOps, about deployments, but not
now. Now I want to focus myself on web frontend development
and also I want to get staging environments
for the case before publishing
a new version to my, let's say main domain.
I want to test it,
maybe to apply some end to end testing integration tests
or maybe just to show my friends and gather their opinions on
this or that new feature. So I
want to have this staging environment or test environment, you name it,
without any effort from my side. So I want to stay currently
as a web frontend developer, not DevOps engineer. At the same time
I want to get all these features. Then I
told you that I have some simple roadmap
for this application. In particular I want
to create couple of API endpoints for example for letting
people possibility to vote was this
detection good or not? Just simple down
and I want to gather this data in
the database somewhere. And also if we talk about
gathering stats for a particular user,
we start the discussion from any kind of authentication,
right? So providing user account where
you can log in and check your stats.
I can definitely implement it myself using
OpenID, connect and other authentication
mechanics. But if I can get help from
hoster from the cloud, this is always better,
right? Like less efforts needed to implement at least authentication
flow. I don't want to create this login
screen, reset, password screen, et cetera and all code,
all the logic behind it. I'm completely fine with authentication
via third party providers, for example GitHub or Twitter or something
like this. And after
all, if we talk about testing
API endpoints and especially testing authentication,
it's sometimes quite challenging to recreate
the environment on my local machine. But I want to
develop, I want to build my application at home using
my local machine, maybe even without Internet connection. So I
need some tools to help me with mimicking
this environment if we talk about some
extra features. Last but not least,
I myself talk about my
hobby project. So I invest some spare time
into this. I invest some evenings
to build this tool, but I don't want to invest dollars,
right? At least now I don't have any plans
to commercialize this and do. I don't want
to spend too much money on that project. So I registered
domain and maybe this is my only investment so far. That means
I need a good free tier from the
cloud provider for my web frontend application.
And you know folks, such cloud provider exists.
It's delivered by Azure
cloud and called static web apps. I'm proud
to take some part in building
this service for web frontend developers so I
provided my feedback. I took part in
architecting some of the pieces of this
service so I started with this service.
I am super happy with what it brings to
me as to web frontend developer and I
definitely want to share my knowledge with
you. So you can start and you can use all the benefits
of Azure static web app. Okay,
how to start? That's very simple,
multiple options. But I decided to
list two of them on this slide. Maybe the simplest
one for you to install extension for vs code.
Of course, if you use vs code as your main code editor,
many developers do so install
the extension called Azure Static web app. You will find this
super easily open your web frontend
project. Maybe it's created using react or angular
or vue swelter, whatever your own framework without framework at
all. Just open this folder and click plus button.
Create static web app and then you'll follow some
mini wizards to complete the steps. And the same
flow is when you use Azure
portal to achieve the same. So you just create new resource called
Azure static web apps. So what
questions you will answer before the flow
will be completed. First, it all starts with source
code repo. Well it's not a secret that I
believe, I hope that vast majority of developers,
any kind of developers, store their code
not just as a file on their machines, but as
a source in kind of source
code repository. Maybe git is the mainstream.
So if you have your code hosted,
for example on GitHub you are good to go. So you point to this
code repository, then you confirm a
few points of the configuration about your application where
your frontend code is resizing. Is it a root
folder of the repo or maybe some subfolder? If you
for example use mono repo approach
then you point to build artifacts folder
where the resulting set
of resources after you build your web
frontend application is located. For example for react this
is folder called build. And then you
count three, two, one, maybe a bit longer.
If you have quite complex build flow and
automatically your application is online,
you will immediately receive test hostname,
test domain name, couple of random words,
Azure staticapps. Net something like this. So good to
start with. Of course then you can connect your custom domain and
yeah, your application is distributed over multiple
data centers, multiple locations, multiple continents.
Isn't that cool? So it was the start flow.
Now how to deploy a new version,
right? So you created this Azure static web apps resource and
immediately you found for example bug in your
application and you want to deploy a new version.
Which steps do you need to go from building
your code to having the new version deployed
globally? First step code like
fix your bug or add new feature and push it
to your source code repository.
That's it. And you know folks, there is no step number two,
this is only thing you need to do. Basically no
extra movements except your regular development
flow, right? So you create a new code, you push it to the repo,
then Azure static web apps together with
GitHub actions where your source code is located will
take care of the rest. Of course, under the hood many
things are happening for you after
you merged your code to your main branch or
the branch you specified as the branch to
monitor when you created Azure static web apps resource.
Well, GitHub is taking control if
we talk about your repo hosted on GitHub. Of course,
maybe you heard that GitHub has awesome CI CD
tools called GitHub actions. So this
is where all the magic happens on recreating
environments for your application,
installation of modules from NPM and
after all the build itself,
by default it's just NPm run build. Or you can provide
your custom comment. If you use some
different comment then GitHub
actions has the set of build artifacts.
Well for many front end web applications this will be something
like index HTML, main javascript bundle,
main CSS bundle and yeah, it just copies
this over multiple data centers. And if you are using
not GitHub but Azure
services for storing your source code,
that's also absolutely possible to set up
same flow for Azure repos and Azure
pipelines. What will it
take from you to develop your
application locally? Well, we have
also helper for this,
also called Azure static web
apps CLI command line interface this is optional,
but I strongly recommend you to use this tool just
to recreate complete environment like we have
on the cloud, but on your local machine. This will help you a
lot in emulating all
API endpoints, all things around authentication.
And after all this is just a nice static web server for
you to help to debug and test your web frontend
application. So how to start with Azure
static web app Cli? Well classic, you just
go and install corresponding package. I strongly recommend
you to install it globally and then you will have
SWA command available for you where
you provide a few parameters to configure
this comment for your particular application.
Of course every frontend application is different,
right? Has its own settings,
but if we talk about very
generic react application created by CRA
create React app library, the comment will look something like
that. Swa start and then you point to your
dev server and then point to comment which
you use to start the application and API
folder. So this one single comment starts pretty
much everything on your local machine.
Now demo time, let's have a quick demo of
the application I mentioned and I built
myself called BPM
techno which counts BPM. So let me
open this online. It's located at
bpmtech ino. Please feel free to use this application.
It's in production and it just works.
So I will start listening.
So now it listens microphone on
my machine via the browser and you
see the spectrum analyzer is working and it tries
to calculate Bpm of my narrative
which has no sense of course,
but if we clap, you see there are quite visible peaks
and I even have sample demo file
with a track I created. Let's listen
this and let's make sure that BPM was
detected correctly.
Volume up frontend
yes, after some stabilization it
displays 120. Now it measures my voice again and
this was correct. Bpm. This is BPM I created this track
with and I can give thumbs
up and this triggers API endpoint
I have as a part of this application. Code wise
this is classic react application
and to make it working with azure static web apps
we just need to provide build command. So you
see this on your screen
now build and no exotic,
just a react application plus service worker to make it working
offline. Also I want to show you this
file which was created automatically right after
I connected this resource to static
web app service. This is
workflow file for GitHub actions.
So this file will appear on your GitHub account in
your source code repository after
you did this configuration.
And there is no need to learn
what's going on here, at least for the beginning.
I mean you don't have to explore all
the details of this file. This is what GitHub actions
will do on every push to the source
code repo and it basically builds your
application and you can fine tune some parameters
here if you wish, if needed, if you want to customize this flow.
Yeah, so it was created automatically for
you to save some time. I will not
go through all the details
about my application and the features it uses
from Azure static web apps functionality.
Please feel free to explore this GitHub
repo. I will give you a link in just a few
seconds. It contains pretty much
end to end journey from how to build
your Azure static web app or how
to create this resource out of your web frontend project to all
more or lets core functions,
staging environments, authentication functions
in form of API endpoints I have here. So you'll find
all the explanations on this GitHub repo.
Now I'll go back to my slides because
I want to explain one last thing,
how to continue learning about this interesting service.
Well, we have awesome resource called Microsoft.
Learn where you will find guides
from scratch, from zero to hero, how to complete
this or that task using Azure static web app.
Of course, we have very well written
documentation on every single piece of functionality of Azure
static web app, every single method. And this is
a link to my demo itself. Please feel
free to use it, to fork it,
to edit it, to send some issues
to me. Yeah, do whatever you want. This is open
source and a reminder that it includes includes
really detailed demo of all Azure static web
apps functions. That's pretty much it from my side.
Let's stay connected on LinkedIn and Twitter. And thank
you very much. Maxim Salnikov was with.