Setting up intelligent observability business architecture approach
today in the agenda we'll be talking on trends
and shifts in observability, the need of multilayered
observability and the proposed business architecture
approach. What are recent trends and shifts we see in the intelligent observability
area? One the maturity in the SRE
space. What we see is that the SRE function,
the various processes and the engineering teams working together.
It's becoming more and more on the ground and mature.
Next when we see the systems health.
Now there are more correlation available with the business metrics.
Business metrics as in the sales, the manufacturing
metrics and the customer experience associated with
the sales. All that correlations the business applications
SRE happening with systems health and so that we
can correlate how the business is functioning.
Generative aiops now this is a trend where
the generative AI OpS means it is generating
more and more insights using AI ML and plethora of
data sets available through operations, data alerts
from systems, hardware and others.
This generative AI Ops has lot of promise because it will
use large language models. It will bring up thorough
insights and can correlate through deep learning techniques.
Also enterprise architecture.
Now enterprise architecture is really responding
on taking on observability tooling. We see that
the tooling is getting tied with the business processes.
It is coming together with how the architecture
of either a cloud environment or business application
is planned. Observability is key in the design stage
and that's how enterprise architects are working, making in the
design principles. And when we develop it, when we put it
into production, it brings the real insights based on the observability
setup. Done. Moving on.
Now you can see in this figure there is lot
of application space and there
SRE various channels, whether online cloud
SaaS applications, partner applications, the B two B applications
on payments and supplies and logistics.
And then there is an integration happening with the systems
of records. Now this systems of record is sitting in the data layer.
Now data has like data on customers, data on transactions,
data on systems, data on third party suppliers.
Now what is happening is these all are giving
multiple transactions and thanks to the
cloud environments, it's getting into hyperscaling.
What is required is afresh with this architecture approach is
needed where we can establish the multilayer
observability. Multilayer observability.
It can tie in through the front end
applications, it can talk through the various integrations on
cloud, on social and other things, and it can establish
really a good observability where it
will provide the end to end visibility on
the transactions on the type of business functions
that need to be successful. Now what is this business architecture approach?
I would like to share with you business
architecture approach where you can see there are
three levels to it. One is the
dev and QA production environments where we have
various engineering teams working. Whether we have DevOps teams, we have
QA teams, SRE teams. Then the second
level is on the events, the events level which
is this all is generating lot of events.
Where events are on application logs, traces events,
SRE on networks, events on threats, external internal
events, on incidents, happen, problems. We have storage
data, we have other user experience data.
All this is becoming a lot of events to be captured
and correlated properly. Now there are
tools available which can do this and right from the
open telemetry and other things. But the key here is
also that how do we establish the end to end
business observability now end to end business observability,
what it means it has broadly
end user experience. It has application performance, it has
infrastructure monitoring, it has security monitoring,
it has ITSm process performance, it has cloud monitoring.
Now what is happening here is there SRE
business processes running when we say procure to pay
or similar on business process. Then there are various applications tied
on it. But these applications do not have end to end
business observability. What is required here is approach where
we can correlate the end user experience with performance,
with monitoring together and securities and
even the process performance and find out the process optimization opportunities.
We can find out from various cloud logs. We can find out
based on the type of optimization needed in the cloud environments.
So when we bring it together, it becomes really end
to end observability. And that observability is
required for the various target
departments and organizations and teams. And some of that
we have listed here, there is the head of DevOps, there are ITSM
teams, SRE teams, the network operations teams, the cloud
monitoring team and many more. Now what is
unique here. Now what is unique here is that
two factors are there. One, we do a Persona based observability,
that is a custom Persona based where it can takes the
end to end business observability and then it can also
have automated self feelings. Now once
this architecture is set up, then it gives you lot
of patterns, lot of insights which can be used to
plan automation, whether you can do partial automation,
self healing, but really a planning can be done. Now this
planning can be used while on the systems, or there can
be a process which the SRE engineers can run on it when there
is a normal anomaly or event happens.
Now this all is giving rise to a good architecture
which can be used while setup of the overall platforms
and the benefits of using this is there
will be easy usage of AIML on this because
the data will be collected across logs, traces metrics across
together and when an incident happens, whether it's a security
incident or a performance problem on application or something
happened on the cloud environments, there can be a deep correlation available
and we also want to encourage that there
SRE business process automations also where we can use the
business processes to find out various points
where the value stream can be improved and then the
real KPIs and metrics can be tied in and
the type of slas which are to be met for the given
applications can be met appropriately and
various collaborations of other teams
can happen and there can be a shared impact
and prioritization view that what is happening
less optimal or what is wrong in the systems and
which business process is getting impacted.
This is what I wanted to present to you today.
Thanks for joining in.