Hello everyone. Today we'll ble discussing about
attacking Bluetooth, le design and implementation in mobile
and also wearing Lego system. Before starting with our
presentation, I would like to introduce ourselves.
I am Ananya Mkauda. I work as a security analyst at
Deep Armor. Today I have with me my colleague Megana Vidarali
who also works as a security analyst and deeparmer.
So coming to deeparmer we are a cybersecurity
forms based in Bengaluru. So we have got consulting
services and cloud security as our two platforms.
Coming to consulting services, we provide secure design
and threat modeling, vulnerability assessment bands,
penetration testing, and the third one is certifications
and regulatory compliances. So coming to cloud
platforms we have got two in house products that is
gauntlet and recon. So let's get into the agenda
of a presentation. So we'll be discussing about blueprint
of an IoT available ecosystem. Also challenges
faced in securing these kind of modern day gadgets.
Also introduction to bluetooth and ble security. And finally,
we will be showing a demo about attacking
bluetooth and ble networks. So after the demo we'll
be also providing the recommendation for this ecosystem security.
With that we'll be summarizing our presentation.
So let's start with our presentation. So as you can see,
the first slide is about IoT or wearable ecosystem.
So this is how the typical Iot wearable ecosystem looks
like. So it has got four components. So as you can
see in the picture, there's a backend services that is nothing but a cloud,
and there's a smartphone and there are protocols
and also there's a gateway. These all like four
components make up a wearable ecosystems or IoT ecosystem.
So let's take an example of home automation
system. So coming to home automation system, there will be
devices which are called as nodes, and these nodes
will be having sensors. And these sensors could be deployed
across the house. So what are these sensors going to do?
So they would collect information like temperature,
fire alarm, and also fire security alarm. So the same information
is sent back to backend services. That is nothing but a cloud
which could be private or public. So you
will know. Most of the examples like have to talk about cloud
could be AWS or Microsoft Azure,
many more. So the same whatever the
information is sent to cloud could be viewed
on your smartphones too. So as you can see in the diagram
that there are nodes present and there's gateways
of present show. So based on the requirement, there can be
multiple nodes and multiple gateways. And it is not restricted to
one or two like how we have given. So based on the requirement, you can
have your own nodes there. So coming to next slide
here we are mainly taken fitness trackers
as an example and we have given a case study about them.
So everybody would want to buy us
fitness tracker like nothing but smartwatches.
The main reason is because they're very comfortable.
When I talk about comfortable, it's nothing but they
don't have wires around them that makes
IoT easier and simpler for a user to use them.
Also they're smart enough to take user commands
and also give the required output to the user.
And also they're into continuous
learning, they keep learning bands, they keep evolving as
the user requirement. So this overall improves
the quality of a user. So as I told
you in the previous slide, that why anyone would want to buy
a wearable device, why they would want to use it in the daily life.
So now let us talk about the challenges
in securing this modern day gadget.
Here we would mainly using
to understand what kind of challenges they're
facing today's world. So these variable advisors
are prone to attacks like the many attacks that has been
taken place on these kind of wearable devices. So therefore it
is very quite challenging to secure these kind of gadgets,
mainly because the traditional STLC frameworks
are applied to products which are having a long shelf life
with constant requirement. But whereas with these type of
gadgets, time to market would be very less and the
requirement will ble continuously evolving. So that
is one of the reason one
of the main challenge. And the other one would be like there are 30
to 40 protocols and to choose the right one
by a developer would be very difficult. And the fourth one is like
there's not much privacy. And last one would be,
there's no much research made on IoT security. So there's
a lack of research that is being done.
So next, as we saw the
challenges in those devices, there could be even
technical challenges. So if I have to take an example
of these wearables devices, these wearable devices contain
lots of information, they have lots of data in them. So it could be
geolocation information, or it could be biometric data,
or it could be sensor data, or it could be payment services.
So it is must for
us to secure these kind of gadgets because they have lots of information
stored in them. So one of the challenge is because
these gadgets will be running with limited software stack,
which makes it very difficult for us to provide
them with asymmetric key cryptos because
they're heavy on these kind of limited software.
Stack. So because of which the security will obviously get
compromised in the same way. Coming to cloud,
there could be cross domain flows or it could be multiple exposure
points is because of this kind of limitations.
So along with the hardware part, we need to
also protect cloud and mobile applications as
well. So coming to today's agenda, so we'll
be mainly using on two protocols, that is
Bluetooth and the other one is ble. BLE is nothing
but Bluetooth low energy. So let's get into so
ble and Bluetooth. So coming to them,
there are various protocol for short read data
exchange. So coming to Bluetooth, it is having a range
of one to 100 meters. And blE,
which is nothing but Bluetooth low energy, is having
a range of ten to 600 meters. So this ble
is a lightweight subset of classic bluetooth with low power consumption.
So these are used where there's less throughput and less power consumption.
And also they're having a frequency of range from 2.4
to 2.45 ghz. So this ble,
Bluetooth and all are maintained and governed by Bluetooth Special
interest group. Any updates that are being made is done by the same
group. So coming to popular use cases,
there could be wearables devices, smartphone system.
You also heard about Alexa is a famous devices
being used. These are all few of the examples where Bluetooth is
being used. So coming to Bluetooth
security. So Bluetooth security mainly depends on
pairing mechanism, like how they are getting paired, like how
the variable device bands, the Bluetooth,
which is like via phone is getting paired.
So let's discuss more on that. So there are like four
of them, four methods. First one is deskworks. Coming to deskwork,
it's very limited bands is having no user interface and
by default IoT will have four or six zeros. And the second
one is numeric comparison. Coming to numeric comparison,
we are having a device with a display which will have
yes or no button. When you have to pair your device, you have to type
in s. And the third one is pass key entry,
wherein you will be provided with six digit pin.
You have to enter the same pin in order to pair
your device with that of a Bluetooth. And the
fourth one is out of bands. And I can tell this is the most secure
one because here the user authentication is being done
using other protocols like WiFi, direct or NSC.
And once the pairing is done,
the network traffic between the two will be encrypted
via AdS 128 algorithm.
So we understood about the pairing mechanism,
that is like four of them. And once the pairing is done.
The network traffic is being encrypted. So now let us
understand more about the weaknesses in this bluetooth
or ble. So coming to the weaknesses,
I just spoke about the pairing algorithm. Simply the
algorithm we're
compromising with our security. The first one is
the same thing. That is security of the communication
link depends on pairing algorithm. So if it's more
complex then the security is also good enough.
And the third one is as I told dustworks
method will take keys by default
and it will have these four or six zeros. So it will be prone
to man in the middle attacks. So also there is key exchange
that is taking place between the two during
pairing mechanism that could lead to eavesdropping.
The fourth one and the most important one is the app
on the fourth. So the more about it we'll be discussing further
in our slides. Thank you Ananya. Hello everyone,
I'm Meghana Rao. I work as security analyst at Deep Armor.
As we now understood the problems and weaknesses
of Bluetooth IoT ecosystems, let's dive into practical exploitations
of ble system. Here we are going to attack
wearables device with the help of mobile ecosystems.
So for today's demo we'll be using Mi bands. It is a
fitness tracking device, performs activities like sending app notifications,
calculating calories, step count, heart rate,
sleep rate, et cetera. Let's see how this device can be breached.
And this is the ecosystems overview. Similar to
IoT ecosystems, this overview is specific to wearable
device. It comprises of wearable device, mobile application,
cloud and here wearable device communicates
with its application via Bluetooth. That is ble
protocol. Sometimes wearable device and mobile app communicates
with cloud directly using HTTPs protocol.
In today's presentation, our main focus is on the communication
that is happening between the band and the app.
This is how a device communication looks like. We can see that there
is lot of data exchange happening from mobile to device and
back. So mobile sends information like put device into
recovery mode, firmware update, social app
notifications, et cetera and band sends notifications
about user activity, data profile update and response to
social app notifications. So the traffic
between the band and its app is encrypted using LTK.
That is the long term key. When attacker is in this vicinity
bands, he's trying to sniff this traffic.
Then he would be ending up with the garbage data that is encrypted data.
Then where does the problem exactly occur? The problem mainly
occurs when we have a malicious application residing on our
phone because whenever encrypted data from variable
device reaches the Bluetooth layer. The Bluetooth
layer decrypts the encrypted BLE data which
will be forwarded to mobile app to display
the actual content in user readable format. Just like if
encrypted data says XYZ and it
would be decrypted as calories count is 30. During this
data transfer, any app residing on the
phone can sniff and fetch all the data that
is being exchanged. For this demo, I'll be
pairing my Mi band with its companion
application. That is mifit app which
is installed on my smartphone. As an
attacker, I'll try to sniff the traffic, steal step counts
and calories using the farmer's custom malware app.
Okay, so let's get started. The white screen
here is from Android Studios. It is a cat window.
It displays all the logs on the phone. I've added a filter here to
display logs from malware application and I'm casting
my phone using wiser app. We can see that I've installed both
mifit app and ble malware app to begin
with. So to begin
with, I've launched my malware app which
is configured with band's Bluetooth address. Now I'll
access this MIF tab which is paired with my Mi
band. I'm trying to perform
certain activities so that I can add step
counts or I can simulate step counts. I'm rotating my hand,
I'm performing a few activities. We can see that
step counts are getting updated on MI application and
we can also see that it is getting updated on malware app
due to data traffic sniffing. So the latest or
the last updated value I see is 1026.
It is same on Lockcat Window as well because Lockcat Window is
capturing the logs from malware app and it says the
step count is 1026 and calories are 30.
A quick recap, we paired our Mi bands to phone,
tried sniffing the traffic between phone and the device where
we were able to steal step counts and calories information.
This is the Gat profile and these are the UUIds.
That is universal unique ids that are responsible for heart rate
and step count and the universal unique
id or uuId that is ending with f nine
b 34. FB is responsible for heart
rate bands. One that is ending with seven
double zero is responsible for step count.
So coming to root cause of this issue the root
cause of this issue is app. On any app on Android
or iOS that is subscribed to Bluetooth services can rewrite
or fetch all the Bluetooth data just like a legitimate
app all that app needs is Bluetooth and Bluetooth
admin permission. Bluetooth admin permission is needed to
make device discoverable or to find a device that is
discoverable. And Android documentation has
clearly added this clause that all
the apps will have. Like all the apps with these
permissions will have this extra feature but application
using it should not misuse this power and
it goes same with the iOS as well in which we need core
Bluetooth framework permission. As we
previously discussed,
LTK encrypted data gets decrypted on reaching Bluetooth
layer and in order to mitigate this malware attack
we have to encrypt this data with app specific
key bands Bluetooth layer so that only legitimate
application can access it. And problem with this trust model
is device is trusting entire phone and all the
apps on it and the only solution to this
problem is confining the trust boundary. That is the
trust boundary should ble from device to its companion
application or legitimate application.
Let's quickly summarize the next generation IoT device
has next generation problem and entire IoT
security comprises of device, phone, communication protocol
and cloud. So all these components has to be
included in SDLC process that is
secure development lifecycle process a development phase itself
and continuous security should be including as
part of CI CD pipeline. And today privacy
is of bigger concern. So privacy security bands
legal has to be oven from the development cycle itself.
We also have to consider integration and interoperability
problem while finding solution to the existing problems and
make sure the entire Iot security is like
entire Iot ecosystems is secure.
Thank you.