Hi everyone, thanks for joining for my talk on isolation
levels and partial failures in distributed systems.
So most of my talk in this particular session
will be covering the non functional aspects of distributed
systems like consistency,
isolation, concurrency, performance,
availability and reliability. Why they're important and
what problems are we trying to solve. So to begin with,
I would start off with the concept of isolation
and why is it important in transactions?
And even before that, what is a transaction?
Right. So any event or any
operation that we do in our day to day life, say you're purchasing
something on an e commerce platform, or you're editing a Google document,
or reading from a Google document, or browsing
something on the Internet and looking at some data. Anything and
everything involves two things. Either it is a read
or a write operation in the distributed system. Say when you are purchasing something on
the Internet, on the ecommerce platform, you are actually making
a payment. And for that you need to update a database record.
So that means you're writing something in the DB, the database, in the backend,
or when you're viewing something on the
ecommerce platform to purchase something, that means you are reading the data.
So it's just read or write. What happens
when so many of us, it's not just one person,
millions of people across the globe trying to read and
write the data onto these distributed systems
concurrently, at the same time. So lot of
things needed to be handled at the back end. What is that? Lot of things.
So most importantly, concurrency. So the concept of
concurrency in itself explains that it coming
into picture as we all try to interact with these distributed systems.
So what is important is the
acid properties of the database. Like what is
acid, the atomicity, consistency, isolation and
durability. So among these four, I would be focusing
on the isolation aspect of this
particular data based systems in the distributed
environment. So these properties are fundamental
principles of these database management systems that ensure the reliability,
integrity and correctness of transactions. Now in this,
let's talk about the isolation and what is
isolation? And in that, what are these isolation levels and
why are they needed in this distributed systems environment?
So isolation means that a transaction should take place in a system in
such a way that that is the only transaction that
is accessing the resources in the distributed system. So like
I mentioned earlier, many of us are trying to access these systems.
Say, while I took this example here, e commerce platform,
some users are trying to, users are trying to
say, purchase some items. Buyer one is trying to look
at all the products and also buyer two and
buyer three, all of them are looking at some products and as you can
see, buyer one and buyer two are trying to purchase,
read and write, that is, view and purchase the
same product, which is the Jim Klaus here. And there is
a view buyer three who is trying to also read
and purchase, read and write a couple of products like
motorcycle helmet and office chair at the same time while the seller is trying to
update the price of the product. So that means a lot of concurrency.
Lot of concurrent things are happening here. So imagine
that you're implementing like a distributed system, an e commerce system like this.
All these operations have to take place at the same time, right? Multiple customers
simultaneously want to purchase the same product, prices of the product
may change, and new products are still being delivered. So on. As you know,
a single action done by a user is run as a transaction
in a database, which I just explained. So we need some logic to
maintain the consistency. And that's the role of isolation,
because it controls whether locks
are taken, when the data is read, and what type
of locks are requested, how long the
read locks are held, so that the
viewer is able to see a proper consistent data
before some new data gets updated. Whether a read operation
referencing some rows modified by another transaction,
say here, the seller updating the price of a particular
product, which the buyer three is reading. So it blocks until
the exclusive lock on the row is freed or
retrieves the committed version of the row that existed at the time the
transaction started. It's depending on the isolation
levels. So these are the things which is controlled by
the isolation level. And let me again go into
what is an isolation level and what are the different types of isolation
levels. So simple, right?
Putting in simple terms, database isolation defines the degree
to which a transaction must be isolated from the data modifications
made by any other transaction. Say multiple,
multiple transactions, or multiple people are trying to access the same record.
How much degree of isolation, how much isolation is needed for
either reading or writing is called this
isolation level, and there can be a large number of concurrently
running transactions. So that's why the goal is to prevent reads
and writes of temporary, aborted,
or otherwise incorrect data written by concurrent transactions,
right? Say if someone is writing the data and hasn't committed the data,
and someone else is reading the data, which is not committed,
not supposed to happen, right? So you shouldn't let read happen, say when,
until a transaction is committed, write transaction is committed. An example,
by the way, while I'm explaining that, I already gave an example of dirty
read. So here you can see there's a problem or a phenomena
of concurrent transactions called dirty read,
where a transaction reads data written by
a concurrent uncommitted transaction. Here, the uncommitted
data is called dirty. For example. Let's take the example on
the right hand side. On the screen here I presented,
let's say a transaction one updates a row in a database
and leaves it uncommitted.
Meanwhile, transaction two reads the updated data updated
row. So if transaction one rolls back that change
like it's aborted, or it rolls
back, transaction two will have red data that is considered to
never have existed, right? So we shouldn't let
someone read until the data is actually
committed. So that's what this read
committed isolation level means. As you can see on the left
side of the picture, not letting transaction two
read the data. T two to read the data until the t
one has finished writing and then updating it. So that's
what read committed isolation level
means. Now,
the isolation level does not allow any other transaction
to write or read row to which another
transaction has written two. But dotnet committed another
transaction. Here is t one. That's what I just explained. Thus it does not
allow allow dirty read, right? So you're locking
on the read, not letting read to happen. The transaction holds a
read or a write lock on the current row, and thus prevents other transactions from
reading, updating, or deleting it. Now, what things are guaranteed
with this? Right? Firstly, let's talk about three aspects,
which I was saying the non functional aspects. First is consistency. So read
committed provides good balance between consistency and concurrency.
It ensures that transactions only see committed data, right? So preventing
dirty reads so consistency is good.
You are like across different systems or different
nodes, there won't be any wrong data or inconsistent data.
Secondly, concurrency read committed
allows for higher concurrency compared to other strong isolation levels
like repeatable read, which we'll be covering later because it
releases locks as soon as the data is read.
So it's not like in
this particular read committed doesn't hold the lock for a
long time, which is good for.
Which is good for concurrency. A lot of concurrent operations can happen
since you're holding the lock for lesser time. However, it still suffers from
non repeatable reads and phantom reads, which we'll
be covering in the next sections again. Now let's move into
the performance so performance is again, read committed tends to have
better performance than other stronger isolation levels due to its lower
level of locking and reduced contention. I just mentioned
a few seconds ago it allows for more concurrent transactions,
but may still incur some overhead due to lack of acquisition
and releases. Now in this
direction, let's move into the next problem, which is non
repeatable read, which I just gave an intro about.
So what is a non repeatable read which the read committed isolation level doesn't
solve? Say for example, suppose transaction
t one reads data, okay?
Now due to concurrency, another transaction t two updates the
same data and commit. Now, if t one rereads the
same data, rereads like the same again repeated reads
the data, it will retrieve a different value, right? So you're
not rereading the same value, but a different value after
the t two has written and committed the data,
right? So the read committed
doesn't guarantee this particular,
you know, don't want to, you want to read the same data within the same
transaction flow like read and read. Right?
Now how is it solved by now? This can be
solved by repeatable read isolation level.
This isolation level makes sure any transaction that
reads data from row blocks any
other writing transactions from accessing the
same row. So this is the most restrictive isolation
level that holds read locks on all rows it
references and write locks on all rows. It inserts,
updates and deletes. Since other transactions cannot read,
update, or delete these rows. Consequently, it avoids non repeatable read.
I just demonstrated all of this using the picture
on the left t one is trying to
do select and select two select send.
No other transaction can do any operation
while you are reading. While one transaction is reading here. So two
reads are happening and it's locked completely.
All the locks, all rows it references
are being locked completely. So that way non
repeatable road non repeatable read can be
avoided. And now let's
talk about the consistency, concurrency and performance.
So as you can see, firstly,
holding lot of locks, right? Holding locks on all the
rows. Let's talk about performance.
Repeatable read have slightly worse
performance as I just described, compared to late
committed recommitted isolation level due to like increased locking
and reduced concurrency. Its impact on
performance depends on the workload too, and the level of contention system.
So why reduced concurrency? Let's talk about concurrency.
Repeatable read typically results in lower concurrency compared
to read committed because it holds locks for the duration
of the transaction. Because you're doing two reads, right read
read for the entire duration of the transaction. T one
is holding the lock entire duration
of the transaction to prevent other transactions, say t two in this aspect to
do any kind of updates from modifying the data.
This can lead to increased contention and potential deadlock situations because as
you are holding the lock for a long time, there'll be a lot of contention
and waiting and there's bad concurrency,
things are not happening in parallel. Well, so holding
lock for longer and not letting other writes
to happen in parallel is something not really good.
But consistency, yeah, repeatable read provides
strong consistency than read committed because you're solving that other
problem as well by ensuring that once data
is read by a transaction, it remains unchanged for the duration of
the transaction. So that's good consistency. Even though someone
updates the data and commits, you can't do that like in read committed.
That is allowed, right? Until, if it is committed, you can
read again after it is committed. So two reads will result in
two different data. It's not totally consistent if it is read committed isolation
level. But with this particular readable
repeatable read isolation level, you're actually providing
stronger consistency.
But the non repeatable reads may not.
This prevents non repeatable reads, but it may
still allow something called phantom reads. Now, what is a phantom
read and who solves it? Let's talk about it. Now, the next
thing is snapshot isolation. This is another very
very very deep or strong isolation
level. And what it solves is something called phantom read,
along with the dirty read and the non
repeatable read as well. So phantom
read a transaction, say, re executes
a query returning a set of rows, not just one row, but a range
query. A set of rows say greater than, say, for example,
let's list all the players
who earn more than say blah blah blah, certain dollars. So list
of all, like a range query. So set of rows that satisfy
search condition and finds that the set of rows satisfying the condition has
changed due to another recently committed transaction,
say new entry got added, right? So this
is similar to a non repeatable read, except it involves
changing collection matching predicate rather than
a single item. So as I have given the example
as well here, say transaction one has read something and
now there is something written by transaction two
appending to the list. It's just range query appending to the
list and it's committed. And when you read the transaction
after some time, again double read,
it's similar to non repeatable read. Exactly the same thing. If you
look back, it's even in
the previous one you're reading, and then transaction two is writing committed,
and then another read. Similarly reading, and then another
transaction is writing, and again a second
read. So it's similar to non repeatable read, except it involves
changing collection matching predicate rather than single items.
It's a range. So how is this solved? By snapshot
isolation level. This isolation level can greatly
increase concurrency at lower cost than transactional
isolation. Now, when the data is modified. The committed
versions of affected rows are copied to a temporary
data structure or a temporary place and
given some version numbers. So this operation is called copy on write and
is used for all inserts updates. And I'm referring to the diagram
on the left. And when another session reads
the same data, the committed version of the data
as of the time the reading transaction began, it returned.
So when someone initiates read, it will be provided with
a snapshot of the current data. And if
someone is doing a write at the same time,
the write gets its own snapshot. As you can see in
t one and t two, two transactions are trying to write say
odd to even and then even to odd. So the
green, like t one, is changing from odd to even.
All the greens, it has its own snapshot and then changed. And t
two, it has its own snapshot and it's changed event odd.
Ultimately, though, all are combined once the transactions
are complete and written to the original database. So same way when
there is a read happening, when these two t one, t two, like t three
is doing some read, it will be provided its own snapshot,
and so there is no one interfering with their
own say, transactions, say read or write.
So that way, maintaining everyone
having their own snapshots has this high level of concurrency
and also strong consistency maintained.
So let's talk about consistency. Firstly,
snapshot isolation, as I said, provides the strongest consistency guarantees
among all the three isolation levels I just mentioned. It ensures that
transactions see a consistent snapshot of the database. As of the transactions
start when the read, say started. By the
time the read is finished, like two or three reads the whole transaction,
the data is still the same because it's using snapshot,
preventing both non repeatable reads and phantom reads.
There's no change. If there is a change, that's when the phantom
reads and non repeatable reads come into picture their problems.
Now, concurrency snapshot isolation typically allows for higher
concurrency because it doesn't hold locks on read operations.
Right? Just like previously we were talking about holding locks in
what is that repeatable read isolation level.
Now with this, instead,
it maintains multiple versions of data items, allowing concurrent transactions to
operate on their own constant snapshots. So concurrency is
guaranteed. Wonderful. No performance. Snapshot isolation can
have good performance too in read heavy workloads with
low update contention because it allows for high concurrency.
Like when read is happening, everyone is probably with their
own snapshots and write can also happen in parallel and
avoids the overhead of locking. So wonderful.
But think about it, the performance here,
the time complexity is ensured, like it's
fast, there's no locking, and concurrently things are happening. It's quick.
However, it requires like additional storage space, because where do
you put the snapshots, right? So overhead of maintaining the multiple versions of
the data is coming into picture. So that needs to be considered.
The space complexity is what I'm talking about, especially in
writes, everyone maintaining a copy of their own. So you need to account for that
extra memory in the database when you're considering the
snapshot isolation. So those are the three things
about the read, committed,
non repeatable read
and snapshot, all three levels of isolation which guarantee
certain degree of consistency, concurrency and performance
aspects. Now, switching gears apart from
the consistency,
concurrency and performance, the two
other non functional aspects of distributed systems, especially in
the large language models which are very
important to consider, are these partial failures.
So now partial failures,
like what are partial failures, right. These refer
to situations where only a subset of components,
like what is a distributed system? Like I said, lot of connected computers working in
a network, you have lot of systems connected globally
in a network, interacting with each other, trying to locate the data
and processing, computing, again, merging the data,
all that is happening, data processing in a distributed environment.
Now a lot of communication is going on. So what
if only a subset of components or nodes within the system experience failures
while other parts continue to function normally? That's called
partial failure, the name itself suggests.
Right, this is what I'm saying. But so
the two types of like failures I mentioned here,
as I said all the, by the way, this distributed environment,
again, you can consider it as an e commerce platform where a lot of
people are trying to purchase items on the
ecommerce website and all the transaction
requests coming onto the back end. And that back end is this node,
one node three, node two, node ten, node four connected over a network.
And node failures, like I said, the partial failures can be of two types.
Node failures, individual computers, individual systems may
experience failures due to hardware or software, right? It's very much
possible. Or network partitions, where these
systems interacting with each other may be disrupted due to some
bad network and leading to some network
partitions, or isolated segments unable to reach or
connectivity issues and things like that.
And these partial failures are very unique
feature of distributed systems, only because if you think about a
single program, single computer, or a single system where you are just running
a program and letting it run a standalone application, there's no
problem why it either runs
100%, or if it doesn't run, it's either because your
Internet is bad, or the hardware failure,
or blank screen, things like that. It's zero or 100. There is
nothing in between if it is a single computer, or if there is a flaw
in the software itself, the program you're running. But in distributed environment,
it's not the issue with just the logic of your program or the
code, or it's not the problem with
the connectivity or just the
what is that? Complete failure. But it has to be
completely partial as well, like it's somewhere in
between. So that is the distributed environment problem.
Now, despite the partial failures, some parts
of the distributed system may remain operational, while others experience
disruptions. So this can result in inconsistencies,
degraded performance, or temporary unavailability of services.
Now, how can this be handled?
Is simple, right? Like you need to have lot of replication.
I picked replication. There are other things like building fault tolerance systems and
reliable systems, which I covered in some of my
previous sessions at con 42, which can be referred
to, but here I'll be focusing a bit or giving some
intro about the replication aspect to handle
these partial failures. Now, various replication
strategies are employed in distributed systems to handle these partial failures and ensure data
availability and reliability. First is full replication.
So in full replication, all data is replicated across multiple
nodes or replicas. In the distributed system, each replica
contains a complete copy copy of the dataset. So this approach ensures
high availability and fault tolerance. And since any
node, any single node failure can be mitigated by accessing data
from other replicas. However, it can be costly in terms of storage
and bandwidth requirements, especially for large data sets.
So next is what? Partial replication? Yeah, so partial
replication involves replicating only a subset of
the data across multiple nodes. Different subsets
of data can be replicated based on access patterns, data importance or
other criteria. And this strategy
can help reduce storage and bandwidth costs compared to the full replication, while still
providing fault tolerance for critical data. However, it may require
careful data partitioning and management to ensure, like you need
to understand what is important, data that is adequately used
and needs to be replicated next is sharding alsoness.
It's a very common one, it's a very popular one. Horizontal partitioning
involves partitioning the dataset into multiple subsets called shards,
and distributing these shards across multiple nodes. Each node is responsible
for storing and managing a subset of the data, so sharding can improve
scalability and performance. Scalability is more important or
is a higher, bigger problem, which sharding solves and performance,
of course, by distributing the workload across different nodes, parallelly happening concurrent
requests in the event of a node failure only
the data stored on that node is affected,
minimizing the impact on the overall system. Right. So still
that this is still manageable. Now, replication chains replication
chains involve replicating data from one node to another in a
sequential chain like fashion. Each node in the chain replicates
data to its successor node. This approach can provide
fault tolerance by ensuring that data is replicated across multiple
nodes in the chain. However, it may introduce latency
and complexity, especially in the large distributed systems.
As it's a chain of replication, you have to do, as it sounds
obvious. Next is the primary backup replication.
One node serves as the primary replica,
responsible for processing client requests and updating data changes
made to the primary replica, asynchronously replicated to one or
more backup replicas. So asynchronously replicating is very important.
You don't want to block other transactions while replication is
happening. So if the primary replica fails, one of the backup
replicas can be promoted to the primary role to continue
serving client requests. So this approach,
again, it's like a master slave and new leader, new master election,
and all those things come into picture. So this approach provides fault tolerance,
higher availability, while minimizing overhead compared to full replication.
And the last one is quorum based replication.
It involves replicating data to a subset of nodes,
known as a quorum. Read and write
operations require coordination among a quorum of nodes to
ensure consistency and fault tolerance.
So quorum based replication can provide strong
consistency guarantees while tolerating failures of a subset
of nodes within the quorum.
So yeah, so this is all I wanted to cover
today. Obviously there'll be more
things to talk about, say the fault tolerance.
And like I said, I covered in one of my previous talks.
And for even more detailed discussions or
furthermore problems and handling the problems in distributed systems,
I would like to take some other session.
This is it for now. And thank you very much for
watching all the way through. Thank you.