Let's talk about DevOps and internal developer platforms
and how those might be the only thing that matters
for DevOps engineers or DevOps culture, what terraform
that's called today. My name is Victor. I work for upbound.
We're a company behind Crossplane and quite a few other things you will
see crossplane later. But that's not the focus right
now. When I said DevOps, most of you are probably thinking
about containers. Kubernetes, cloud, GitHub, CI CD
logging, monitoring, infrastructure as code troubleshooting, security service
mesh and so on and so forth. But that's not
what DevOps is about. Those are operations tools,
right? Those are the tools that if they did exist in
the past, some of them did. We would be using them as members
of OpS departments or Ops people or security
experts or sysadmins, whatever we were called in the past.
But DevOps is about combining development and operations
and enabling developers, application developers,
to be selfsufficient, to move faster, to be able
to do things by themselves. And when we talk
about developers, do we really expect them to use and
know all those things? Are they all going to become
experts in containers? Kubernetes, cloud, Githubs, CI CD
logging, monitoring, troubleshooting, et cetera, et cetera? They're not,
because that would be impossible. No single person can
know all that. And yet we want everybody
to be selfsufficient, to self serve their needs.
And that's the core of what we are trying to do in DevOps.
We are trying to shift left to shift operations
and everything that is happening on those right side of application
lifecycle to the left.
Now we cannot do that by saying, hey, now you do it. Here's AWS
account. Create a cluster, create node groups, create vpcs,
subnets and so on and so forth. Learn kubernetes, create manifests
for deployments or stateful sets and virtual services and services and
ingresses and so on and so forth. We cannot shift left
by saying, now you do it. So the
core, the essence of DevOps is about creating services
that use ops tools but are meant
to enable developers to be able. Application developers,
just to be clear, because everybody's a developer,
right? Everybody writes code. So to enable application developers to
do whatever they need to do, you need a cluster, create it. There's a service
for that. You need an application. Should it be back end or front end?
This or that. Anyways, there's a service for that and so on and so forth.
And that's how we are getting to the concept of internal
developer platforms, or idps. They're internal
because they are meant for internal usage. They are developer because application
developers are the customers of those providing
a platform. And it's a platform because that's how it all comes
together. So IDP or internal developer platform is a
layer on top of the technology and the tooling that we already
have. It is about shifting left by enabling developers,
application developers to be self sufficient by consume
services of such a platform. That's what operations and SREs
and DevOps and whatever other names we have for people on
the right side of application lifecycle, that's what they're doing
to enable developers to self serve themselves.
And the reason why we want to do that, the reason why we want to
create services is to free operations
from doing mundane tasks. Kind of hey,
there is an email, I should create a cluster for this team. Or there
is another email or Jira ticket I should create manifest for application deployed
here and there and so on and so forth. No, that's a waste of
time. What is a good usage of time is to put
all that knowledge into a platform and let
everybody use it. Hey, this is how you create a cluster. Don't ask me.
There's a button, you fill in those three fields or four fields, you get
a cluster, you want application. Again, there is a form with
a few fields, you need to specify whether it's this or that. Click a
button, you get your application, and so on and so forth.
And the reason why we want self service is actually there
are quite a few reasons. We want to increase productivities,
we want to reduce lean time, we want to increase deployment frequency,
we want to decrease meantime to repair or MTTR,
we want to decrease change failure rate or CFR, and so
on and so forth. There are numerous studies that show that
selfsufficient teams are performing better than teams,
that depend on other teams who depend on other teams, and so on and so
forth. And then we get to the question, what should such a platform do?
And the simple answer is everything.
Right? And there are certain stages, certain groups of operations
that we need to think about. We need to be able to change those desired
state. That's the state that is stored in git. We need
to perform certain actions like building container images, running tests
and so on and so forth. We need to converge the actual into the
desired state. You know, if it's in git, that's what it should be.
And we need to be able to observe what's going on and all
that can look more or less like this, we have an
IDP at the top, that's those interaction, that's how we interact
with the whole system. And it's tailor made for the needs of
a company. It contains a user interface which could be web or CLI
or ID, I don't care whatever people are using.
And it needs to have an API. And this is now the core of
the issue, that API must be Kubernetes,
simply because that's the only API that we
have today that is widely accepted and has a tendency real
potential to become a universal API. And then we
have the desired state, that's what we're storing it. And then we have the
actual state, that's AWS and Azure and on Prem and
Google and Splunk and elastic and whatever else we are doing, those are
the providers, and we have infrastructure on top of those providers which are servers or
clusters or databases. And we have applications which could be ours
or third party applications. So we have the desired state,
we have the actual state, and we have internal developer platforms
that enables people to observe those actual state
to see what's going on and to be able to define what the
state should be by pushing stuff to git in a way
that is very easy to define and push as
well. And then we have a Kubernetes cluster. Now don't think about Kubernetes
cluster in this concept as a cluster where our applications
are running. I mean our applications could be running in Kubernetes, but that's not
the purpose here because our applications could be running a services
like Lambda or Google Cloud functions, it could be running on vms,
it could be this, it could be let's say a database managed
database like RDS. In this concept I'm not talking about
kubernetes where applications run. I'm talking about kubernetes
where we can define custom resource definitions,
define what something is, because we already established that
things are too complicated for an average developer.
Defining all the resources for an application Kubernetes is too
complex for people who are not dedicated to kubernetes to understand defining
all the resources in AWS, again too complex. We need
to simplify that and we simplify that by creating
new custom resource definitions. Hey, in my company
this is what it means to run a cluster. And I'll show you that in
a second. And this is what it means to run an application. Again,
I will show you that in a second. And those CRDs have associated
custom resources. Those are the manifests that we store in git that are creating into
custom resources. And the goal of those CRDs is to define what something
can be. The goal of CRS custom resources is to define what
something is. And the goal of kubernetes and controllers in
kubernetes is to convert those custom resources into
something which is the actual state, which could be in our providers,
infrastructure, applications and so on and so forth.
This is what unites it all. And to do that
we need tools, we need pipelines, we need GitHub tools. That's the tools
like ArgosDM flux that synchronizes desired state into what is in Kubernetes.
And Kubernetes synchronizes what is in kubernetes with the actual
state. And we need infrastructure and we need Arbec and
a bunch of other things. And I will show you all those things in
a second. Actually, not all those things, but some of those things in a
demo, because I get nervous speaking for too long without
touching my keyboard. Actually. Now I'm going to think about it. Why not go into
demos right away? I had five, six, seven slides
prepared to talk about it, but that's boring. So let's go straight
into those demo and let me show you how all that looks like,
how we can combine couple of tools to do just
that, and it's not going to be hard, so bear with me. So let's say
that I'm a developer and I want to have a cluster in somewhere.
Let's say aws. And that cluster should have all the things that I
do not really understand, but it should be a cluster, kubernetes cluster. Eks cluster.
How would I do that? How would I do that to the level that is
easy for me to define and consume it as a
service. And by the way, that cluster should not be just a cluster,
it should be production ready cluster, meaning that it should not
be only an eks cluster with node groups and kubernetes and vpcs and so on
and so forth. But everything that I need inside of that cluster already
baked in. And I could do that in a very easy
way by showing you this file. Infrawks.
Here we go. And this file is relatively simple.
Bear in mind, if I would do this without the way how I'm doing it
right now, which is by the way, crossplane, I would probably
end up with 500 lines of yaml or hcl or something
like that. But in this case it's much easier because I'm saying, hey, I want
to create or I want to define something called composite cluster. Now what is
composite cluster, well, that's what other people defined and already prepared.
In my cluster there is a custom resource definition,
or what we call in crossplane XRD or crossplane
resource definition that is called composite cluster. And I
can just say, hey, I want to consume that thing and I will give it
an id and I will say, hey, this should be
an AWS cluster. And that's where we are going into compositions
because this custom resource can have many
different compositions and I can choose, hey, do I want in Google? Do I
want in AWS? Where do I want? And finally,
I have a couple of parameters. I'm saying, you know what,
I do not know what is t two something something or whatever are the sizes
in AWS and Azure and Google. I just want the nodes
of that cluster to be medium size, whatever that means. And I
want to have a minimum of three nodes because hey, you should
have a minimum. And I assume that it will auto scale up, right?
We are defining something that doesn't exist in crossplane. It's what
we call crossplane resource definitions, which are basically base
for operations in my company, or sres or DevOps or
whatever they're called to use to combine different
resources. And I will show you those resources later into something that
is meaningful to everybody else. In this case me and I have
a second xrd called Gitops because I want this cluster to
be Gitops ready and I do not want really to
install argo CD. I do not want to create argo CD
applications and projects. I do not want to configure git repository myself
and so on and so forth. So I'm using yet another custom
resource definition that was created by others. It's called Gitops.
And I'm saying, hey, you know what? I want to use Argo CD. I could
have other implementations of this like flux, but in
this case argo CD and I
wanted to run in a cluster that is identifiable through this
secret and secret namespace, which happens to be the one created by
this guy over here. And most important, this is what really
matters. Hey, I do not want to go into details. What I
do want to do is to tell you that those is the repository you should
monitor and make that cluster the one defined above.
GitHub's ready. Now all I have to do is push this manifest to
git repository. Argo CD will pick it up, it will
create whatever needs to be created in the management cluster, and then crossplane
will do everything else. But I already did that in advance because it
takes 20 minutes, 30 minutes or something like that. So let me show you the
result of me pushing that to git. I did that in
advance. And the result from operational perspective can be this
get managed. And then we can see that
behind that simple definition many things happened.
And I got all those role policy attachments
and roles and different objects installed in that cluster and
different helm charts installed in that cluster, and a node group
and a cluster and subnets and all
those other things that are really necessary. But I
do not want to bother with somebody else create
a composition that combines all those resources and exposes them
through that composition that I showed you a minute ago.
Now that was from development perspective, from operational perspective,
from SRE perspective, there are a couple of things that I had to create,
somebody else had to create in advance. And the first one is definition
saying, hey, I want to create something completely new,
completely new definition. And that definition will be
called composite resource definition. That does not matter.
What matters is that the name from user perspective will be composite cluster.
That's the one I used a second ago. And there is open API
schema that creates a completely new definition.
It's a typical open API schema, nothing really special.
It says hey, you should have an id and you should have some parameters,
and within those parameters you should have version and node size and minimum number
of nodes. And that's what crossplane took to
create that new custom resource definition that I used at the very beginning
of this demo. And then I need to create a couple of implementations of that.
Something I will show you eks, even though I have the
implementation of that same resource definition for Google and for
Azure and so on and so forth. But eks is like this.
Here we go. This is a composition. So one composite resource definition
can have many compositions. So we can pick and choose which
variation we want. And in this case it is composition.
That is called cluster AWS. That's the one I used.
And here we have eks cluster defined, and we
have a bunch of parameters here taken from those user
and node group, and again with some parameters hard
coded and some parameters provided
by users. Like in this case I'm saying, hey, whenever somebody
writes in their manifest parameters, node size, that should be
translated to instance types, because that's what AWS
understands. And whenever somebody says small, it should be t three small,
and whenever somebody says medium, it should be this and large should be
this and so on and so forth. I have here what
else? Role and another role and
role, attachments and so on and so forth. Those are all the things that
you need to do. No matter which tool you're using if you want
to be in control. But we can hide this from end
users, from application DevOps, all those things.
And it's not only about AWS over here. I'm also deploying some
helm charts and kubernetes resources and so on and so forth,
everything that is needed to run a cluster production ready,
cluster in production. And I did those same thing with Githubs.
The variations, whether it's flux, whether it's argo CD, what happens when
argo CD is installed? How do we create this? How do we create
that? And from the user perspective, all those things,
from application developer perspective, all those things are digested
into something that I showed you at the very beginning. I do not need to
worry about those things. I know that this is what operators
in my company, sres did. I can just consume those services
by defining penetrate lines of yaml, like here.
Now let's verify that the newly created cluster really
works. And remember I pushed it to git and I'm
not going to interact directly with my kubernetes cluster at all.
It's all githubs only by pushing to git. But first let me double
check that I can connect to the new cluster and I'm going to do that.
You can ignore this is fetching the secrets stored in the management
cluster. What does matter here is that I can confirm that
the new cluster is up and running by saying hey,
get all the nodes, for example.
Let's go, come on. And were we go, this is
the newly created cluster, right? With everything inside and among
other things it already has argo CD up and running and I can prove it
to you by opening those port. I should have created those domain for
that, but I didn't, I was too lazy I guess. So here we are,
this is Argo CD already baked into that cluster and
I can prove it to you. Admin admin one, two, three, there we go,
it's running. I'm not going to save the password and it's
empty. Nothing there going on, right? Nothing here. And if
I go here, nothing here, right? Because I did not yet push any application
manifest to my git repository,
but I will do that right away. So I want to have an application
running in this cluster. And let's say that it should be a backend
application with database. And let's say that that
database should be AWs RDS database. How would they
do that? And again, that would be very complicated because if I would
like to do that myself, I would need to define stateful set or deployment.
I'm not sure because hey, Kubernetes is complicated a service,
ingress virtual service, this and that. And then I would need to define VPC
and subnets and what's or not for RDS database and RDS database
itself. Create some users in that database, choose this or that, it would
be complete. But the operations of my company, the SRE
or DevOps already created a service for that. Remember this is crossplane
now still and I can show you that service. I can define
a new application based on that service which will be
this one, and says hey, instead of all that nonsense,
I'm going to define something called app,
operator, already created crossplane composition that is called app.
And I'm going to just say that I want to be a backend with a
database. This is the image that I care about.
This is the those it should be exposed to and this is the port that
the application is listening to. And I want also something called SQL.
And that SQL should be in AWS and PostgreSQL
and it could have a couple of parameters and it should write
the connection string to this secret so that this application can
connect to that database through that secret to authenticate there.
Right again, I'm reducing hundreds and hundreds of lines of YAML
or HCL or whatever you're using to a few lines, 30 lines
of Yaml. So what should I do? Well, I should just copy
this file from examples and then what was it?
Backend app, backend backend
AWS, PostgreSQL and no claim. That's the one
I'm going to copy to the directory apps. That's the directory in
repository that ArgoCd is already configured to watch.
And I'm going to add that file and I'm going to
commit with message that says something and
I'm going to push that to git. And that's it. That's all I need to
do to have my application up and running in the newly created cluster.
And that application is very complex. There are many moving pieces, many resources,
but I'm using a service provided by others.
So let's see whether it's working by opening it in
Argo CD. Here we are. Is it working?
Let's see.
There we go. It's coming right? It found two
manifests, app and sql. And so far it's
not doing anything with them. But look at it. This is now crossplane expanding
those compositions into some objects and provider
configs and DB subnet groups and RDS instance and Internet
gateway and so on and so forth. All those things could need to be created
by me, but I don't have to do that because somebody created a service that
I can consume and that service is called. One service is called sql, another service
is called app. And I can just define what
I want. Those let the details and the complexity
into the hands of whoever is creating those crossplane compositions and
just push simple YAML into a
git repository and let Argo CD get it to the management
cluster and let Crossplane do the rest. Actually, it's not
going to the management cluster. It's going directly with Argo CD from git
to the cluster that I created before I started those demo. And I
showed you already how. And if you don't believe me that all those things are
happening, I can prove it to you. I can go to that newly created
cluster, say, hey, this is the kubeconfig that
I fetched before, and get all the apps
and sqls in that cluster. And there we go.
You see, they're not yet ready. Application is ready,
but database is not ready because it takes like ten minutes,
I think for AWS to create airds instance. And I can
also do something similar with get managed all the
resources managed by crossplane. I would not do that as a developer
because for me this is what really matters. But as operator or
SRE, I can see all the details. What did Crossplane create
from those two? And this is what it did.
Those are all the resources that it created for us.
Here we are. All those two were expanded into
those RDs instance in AWS, DB subnet group.
Some objects creating in Kubernetes cluster like deployment,
egress service, Internet gateway,
Kubernetes, VPC, security groups, route tables.
Right. All the complete is now moved to the cluster. It is grouped
into compositions so operations, accessories,
DevOps care about creating those definitions and
controllers behind it. It's relatively easy, as you saw,
and then exposing them through a simple interface
to everybody else so that everybody can consume without dealing with such
a complexity. Thank you so much for watching. My name is Victor.
Let me show a couple of slides. I didn't show many slides. I work for
outbound and what you saw in this demo was very brief,
but probably gave you a glimpse of what you can do with Crossplane to create
your own platform for your own people in your own company.
And that is called Crossplane. And the company
behind Crossplane, actually the company that founded Crossplane is upbound.
I work there, but Crossplane is open source. It was donated
to cloud Native Computing foundation, CNCF, so you can use
it freely, at least in this concept. You might want to
check what we are doing at upbound, but Crossplane is open source.
You might also want to listen to the podcast Devil's paradox. You might
want to come to my YouTube channel, DevOps Toolkit.
And that's about it. Thank you so much for watching,
for listening. See you next time in the next conference or
in my YouTube channel. Come there. Thank you so much.