You. Hello, everybody. How are
you doing? I'm really hoping that you're having a good day. It looks like an
exciting day today at comforty two chaos engineering with
plenty of good content. Looking forward to that. I'm going to talk to
you about chaos engineering in 2021. I know
that this is a lot like, we all have very high expectations
of what 2021 will bring, given how the
last twelve months went and how challenging they were. But I'm going to
try to focus on what I hope chaos engineering is
going to achieve soon, where I think it is in 2021,
the journey that we've made so far together. And spoiler
alert, I'm going to argue that it should be boring and
that boring is a good thing. So one of the things that
the last twelve months tested was our
resilience. And we started talking about resilience and reliability
much more because we realized that things that we were taking for granted couldn't
be taken for granted anymore. Things like going outside
and going for a walk or shopping and getting the basics
or even the infrastructure and electricity.
Turned out that all of that is actually put into
question when there are unprecedented events happening.
All our systems are being tested. We talk about reliability
a lot and resilience, things like the resilience of our
healthcare systems, the reliability of our infrastructure
and stuff like that. It's probably a good moment to kind of
look at what we really mean about know.
We talk about reliability in terms of software engineering
kind of all the time. But if you take a look at the definition,
this is from Oxford Dictionary, is the quality of being trustworthy
or of performing consistently well. And one of
the examples they give is the fundamental aspect to building relationships
is providing reliability. So I was thinking of a good example of
what a really reliable system would be. And I came up
with this. The pyramids, if you think about that, they have been
performing remarkably reliably for thousands
of years. They're still working as expected. They were built,
there's still a tomb, there's still a bunch of rocks put together,
and chances are then a few millennia from now, they're still
going to be standing there virtually unchanged. So it's
a really reliable system. When you think about it. It's not maybe has
exciting as kubernetes, but it's a really reliable system,
or perhaps it's more exciting. And then we have the resilience,
right? The resilience, again from the Oxford Dictionary, is defined
as the capacity to recover quickly from difficulties.
And another definition they also give there is the ability of a substance
or object to spring back into shape.
And I think I might like the second one even more than the first
one, because the springing back into shape, it kind
of gives you this image of pressing or pushing
or compressing, and then the thing comes back
springing back into shape, elasticity of it, right?
So 2020 has been a real test of resiliency on
all kinds of ways. Our lives have been modified from
one day to another. Things that we were taking for granted, like going on
holidays, going outside, have been tested, and the
resilience of our institutions, of our infrastructure,
of our companies, of our teams, we spent a year
basically video conferencing with people and trying to maintain social
interactions with them. All of that has testing whether we can still
be pushed and compressed and then go and spring
back into the previous shape. It's interesting to talk
about this in the context of chaos engineering, because chaos engineering
is all about testing the resiliency and the reliability.
I'm probably talking to two very distinct groups of people here.
Some of you came to this conference to learn about chaos engineering
and how to adopt that and how to get started with that, kind of ramping
up the adoption curve. And some of you might be practicing that
and might be preaching that and are looking for an update
on what's new. So I'm going to try to address both points of view.
I think it's fair to say that, at least in my point of view,
chaos Engineering is at an interesting crossroads
right now, at an interesting point in the timeline, because there are
different trends and phenomena in software engineering that kind of
put chaos engineering in a nice spot for the adoption. And also
we are slowly moving onto that adoption
curve, and we can see that by a number of companies that start doing that,
a number of companies that offer services and stuff like that.
But why is it an interesting crossroad? I think there are different
trends that kind of made it possible for chaos
engineering, kind of made it really necessary for
chaos engineering to emerge. I wanted to mention a few things.
I wanted to mention scale, cloud, native and complexity.
So let's start with the scale. Scale is a little bit,
it's probably the easiest one to explain. Here in our global connected
world, we start having bigger systems. We have bigger
companies that manage not hundreds of thousands, but hundreds
of millions of users. And the systems that we build are getting
bigger, they're getting more complex, they have more features, they have bigger scale.
And from the geographical point of view, we have users
from all over the world. It's all connected, and the scale just becomes bigger,
which increases the complexity. Another kind of factor,
a trend that makes chaos engineering
so important right now is the cloud. We've been on this bandwagon
for a number of years now. When you're using someone else's computer
and you're calling it a cloud, and if you're starting a company right
now with any kind of stack, chances are that you're
probably using some kind of cloud. You're probably going to AWS
or Azure or Google and you're using someone
else's computer. And that layer means that it solves
some of the problems, but it also adds extra layer of complexity,
because now you not only have to understand your application and the
underlying operating system, but you also need to understand how
the cloud is built underneath because most of the time you can probably not think
about that and get away with that. But if things go wrong and
get complicated and you need to debug something, you need to understand that
you also have tools that you need to use to talk to the cloud
provider. You have the APIs, you have caveats, you have
quirks that you need to work with and the differences
in operating between the different clouds. But it's also a driver
that kind of goes back to the scale, because now you can literally go
to a cloud provider and say, oh, tomorrow I need
ten times more resources than I have today, or in an hour I need ten
times more resources, and chances are that you'll be able to get that. So that's
another trend. Then with cloud came the cloud native ecosystem
that has flourished and absolutely grew
enormously in the last few years. And the prime example
of that being kubernetes in this short time,
it basically became the de facto API
for scheduling, orchestrating containers across a
fleet of vms. That was also made possible and made popular
because of the cloud. Right. And with kubernetes, you get another layer. So now
you have the cloud, then you have the Kubernetes layer that works great
and has some amazing features that you can leverage and
that you get for free. But you also need to understand these
are things that can go wrong. And when they do go wrong,
you need to understand how to debug that. You need to understand where to
look for trouble. There's another part of the learning curve that becomes
relevant to you, and that kind of all boils down to the extra layers
of complexity that if you are deploying software today,
it's no longer just about the software. I mean, it probably never has
been, but it's not about just the bugs or memory leak. Now obviously
I know that you guys don't do bugs or memory leaks,
I do. But even if you write the come that works
perfectly, you can still mess things up with configuration
or versioning. If you have a dependency that you point out
to the wrong version or you point out to the wrong dependency,
you have a problem. So even if all the bricks involved are
coded correctly, you can still mess things up. Then there
are things, the embarrassing things like certificates, expiring licenses
probably. Once again you never had this problem, but I
suspect that the certificates expiring on people
is more popular than they want to admit.
Then because of the fact that we have this increasing scale and everything
is in the cloud and more and more
distributed, we have this entire family of
problems that come from the connectivity. Connectivity.
Networking is pretty hard. Latencies, how do latencies
affect your systems? Do you survive them? What about timeouts?
Are the timeouts reasonable? Are the timeouts aligned between
the different components so that the whole thing makes sense? What about retries?
If you get a timeout, how do you retry? Do you get that thundering
Hertz problem? Do you exponential backup? Do you have circuit breakers?
For example, if you retry enough times do your circuit break,
when do you come out of circuit breakers? How do you do all of that?
And then on top of that you also have now new bricks and
new things in the equation. If you're using kubernetes, you're probably using
an overlay network. That means that you have to now understand how
that overlay network is set up and how it
fits with all the other components. Maybe you have a service mesh on top
of that that also includes its own features and
these extra layers. They solve come problems, but they obviously
include their own problems and their own complexity
that you have to somehow manage. Then if you look at the infrastructure
level, you build for redundancy, which is great. In theory
it should be easy, but it's another bit of complexity
scheduling. If you're using kubernetes, like I mentioned, you have to
understand how it's scheduled, you have to understand what the weak
points are, what are the actions that you might
take that will break the scheduling or things like self healing.
It's a wonderful feature of kubernetes and to be able to get self healing for
free. But what happens when that stops working? You now build
your application in a way that relies on the behavior of
kubernetes to bring it back to healthy state. What happens if it doesn't? Or what
happens if you made it stop doing that because you
misconfigured something, then obviously the isolation, all of that makes sense.
If you're making good use of your machines,
that means that you're going to be sharing things. That means that
you have to take care of things like resource starvation. Do you understand
well how the cpu limits are actually implemented?
Do you understand what happens to the process if it goes
and tries to get more ram that's allowed to? Do you have
alerting on that? Will you notice that? Will you know about this?
These are all kinds of problems that we now have to deal with.
And these are all the kind of things that even if you're just starting and
you start your own company, your stack is probably going to involve
all of this wonderful and amazing features at the same time. All of this
extra complexity to deal with. And then obviously, on top
of that, this was all technical. We still have humans involved, we still
have operations. Operations that have the overhead of
having to understand that. Operations that can make mistakes,
incident responses, tribal knowledge, all of that is still has
applicable to all of that. None of the technical solutions can eliminate
these things. So the complexity, it's basically why
chaos engineering is so relevant, because we can go and
we can test the systems as a whole and experiment
on them to see how they cope with all of that complexity.
So for those of you who are new to it, chaos Engineering is the discipline
of experimenting on a system in order to build
confidence in a system's capability to withstand turbulent
conditions in production. And this is what I consider the
canonical definition, circa 2015 from the
principlesofchaos.org from the Netflix gang.
If you remove the fluff from it, it's the experimenting
to build confidence to withstand turbulent conditions.
That's it. That's really what it's about.
And that's why it's so relevant, and that is why it can
be useful on so many levels. Because if you think about it,
it doesn't replace the different ways of testing. You start with your
unit test. When you focus on a small subset of a component
to verify some kind of behavior, this is great. Then you have the integration
tests where you take components and you put them together, and you verify
that they work together. Another layer is probably the end to end tests,
where you take the system as a whole, you spin up a small instance,
and you verify some happy path. And then that's where chaos
engineering kind of comes in, as an extra layer of
verifying things. When you take the system as a whole and you
experiment on this, you verify that when
things happen to it, the unhappy path, when things happen to the
system and might have nothing to do with the correctness of the
code that you wrote. The system continues working as designed.
And when we design the skills experiments, it's basically like
the game of what if, right? It's all about thinking,
what if. What if the network latency increases? What if
traffic spikes? What if the database becomes slow or
we trigger a circuit breaker? What if the application needs to
heal? The what ifs about the system as a whole.
You've verified your unit test, your integration test. But what happens
when you don't have enough cpu? Or what happens if the slowness
happens the way that you didn't expect it to? It's basically like the
what if book by Randall Monroe. One of my favorite reads,
where you go and ask yourself hypothetical questions. Probably not the
kinds that you cover here, like how could we build a Lego bridge between
London and New York? By the way, I really recommend that book if you haven't
read it. But the kinds of what ifs that are realistic
to your system. Right? And speaking of the chaos experiments, we've kind
of bolded down to four steps. Now we're calling them
experiments because we want to underline the kind of scientific
behavior of that. If you really apply the scientific method
to that, it boils down to four steps. You ensure
observability first, and this is important, observability is this
nice word about basically being able to measure
something reliably so that you can observe a behavior.
So for example, if you have some kind of API server
and you serve requests over the Internet, if you pick a
variable that you can reliably measure, you can build your
observability on that. So if you, for example, measure the
request per second, or average latency, or whatever
it is that your metric is, you can build your observability on that.
Then measuring the steady state, steady state
is just a fancy way of saying that this is the normal range.
So let's say that, for example, we measure the request per second
and our normal range with the hardware that we have. And the setup that
we have is about 100,000 requests per second, right?
Let's say that plus, minus five or 10%
of that is our normal range. This is the steady state. And the first
step is when we start having fun, we go and we think
about what if, what happens if 20%
of the servers go down? What happens if the servers
don't have enough cpu? What happens if one of the servers
restarts? All kinds of things that we can take a look
at and we can actually implement as an experiment.
And if you go and form this hypothesis and you have the right
observability and, you know, your steady state, then you can run the experiment.
And ideally, we spend a lot of time trying to automate that and trying
to make sure that this is repeatable and verifying that,
because we're working on an entire system. So it's easy to influence
multiple variables at the same time. And sometimes it's not obvious
to isolate what you want to do, but you run the experiment, and then
the nice thing about the experiment is that whatever the outcome is,
you're good, because if it works, that's great. That means
that you get more confident in your system. You know that in this particular
situation, the system behaves the way that you expect it to if
it broke. On the other hand, that's also great, because that means that you found
a problem and you found a problem that you can fix before the problem
found you, or before a client came and complained to you.
So this is the ideal situation. These are the chaos experiments,
these are the trends that all put us in this
kind of interesting position on the innovation adoption
lifecycle. This is what typically looks like it's a bowl curve.
You will see that when you read about adoption of
new technology. Every new technology goes through something like this,
whether it's smartphones or tablets or wearables or whatnot.
And it basically means that we have a very small group of first
innovators, people who see enough value in the new
technology to put up with the terrible uis,
terrible UX, or bugs, or just bad
first versions. Then after that we have a slightly bigger group
of early adopters who are still able to put up with a certain
amount of things and come lies that are not ironed out yet,
but still see enough value to drive the adoption.
And then that group grows and grows, and eventually, when we hit a certain
critical mass, it becomes an early majority, the late majority,
where most of the people already use the technology,
and then potentially some laggards towards the end
of the curve, the right hand side of the curve. So what happens to a
technology is that it goes from exciting and new and
unusual, and as it goes and gets more and more adoption,
it turns into boring and just part of the landscape.
And I'm going to argue here that we really want chaos
engineering to be boring and be part
of the landscape, and that this year might be just a moment
when it becomes a fact of life. And boring is good, because when you
think about smartphones a few years ago, every new version
of a smartphone that got released has significantly
better than the previous one, got all these new features and all
of that. But at some point, the speed of innovation plateaus.
It becomes more and more boring. Every new smartphone now basically
looks the same, has roughly the same better life, and until
there is a new breakthrough. Looking at you foldable
phones, we are at the boring stage. And that means that smartphone,
everybody has one. That means that it's just part of the landscape. That means that
there are parts of the world where you don't have a pc, but statistically,
you do have a smartphone, and that is a good thing. That means that everybody
has access to that, and everybody can get value out of that. Another example
is rocket science. We're getting to the point now
with SpaceX, where no one's really watching their
launches anymore because they got boring. First time
I saw that rocket go up there, and then one of the stages
land, kind of like in science fiction movies. It was
really, really exciting, but now just kind of happens and doesn't make
headlines anymore because the rockets keep landing.
The starship didn't land particularly well for the last
two tries, so that made news. But when it gets boring, no one
will be talking about it. Right? Same for flights before,
COVID you could just jump on a plane and be reasonably
sure to be delivered safely to your destination at
a reasonable price. Something that people not
that long ago couldn't even imagine. So boring
is good. And the closer we get to boring with chaos engineering,
the better, because everything improves, right? If you
looked at it in 2015, there has the chaos monkey,
and you had a choice of either use chaos monkey or write your
own tool. If you take a look at it today, there are dozens
of open source projects that you can use. There are tools for pretty much anything
you can think of. There are dozens of commercial tools that you can use.
You can actually go and pay someone come money, so that they bring the
knowledge for you in house, and you can get started really quickly.
Things are improving, and then we need the critical mass
of companies that start seeing the value, and we're seeing the
increase in that. We're seeing companies that have been historically very
risk averse, that become more and more interested in that.
And this is how we get it on the roadmap.
We get it boring, and boring is good. Unfortunately,
it's not all rosy quite yet. There are still things that we need to address,
and I'm really hoping that 2021 is when we do that.
This is a little poll that I did on LinkedIn towards the end of last
year. And I asked people, what's blocking you from doing chaos
engineering? And the top two responses were difficult to generate.
Buying with 50% and inadequate training with 27.
The missing or hard to use tools only got 11% of
the votes. So after speaking a lot to
different people in different companies, I identified the
myths that still kind of float around
chaos engineering as one of the top contributors
to why generating buy in for chaos engineering is still a
little bit tricky in 2021. And so I wanted to
cover some of that with you so that you're prepared for having these conversations
so that when that arrives and someone tries to use that,
you can debunk them. One of the things is the
it's chaos monkey, right? Kind of situation. It's an interesting one to
kind of talk about, because, yeah, in a way, it was all kind of started
by SCS monkey back in the day. Netflix moved on to AWS
2010 eleven, I think, and they started doing chaos
monkey. Eventually they spread it, and that's how the chaos engineering name
was populated. Right. That is a testament to chaos monkey being
a good name, because everybody seems to know it, but it's so much more right
now. It's like the entire spectrum. You have the chaos
monkey on one side, where you don't really need to know that
much of your system. You can set it up very easily,
and you can randomly break things and see what happens. And this
is valuable. This is how it all started. It allows you to detect
things that you missed in other layers of testing. It allows you to test
for emerging properties, the things that happen
because of the interactions between different components that
you wouldn't have caught with your unit tests or integration tests.
And this is great. This is a very good start where you don't know where
to start, but there is the entire side of the kind of other side
of the spectrum where you can start by analyzing your system and
start from the weak points of your system, and design very
custom tailored experiments that
deal with very particular failures that you expect to
do. And the fact that we have this entire spectrum and you can find
your happy point, your happy spot,
anywhere on this line, means that adoption
is possible for different companies with different constraints,
different possibilities for what kind of risk is acceptable
to take. Right. Another thing that I keep hearing is that it's testing
production. And I'm expecting this one is probably never going
to go away, because there was so much about breaking things randomly in
production at the beginning. And it's also understandable because it is the
holy grail. Ideally, we would all be so amazingly
confident and have done so much testing with all the other phases
that we would inject the failure in the production system. Because if
you think about it, that's where the real data is and everything else is
an approximation. We will never be 100% sure.
We can never 100% test a system because it's
a copy, a clone, an approximation of what the production one is.
But it obviously doesn't mean that you have to start there. And it doesn't mean
that if it's not in production, it's not case engineering.
You can get a lot of value, and in some cases, you probably can't
ever go to production. If people will die, if you accidentally
detect a failure in your system, probably never going
to be acceptable. But that's okay, because everybody can apply
that to the level where it makes sense for them. And if
you can go all the way to the production, that's great, and we should probably
talk. But it doesn't mean that this should hamper
your adoption. Another one is, it's only for
x massively distributed systems, or microservices,
or golang, or kubernetes, or cloud.
And this is also a myth, because kind of like similar to
adapting to come engineering to your system, it doesn't really matter
what your system is. You can still use the same methodology,
you can still apply the same scientific framework to designing
and running this experiment. And in my book,
I'm going to give a link at the end, I have an entire chapter that
talks about a single process that's legacy that you're
not even taking a look at the source code of, that you can play with
and tinker and experiments to verify that the retry logic
that it supposedly has is working on
a single process, on a single machine, without a distributed system
or without kubernetes. So it's really important to
stress that it's flexible enough that you can get value out
of applying this to pretty much any system as big or as
small or distributed as it is. And obviously, if you
have a massive, amazing system and you do that
at scale, that makes for a nice, better blog post. But you can apply
that to anywhere, and there is no reason to not harvest that low hanging
fruit and their nice return on investment. Another one that
I keep hearing is that our organization is not mature enough
for cash engineering. And I get it. It probably
comes from just being a little bit intimidated by the big guys and
thinking, okay, yeah, but we're not Netflix or Google, so we might not
be mature enough. It might be coming from just not
being confident that confident in the existing test.
If you expect things to break, that can be intimidating.
But once again, this is a flexible framework that
you can apply to whatever makes sense for you.
So if you don't feel you're mature enough to run
that on a big part of a system, you can start with a small part
of a system. It's something that really can be applied at
any level of maturity. And obviously the value you get will differ,
but it's good to get into the habit of doing that anyway.
And you can already get value and then connected to that
is like this one. I literally get it pretty much every time.
We already have chaos, wink wink, kind of joke.
And if you're saying things like that, you don't really understand what chaos
engineering is about, because it's not about increasing the amount of chaos or
increasing the number of things that can go wrong and unknowns.
It's about decreasing that by injecting failure. That's very
controlled, that you understand. If you just inject random
failure into your system, that's probably not going to teach you much apart
from potentially, oh, your system doesn't work when something breaks.
But if you know exactly what you're injecting and it's a
reasonable thing to expect to happen to your system, the popular kinds
of failures, you decrease the amount of chaos, you know
how it's going to behave. So that's no longer an unknown,
that's something that you control, you can fix, you can modify.
So if you're saying that, have a think about what chaos
in uni is really about, because it's not about increasing
chaos, it's about decreasing that and finally breaking
things randomly. Kind of goes back to chaos monkey. And I kind of
touched on that, talking about the spectrum. But it's really, really important to stress
that the randomness, it's kind of like the practice of fuzzing when
you generate random inputs or random race
conditions and random orders, and you verify that the system works
well, and this is great, but it's just part of it now, and there is
more to it. And if the randomness doesn't work in your case,
you should probably look at the other side of the spectrum.
Okay, so this is the myths that I keep hearing, and if you
are able to talk about them, you're already in a good spot to
get cursed in your roadmap. But there's also two
conversations that you need to be prepared to have
with other people. And these are the things that I called getting called
less and risk versus reward or sharks versus
hamburger kind of situation. So let's start with getting cold
less. Because if you're talking about cursor engineering and to
the people who actually get cold at night, this is likely to land
as the best argument that you can use. If there is something
that can be done so that I don't have to wake up at night
and log in and context switch and try
to figure out what happened and get coffee. Anything I can
do to avoid that is great. So the selling point of curse engineering
for these people is just that you can do it during working hours.
The more we experiment and more we find things
that break during working hours. That means that you don't
have to be cold at night. So typically that lands really well. And this
is a very simple argument in favor of gas engineering.
But the more complicated conversation typically
is with your manager or someone who needs to okay doing something like that.
And this is the risk versus reward situation. So it
turns out that when you think about that, we tend to be pretty
terrible at estimating the risks and rewards
of things. And there's the entire evolutionary
history behind that. But if we don't put numbers on a napkin,
back of the napkin, we're probably going to make some bad
decisions if we just follow our instincts.
And to illustrate that, I would like you to think about how likely
you are to be in danger of a shark attack.
How likely are you to die of a shark attack?
How scared should you be? And if you ask a person in the streets,
chances are that they're going to overestimate that risk very,
very strongly. If my googling skills didn't fail me,
2020 has three fatal shark attacks in
the US, the country that tends to have most of them.
Whereas if you take a look at the actual things that kill people,
heart disease number one, takes about 650,000
people every year in the United States,
meaning that the likelihood of you dying from eating
hamburgers that look really good but are unhealthy
for you and increase your bad cholesterol is so much higher
than getting killed by a shark that it should really not
be difficult, one, to compare, but because of the fact that sharks
have this teeth and they look scary. And also,
there was a movie about them, or maybe two.
I'm looking at you, the meg. The fact that the
stats doesn't support your fear doesn't prevent
you from being scared of it, right? So next time
you look at that hamburger, think about it, because that hamburgers
is potentially much more dangerous to you than sharks.
But what does all of that have to do with chaos engineering. If you put
numbers together for the risks that are involved in
doing some of this curse engineering, and you do things like monitoring
the blast radius and minimizing the blast radius, and you do things
like making sure that you only apply the experiments to
a small subset of things, and you don't just rush into production and
you do things properly. The risks can be controlled,
can be managed, and they might be your shark
that you're scared of, whereas you should be scared of
that hamburger instead. So with these two conversations
and the myths and understanding the trends and kind of like interesting
crossroads moment for chaos engineering on the adoption curve
right now, we're finding ourselves in this very interesting point in
time when we can make the push and we can get
the curse engineering over that bump where it becomes boring
and it becomes a part of that landscape. If you would like to learn more
about curse engineering, I published a book about it last
year. It's called curse engineering. Site reliability through control
disruption. It's from money. It's a complement to existing
books where I try to bring a very, very practical approach
and cover all the tools that you might need and show you
and kind of demystify that using chaos engineering can
be fun, can be easy to start with. You don't necessarily need
very complicated or sophisticated tools. You can reuse
things that you already know and that all you need to do is change
a little bit your mindset and then use all those tools. So the book
is covering various different levels of your tech stack that you
might be exposed to. It's starting with, like I mentioned, a single
binary that you don't know what it's doing, apart from
the fact that you know it should be handing the errors, and you manipulate
system calls to verify that the retry logic works okay
through things like containers and how they break, how they work, what's actually
Linux containers, what's actually under the hood, how that works,
how to understand what happens when you hit the limitations of
Docker, how to implement your Liu container, and how to test applications
that run in containers all the way to Kubernetes,
and how to test Kubernetes itself. If you happen to be one of the people
who are responsible for a Kubernetes based platform, where you
need to make sure that it runs, how it's built under the
hood, how it breaks, what the fragile points are,
and also testing kubernetes, the software that runs on kubernetes,
to verify that the ongoing verification of things like
slas and various other things like working with JVM and injecting bytecode
to trigger exceptions to verify that the
behavior is the way that you expected, all the way up to JavaScript and
working with browser to verify that your uis that
get more and more complex and more and more fancy are actually behaving
the way that you want it. So there's a discount code that you can see
here. I think there's also going to be
some free copies if you want to grab some for the conference. And let
me know if you'd like to connect. This is LinkedIn.
If you scan this code, that should bring you to my profile.
Probably the best way to reach out to me the photo credits and
if you are interested in this kind of problems,
we are hiring at Bloomberg. Go to bloomberg.com careers
and reach out to us. And with that, thank you very much.
I'm really hoping that the 2021 will be the time when
we get the chaos engineering to be the boring part. We get
it over the hump of the adoption and it's going to be part of
everybody's framework, because there's really no reason to not
get all of that return on investment because it's
easy. So thank you very much. Have a great day at the conference, enjoy the
rest of it, and I'll speak to you soon.