You.
Hello and welcome to my video. I will make a simple multiplayer game
in this video using react and socket IO
before we begin, let's make a short brief we're going to implement
a battleship game. What is battleship
game? It's a game
for two participants in which player makes
turns, calling or otherwise communicating
the coordinates on the opponent map.
If the enemy has a ship on a viscord
generates ship or its deck killed and the
enemy makes another move a player's goal to be
first to kill all opponent's ship.
On the party enemies each player
has two field, on the first he can see
his own ship and on second opinion ship
each player wake their move and if a player
hits ship he can make another move until he missed.
Each field has ten to ten cells and each
each ship can be placed on vertical on horizontal
but ships can overlap and of
course ship should be hidden from the opponent.
I saw many variants rules for this game and in
our we're going to use next variation carrier
five cells x one battleship
four cell six two cruiser
free cells and free items and destroyer two cells
four items and
how is going b interaction with player
and server and opponent when
player check on board some
position it sends to server and
server ask the opponent about what happens on
this position open end make response
with status can
user make another move and new
board status and server makes some cache for it
and return results layer we
can have next cell statuses unknown
we don't know what happens on this board mist
if we strictly know what on this place where
are nothing killed if we have wrecked
on second ship and field for
access ship but status don't sell to open
end and he replaced us unknown if
we have that's all
on status and
let's make a little bit code I
have prepared some boilerplate for it. We have here
client folder,
server folder and shared folder for components
which will used on both sides and
yeah I know it can be as a normal package but I'm a
little bit lazy to create a normal package for
client we require install
also socket
I o client it
and for server we need to install
expressjs course and circuit
I o libraries and
I'm going to start with shared libraries and first
of all it's one side of library
named the buffer and it will be used in generate
it generate our
boardroom
create types file which
contains cell status and one variation
of ship and
tilts for calculation position
you it let's
create generate board file as
you can see very prepared because it
will be not to take so much
time your time function
generate board accepts ships list and board
sites which by default equal 100.
What happens? We sequently place each of ships
according the following principle.
We get random ship at
first of all we find all possible position for our ships and after
it we take one of them random and place
on board. For place on board we mark
all positions as missed. It will
be used for next iteration of place
on board and after we marked it
marked all we place our ship
on the board.
After we have placed all the ships we clear the game
board and at all we have
only field or unknown cells.
Next what we need is check our
board when sound will fire.
What happens to here? This function takes this
function takes current user
playboards and position what we need to position
what need to be checked and return boolean
and new board status.
If board position is unknown, we marked with a cell and
return false and new board if
this position is filled if
this position is filled is not empty when we begin to check status
of neighbor position and all direction from this
point if all of them killed
when we marked around ships
as missed and return new board status.
Next what we need to create is sunken ships.
What happens here?
The fatching text takes player current board and the return of
sulkan ships verification algorithm
is following. We go from
left to right through all position
and if position is marked skilled we
checked top and left
position and if equals one
as missed we check right
and bottom positions and
if our ship has neighborhood everywhere
missed, we mark this ship as sunken
and in the end we sort from big to
less.
Also we need to get move
ships that will be used for our AI
function really similar to previous but we
find no tank and ship and
we check all available position for next move.
Also we need to clear our
board. I moved it in functional
main principle of it.
If we have onboard field position we
replace it by zero and
we need to check what we
still have the fillet ships
you it's
okay. I think we finish with shared files
files and let's create our
backend. First of all we need
to create server.
Here's really easy and let's
start from make AI almost
forget expert
check file it.
Okay this is our eye. The main algorithm
is following. We generate random board when initialize
this status and when
make moves we get user boards and
five find rack chips and if we have some rack
chips we fire for zero place
otherwise we get random move get
random unknown cell and
make us move and also we
need to handle use requests for
hit we
need let's create game file which
represents main actions,
the main class of game and the main task of this
much simple he has
cached user boards well.
In the future it will be possible to create observer function so
what third party can watch the process and switch
active player depending on where answer.
Also we need to cache games
and create some observers
for socket IO you
it we
need to implement next event handlers
new game AI also
fire v seven will be sent by
user for check position and
catch result to
handle opponent's response to a check and for check
and in our case it will be response for either
request for position from user.
Let's make new
game AI we generate game id cache new
create new game and send to user
game created event. Next will
be fire event and
what happens here? At first of all we get current game
by game id and check
if current move user we
gave our AE position and for
check response and
send this result for place
new status in game class and send
result. Also if
we play in vfai we can from now
make some moves from AI and check
user's position and
catch result.
We also have game id and if current move game id
we pass our data to
AI and if AI
is filled with position is catched
with position he can make move again.
Oh we've backend that's all.
Let's make some little bit front end.
We have boilerplate from yjs.
Let's make some cleanup
it here.
What's our boilerplate also for gamer
we need next variables.
It's a sen it's opening boards,
user board and game id.
While it's neat sen it's current representation
of what we need to draw opening boards
for view. What happens on opening boards user boards it's
our board and game id will be set on one
of next moves.
Also we need to perform next events
from so it IO game
created fire result and catch game
created we give when game
is really created fire result we
have result of what we are fired and
catch if someone to
get know what missed here
or no and
let's create some components and
styles it
draw basic cell for our board. It can be
clickable if you have
special boolean variables and on click function
after it. We need to draw user's
board it it and
styles for it's
it's really simple function and
to be in fact it's just a wrapper for cells
and let's create some sense as
we know we have four sense first
of all sit up second game in
the game and we have finish win and finish
lose sense for our game
result. Let's create
setup.
Here is set up. On the left side we show users
board and on the right side we
have two buttons generate and radio.
User can see his generated board and if he likes
it he can press ready. If not he press
generate and makes new field.
When we have and
next stage is gameplay.
Here is game. On left side we
can see users board and on right side
our opinions board and
let's fill some.
Let's use some sense.
Also we need to create function on
click radio which set
up a user's board and send to our back end event
what we are ready to play and
on click board event which sent to backend users
ask position and
move handlers. First of all on game
created and here
is with set game id
and change send to game next
on fire result if
backend sends what game over. On website we
show send what user wins and return.
Otherwise we set up current opinions board which
will redraw and
on catch event what
happens on this file on this callback. At first of all
we check users board for current position and get result
and check if is game over and
make response with current data.
And if our board is
loose we show what we lose.
Otherwise update our board.
Let's check what happens.
McKenzie started on real
sport and
our front end started too.
Okay? Yes.
As we can see it's guinea
rattle board. We can press guinea rate and
it's change. When we press
radio we show two fields hour and opponents.
Let's play and check how. I'm lucky it's
not correct colors but
you can see what his answers and
backend kills one of my ships.
Mito and
I'm Vin.
Basically we made a little game. I understand what
many aspects are not covered. For example
normal multiplayer. But I think we're
starting small and purpose of this video is to inspire
you to create your own games. And what it's not difficult.
Also what react can be used not only for
forms from
what we can improve in the current game.
First of all, we can send some
hash of our board to prevent what someone
of players is cheating and changing his
field during game.
This happened next in the following way.
First of all, when we generate board we make some hash.
It can be MD five it's not so necessary
and send it to backend and his
story both hashes and in the end
game one of hashes not
equals. That means what someone cheat.
Also possible to
create AI based on some
statistics. For example, after a few games
AI can get some boards which
played and
calculate positions where most popular
position and start playing from them.
Yes, I think that's all. The source
of this game will be available on QR code
on screen. And thank you for watching,
waiting for your questions.