This is security implications of quantum
computing. A little bit of introduction
since we've got
it here. Let me see. I've got get the
chat and see if I can do that. No.
Okay. I'll have to pick it up.
Where are we here?
There we go.
Okay. There's the details
in the chat screen if you want
to do pick up those things.
But anyways, that's sort of the introduction
to a set of blog postings that I did some
years back. That was five years ago,
so that's got a little extra detail and
introduction to what this is doing,
because quantum computing. Well, quantum mechanics,
I think it was Niels Bohr who said that anybody who
thinks they understand it and their brain doesn't hurt, doesn't understand.
You know, quantum computing is really
interesting stuff. We definitely do not have
an awful lot of an idea of what it really
means, but in terms of not
to get into the quantum physics
and quantum mechanics stuff, but flowing
out of the basic concepts there,
we have the idea of the
qubit. Now, we have bits in computers.
We deal with bits. Quantum computers deal
with qubits. And a
bit is either a one or a zero.
A qubit can be one and zero
at the same time until
we determine what it's ultimately
going to be. The determination
is what goes into quantum programming.
This gets a little bit hairy because it can not only be
one and zero at the same time, but any value in
between in certain situations. So we
won't get into that right now. We'll just say that it can be one
and zero at the same time. What this allows us to
do with sufficiently many qubits is to
set up a situation where we can run
through all possible values at the same time and find out
which ones fit.
That's basically what we talk about.
We have all kinds of weird things about quantum mechanics
and quantum computing.
There's the observer effect.
Schrodinger's cat is both alive and dead at the same time,
and Schrodinger's phone, until you look, it's both
cracked and not cracked at the same time,
and stuff like that. But there's also an issue
called entanglement, and we're going to touch on that
slightly in one of these things in terms of networking.
But the entanglement of multiple qubits
is what gives us the opportunity to perform the
same function on a bunch of qubits. And again, as I say, sort of
find out which answer it is that actually fits with
one operation. And here's the bore quote that I has saying if
someone says that he can think or talk about quantum physics without becoming
dizzy, that shows only that he has not understood anything whatever
about it. So we'll do that.
Now, one of the aspects of quantum technology
with computers is that we
can have quantum
technology to aid
us in producing traditional computers.
So we're making chips and
elements on the chips smaller and faster, and we're getting
into the quantum size range, where there are quantum effects
in what we're doing with chips and traces,
and that sort of know
we need to address that.
There's also the fact that one
of the things that Turing figured out with his
ideas of computing, starting us all off here,
is that irreversible computations,
that's in traditional computers, they have
a sort of a minimum limit. We're reaching
the limits in terms of how much we
can reduce the power consumption with traditional computers.
But with quantum operations, we can do
reversible computations, and in
that case, you can make the power arbitrarily small.
Again, we can build a traditional computer with very
low power consumption if we're using
quantum technology properly.
There's quantum cryptography, and quantum
cryptography is a real thing, but it keeps on getting mixed
up with the idea of using quantum
computers for decryption, a sort of a universal
decryption. And people are saying, oh,
quantum computers are going to kill. Cryptography has. We know it,
and that is not the case, and we'll talk about that
in a second here. But quantum cryptography,
I do want to mention and disentangle it from
this quantum decryption thing. Quantum cryptography is
not cryptography. It is basically
just key exchange. And I have
a demo that we could do, but it takes half an hour, and we don't
have time tonight, so we won't do
that. But it is being used. I mean,
a bunch of swiss banks have been using it, and there
are a bunch of commercial enterprises that will sell this quantum
cryptography stuff, which, as I say, has nothing,
well, has to do with cryptography, but only in terms
of key exchange. And, I mean, basically, you need
dedicated, single mode fiber optic cable to
do this key exchange. And if you've got dedicated, single mode fiber optic
cable, why do you need cryptography, for crying out loud?
Anyways. But it is something that
is, unfortunately, in here
and gets mixed up with everything else.
It's real, but actually a lot more limited
than people.
It's very elegant. It's a really elegant
idea. It just doesn't work in the real world.
As I say, it's always implementation in
cryptography it's always the implementation
that gets attacked, and there's all kinds of implementation attacks
on quantum cryptography, unfortunately.
But quantum decryption, that's just hypothesized.
It's going to be a long time before we see it, and by that time,
we'll have decent quantum
computing proof algorithms for cryptography.
Anyways, the thing is, with quantum computing,
there's also, is it a real, true quantum computer?
And there are various
quantum computers,
fairly small. I think the largest of them is only barely
into the three orders of magnitude qubit
range, just over 100 qubits.
And that isn't enough to do an awful lot of really interesting
stuff. So those are only sort of test beds
for the moment. And then there's d wave over in Burnaby here.
And d wave has
got something, but it's more of a quantum,
um, it's like an analog mean, you know,
we know digital computers, but we have had analog know.
What are analog computers? Well, there's the spaghetti
computer, which does parallel sorting. You cut
pieces of spaghetti to the numbers that you want to sort,
and then in one application, bang, you sort them
all, and it's done. It's a special purpose.
It has a single application, but there it's very effective.
Same thing with the slide rule. We do exact computations, but it's
a little imprecise in terms of how we read it.
The D wave computer is an adiabatic
quantum computer. It looks for situation where
it gets the least energy and therefore the best answer,
least path, best comparison simulation.
So the D wave Orion machines,
they are not full quantum computers.
They have some very interesting capabilities,
but it is at best, sort of a quantum coprocessor.
That's the general idea. So having
provided some of that as a background, let's get
into specific applications
and what we can do with quantum computing in
terms of security. And I've
structured this by the domains of security
to give it a little bit of format
when we do it. But the general functions that we're going to be looking at
here are the same ones that the D wave
can do, and that is looking at least path calculations,
doing simulations, doing pattern matching,
and lease path problems.
The big example that people use
is the traveling salesman problem. And for example, there's like
28,000 cities and towns in Norway.
And the traveling salesman problem,
if you've only got two sites to visit, it's easier to see which
is the shortest path. It's just the shortest distance between two
points is a straight line, one straight line. But as you start adding
different places to go, then what's the
best path to get to all the places?
That's the traveling salesman problem.
And this is not something that can
be done easily with a traditional computer.
As I say, there's 28,000 towns in Norway.
They did the traveling salesman problem. I believe that
it took like ten or eleven years using
multiple network, high speed computers to actually do
this. Whereas you get a big
enough quantum computer, you can do it.
One operation type of thing,
simulation. There's all kinds of
things that we can run with simulation,
climate models, weather maps, those types of
things are a really good example.
The thing is that when you're doing weather and climate simulations,
you divide up the atmosphere into a whole bunch
of cells, and you do calculations on each cell. And then because
those calculations have changed the results in all of
those cells, then you have to go back and redo the calculations
based on the new information from the
surrounding cells. For every cell type of thing, it's over and
over again. There's an awful lot of cells, therefore, there's an awful
lot of processing, and it just takes a lot of time.
Again, with a quantum computer, you're able to do
this big enough quantum computer, you're able to do this sort of
one shot so you can get closer to
real time stuff and much more accurate, and therefore
longer range forecasts.
The other thing that we are really good at,
and traditional computers are not, is pattern recognition. Now, there's a
picture there of airplanes. Immediately you as
a person look at that, and without even fully
concentrating on it, you probably immediately think airplanes,
and then possibly even military airplanes and that sort of thing.
Whereas it would take a computer a long time to figure that out.
People are good at this. Computers are bad, but the
quantum computers are going to be much better at
recognition. That type of thing that we want
computers to be able to do is going to be much
easier with quantum
computers. So into
the domains of security and what we can do with them,
risk management. And again,
this is shortest path traveling salesman type
of problem, because when we're doing risk
management, the tools that we've got for risk management,
we put in all the data, collect all
the data on the risks, on the threats, the realities,
the impacts, and then the efficacy
of different types
of controls that we're going to put in place to
counter, to mitigate the risks.
Once we've collected all that data, we can then put it into
sort of a giant spreadsheet and we can start playing
around. What if we put a little bit of
more effort, more resources into this control and
reduce it in that, because, of course, you've always got a fixed security
budget.
Does this give us a better outcome? Does that trade off,
give us a better outcome? But we've got to do all the
shuffling of increasing
this and decreasing that and see
if it gives us a better result. Now,
what the quantum computers, and again, once we get big
enough ones, will allow us to do is collect all that data,
put it in, and the quantum computer will be
able to do the least energy, shortest path type analysis
and tell us what's the optimum arrangement,
the optimum configuration, the most efficient, the most
effective, the most cost effective,
greatest benefit for the
fixed cost, for our
various controls, for all the different risks that we
have. So again, it'll sort of be a one shot
bang and you get your answer type of thing, which right
now is just not possible.
Information classification, pattern matching is going to
help us there. The pattern matching capabilities of quantum computers.
Risk assessment is not
something that people look forward to, like we said, in the risk
management area, but we're going to have to do
some thought here.
Is it going to be worth investing or not in quantum computing?
And again, figuring out
what it can do for us and what the benefits are is
going to be part of that decision as to whether or not we're going to
get into the field of quantum computing for those benefits.
In terms of security architecture, the news here is
probably all bad. This is going to give us
new architectures. It's going to be much more complex.
It's going to introduce new vulnerabilities, just a
whole bunch of work that we need to do in regard to that,
simply because somebody might want to put a quantum
computer into our company. But it does
give us simulation of vulnerabilities and protections,
allowing us to sort of test out whether
or not given protections or safeguards are
going to help us in certain
situations.
Quantum devices are going
to, they are subject,
quite subject, unfortunately, to issues
of noise. And that is going
to be something that we're going to have to look at and address
in a variety of different ways.
Right now, the d wave they've
tried to reduce noise has much as possible, but basically
what they do with their systems
is just sort of vote run multiple times and
see if they get the same answer multiple times.
There are new technologies in terms of quantum
error correction, again, going back to
the issue of entanglement, and that
may give us some promise in terms of fault tolerant
computing. So it's an area to be addressed
there in the field of access control
biometrics,
really, in terms of biometrics. Up until this point,
we're using just interesting forms of data representation,
but we're losing an awful lot of the data.
That has implications
for our error rates for false positives
and false negatives. In terms of biometrics.
The pattern matching capability of quantum
computing is going to allow us
more freedom there and more ability to say,
well, yeah, that sure looks like it's
Verne's login or
face or fingerprints or whatever it is,
even though it's not quite so,
that pattern matching capability is probably going
to assist us there in
terms of both the lease path and the simulation capabilities.
Information flow, which is
very time consuming right now, and covert channel analysis,
which again is something that's hard to figure out,
is probably much more possible with
quantum computers. And again, in intrusion detection,
we've got our intrusion detection systems. The pattern
matching capabilities is probably going
to make those a lot more effective.
So cryptography now has, I say
we've got all the things about the
quantum computing, which really is only the
key negotiation, key exchange.
It's the BB 84 protocol.
It's tremendously elegant,
wonderful. It is able to detect
eavesdropping for the first time. All of that
is in terms of the theory, but in
terms of the implementation, there's just been all kinds of ways to attack that.
Unfortunately,
the issue of being able to do sort
of parallel decryption all in one step, do brute
force attacks that just drop the right key out of
the system.
That is limited to the shore algorithm
and others that may use mod functions.
Right now, it's basically RSA
is susceptible to that. And there
are new algorithms that are being pursued to
make sure that they
have a high work factor, both when you're doing classical
types of crypt analysis and the quantum crypt analysis as
well.
One of the really important things in cryptography,
of course, is randomness. And quantum
computers actually can help us there.
On the one hand, because they are so subject to noise,
we can just use the noise as a
source of randomness. But there's also,
for the first know, John said that anybody
who thinks of arithmetic methods of generating
randomness is in a state of sin. But the thing is that there
are things we can do with quantum devices that
can give us genuinely random answers and in
a sense, tunably random. We can take something that has
a random output and sort of
tweak the bias on it. So if we've got another system that is generating random
stuff, but it has a bit of a bias, we can tweak the bias in
the other direction and sort of use these two
together and come up
with a balanced source of random data.
Again, cryptography desperately needs random data all
the time.
Analysis of the implementation problems. Like I say,
you always attack cryptography in implementation,
and quantum computing simulations will
probably be able to help us to identify those issues
in physical. This is really interesting.
Again, the noise, radio frequency interference,
electromagnetic interference,
all of that stuff is a problem and needs to be
addressed. But the big one, possibly, depending on
which technology eventually gets used in
this regard, is temperature. The Orion computer,
well, it's running at super cold
temperatures. Room temperature is
100 times as hot as
interstellar space. But when
the Orion computer is operating,
interstellar space is 1000 times as
hot as the central core of the Orion device.
That's how cold we have to get for some of these operations.
That has implications.
We have to keep the power considerations
in some of the technologies to
create qubits for quantum computing.
If you lose power, you just lose
whatever process you're working on right now.
You actually lose your cpu because you've
got lattices of photons or
electrons bouncing around in channels, in laser guides
and things like that.
It's a nontrivial task sometimes to keep these things
power, heat and cooling.
All of these issues are going to have
to be addressed for operating quantum computing.
So there's going to be special costs, there's going to be special protections
for devices, and you're
probably going to want to deal with physical access control.
Who's going to get access to this business
impact analysis?
I've got to admit,
sorry, business impact analysis and business continuity
planning. Disaster recovery planning. This is close to my heart because,
of course, of all my work in emergency management and
doing a business impact analysis, what's most crucial,
what's your most crucial, what are your
various critical business units and systems
and that sort of thing? The least path analysis part
of quantum computing
capabilities is definitely going to assist us there.
The simulation part will very much
help us with the testing of business continuity plans
and whether or not they're effective, whether or not we've missed anything
out.
But what
really is interesting to me is the disaster management,
again, like the risk management in a
disaster, you want to direct resources to maximum
effect and that it saves lives,
it helps
people to,
well, it reduces the suffering.
So there's all kinds of really good stuff that can happen if
you do proper management in the middle of a disaster.
And like I said,
the risk management that
can be done, that has to be done.
The calculations are very complex
and generally take time to perform with
a traditional computer because there's so many different moving parts.
Well, when you've got a simulation situation,
you're able to do those calculations in real time. So while
the hurricane is going on and when it
hits land 20 miles away from where you thought it was going to
hit land, you've got a whole bunch of things
that are in the wrong place. But with quantum computing,
you can correct that very quickly and
also address issues of what do we
do to move those resources,
to redirect those resources to where
they are going to be most needed as
soon as possible. Again,
the continuity of operations for these special
devices is definitely going to be an issue.
Talking about the power, talking about the cooling, what is
going to happen if there's failures there?
Now, in terms of application security
testing of our increasingly complex applications
is a nontrivial task and one where quantum computing
will definitely be able to assist us and give us
better information.
Database analysis, again, the pattern matching capabilities
will help us. And looking, as I
talked about, in terms of the differential privacy, the cost of
privacy versus the benefit of safety and
some of those calculations,
database aggregation, problem analysis,
and again, the privacy
budget, privacy accounting calculations that
differential privacy is meant
to address, um, will, you know, they're going to be very
complex. And, and so quantum computers are probably going
to be an area that will assist us in there
learning artificial intelligence, machine learning,
the pattern matching capabilities of quantum
computing are probably going to be very
useful, give us new insights in there. And the
thing is that right now,
when we're trying to check the output of
a neural network, say, or of genetic computing
operation,
because those are systems
that are going beyond what traditional computers are capable
of, how do we have a check on what they're
doing? Well, quantum computing
gives us those same capabilities coming at it
from a different. So again,
as with the voting in the Orion systems, probably running
a neural net, running a quantum computing assessment,
and seeing whether or not they agree is
at least a first attempt at trying to
check some of these things that
we want to know about.
Again, as I say, we traditionally
say check the output against what you expected.
Well, with a lot of these artificial intelligence things,
what did we expect? The reason that we're doing them
is because we wanted to get results that
we didn't expect.
But when we get quantum computing in
there and start looking at those results,
how are we going to check them? You know, those things are, are things
that we're going to be impossible to compute by classical methods.
And so how are we going to test whether
or not this is actually working,
malware, botnet decryption, as per the
intrusion detection, the pattern matching capabilities is
going to allow us better
analysis there. Also in
terms of both malware looking
at what family does this come from and
therefore tying it back to what group, what possibly even the
individual is the person who wrote this.
But certainly in terms of botnets out
on the Internet looking at the control and ownership
of these large networks,
it's a nontrivial task and quantum computers can
help us there. There are
going to be completely new paradigms in programming
here. It's already hard for some of us old dinosaurs
to. We're stuck in
the procedural days. I've done a little bit of functional programming
and that can turn your head, certainly object oriented.
I think object oriented programming is basically lying to
you because I want to know who's going to
show me an object oriented cpu.
It doesn't work, or rather it
seems to work, but sort of how, it's kind
of a trick. But anyways, what quantum computing,
they're really going to change our outlook in terms of how
we think about programming. How do we make
sure that they work? Just being able to write a
hello program is not going to mean
that you understand how
quantum computers actually do operate.
So in terms of security, we are going to have limitations
of classical and quantum devices and operations to
increase the complexity of our systems that are already very
complex. So the
complexity there is going to create problems for us. On the
other hand, quantum computers
with simulation, with the
pattern matching will probably provide
tools for us for troubleshooting,
which is a good thing because we will have to be troubleshooting
where the problem lies in a system which contains both
quantum and classical computers.
So again,
it's not going to be an easy thing to do.
Insider attacks pattern matching capabilities of
quantum computing may give us some
tools for insider attack detection.
That has been a very intractable problem.
It's always been an issue and it's not easy to
figure out who's going to deal
with it. So it's
an interesting situation and
maybe we will get a tool that can help us there.
Telecommunications and networking. Again, we've mentioned
intrusion detection systems and the capabilities there,
botnet detection and assessment and looking at the command and control, the ownership,
particularly for fast flux systems, network attack
analysis, all of these things are issues
where the tools that quantum computers give us can help.
We're coming to the limitations of our
spam detection, even with bayesian analysis.
Certainly a number of the systems that I work
with regularly,
it seems to be a problem. And the pattern matching
capabilities that go along with quantum
computing are probably areas where
we'll get new spam decryption tools
in there. Quantum encryption
requires special channels, the quantum cryptography. Quantum devices,
though, are likely to be remote access for
the foreseeable future.
We're going to start out with centralized systems with
sort of like timesharing capabilities that
you can sign on, you can get something
from, pay rent for time
on the computer. So it's going to be remote access. And again,
dealing with telecommunications and networking
for these situations, particularly as we're
doing some computations with a quantum computer and
some with classical, there's going to be data flying back and forth, and we
need to protect that and
perform authentication on who's available to do it.
Interesting communications channels.
The quantum entities
that we use for transmission can
provide for more than one bit per photon.
For example, one test sent enough data for
a small graphic image. I think it was around 128 bits in
one photon. So there's also,
as I say, the possibility of continuously variable
entities. So we have an analog
photon, which is really kind of bizarre because the
whole point of quantum computing was that it was defining
stepwise states in
entities. So being able
to send something in an analog situation is
kind of mind blowing. Quantum networks,
this is something that I came across recently.
I'm not sure about this.
I mean, they made it work and that sort of thing, but it's
probably going to be more local
connections in terms of distributed quantum computing
rather than large scale networking,
at least for the immediate future.
So that's going to be an interesting field of
research and law and investigation.
We're going to have new forensic analysis tools. The pattern matching
and simulation there could be very helpful. But the presentation
and acceptance in court, as per the earlier discussion
on presenting technical evidence in court, is definitely going to be
problematic. So we're going
to have to deal with that. And we managed to
get through all the slides.