What if you could work with some of the world's most innovative companies,
all from the comfort of a remote workplace? Andela has matched
thousands of technologists across the globe to their next career
adventure. We're empowering new talent worldwide,
from Sao Paulo to Egypt and Lagos to Warsaw.
Now the future of work is yours to create.
Anytime, anywhere. The world is at your fingertips.
This is Andela,
everyone. It's wonderful to be participating in this conference
in 2022. My name is Agnes Muthoni,
and I head up partnerships here at Andela. Let me first
start off by describing Andela's model and the
journey we've embarked on to bring the future
of work to life. Andela is a global talent
marketplace that helps companies build remote
engineering teams faster. We help companies like
GitHub, Goldman Sachs and Cloudfair connect
with vetted remote engineers across
different markets. This enables our clients to scale
their engineering teams quickly and build amazing products.
What's important to note is that this has been a
journey. The way the world works is changing,
and Andela's vision of the future of work from when we
were founded is now a more obvious reality.
We've always seen this global remote workforce and have
been working towards it since we launched our very first remote
regions in Egypt and Ghana. Now the rest of the world
is seeing the impact of Andela for both companies
and engineers across the world. At Andela,
we believed in this idea of leveling the playing field for
clients to hire brilliant and amazing talent regardless of
location, and similarly give talent the option
to choose exciting and challenging opportunities
with global companies. And the world is now ready
for this. And we are seeing more companies embrace this growing global
trend and the work Andela has done to bring the future of work
to life. Now, let me talk about
our talent network. When we started
out this mission to connect brilliance with opportunity
by finding great talent in emerging markets,
then expanding into other regions. Our focus is
centered on helping our clients find experienced
software engineers who can deliver against our clients
product roadmap. And the way we do this is through
sourcing for talent, screening them,
onboarding the talent onto our talent network,
matching them against specific client requirements,
and placing them on partner engagements once they
have met the specific criteria and requirements from the client.
Over time, we've built market expertise in bringing
great talent through screening and assessments
and screening over hundreds of thousands of applications
using our data driven process.
As a result, and through our expansion efforts, we now have engineers
who have joined our network, coming in
from more than 90 countries, six continents,
with 175,000 technologists in our community
and a successful placement rate of
96%. Now if you're listening to
me and you are a software engineer,
you may have a question. And one of the questions that you may have is
why join Andela? Well, let me tell you why.
We've spent time clearly listening and understanding our
clients'needs and working hard to meet
those needs. Our advantage as a talent network
are the long term opportunities available,
the global talent community where engineers can
connect with other brilliant engineers across the globe.
We also offer career coaching,
educational advancement and flexibility.
Remote first is changing the way we work and opening
up opportunities for developers in emerging markets
to enter the global talent marketplace.
This phenomena of being able to work from anywhere has become a
more obvious reality that has been cultivated
forward over the last couple of years.
In our recent developer report, what we did find is that
more thats 80% of developing are
keen and are excited about the idea of wanting to
work remote. Now let me share a couple of benefits.
So the first benefit is it gives more people more flexibility
with where they choose to work and live, thus enabling
developers to have more work life harmony. The second
benefit as a software engineer or experienced
talent, you get to connect with global opportunities and
it opens up borderless opportunities, creating new and exciting
opportunities on the global stage. In a most
recent survey, what we did find is that 74%
of all Andela engineers had a quality of life improvement.
65% of them said that they're better able
to save and 81% cited
with longer than one year of tenure did cite an increase
in take home pay. Diversity and inclusion was cited
as a key priority by many corporate leaders
and through our expansion plans we help companies
build and grow more diverse. Thats as
we continue to advance our mission forward of connects
brilliance with opportunity the Andela Learning community has
been able to support thousands of engineers go
through learning journeys that help them grow in their careers.
The learning community offers access to in demand
technology courses through education partners like Google,
Microsoft, Facebook and Salesforce, as well as
it connects engineers with job boards
and opportunities for them to be
able to grow in their career.
As a company, we have been working towards the future of
work and now I'm just excited that the world is ready for
it. Thank you.