Hello and welcome everyone. My name is Barkatul Mujauddin
and I'm excited to be here today to talk about API
testing made easy. I hope you are all having a great day so far
and are looking forward to learning something new. Thank you for taking the
time me to join me today. So here's a quick introduction.
About me I am a developer relation intern at Keploy. I am
a GSOC 2023 mentor this year only and
I am also the founder of a community called Hack for Code.
I am also a kubesimplifier ambassador which I'm really proud of.
I believe that there are many problems
in developers job and the root of maximum problems are
strict timelines. Let me tell you how with an example.
Yes, you guessed it right, the example is related to
API testing. So here's a situation. Due to a strict
timeline, we may have limited time to perform testing
which can lead to regressions. Right? Again, this is
a problem. So as we all know, for every
problem there is a solution. All we need to reduce
the bugs are just three things. Number one, we need
to do the functional testing. We need a tool that
could create the test cases and update the test cases easily
for us so that we don't have to really write the
test cases and spend time on it. We need something that could automatically
orchestrate the testing infrastructure. So that's
all we need. Now let's look
at what if we can record the
traffic from production and we can replay it in a
non production environment. I know this is kind of something overwhelming
and out of context, so let me explain it to you.
So here's the thing. Think it in this way.
This is an application serving the user traffic. Let's say application v one.
And first we captured the user traffic from
production. Then we replayed it after setting up
the shadow database of the snapshot database. And then we
need to write to compare the responses. Obviously this requires
a huge operational effort because we first write to record,
then we need to set up those snapshot database which are expensive,
and then we need to update these snapshots timely.
And then we need to write to compare the responses as well.
So it is a pretty wise strategy,
but it's expensive and it's included a lot of
effort so far in
this approach. The record and replay approach.
Let's discuss some of the pros and cons we are
discussing about the pros. The first one is it is a low code
approach and you don't really have to write the test cases.
It is easy to achieve high coverage because you
are capturing the user traffic, so there are multiple
flows that you are capturing and will be able to replay,
which increases the coverage of the code base that
your application or your API test are going through.
The third one is sometimes there are unexpected user flows that
you discover just via the real user traffic that
the developer never did code for, but they discovered
it from the real world. If we are
discussing about the cons, then the first cons
are the dependency states are hard to manage.
This approach is good for load testing or stress testing,
but not suitable for functional testing because if
some of the APIs fail, there are multiple user traffic
calls that fail and you have to go to each of
the call and debug it. So that takes a lot of
effort and a lot of time to debug and it
causes a lot of frustration as well. The third cons are
handling writes is always tricky in this approach.
So let's come back. We were doing a record keploy
via snapshot database from a production environment to
a non production environment. So let's think it in this way.
If you are capturing and replaying the API request and response,
how about we also do the same for the database
queries? So what if we
create a virtual database which is just the database
query request and response and not a complete database?
I'll show you a deep dive with an example later in this talk. But in
this approach also, there are some downsides.
Like you have to add support
for each of the dependencies, right, that your application is talking
to. For example, if your application is talking to MongoDB,
then you need to add support mocks the MongoDB queries
or to capture
and replay that. This becomes brittle in case your API
schema completely changes and you have to rerecord
the user traffic and replay it. So these are
the downsides. But the upsides are the
complete database did not need to be replicated
to some other environment, or neither. It is expensive because
we were storing just the query data.
So what we just discussed, we are going to
basically virtualize that. So to
give an example, let's say in an application,
if we request an API with a particular user,
it returns what sports that particular user plays.
So the user has Thompson and we got the response as
cricket, volleyball, karam and boxing.
So in this case we have the application talking
to MongoDB, which has all of the relevant data.
Typically if I am going to record replay into
a different environment, I would capture
the request, run it again in my test environment,
and this time maybe user Thompson isn't there.
What I mean to say is it's not the same state.
So the problem is how do we ensure
that the exact state is consistent
with the test case that we captured.
Now in the same example,
if once we do dependency mocking, we can instead
of maintaining the test database, we instead
kind of maintain a mock. So when we
capture the Getgame request, we capture the queries
and the response that we got from MongoDB and just
package it along the test case. So now
when the same thing happens while we are
testing, we can just return the same response that
we got for the particular request. So it's basically mocking,
but actually kind of replaying that exact database
response that we captured and then of course
things will be consistent.
So as of now, we have
discussed the problems we were facing right now as a
developer and how record, replay and dependency approach can solve
these problems. So what
basically Kipployoy does is keploy converts your API cases
to test cases automatically.
All you just need to integrate keploy in your application and
it automatically mocks external dependencies for you.
It also detects the noise and accurately reduce it
automatically. All of these three can be done by keploy
easily. How? Let me show you a demo.
Let me show you a demo of how keploy can
generate test cases as well as data mocks for your backend
application. So in the demo I will take
a Javasample application which is an employee management application
and it does a crude operation on employee. So this
is the main repository of keploy where the server lies. You can just
simply install it. Now I'm going to follow the samples Java repository.
So I have already installed keploy server and I'm
going to start it. And I have also cloned the sample Java application
here. Now to integrate the Keploy Java SDK with
my application I need to follow certain steps.
First I need to add the keploy dependency. So I have added
it here. Then I need to also import
the keploy middleware with my main class. I have done that here and
I also need to have the agent jar. So how
you can go to it is to going to maven central
download the latest version of this agent jar and
put it in the main directory of your application.
Now the last thing I need to do is to set up this agent.
I have just added the vm
options as Java agent and then gave the absolute path to
this agent jar. And I have now added
the environment variable which is keploy
mode record because I'm going to make
API cases and record
the test cases. And denoise is true, it just means that
it is going to ignore all the random fields like timestamps or random
numbers which are going to change in every API call. Now let's go
ahead and run our postcase instance first.
So I'm just going to run the postgres instance.
It is running now and I'm going to start the sample application.
Now let's just go ahead and make an API call.
So I have this post API call which adds an
employee record. Now here are the test cases and mocks
generated. Yeah,
so in the test case I have the request and
response header and also I have the mocks for the Postgres
instance. Now let's make another API call
to get the user that we put on employee id one and there
was another test case generated. The interesting part is that since Postgres
is a SQL based database, it captured this whole
query and you can generate the test cases and mock file mock
like that. Now let's go ahead and simply run the
test cases that we captured. So first we need to set the environment
variable of keploy mode to test.
Yeah, now let's run the sample
Java application. Yeah, you can see on the keploy
server that both the test case is run and passed.
Yeah. Now let's introduce
an error. Let's say we have a field named changed which
is being queried. So instead of first name it will query
name from the postgres instance. Now let's stop the postgres instance.
Even without the postgres it is going to run because we
already have the mocks. So we didn't need postgres.
So yeah, it has run and one test case is passed and one failed.
Let's go into detail. So it is why? Because the
first name is now different. It was not able to query
the name parameter that we changed and thus the first
name was null. So this is how you can capture
the test cases quickly, run those and achieve
good line coverage with keploy. I hope you have understood
how keploy works.
So I hope I made it clear how you can integrate
keploy in your application and how it
works, how it can generate test cases and data mocks for
you automatically. So thank you and that's basically about it.
And you can also find us on GitHub and
if you want you can star us. Also, we don't mind and
feel free to join our slack channel. We would love to have all of you
in our community. And thanks
again and thanks for joining today.
And feel free to reach to me if you have any
questions. Till then,