Jamaica real
time feedback into the behavior of your distributed systems
and observing changes exceptions errors in
real time allows you to not only experiment with confidence,
but respond instantly to get things working again.
Clone hey
everyone, Andy Knight here, automation panda and developer advocate at applitools.
Today I'm going to show you how to run visual tests for your storybook
components across different browsers. And you won't even need
to write a single line of new test code. Let's learn
here. I have a small react app that I developers myself using a
storybook component library. I have it running on my
local machine.
All the different things you see on this app are components which
are small, reusable places of the UI.
Here I have three examples of components used to build this app,
a button, a text input field, and even the
scroll button I just clicked. Components are richer
than plain old web elements. A web element
is simply an entity declared by an HTML tag.
A component, however, is a unit of UI.
Components are made up of elements. Small components may
be a single element with some CSS styling,
but larger components like headers and sidebars may use
multiple elements in order
to make consistent designs. Web developers create component libraries
so they can reuse components anywhere in these app without duplicating
code or breaking their uniformity.
For example, let's say you want all buttons in your app to be round
and blue like this one. You could define a component
for could blue buttons and use that component everywhere
instead of explicitly setting every individual button to be
round and blue. Tools like storybook
enable developers to build and maintain libraries of reusable components
like this.
Components, just like any other pieces of code, can change as part of
software development. Some changes are intentional, but others
are not. What happens if that round blue button
becomes rectangular? Or what happens if
it turns red? Is that good or bad?
Will anyone even notice?
Some changes are obvious. For example, if the button accidentally
becomes enormous due to a CSS typo,
everyone would notice. Not all changes might be this
obvious, though. Think about could buttons turning rectangular?
Subtle changes can be easy to overlook.
We need a way to visually inspect components. If we
could compare a good baseline image side by side
with the latest checkpoint image these we could easily see
any differences. App tools eyes does this automatically
for storybook components. It captures snapshots for each story
and uses visual AI for comparisons. In fact,
you don't even need to create any test cases or write any automated
code. The applitools Eyes Storybook SDK
automatically creates tests for each story it finds.
We could do this testing manually using the storybook viewer, but we would
probably miss things. Manual inspection would
be difficult to scale with a large component library.
It's also a hassle to do cross browser testing for these components.
You need to reopen the storybook viewer in different browsers
and grind through all the stories again and again.
So let's see how to automate visual tests for storybook components
using Appletool's eyes. I'll show you the storybook component
library behind this app, and then I'll show you how to configure
that project for visual testing. We'll run a few tests
together and see how they appear in the applitools dashboard.
Let's go. So here
is the storybook component library for
that react app we just saw. I have it opened
in the storybook viewer in my browser. As you can
see in the left sidebar, there are four components
for this library,
the button, these header,
these scroll button, and the text input.
Now, some of these components, such as the button, actually have multiple
variations or stories for them. Here we
can see the enormous button. We also have a
large button, primary color,
a rectangular button, and a secondary color.
We can also use the different controls to view
what the buttons would look like under different conditions.
So here I can toggle the rectangular button between
the primary and secondary colors.
It's nice to come in here and manually test out our components as
we're developing them. But keep in mind,
as our component library grows, we're going to have more
and more things to manually test. And so
manual testing isn't going to keep up with the scale of
most large web app projects. It'll be
much, much better to have our visual testing automated.
So here is the source code for that react
app. I have the project open in vs code under
source. You can see all of the
stories for the different components in our
library, as well as the app's main page and
all that other react stuff if
we want to add applitools eyes Storybook SDK to this
project. Thankfully, we don't need to muck around too
much with code. One thing we need to do is we'll
need to add the Applitools
Eyes storybook package to
the project. Now, I've already done that, so you'll see it here in package
JSOn. But if you wanted to install it into your
own project, it's as simple as NPM install
and then the name of that package.
And you can do that for any project that has a storybook component
library, whether that's react angular view
doesn't matter. Now the
other thing I need to add to my project is a config file,
and that's here at the root project directory level.
Appletools config js.
Inside of this put a module exports
objects, and add the following settings. First, you'll want
to set a concurrency setting that will dictate how many
parallel visual tests can run in the
app tools Ultrafast test cloud. Note that if
you're using an app tools free account, you'll be limited
to one level of concurrency.
Secondly, you'll have the batch name, which refers to the
collection of tests that you will be launching at one time.
So that way when you go to the app tools dashboard, you can see a
helpful name for all the tests you have. I'm going to call this
visually testing storybook components.
The only other thing you need to do this kind of testing
is an Appletools account. You can go to appletools.com slash
register and sign up for a free account. Just to get started
with your account. You'll get something called an API key,
and you'll need to set that API key as an environment variable
like this applitools
API key equals and just paste whatever that key
is. Now I'm going to keep mine secret because I don't want
you running tests on my account.
With those few things set up, it's time to run some visual
tests. So from your project directory,
run the visual tests using the following command,
NPx eyes storybook,
and you'll also need to give it the static directory of
files, in my case, the public directory using the
S option and let's run it.
What this will do is it will start up storybook and
the eyes SDK will look for all of these stories inside
of it.
Then it will perform the visual testing on each story it finds.
So in our library we had four components, but it had a total of
nine stories.
Once all those stories are found,
it will run the visual tests in the ultrafast
test grid and it will upload the results.
Here you can see a spill out for all of those results.
There are those five stories for the
button, each one with its name tests on chrome under
the default viewport. We also had those two header, one scroll button,
and one text input. And notice how all these were reported as
new. New means it's establishing new baseline snapshots for
each of these stories, and you can go to the
applitools eyes SDK to see these results. All you got
to do is click this link.
When we visit the applitools dashboard. We can see that our batch
of tests for visually testing storybook components has been uploaded
to the dashboard. And in here,
we have all nine of those new snapshots.
So it's taking those baselines that we'll say are good,
and we'll use those for future comparisons.
You could even open them up to see what the baselines look like.
For example, here's the baseline for the header.
All good. Let's try running
these tests again to see what happens when we take our first checkpoint.
So back in our terminal in vs code,
let's run the same test again with no changes to
anything.
Again, same thing happens, starts up storybook,
identifies all the stories and will perform the visual testing
on each of the nine stories it finds.
And it does it pretty quick, thankfully. All right,
so again, we have those nine test results, and now
instead of saying new, each one is saying passed.
Let's go look at those results in the dashboard again.
Now, when we go to the app tools dashboard, we see
that second round of tests having been uploaded,
and they're all reporting as passed. They're not new anymore because we had baselines
before they're passed, because applitools compared
the checkpoint images to the baseline images. If we open
them up, for example, like with the header here, we can visually
compare the baseline with the checkpoint side by side.
And upon visual inspection, it's obvious nothing has change.
Therefore, all of these are good, and applitools marked them all as passed.
Now, let's run our tests a third time. But first,
let's introduce a visual change and see how Appletool's
eyes identifies it.
So let's turn our nice blue button
into a red button. If we go into our stories
and we go into button CSS, we can
see all the css for styling those buttons.
Let's tweak the class for the primary
color instead of blue.
Let's make it red.
Nice flaming hot red. All right,
let's save that. Let's run the tests again.
Uhoh, what happened?
So we can see that there's a little x by our nine of nine stories.
And when we see the printout of the results, seven of the tests
have passed, but two are marked as unresolved.
Let's take a look in the dashboard.
So here in the dashboard, we can see our latest catch had two unresolved
test pages. Now, unresolved means that app tools
has identified a visual difference, and it needs
you as the human to come in and determine if that's good or bad.
Remember, some visual changes can be okay if they were deliberately
intended by the developer, but others may be bugs
that happen accidentally or unexpectedly.
So let's take a look in one
of these. So here we have the visual snapshots
for the primary button and if we open them when we
compare side by side we can see there's a clear visual difference.
The one on the left, the baseline is blue. These these one on the right
is red. And Apple tool's eyes also highlights the
differences for you in purple. So here
we can say if this is good or bad.
If it's good we can give it a thumbs up. And these, the latest checkpoint
becomes the new baseline image against
which future checkpoints will be compared. Or we could say
this is a bug. And so at that point we would give a
thumbs down and then the original baseline is
kept and this one is seen as a failure.
Let's say that these change was deliberate and expected and good.
I'll mark it with these thumbs up and
then what the app tools dashboard will do is it'll take you to
the next unresolved test. And so here again we can see
the differences in the component. This time we're looking at the header
and Appletool's eyes narrowed in on the sign up button on
the right being the only thing that change. All the other stuff in
the header was the same so nothing was highlighted again.
Since this is a good change, we'll say thumbs up and
boom. Now our catch results
have been updated. Anytime you save new baselines like
that, remember to save your results.
And now things will be good. And we have new baseline images
for those tests.
Let's make another change. This time I want to tweak the
header. So let's go to our header
JSX file and I want to
do a couple of things here. First of all,
I want to change the title text in
the header. Rather than saying visually testing storybook components,
let's change it to something else so we
can see a text based change here.
Also I want to tweak the layout. So if
I go to header CSS,
notice here in the wrapper, this controls how
that layout of left and right with the buttons go. I'm going
to be devious. Pretend I accidentally deleted
justify content. All right,
clearly this is going to mess up the visuals. So let's run the tests again
and see what happens.
Uhoh, bump, bump. But again, two of
our tests are unresolved this time both of these the
header component. That's to be expected given the change we
made. Let's hop over to the dashboard to inspect.
The latest batch has those two unresolved test cases.
So let's take a look at them. I'll open
one. Let's see what's different. Wow.
Pretty much everything. So we can see that not only was
the title change, but the buttons were changed.
So on the original, the title was on the left and the
buttons were on the right. In the latest checkpoint,
the title text is different and the buttons no longer
appear on the right, but are smashed all the way to the left, right next
to the title.
We can actually inspect these changes more deeply if
we go to preview match level. We'll notice that right
now it is on the strict matching level.
Strict means app tools eyes is going to look for differences that
a human eye would notice. This includes things
like content, layout and all the above.
But we can change the filter to look at different things. Let's try
a matching level of content.
What the content does is it looks to see what has changed
in terms of the content. Not so much these layout
content looking at colors as well as text.
And so we can see here, because we changed all those things,
it's still highlighting everything.
But if I changed it to layout,
meaning don't look at tests, only look at
the things that have shifted in layout,
then we see a much different picture here.
The thing that app tools eyes denotes as being different in layout are
the buttons themselves, right? The text
visually testing storybook components versus mycool site is
ignored by app tools eyes. And this can be helpful
because sometimes it doesn't matter what these text is in a
particular layout or field or
grid or whatever you're doing. Maybe it's
just these shifting of elements that you're looking for. So you
can use these to help determine if this is a
good or bad new checkpoint. For me, though,
I do care about both layout and content, so I want to keep
it on the strict comparison. And to me,
the shifting of the buttons is a pretty bad thing. I would
see that as a visual bug. So in this case, I'm going to
give thumbs down for a failure.
We can see in the other story of this component,
there's only one button instead of two, but still it's been shifted and
I don't like that. So I'm going to thumbs down that as well.
Now we can see we have failed results because things were not equal.
If I save, that will become saved. And so anytime
that type of failure happens again, it'll automatically be logged as failed.
What we should do now is we should go back to the code and update
it to make sure that things will pass again.
Let's do that.
And bam. So what I did real quick is I went behind the scenes
and I undid the changes and rerun the tests and now we can see
everything is back to passing. If I look at those specific
header comparisons, we can see boom.
Boom. Our baseline was unchanged. Our checkpoint
is fixed now. So that's how we can use
visual testing to spot bad changes and then use that feedback to
quickly make the improvements and fixes,
rerun our tests and set everything back to being good.
So far, all these testing we've done has been on Google Chrome.
But with the Apple tools ultrafast grid, we could test
our components against any browsers that we want.
The advantage of doing cross browser testing is that we can render
all of those snapshots under different configurations and detect
if there's any weird differences between them. For example,
maybe there's some weird thing with
IE or safari that doesn't render our button
as appropriately as we would want. And we want to find that. But before
our users do another nice thing with cross browser testing for
components is that if we have larger
components, they may have some aspects of responsive
design. So we want to make sure that those bigger components are
rendered properly and all their elements appear appropriately,
which in isolation is really nice because we can catch that
before it spreads out to other pages. Thankfully,
the app tools eyes SDK for storybook makes cross browser testing
a breeze. All we have to do is update our app tools config
js and in here you can see I've
added this browser setting with a list
of different browser configurations. I have
five desktop browser configurations, each with their
own viewport size as well as these name of the browser and
I have five mobile browser configurations with
these device name as well as the screen orientation
being portrait or landscape. It's important to test not
only different browsers, but also different viewport
sizes and orientations. So let's
see what happens when we run our nine stories
against these ten browser configurations.
And boom. Check it out. So here
we had many, many more test results, 90 to
be precise. And even though we
had run some of these stories before for
visual testing because they now have these new browser configurations,
they have to establish new baselines. So that's why all of the results
now are new. If we go
to this link, we can see it all in the dashboard.
And here are the results. As we can see we have 90 new
results across all the different browser
configurations we specified. And notice how
little time it took this entire catch only took 37 seconds.
37 seconds for 90 tests in a
browser is really, really fast. That's why it's called the apple
tools ultra fast grid. If you were to do traditional
cons, browser testing for these 90 tests could take
several minutes, possibly even an hour or more
to execute.
So cross browser visual testing for storybook
components is really, really nice.
One more thing I want to touch on is when and where to run your
visual component tests. Now, component tests
fall somewhere between your integration tests and your
end to end tests, because components are like
UI units. What I recommend is
to run your visual component tests from some sort of
CI process. I actually created a GitHub action
in this example repository so that I could run them, let's say
whenever a pull request is opened. Here is the
workflow yaml for my GitHub action.
It's pretty straightforward, so there's no reason not to do this.
I run it on a Ubuntu image, and to do
it you simply check out the code, you set up node JS,
you install the dependencies, and then instead of running that command
locally like we did before, you just run it here. You will need
to configure your project with your applitools API key, but that
should be the only input you need. And then you
can specify the different steps in the workflow when you
want to dispatch these, and they'll run and upload your results to the
app tools dashboard. It's pretty nifty,
and that's how you can run visual component tests for your storybook libraries.
All you need to do is add the app tools eyes SDK to your
project, declare some config, and run the tests.
You don't need to explicitly write any new test code.
If you want to try this for yourself, check out the example code in this
GitHub repository and read this article I wrote recently on visual testing
for storybook. Again, my name is Andy Knight. You can follow
me on Twitter at automation panda. Feel free to hit me up with any questions.