Hello everyone. Thanks for attending my talk today. My name is Andrew Knight,
but you can call me Pandy for short. I'm the automation panda.
Check out my blog and follow me on Twitter. Just Google Automation Panda and
I'm sure youll find me. Currently I'm a developer advocate
at Appletools, where I help folks get the most value out of their QA work
with automated visual testing. I'm also the director of Test Automation
University, which offers several online courses to help you learn
testing and automation. And it's completely free.
Please check it out. It's awesome. Now,
you might be wondering what an automation panda is doing at a machine learning
conference. Well, I want to share one way that
AI is making a huge difference in the software testing and automation
space, and that's visual AI.
Traditionally, automated tests focused on things like text
and attributes to make sure apps were correct.
Unfortunately, that youll miss lots of problems.
Visual AI can quickly flag visual differences that both
scripts and manual testers might miss.
I'm guessing most of you in the audience have done some form of testing before,
even if it's as simple as making a small code change and rerunning
your program. That's awesome. There are
all kinds of testing unit tests,
integration tests, end to end tests, web UI
rest app, mobile load testing,
performance testing, property based testing,
behavior driven, data driven, you name it,
there's a test for it. But what is testing?
In a nutshell? In simplest terms,
testing is interaction plus verification. That's it.
Youll do something and you make sure it works.
Every kind of testing reduces to this formula.
Manual testing accomplishes both interactions and verifications by
direct human interaction. Somebody needs
to bang on a keyboard to drive a test. Automation drives
interactions and verifications with a script. We'd like to think
that automation is so great because it doesn't need any human intervention,
but we all know that's not true. Humans still
need to write the tests, develop the scripts, and fix them when they
break. Paradoxically, test automation
isn't fully autonomous. Visual testing helps to change
that. Although humans still need to figure out interactions,
visual testing techniques make verifications. Autonomous tests
take snapshots of their views and look for changes. Over time,
they catch more kinds of problems while ironically simplifying
test code. Unfortunately, many folks
seen to have the impression that visual testing is an advanced technique that
requires a high level of testing maturity to be valuable. That's not
the case at all. In fact, I want to flip that scripts entirely.
Visual testing is easier than traditional test automation.
This isn't some bleeding edge technology useful only to fang companies.
It isn't out of reach for teams just starting their test automation journey.
Visual testing makes functional testing easier
and stronger. AI simplifies test
development. It's something teams should do first before attempting
to automate longer, more complicated tests with traditional techniques.
Big claims, right? Let's see what I mean.
We are going to automate a web test together in Java with selenium
Webdriver using traditional interactions and verifications,
and then we will supercharge it with visual testing techniques
using Apple tools. First we need a web app
to test. We could test an app of any size,
but I'm going to choose a small one for the sake of our demo.
This is applitools demo site. It mimics a banking
application. You can try it yourself at demo appletools.com.
The login page has a main icon, username and password
fields, and a sign in button. Since this is
a demo site, you can enter any username and password to log in
after clicking the sign in button. Those main page loads there's a lot
of stuff on the main page. The top bar has the name of the
app, a search field, and icons for your account.
The main part of the page shows financial data.
Those left sidebar shows different account types.
We could write a basic login test for this app in four steps.
Load the login page, verify that the login
page loads correctly, log into the app
and finally verify that the main page loads correctly.
This could be a smoke test. There's nothing fancy here.
The trickiest part for automation would be deciding which elements
to check on the loaded pages. We could automate this
test in Java using selenium webdriver. Technically,
we could automate it using any popular language and tool.
Personally, right now I really like playwright and Python,
but based on different reports I've seen, Java is still one of the
most popular languages for test automation, and selenium Webdriver remains
the most popular browser automation tool.
JavaScript, C sharp, Python and Ruby
are other popular languages for test automation, and Cypress
is a very popular alternative to selenium.
In Java, we can write a junit test class named logintest
and create a test case method named login.
This test case method calls four helper methods, one for
each step. The first method, load login page,
loads the demo app's login page in the browser.
The second method, verify login page, verifies the appearance
of five critical elements on the page, the logo,
username field, password field,
sign in button, and the remember me checkbox.
It waits for each of these elements to appear using a helper method
named wait for appearance. The third method perform
login, enters a username and password and then clicks the
sign in button. So far, so good.
Nothing too bad. These are all typical webdriver calls.
The fourth method verify main page is a doozy.
Remember all the things on that page?
Well, they'll need several assertions to verify.
Some assertions merely check the appearance of elements.
Others need to perform text matching. For example,
to check the banner at the top that says your nearest branch
closes in x minutes, we need to find the element, get its
text, and then perform a regular expression match.
Checking the account types and status fields require getting lists
of elements, mapping their text values, and transforming
the resulting data for comparisons.
Despite this heavy lifting, this page still doesn't check everything
on the main page. Dates, amounts, and descriptions
are all ignored. Has a riskbased tradeoff.
We could add more assertions, but they youll lengthen this method even more.
They could also be difficult to write and become brittle over time.
Tests just can't cover everything.
If we run this login test against our app, it should pass without a problem.
But what if the page changes?
Here's a different version of the same page, with some slight visual differences.
Can you see what they are? Let me go back and forth a few times
for you to see.
Will our login test still work? Will it pass or fail?
Should it pass or fail?
Looking at these two pages side by side makes comparison easier.
The logos are different and the sign in buttons are different.
While I'd probably ask the developers about the sign in button change,
I'd categorically consider that the logo change is a bug.
Unfortunately, as long as the page structure doesn't change,
our login test will still pass. It wouldn't detect these changes.
We probably wouldn't find out about these changes if we relied exclusively on
traditional test automation. The step to verify that
the login page loaded correctly only checks for the appearance of
five elements by locators. These assertions will pass as
long as these locators find elements somewhere on the page,
regardless of where or how they appear or what they look like.
Technically, this login page would still pass the
test, even though we can clearly see it's broken.
Traditional functional testing things on those most basic functionality
of web makes, if it clicks, it works.
It completely misses visuals. Those are huge
test gaps. Adding more assertions probably won't
catch these kinds of problems either.
So what if we could visually inspect this page?
That would easily catch any changes on the page we take a
baseline snapshot that we consider good. And every time we
run our tests, we take a new checkpoint snapshot.
Then we can compare the two side by side to detect
any differences or any changes. This is what
we call visual testing. If a picture is worth
a thousand words, then a snapshots is worth a thousand assertions.
Automated visual testing is what tools like Apple tools does.
One visual snapshot captures everything on the page.
As a tester, you don't need to explicitly state what to
check. A snapshot implicitly covers layout,
color, size, shape,
and styling. That's a huge advantage over traditional
functional test automation. To be honest,
testers have been doing visual testing since computers first had screens.
Anyone can manually bang on a keyboard and look at the screen to
see what changes. That's arguably the first kind
of testing that anyone does. It's super valuable to
take a quick glance at a page to see what's wrong. Humans can
intuitively judge if a page is good or bad in a few seconds.
Unfortunately, human reviews don't scale well.
Modern apps have several screens worth checking, and continuous
integration systems deploy changes multiple times a day.
Humans make mistakes, they get tired,
they miss things. They also have a limited time.
This reminds me of the legend of John Henry, a folk hero from
the United States. As the legend goes,
John Henry was a railroad worker on the great Bend Tunnel along
the CNO railway in West Virginia.
When the company bought a steam drill,
John Henry competed against it head to head with a ten pound
hammer in each hand to see which could drill faster.
John Henry drilled deeper than the steam engine could,
technically winning the contest, but he died from exhaustion
afterwards. The legend of John Henry serves has a
parable that even the strongest, sharpest human is inevitably
no match. For a machine to
be relevant in a modern software shop, visual testing must be automated.
But that's easier said than done.
Programming a tool to capture snapshots and perform pixel
to pixel comparisons isn't too difficult. But determining
if those changes matter is.
A good visual testing tool should ignore changes that
don't matter, like small padding differences, and focus
on the changes that do matter.
Otherwise, human testers will need to review every single result,
nullifying any benefit of automating visual tests.
Take a look at those two pictures. They show a cute underwater scene
with an octopus in a garden. There are a total of
ten differences between these two pictures.
Can you find them? I'll give you a few seconds to look.
Unfortunately, a pure pixel to pixel comparison
dont find any of those changes. I ran those two pictures
through Apple tools using an exact pixel to pixel comparison and
this is what happened. Except for the white space on the sides,
every pixel was flagged as different as humans.
We can clearly see that these images are very similar, but because they were
a few pixels off on those side, automation failed to pinpoint
meaningful differences. This is where AI really
helps. Apple tools uses visual AI to detect
meaningful changes that humans would see and ignore inconsequential
differences that just make noise. Here I cause
apple tools strict comparison which pinpointed each
of the ten differences. Take a look. Did you
find all ten yourself? Do you see any that you missed?
I'll pause a moment for youll to look.
That's the second advantage of good automated visual
testing. Visual AI, like what Apple tools
does, focuses on meaningful changes to avoid noise.
Visual test results shouldn't waste testers'time over small
pixel shifts or things those human wouldn't even noticing.
They should highlight what matters like missing elements, differences,
colors, or skewed layouts. Visual AI
is a differentiator for visual testing tools. Pixel to
pixel comparisons are inherently fragile.
Visual AI makes visual testing robust and practical.
So let's update our login test to do visual testing with applitools,
first we need to create an appletools account.
Anyone can create one for free. At the link I'm showing here, you can
use your GitHub account or an email, and you don't even need a credit card.
The account will come with an API key that must be set as an environment
variable for testing. Next, we need to add
the applitools eyes SDK to our project.
Since we are using selenium Webdriver with Java, we need
to add the Appletools eyes selenium
Java three maven dependency to our PoM file.
Then we need to set up the applitools configuration and
runner for all tests in a suite.
The visual grid runner will upload snapshots to Apple tools ultrafast
grid and the configuration object sets the API key.
Those test batch name and the browser configurations we want to test.
This snippet shows configuration for Chrome, but we could test
any other browser like Safari, Firefox or
edge for genuine cross browser testing.
The setup for each individual test still needs a Webdriver object,
but it also needs an eyes object for capturing snapshots.
Here we construct the eyes object, hook it up to the runner,
and set its configuration. Then we open
our eyes to start taking snapshots.
Opening requires the webdriver differences, the app name and
the test name. Those interaction methods can remain unchanged
but we need to update the verification methods. Traditional assertions
can be completely replaced by one line snapshot calls.
Take a look at load login page.
Five lines reduced to one and the visual snapshot technically
has far greater coverage. The impact
on verify main page is far greater. One visual
snapshot eliminates the need for several lines
of assertions. Things is the third major
advantage visual testing has over traditional functional testing.
Visual snapshots greatly simplify assertions.
Instead of spending hours deciding what to check,
figuring out locators and writing transformation logic, you can make
one concise snapshot call and be done.
As an engineer myself, I cannot understate the cognitive
load things removes from the automation coding process.
I said it before and I'll say it again. If a picture is worth
a thousand words, then a snapshot is worth a thousand assertions.
So let's see visual testing in action. It's time
to dive into code and run it. All right,
so here is that Java project I mentioned.
I have it opened in Intellij idea and the
visual test junit class has all
visual testing code that I just showed you. Just to
show you again, we have our setup before
the entire test suite that creates our runner and our configuration.
We have it configured to run against one browser,
chrome browser with 800 by 600
viewport. We seen we're using Chrome
driver. We're setting up our eyes with our configuration.
Opening the eyes test case has four steps,
loading the login page, verifying it, performing login,
then verifying the main page. At the end we quit and
then we have the code for our interactions and verifications.
So let's run this test to establish baselines snapshots.
I already have it configured so I'm just going to hit the run button.
And now Intellij idea will run our test.
It should take only about a minute.
So right now it's running it locally. Now it's going to
upload the snapshot to Apple tools ultrafast grid.
And if I switch over to the dashboard right
now it's empty. If I refresh we can see
that that tests catch is now there has those name of the catch
we gave it and after, let's see,
after 17 seconds it captured
both snapshots and it's marked them as new green
for passing. So we can see those are our new baselines.
So we have a baseline for the login page and
we have a baseline for the main page.
So now let's run that test again on the second run
since it has baselines, what the visual testing comparison will do
is it will capture a new snapshots and treat it as a checkpoints
and compare against the baseline using visual AI
to see if there's any differences.
So let's run again. Again, it'll take
just a moment here. Running locally now
running in the dashboard.
If we refresh the dashboard,
we can see it's there, it's running and
it passed.
So if we look at the checkpoints,
we can see baseline versus checkpoint image and they're the same.
So nothing is highlighted differently. Same goes
for that main page. Everything's the same, everything checks out.
But now what happens if we introduce a
visual difference like we saw before?
So I'm going to run those test again, but this time I'm
going to use that alternative login page and
we'll see what happens here.
So we'll give it a minute. I just launched it again.
It's running locally and
now it should be uploading to the grid. So if I refresh
we can see there's the new batch and it's running.
Give it just a few seconds.
And this time we have a problem.
So the results show here the
main page didn't have any significant changes. So it's still green,
but the login page certainly did. And so it's marked yellow
as unresolved. What that status means unresolved is
that appletools has detected a visual difference and it's up to you
as those tester to determine if that was a good change or
a bad change. So when we pull up the side by
side we can see all the things that were highlighted different. We see the icon
has different, we see the sign in versus login button was
different and we see that the remember me check mark
has shifted. So I'm going to say that this is
a bad difference and I'm going to give it a thumbs down.
And what that does now is it will mark this particular snapshot
as failed. So we save our changes.
And what's really cool now is that if we were to run this test again,
which I'll do here, I'll just click those run
and we'll wait for it. What should happen is that since we've already
marked that kind of visual change as a failure,
anytime that visual checkpoint appearances
again app youll should automatically mark it as a failure rather than
us need to come in here and repeatedly fail it.
So we run again and there
it goes.
And automatically look at that. Because it was the same type
of failure apple tools was smart enough to know. Boom,
failed.
So there's another really cool thing we can do with these visual snapshots.
Let me jump back in the code,
look at those browser configurations.
Previously I only had one browser configured,
but with Apple tools, if you test in the ultrafast grid,
you can actually test against multiple browsers. How is
this possible? It's the magic of a snapshot.
So I've been careful to say snapshot and not screenshot.
A snapshot captures everything on those page in the
DOM, the HTML, the CSS and the
JavaScript. A screenshot is nothing more than a
collection of pixels, which it's static and doesn't change. But if you
have a snapshots with all the stuff on the page,
what youll could do is you could rerender that on any browser
configuration that you like. So even though you captured
the page, let's say on Chrome, you could rerender
that snapshot on Safari,
on Firefox, on ie, or maybe even on
mobile browsers, which is really, really cool.
So let's do that. We'll get rid of our one browser configuration
and I'll bring these back to the forefront.
So here now we have five different desktop browser configurations,
Chrome, Firefox, iE, Edge, Safari,
as well as five mobile emulated devices,
iPhone X, Pixel, Galaxy Nexus and even can iPad.
Each one has a different viewport size as well as a different
orientation. What's really cool about this
is you can test browsers and devices that
aren't on your local machine. For example, I'm running on a Mac,
so I'm not going to have ie eleven here, but I could run these
tests visually against ie eleven in the Apple tools
test cloud. Really awesome stuff.
So let's run this again just to
see what happens. Going to run it back on the
original working website.
So we'll kick it off and then let's flip over to the dashboard
again and we'll wait for
results here. When we do
this, even though we specified ten browsers, it will still only run
one browser on our local machine, which we decided was Chrome.
And it'll take that snapshot. And here we go. You can see
how it's testing all those checkpoints against the
different browser configurations. Chrome, ie, Firefox, Edge,
Safari, and it's doing it concurrently.
I in my code have set a concurrency level of five, meaning five
checkpoints can run in parallel. And already we're seeing.
So the first one is marked as pass because that
was the previous configuration that we had,
but all the others should be marked as new because they would be new baseline
images.
And there we go. Everything passed. This is a really,
really cool way to not only do visual testing, but also to achieve
cross browser testing. You run the test once on your machine
or in a CI server and then you leave the rest
up to applitools test cloud to render it
against all the different browser configurations. This is much,
much faster than traditional cross browser testing where you would need to run those entire
test from start to finish however many times you want
for the differences. Browser configs if we look here,
these ten tests finished in only 46 seconds.
Typically a web UI test would take about half a minute to
a minute to run ten tests. You're talking several minutes.
Here were sub minute 46 seconds. Really, really cool
stuff. Lightning fast cross browser testing is visual
testing's fourth big advantage. To do cross browser testing
with traditional functional tests, each test must run on each browser
configuration all the way through with visual snapshots.
Each test runs only one time and snapshots are rerendered on
each target configuration, making tests faster and more reliable.
Before I conclude this talk, those is one more thing I want y'all
to consider when a team should adopt visual
testing. I can't tell you how many times folks have told me,
Andy, that visual testing thing looks so cool
and so helpful, but I don't think my team will ever get
there. We're just getting started and we're new to automation
and automation is so hard and I don't think
we'll ever be mature enough to use a tool like apple tools.
I just smacked myself in those face because visual testing makes automation easier.
I really think teams should do visual testing from the start.
Consider this strategy start by automating a smoke test
that navigates to different pages of an app and captures snapshots of
catch. The interaction code would be straightforward,
and the snapshots are just oneliners that would provide an
immense amount of value for relatively little automation work.
It's the 80 20 rule, 80% of the value for 20%
of the work. Then later, when a team has more time or
more maturity, they can expand the automation project with larger tests
that use both traditional and visual assertions. Let those
power of AI help you test
automation is hard. No matter what tool or language you use.
Teams struggle to automate tests in time and to keep them rumbling.
Visual testing simplifies implementation and execution while
catching more problems. It offers the advantage of making functional
testing easier. It's not a technique only for those on
the bleeding edge. It's here today and it's accessible to
anyone doing test automation. You don't need to be an
expert in AI or ML to use it. Visual testing
is a winning strategy. It has several advantages over traditional
functional testing. Please note, however, the visual testing does
not replace functional testing. Instead,
it supercharges it. If you want to give it a try, you can
sign up for a free account with Apple tools. Clone the example project I
showed today, or any of our others, and run tests on your local machine.
Thank you all for attending my talk today on visual testing.
Again, my name is Pandy and I'm the automation Panda developer
advocate at Apple Tools and director of Test Automation University.
Be sure to read my blog and follow me on Twitter. I always love
to chat about testing and automation, so thanks again and enjoy the
rest of 42.