Hello everybody. Today I would like to talk to you about trust driven development
and how this approach can help us in DevOps transformation.
Firstly, when we see be the transformation world,
what do we think about that in our minds?
It can pop up that it will be a change, it will be a
change in the ways of working, it will be a change in
the tools that we are using. Definitely the change.
And if we are going through change, the most important part
is trust. And today I will tell you why and how we can
transform our organizations. Let's think for a while
about the world, what we operate in.
It is Vuca World. I hope that
some of you have heard about this term. It was defined in the
US after Second World War.
And this is telling
us about four dimensions of our nowadays world.
Our nowadays world is volatile, it's arts uncertain,
it's complex and is ambiguous. All right.
On the other hand, we have our agile world,
we have market dynamics, because our iT environment
is very dynamic. There are a lot of companies are popping up every
day, some startups are shutting down.
So the market is definitely dynamic. Then we have unknown
requirements. Obviously we as engineers,
we know that we have a lot of discussion with the business
that they would like to develop something, these would like to earn money. But then
they ask us, okay, so how this feature should look like, what it
should do. And sometimes we
are frustrated, right, because we are the
engineers, but they are the business guys. But in reality,
right now we need to advise our business folks what
to do and how to do it. We solve the
complex problems, right? Because we are these to solve the complex
problems and complex riddles. And last but not least,
we have ambiguous estimations, right?
When we develop something, we need to have a founding
for that. And our business folks usually ask about,
okay, nice feature, how much money does it
cost? So we have those four aspects of
our agile world, I call it Muka,
acronym. So market dynamics are no requirements, complex problems and
ambiguous estimations means muka. And it is sort
of for me the answer for this Vuca world.
Now, if we see the
agile manifesto right now, we can see
that in every single item, in every single line,
there is a trust involved. Because these
first one individuals and interaction of our processes and tools.
Okay, so if we would like to interact with each
other, we need to trust each other, right?
Customer collaboration of the contract negotiation. We need to trust
our customer that we not will be negotiating
and fighting for every single feature. We will be collaborating,
responding to a change. Definitely. We need to trust ourselves
that we are able, we are capable to respond to the
change that is happening. And we need to acknowledge that.
And working software, someone needs to trust us.
Most precisely, the investors needs to trust us that we
will develop, they will put their money and we'll develop their
software. So let's think for a while about
this trust aspect. Isn't it a little bit of fuzzy?
For me as an engineer, I didn't know what does it mean to be
trustful and to have trust, to build trust with each other?
So what I did, I did some research about that,
and I observed that there are two aspects of building trust.
The first aspect is cognitive aspect, and the other aspect is emotional
aspect. Cognitive aspect is transmitted through
thinking. So everything that we think of,
everything that we have in our mind, the skills
we have, the knowledge we gained, the experience we've
got, this is the cognitive aspect of
trust. And emotional aspect of trust is transmitted
through feeling. So everything that
is connected with our intentions, with our openness
and honesty,
everything that we make people feel,
if they are interactive with us, it is emotional aspect
of trust, and we call it that. We are in integrity
when we have those aspects. So cognitive aspect is more oriented for
the results. Emotional aspect is more oriented to the
being in integrity as a person. So we
have those two pillars. And while building
trust, during DevOps transformation and during DevOps
practices, we need to think about those two.
The first pillar is all about competence, and the second pillar
is all about character. So it means that trust is
a combination of competence and character. Of us,
competence is the cognitive intelligence that
we have. We are engineers,
so we all know that when we work, we use our analytical
skills, we use our logic,
we have the specific language. It can be Java language
or c plus plus language. But it also can be
specific technical language that we are not aware.
Even like we are talking about deployment,
we are talking about measurements, we are talking about having the
ceremonies, like planning, retrospective, and so on,
that specific language. And people outside of our domain
will not understand that. The same with the data.
We use a lot of data, we analyze a lot of data,
and we know what does it mean
if we are analyzing those records in the database,
for example. But this is the meaning for us, for our cognitive
intelligence, not for others.
We have also emotional intelligence. And emotional
intelligence is basically how to recognize
and understand our emotions.
So when we are in such a state,
for example, during the meeting, and we don't understand
our emotions, we will not be able to also
react properly. So the first things first is to understand
in which state we are in and what's going
to happen with us and then we can define our
reaction on the certain situation. For example, during meeting,
it is also recognizing and understanding emotions
of others. Because if we, for example, we are doing the
planning meeting, we need to understand what's
going on in the room for different people.
So for example, for product owner, he or she
might be worried that the feature will be not taken into
consideration or he or she might be
excited that there is a new feature coming in. But the team
can be worried that it's difficult feature and we are
not able to deliver these. So there are a lot of emotions that we are
not aware of. And this emotional
aspect is for us to understand.
So when we embrace our emotional part,
then this is the way to build
a bit trust and break out the silos. And why I'm talking about
the silos in the organization, because this is a clue. This is a
crucial part in terms of the DevOps
transformation. When you see this picture, there is
an example of tools ecosystem for DevOps, there are
a lot of different tools that we are using. We were implementing
in the companies, or we would like to impediments. And you can
see that there are certain domains of
the tooling we use, for example, GitLab to build
application, we can use chef to deploy the application,
Docker to run it, and so on and so forth. These are a lot of
different tools and we are keen on implementing those new tools.
But if we have domains, we also
may have silos, right? So there can
be a certain amount of people building the app and then
there can be a QA group who are testing the app.
Obviously nowadays qas and developers, engineers are
sometimes, usually, I guess, mixed in the one
team, but this is just a part of this
example. We have then people who can deploy the application
and run on production. We can have the operations
who monitor the application.
And that's why if we talk about DevOps,
DevOps means, as easy as it is,
DevOps means development plus operations. So the shared
responsibility, shared goal and shared
working ways. So in
order to have it, we need to break these silos and
build trust. If we will build trust between those
groups, we will be succeed. And the
tooling is just another example that we
will be using. But definitely we need to have trust.
Why it's so important, because for example, let's have this
example of building and testing software. So we have developers who
build the code, we have qas who test these code.
And I remember like 15 years ago when I was a
Java developer, there was a little competition in the company.
Between engineers and the qAs,
that the software will have a bugs or will
not have the bugs. So DevOps were
building software and saying, yes, this software is ideal. Works for
me, works for me in my environment. It works, it is perfect.
There is no bug. And then this
jar file, whatever this app were going to
qas and Qas were saying, oh, there's a lot of bugs
over there, please raise the tickets to injira.
So that was a little competition. And obviously engineers,
I was an engineer and we were saying, it works for
me, works for me. Do you know that? Yeah, it works for me.
And Qas, they were saying a lot of bucks. A lot of bucks.
The same story can be between production
and monitoring, right? Production people. So let's say
building and testing and deploying to production
and passing over the app and saying, everything's fine,
I've done my work, everything's fine.
It break production. Oh, you know, there is operations
guys who can fix that. And that is also challenge,
right? Because operations guys may say also,
oh, the production is broken. That's because of
the qas or because they didn't test it or because of engineers.
So there's a blaming game starting at this point.
And if there will be a trust like this
that will have one common goal, one common mission, and people will trust
each other that engineers, yes, they did the best work they've
ever done, but bugs can be there.
Or engineers can trust operations that, yes, operations,
they have a lot of good intentions
in running on production, but sometimes they need to
fix something in the code and we can help them
understand the code. If there will be a trust, I'll be helpful
for everyone. This is about also exchanging
these knowledge. So I met a lot of operations guys who wanted to
do some coding part, but engineers said, no operations
guys, you just run the applications,
we are fixing the bugs and vice versa. I met a
lot of operations guys who told me that
we are just running the app and everything that needs to be fixed will be
done by developer because they build these software.
There was an idea a couple of years ago, you build it,
you run it. So having the same people building the same people run
it. So this is as well this direction
that the DevOps is going to. And if we build
trust by showing our results, showing that
we deliver something, and also showing our attitude that we
are open to discussion with other people, then the whole
tool chain of our ecosystem can be shared and
DevOps can be implemented.
As I mentioned at the beginning, there are three aspects that we change.
We are changing a lot during DevOps transformation. But there are three aspects
that we change. Team structure, process adjustment and tools review.
Sometimes we don't need to change, but sometimes we need to review
those because team structure. I'm not going to the details about team
structure here, but there is a separate
book, team topologies, where you can find
the different structures for different organizations.
But definitely if we review our organization, we think about structure.
Do we have the right people in the right team, for example,
Dev Qas, dev operations. So we need
to have these trust to management and
from people that these
team structure or restructure will be done
smoothly. We may do some process adjusting,
so some of our processes, ways of working that we are following
right now. It's maybe not efficient or maybe can be improved.
So we need to have trust
in the group in order to change it, because there will be definitely resistance
of people who like the process and there
will be some difficulties in trusting the
others would like to do it better. So if
the group that would like to change something will show their
knowledge that they know what to do, they know how to do it and
will show the openness that we are here together to work
this out, then the resistance can be lower
and the tools review. We love that as engineers,
right? When we do these DevOps transformation, we do tools
review, implement a lot of new tools and so on. But in that case,
our management needs to trust us that we
know these tools, we will be using good tools and we'll handle
that to make our software
successful. And then once we have this trust,
we as engineers can have the autonomy, right? We are striving
for autonomy. You would like to do autonomously,
a lot of things. So once we show people results
and then show our intentions that they can trust us,
we can get the autonomy. And it's even mentioned in the DevOps
evolution model on the third stage, that individual,
that's the example that individuals can work without manual
approvals from outside of the team. It is also about trust
because this approval step, for example, while deploying
to the production, having this continuous delivery piece,
right, usually in the companies, there is the green
light that someone manually needs to click in Jira or whatever.
So that's this approval. And if these
people who make a green light will
trust developers, then we can go towards more
deploying without approval. And I
would like to mention also Brenda Brown here and
her quotation, she is a us psychologist and
researcher and she said that trust is not
being built in big sweeping moments. It's being
built in these tiny moments every day. And it works
like this, that you have one engineer joining
the team and you have the other engineer in the team. And our brain subconsciously
is assessing these relationship.
Setting up the relationship between us is assessing the
two aspects that I mentioned. Do this new guy have the knowledge
and can help us in our team?
And how about intention of this guy, of this
person? And every sweeping moment, our brain
subconsciously assess those two aspects. And once it's
assessed, a relationship is being built
and is built and trust is established.
Now I have two example for you guys per programming.
That's the first one in per programming we need to have
the trust between each other, right? There are some
challenges. When I met with the engineers, they told me that there are
challenges in the per programming. There is a fear of
being assessed. These first things first. I am the developer.
I'm a senior developer. For example, doing the per programming with a junior guy.
But is it my code senior? Is it
enough? Does the other
guy will see the value or the other
hand, vice versa, that I'm junior guy and I don't feel that
my code is good enough in this process.
So that's a trap of obviously not for everyone, but for
some that we can have.
And behind this fear is
a fear of rejection. Will I be rejected as a junior and I don't know
anything because I don't have this knowledge? Or will I be rejected as
a senior because I may not have a knowledge
and my attitude may not be right? So this
is about fear. And if we will be
brave enough to show ourselves, then it helps building
trust. Similar with a code review. When we have code
review process,
we are putting ourselves to the assessment of others,
right? The question is if they are assessing my code or if
they are assessing me as author of the code. I also need to be courage
in order to build trust and to show my code and
not to take these comments about my code into
me. At the end, I would like to mention about the
vulnerability that Brenda defined. Brenda defined the
vulnerability people with vulnerability as a birthplace of innovation,
creative and change. But what does it mean to be vulnerable? It means
to show our weaknesses to others. Like with this example,
with this example with the code review or per programming. Because we know
systems of vulnerability as a flow or weakness in
the computer system which could be exploited and volatile
the system, right? So that's our meaning in the engineering
of vulnerability. We are searching
for those weaknesses and we try to fix them.
The human vulnerability is more showing the weaknesses
and not to try to fix them. Maybe we can try to fix them at
some point. But first things first is to show this vulnerability
that yes, we are humans, we have some weaknesses and
if we admit that to people, then people will trust
us more because our attitude,
our intention will be clear.
If we are talking about agile or scrum,
we also need to be vulnerable to do scrum.
For example, quick example for today is retrospective. So we
do retrospectives. And in order to have meaningful conversation,
we need to show ourselves as we are.
A quick example with the metrics
from our world. We need to trust each other to show proper
numbers, right? These say, give me your metrics and I will
tell you whatever you want to hear, right. You know
that every single metrics can be work
around it, right? We have four metrics here. Like just example,
deployment frequency. They said that we need to
frequently deploy to production and we need to measure it. Yes.
We can split our user stories for so small items
that we'll be deploying very frequently and our number will be very high.
The same lead time for changes, right?
This is about cheating a little bit, right? But splitting
work for small chunks so small that the numbers will
be perfect. But this is not about that. It's about being
true with ourselves and showing our work in
these metrics with the meantime to recover.
I saw the workaround that when we
deploy to production, we deploy to production. But we
have these feature flag that says it is invisible to
the client. So when we would like to measure the time
to recover the system, we can measure
up until delivering to production but
not showing to the clients, right. And the
time will be shorter because at the end of this process, for example,
let's say we need to do some tests at the
end and not calculating these time at the end we will
have better results, but we will cheat the metrics.
So in order to have proper numbers and to have proper
meaning numbers, we need to have trust together,
to be brave, to show ourselves.
Then we will be able to build software better, build relationships better,
and establish trust. And those three teams will
show us the aspect of belonging that we will feel
belong in the workplace, because we'll be
truly ourselves as well.
And at the end, I would like to show you and finish with a
quotation from Simon Sinek. These team is not a group of people
working together. The team is a group of people that trust
each other. Thank you very much.
Let me know if you have any questions. I'm available.
You can also reach out me on social media and have
a nice conference.