You. Every January, thousands of people
go out and buy treadmills, and come February,
the vast majority of them wind up looking a
little bit like this. And there's a reason for that.
Basically, what it boils down to is one simple truth,
and that is that buying a treadmill doesn't
make you a runner. Now, you might be wondering,
well, wait a minute, what in the world does that have to do with DevOps?
Well, as it turns out, there really are
no magical tools. So just as going out and
buying a treadmill isn't going to magically make you a runner,
going out and investing in bring new CI CD
tooling, brand new project management software,
et cetera, isn't going to magically,
in and of itself, take your team
and enhance your entire DevOps
process. Now, don't get me wrong,
tools are important. Having the right tool
does in fact make a difference.
But the tool itself is only going
to be helpful if it's being used.
Now, a couple of months ago, I participated in
a set of roundtables at GitHub universe.
And these roundtables were attended by all
sorts of different DevOps professionals, all sorts
of different leaders, sea level folks, et cetera.
And if there was one common theme throughout all
of the conversations that we wound up having,
it was this. The most common blocker
to being able to implement new techniques,
new patterns was team culture,
that all of this investment was being made in the tools,
but nobody was using them.
So rather than focusing solely
on what some cool new tool can do for us,
let's instead turn our attention to how
we can actually use those tools, how we can actually
implement the necessary changes to take
our DevOps practices to the next level,
and what it really all starts with, and I'm
going to work through kind of three main key points here,
is, number one is asking the right
questions. So going back to the beginning,
buying a treadmill doesn't make you a runners. I'm now a
runner. I didn't start life as a runner. It was
something I picked up about ten years ago. And the reason that I
became a runner was because my body had
found itself in a shape, in a level of fitness
that I just wasn't really happy with. So I
wanted to improve upon that. But I knew in order
to do that, I was going to need
some form of exercise, some set of
habits that I was going to be able to
stick with. And in particular, I needed something
that was going to be portable, and I needed something that was going to
give me tools. And the great thing about running is
all you need is a pair of shoes. You don't even need that treadmill.
And there's always some new race,
there's always some personal record that you want to be able
to beat. I want to go a little bit faster here. I want to be
able to run a marathon. I want to run some
new distance. So I had those challenges and
I had something that was portable and so that was
going to allow me to achieve my primary goal.
What was my primary goal? Well, it was to get myself
fit and to make sure that my body took on a shape that
I really kind of wanted it to be able to take on.
Let's bring this then into our software
development processes. And we need to start by
asking the right changes, by asking the right questions
even. And number one is why
do we want to change? So it's
not just simply a matter of, hey, we want to
start automating CI CD. It's not just simply a
matter of we want to
adopt new agile methodologies.
The real question is why? What is it that
we are bring to achieve? I didn't set out just to go run.
I set out to try and improve my shape and try and
improve my fitness. So what is it that we're trying
to improve? So let's take an example of we have a mobile
app, and our primary challenge when it comes to our mobile app
is we're not as responsive to customer requests as
we would like to be. So we have bugs in our application.
We don't have a really good methodology for
taking customer requests, taking customer feedback, being able to
bring that into the product and our process
of, in turn being able to add those features and deploy
that, but is also problematic. It's shoddy.
So what's our real goal here? Our real goal is to be
more responsive. Our real goal is to try and ensure that our
mobile app is going to be updated in a
timely fashion. So that's our real goal. That's our real why.
Once we've established that, then we can
turn our attention to the how we're going
to do that. Then we can start to find,
well, what tools are we missing?
What are the challenges, what are the barriers that
we currently have? So is our CI CD solution
meeting our needs? And if it's not,
then we can take a look at incorporating that new tool. But you'll
notice that we're starting with the why. What is it that we're trying to
really do here? What's the core of it all? Then we can start incorporating
those tools and identifying the challenges that are currently getting in
the way of us being able to achieve that goal.
Additionally, when it comes to making
these kinds of changes, we want to not just
identify what tools we're going to need, we want to not just identify
what processes we may need to implement,
we also need to identify who is
key to success. Because again, it's all about culture.
If we can get everybody on board,
the rest kind of doesn't matter.
Now, when people start to look around and try to identify,
okay, well, who are going to be the key voices here?
People typically start with the obvious, which is going to be leadership,
it's going to be sea level people, it's going to be our managers. And don't
get me wrong, that's certainly going to be important.
That I remember years and years and years ago that I was working
with a team to try and help them get from a waterfall
methodology to something that was going to be more agile.
And while the manager kept insisting, oh yeah, I'm all
for it, I'm all for it, I'm all for it, in reality,
he wasn't. And on top of
that, he was also listening to a couple of curmudgeonly
developers that really weren't on board
either. And so as a result, the whole
project kind of was doomed from
the start here. So we want to identify who's going to be
key to success. So certainly, yes, it's going to be all of those
managers, c level people, 100%, but it's
also going to be individual developers,
it's going to be my mentors, it's going to be my leaders,
and it's also potentially going to be a
couple of those, hopefully lovable curmudgently developers,
the ones that are strongly opinionated,
because if I can bring them over to
my side, if I can impress upon them the importance,
the why we're making these changes now,
they can be champions for the cause,
they can be champions for the change that we
are trying to implement.
So why are we trying to change? What is that we're really hoping
to do? What are the challenges? What are the roadblocks? What do we
need to actually invest in? And then finally,
who's going to be key to success?
Once we've established the right questions, then we need
to establish a plan.
So kind of kicking this back again, my plan
again, just trying to lose weight, find a particular set of
fitness, was to run a half marathon.
For those of you not familiar, that's 13.1
mile, 21.1 km roughly.
So I had a plan and
it was going to be to start from a particular set
of mileage very low because I was really just starting as a runner
and then building up incrementally until eventually I was going
to be able to run that race. So I had
a plan. I put that forth
and now it was my job to start to
follow that plan.
So let's now bring this back to our scenario.
So we know we've established our real goal
here is to improve upon
our mobile app, that we want to be able
to be more responsive, we want to be able to deploy faster, et cetera.
So let's start by clearly defining
success. In my analogy, again becoming a
runner, my way of defining success wasn't
just that I was going to be able to complete the distance, but also that
I was feeling more fit, that my clothes were going to fit
a little bit better. I want to be
able to clearly define success. So that might be that we're
bring to reduce the amount of time that
it talked for a piece of feedback to it
finding its way into our code base, to it
finding its way into my deployed application.
I want to define this is where we are,
this is where we want to get to. I want to make sure that it's
measurable. I want to identify all of
those different metrics so that way I know did
I succeed or potentially did I
wind up failing? So, clearly defined success.
The second is to now find the
right team, find the right champions to
begin to follow our plan, to be able
to implement this plan.
Now, hopefully you've already got
a handful of teams that are all set and ready to
go, but you may need to make
some changes to put together the
right set of people to start down this path.
One of the things, of course, that's going to wind up happening as part of
this is you're going to
be asking people to change behaviors. Potentially you're
going to be asking them to do new things.
And one of the biggest roadblocks is if people have already
been bring the exact same thing,
they're going to keep bring that exact same thing.
And that's really what we're trying to change.
That's what we're trying to break but of. And so
one big strategy that you can use is
to start to form new teams. Now,
forming new teams actually does bring an additional set of
benefits because it allows me to cross pollinate, it allows me to take
experiences from different parts of my organization and
share them together. That lessons that a developer may have
learned over here, lessons that a developer may have learned over here,
we can bring that chocolate and peanut butter together and find
ourselves a more diverse team.
Diverse teams are inherently going to be more
successful. But on top of that, if we're already
making this big change that I'm taking these developers and I'm putting them
onto a brand new project,
it's the perfect time to now
start to implement additional changes. Because after all,
if you're already like changing the team that you're on,
changing maybe the frameworks that you're using, changing the
project that you're working on, you're not going to bring
with you some of those mental barriers of I've always done things
this way because you're working on a brand new project.
Now is a perfect time to start to develop some
new habits. So identify those teams and maybe
start to form some new teams as
you've identifying the teams that can then be that
part of that pilot, that can then be those champions,
find the project for them to work on.
Now, in my example, I've been talking about a mobile app,
so of course that's then going to be the pilot project,
but that's admittedly
overly simplistic and it's being used for purposes of the
talk. Instead, what you really want to
focus in on is find projects,
find components that are going to be
meaningful, that are going to be large
but not overly
difficult. Try and find a better way to kind
of explain that. Sort of a Goldilocks for anybody's familiar.
Porch is too hot, porch is too cold. You want to find something that's just
right. So this might be an internal service
or an internal library that is used in
a lot of different projects. Maybe it's being
shared. And what's nice about that is maybe it's something
that's relatively small, maybe it's handling auth or
whatever it is that it happens to be doing. But it's really important
to the success of the organization, to the success
of multiple applications that are now using this service, that are
now using this particular library. That winds
up being like a perfect spot for me to start.
So let's start to work on implementing
our updated processes. Let's start to
work on incorporating some of those new
tools, some of those new techniques into that
pilot, into that project. Or maybe it's,
hey, we know we're going to be developing something new. Maybe we've been
doing an Android app and now we want to do an iOS app or
whatever it is that can also be a perfect pilot.
And again, it's going to have that advantage since we're not already building
it, that it allows us to more easily
incorporate changes to that.
And then lastly, number three is implement
and review. So again, going all the way back to that analogy,
I start running and now I'm going to start to look
at am I having success?
And if I am fantastic, let's identify why and keep doing those
things. And if I'm not, then let me
go back and take a look to see, well, is there an
existing behavior that I need to change or do
I maybe not have the right tool? Do I maybe not have the right plan?
Is there something else that I need to maybe adjust
or update to allow me to have success?
So I'm using an iterative process here,
bringing this back to our example of our mobile
app and all of our teams or
our singular team that's now going to be working on this.
How can we start to implement these changes?
I think the biggest thing that we can do is
to focus in on adding behaviors rather
than changing them from the start. So for example,
one of the things that can be potentially problematic,
that can cause problems is
large prs, large pull requests. Because the problem with a large
pr is it's more difficult to review,
it's more difficult to roll back. It can wind
up making changes to multiple different components inside
of whatever it is that we happen to be building.
And it then in turn becomes
lets manageable. Okay, so I know that
a point that I probably want to get to is a
new behavior of smaller prs,
but I don't want to go to my teams and go, hey, let's start change
this. Let's start now only doing smaller prs
because again, that's going to be that behavior that's maybe ingrained into them
and we're not ready for that yet. Okay, cool.
We're not ready for that. So instead let's focus
in on trying to add new behaviors. So again,
kind of going back to that running analogy, I wasn't quite ready yet to
start having up all the burgers that I was eating. That's fine.
That wasn't the most important thing for me to start doing. The most important
thing for me to start doing was to add to what I was
doing in my life. So start lacing up my running shoes,
get out the door and away we go. So rather than
let's change to get all of our developers to start buying
smaller prs, let's instead focus on
adding behaviors. So if we're not already bring code reviews,
let's start to add those in. If we don't already have
tools to start doing linting or
automate for checking code quality or
to add on unit tests and to start to run those.
Let's add those behaviors in, because here's what's
eventually going to happen, is a smaller
pr is going to be easier to review, a smaller PR is
going to be easier to add unit tests to. A smaller
PR is going to be able to be updated
that much easier. And so eventually
what's going to wind up happening is because we're adding on
these new behaviors, because we're adding on code reviews,
eventually people are going to want to make that part easier,
that if I haven't had a burger the night before the run, the next
morning becomes a little bit easier. Same concept here,
that if I'm adding on code reviews, code reviews are going to become easier
if I'm using smaller prs. So what's going to happen over time?
We're going to wind up naturally trending
in that direction towards smaller prs.
So let's focus in on adding behaviors rather than
changing behaviors, especially from the start. And what
we're going to find is that eventually those
bad behaviors, those behaviors that are getting in the way are
eventually bring to decrease.
Next, document our successes and
our failures. Things are going to work.
Things are not going to work. I want to know in both
situations why and what
can I do to continue to replicate and build upon my
successes and what can I learn from the
failures? What changes can I make here to
help ensure that we're now going to continue to
move in that right direction,
which then leads us to that last little circle there of
iterate and grow.
So as we continue to learn, let's now
turn our attention to bringing on another project, bringing on
another team, and continue to grow out from there.
Now, at this point, sometimes people will give me a little
bit of pushback and they go, hey, wait a minute, Christopher, it sounds
like what you're really trying to say here is you want to
implement change through groundswell solely. And that's
not at all what I'm trying to say, because it does need to come from
both directions, that I need my managers, I need my leaders
to buy into what we're bring
to do what we're trying to accomplish. That's key to
success. But the other part to the key to success is
ensuring my developers are there as
well. And so I want to be able to grow from both directions
there. So let's continue to iterate. Let's continue to identify
what's working, what's not working, what changes can we make?
What behaviors can we add on and then continue
to grow from there?
Obviously there's no magical
solution. As I said at the top, yes,
tools are important, but there is no magical tool.
Change, particularly when we're talking about cultural change,
is bring to take time and there are going
to be setbacks. We need to accept that.
We need to make sure that we're in this for the long haul,
that we're not just simply trying something, just for
the sake of trying something, that we have a clearly defined
goal, that we know what it is that we're
trying to do, we know what it is that we're trying to solve. So that
way when there are those setbacks, we can bring that
right back to the very beginning. And what's the very beginning?
It's asking the right questions.
Bringing in a brand new tool just because
it's the cool new thing, just because everybody else is
doing it, or to make
a reference that some people may or may not get, just because it goes to
eleven rather than going to ten isn't
going to bring about the change that
we hope that it might. What's going to bring about
the change is, is defining
those goals, defining the why,
finding the right people to then champion that
and then starting that process of adding on the behaviors
that we're looking for, figuring out what it is that's working,
figuring out what it is that's not working, and then continuing
to make the changes from there.