Only a third of enterprises are realizing their current
ambitions. This pessimistic but unsurprising number was
published by HFS Research in their market vision paper.
These results came from serving over 500 senior executives
across the largest companies in the world. Welcome to
Conf 42 Cloud Native Conference and thank you
for attending the session. I'm Ashu Siddiqui,
senior principal software engineer at Silicon Valley
bank, division of First Citizens bank.
This talk will be split over three sessions, starting off
with cloud reduction framework and why it has to be a
starting point for every cloud journey in Azure.
Next section will be azure Landing zone and the key role
it plays in a robust foundation.
The third and last session will be about deployment strategy and
how to realize this goal. Cloud Reduction Framework
is a comprehensive lifecycle framework to guide organizations
to success in their cloud journey. The best practices
aid organization in aligning their technical strategies
with the business value. The framework provides
distinct phases with specific goals, solutions and benefits.
Strategy starts with the question, why are we moving to cloud?
The multiple motivations vary from
to, but it is imperative that motivations are tightly coupled
with the business outcomes. On a broader level, there are
three categories of motivations. Number one,
critical business events, such as being on the hook to exit
data centers or for example, dealing with mergers
and acquisitions. Second category of motivation
is migration, such as pursuit of cost savings or raising
business agility. The third category is innovation,
such as scaling to meet market or geographic demands.
Client phase is about transforming strategy into an actionable
plan. The application portfolio needs to be analyzed
to determine which apps are suitable for migration or modernization.
In addition, this phase also brings personnel together.
Alignment, in my mind, is one of the most underrated elements of
the framework. This is because the program's
success is contingent on a vision that must be shared
by all the stakeholders. Another key component of this phase
is determining skill readiness. For the
people in the trenches to be successful, assessment of the skill set
is a requisite to find their gaps.
The identified gaps can be bridged by training and upskilling,
which brings the necessary expertise into the organization.
Ready phase requires defining operational models
from the three choices of decentralized, centralized or
distributed operations. This phase also
includes the highlight of the stock Azure landing zone and its implementation.
Migrate phase provides the best practices for migrating workloads
to Azure based on workload assessment.
There are choices to consider rehost aka
lift and shift versus refactor versus replatform.
Since a salient purpose of innovation is to drive business value,
what is business value? Needs to be formally and mutually defined
by the stakeholders. Building the first minimum
viable product MVP and measuring the customer impact
are also considerations within the innovation phase.
The significance of secure phase should require no introduction.
It is an area that industry trends repeatedly remind
requires more and more focus to be able to safeguard enterprise data
and intellectual property. While Adafil
focuses on getting you into the cloud, online operations
is what draws out the business deliverables. Every workload
needs to be managed by its business criticality which focus both on
cost and SLAs. Governed phase
is an iterative process to ensure application portfolio complies
with the corporate and as applicable, any regulatory
compliance requirements. In the cloud
space, it seems enterprises struggle with the dual challenge of
harnessing innovation while maintaining a robust security
posture. Azure learning zone is the antidote
to this enterprise challenge. It delivers an environment that
adheres to key principles across eight design areas.
Azure billing and entertainent is a first design area and
deals with the top two levels of alignment. As depicted
on the slide, it deals with billing and the entertainer
that it is encompassed by. Identity and access
management is another critical area that establishes secure access
controls. In addition to the focus
on authentication and authorization, it also caters to
separation of duties. A significant number
of enterprises have their own data center, which means hybrid connectivity
will be a requirement, resource organization
plans for how resource will be organized, and the use of
consistent patterns in regard to resource naming,
tagging and sufficient designs.
Scope of security transcends into all areas
of the Azure ecosystem, including network
and workloads. In addition to industry standards
such as NIST, Microsoft provides its own security
benchmarks and attestation.
Management is a design area led by cloud Ops team.
It focuses on business alignment and cloud management
through engagements with business stakeholders.
SLAs such as RTO and RPO can be agreed upon.
Governance is an iterative process. The team
plays an overarching role to focus on enforcement of
compliance security requirements. For the last design area,
platform automation and DevOps the cloud platform team
drives automation should lead the way for the adoption of
infrastructure as code options. One piece of information
that will help up to this point is that on a higher level, there are
actually two types of landing zone. Platform landing zone centralizes
the shared services that are generally considered foundational example,
networking and identity. Application Landing
zone is the second type of landing zone and this is where subscriptions for application
workloads reside. To create isolation
between Internet facing and internal
workloads, Microsoft recommends subcategories.
They've chosen the name online for public and corporate.
For private workloads, this slide provides visual
insight into how Microsoft advocates architecture
for landing zone at the highest level. There are
four management groups aside from the first two,
platform and application that I've already talked about. The third
management group is for subscriptions that are intended to be retired or decommissioned.
The fourth management group is sandbox.
The primary reason for having a dedicated management group
is to isolate sandbox subscription from all other types of subscriptions.
To take the conceptual architecture of Azure
landing zone to reality, Microsoft provides accelerators.
The accelerator is the most efficient way to implement the landing
zone. There are actually three ways to perform the execution
azure portal bicep, which is Microsoft's own
domain specific declarative language and the third option being
Hashicorp's terraform. Out of the
three implementation options, I'll focus in on terraform because as
infrastructure as code tool, it is a huge presence in enterprise,
among other reasons. Because enterprises are increasingly heading
towards a multi cloud strategy. To Microsoft credit,
they have published modules for the landing zone
in Terraform's public registry as well as in GitHub.
There is detailed documentation that provides guidance from simple to
advanced use cases. For the landing zone, the execution
has been done how the landscape looks like
I realize this is a busy diagram, so let's focus
in on few areas that kind of ties back to the stock.
Notice the four high level management groups, platform,
application decommission and sandbox. Then within
platform you have those three shared services,
identity management and connectivity.
For example, in this case, connectivity is doing the hub and
spoke model and then you have the identity subscription
here. Similarly, your application workloads reside
under this management group. As depicted
here, the subject of cloud reduction
framework and azure landing zone on an enterprise scale
is an expensive topic. Given the breadth
of this topic, I hope I've been able to give you a condensed flavor.