Hi, I'm Josh Stella. I am a chief
architect here at Snyk. Prior to that
and presenting at Conf 42 in the past was
the co founder and sometimes CTO, sometimes CEO
of fugue, but now Fugue has joined sneak and we're
building some awesome stuff. So I get to
go back to designing computer software, which is what I'm
most passionate about. Okay, great to be back here
at Conf 42. The topic
today is understanding cloud.
Cloud. Cloud cloud control, plane compromise
attacks to prevent these,
a methodology of how to think about the
problem so that you
can hopefully not be one of those folks who end
up in the news. Right? None of us want that.
All right. The cloud fundamentally changed
computing security, and it did this because it
is software defined. And when
you fully automate something and make it software defined,
it has very different behavioral characteristics
than a kind of a manually assembled
pile of atoms in a data center, right?
You can bring things into existence and modify them nearly instantaneously
out of this effectively for most people,
infinite pool. So it
really changed what you're securing the lifespan of
the things you're securing. It changed the
amount of time you have to secure them,
right? So in the data center we had,
we bought boxes, we stacked them
with humans, we ran cables with humans,
right? And therefore, it was relatively static
and persistent. So fairly
normal recapitalization cycle would be three or five
years. You buy a new switch, and in somewhere
between three and five years, youll look to the replacement for that
switch. That's the upgrade. The same with a server
or a network attached storage device or whatever.
But these were long lived static entities
relative to cloud.
And as a result, we gave them names, right. Whats were like
permanent names. There was
typically a team that owned those assets in
terms of making sure theyre kept running, had adequate
power, had HVAC, had working with these
security team, the correct defenses around them.
Typically defined in the network, right? Typically defined
as, I mean, you had some operating system level stuff too, of course,
both in terms of hardening guidelines and in terms of software you'd
run to secure servers and anti malware
stuff and things like that. But a lot of it in the data
center era was TCP, IP based defense in depth,
based on the network with devices,
devices like firewalls and intrusion detection systems,
all these colorful one and two U units in your racks
coming out of security companies,
the scale, even in big data centers,
typically thousands of components, as opposed to tens
or hundreds of thousands or millions of components.
And by component, I mean something screwed into a rack,
not every chip on every board. And the services were
pretty simple. When you
look at these services that a data center offers
to a business unit or an application development
group, they tend to be big chunks like compute,
which might be defined as virtual machines or containers, but some
kind of compute, some storage, typically block storage,
right? So your
application is defining how that block storage is used,
right. It's a disk,
remote or local.
There are network services around DNS, et cetera.
But even if you were operating
in an environment with a lot of these things,
monitoring services, what have you, theyre probably in
the teams, I would argue,
and the big ones are a handful.
Compute, storage, network are the really big ones.
Well, okay, let's look at the cloud and how different this
world is. So when you were procuring resources
for the data center, it was a hardware procurement cycle. You had
to ship things made of metal around in
the cloud. It's software defined from a user perspective,
right? It's an API call away. Now, there's still a
box made of metal, but it's already sitting there at Amazon or
Microsoft or Google or the real cloud providers.
Because it's software defined, that means it is expressed
in the form of API, and that means it's programmable.
And we know what that means, right? When you can program something.
Well, first of all, your mistakes can be much costlier, much faster.
Your errors are executed at the
speed of electrons firing across
circuits, not at the. You don't have that. Wait a minute, maybe I shouldn't do
that, right? It's programmable, so you
can fully automate things. But you can also use
decades of knowledge about programming
and computer science and software engineering to
make things right, to check
things, to test things. It is dynamic and
ephemeral, particularly if you are using truly
cloud native patterns, immutable infrastructure,
serverless functions,
containers if done right.
So where you had a box that you
would slide into a rack and name Frodo in the past,
now you have an instance or a container or a serverless
function. Whats comes and goes in hours, minutes or
seconds, it never gets a name. It just has to join
some service group and become aware of its
role while it is needed.
There's no friction here. There's very little friction here.
And because of that, the developers
own a lot of this stuff. They build a lot of these stuff.
My background is as a developer and as a software
architect and not as a
data center operations person or a security person.
Those folks don't tend to out of the
gate know as much about code as developers, which is natural,
right? That's because of how the data center worked. But in
the era of cloud security, this stuff is all programmable.
If humans can put an API on something and
program it and automate it, we're going to do it.
And the cloud is kind of that for infrastructure. So you
end up with developers, maybe not the ones living in the application
development teams, maybe living in the security team,
maybe living in the dedicated DevOps team or platform
engineering team, owning how
this cloud infrastructure is created,
maintained, configured, et cetera.
And the scale, I mean, at what was fug
is now Snyk becoming sneak cloud, which is,
I don't have any announcements today, but we're working on some really cool
stuff. We manage millions of
resources for our customers, resources being like,
again, not chips on boards, but servers,
databases, network definitions, et cetera.
There are a lot more objects. They're coming and going much faster,
right? Dynamic and ephemeral and much
bigger scale. And on top of that, there's more diversity
of what they're made of, of what types they are.
So in the data center, we primarily had storage,
compute, network, and then there's a bunch of other stuff too, but it's kind
of along those lines. In the cloud, you have like how many different completely
cloud service provider managed databases are there at Amazon,
a dozen. Those are abstractions
where the database is just directly accessible,
DynamoDB, RDS,
et cetera, at Google,
bigtable. And the cloud providers are
coming out with more of these all the time.
And it's an imperative for them, it's a competitive imperative for
them. So when you're thinking about security,
you're no longer just thinking about TCP IP packets traversing
networks that lead to compute and storage. You're now thinking about
how does this container that only lives for two
minutes access that database? And by the way,
it is completely a separate control
plane than the TCP IP network.
So at the bottom, traditional security doesn't work or
scale well in the cloud.
Hackers also started acting differently concurrently with
the rise of cloud.
So you never
know in this kind of scenario. Well, let me say I don't know in this
scenario if it's coincident or causal.
However, the behavior has definitely changed. And the
kind of pre cloud era was
really the most common attacks,
successful attacks. The attacker would pick a target,
they would search that target for vulnerabilities, and then often
they would end up doing a low, slow exfiltration,
maybe things like outbound DNS requests containing
little bits of the database they wanted to extract.
And that is kind of the Hollywood version
of a hack, right? And a couple examples
of these, the Sony motion pictures hack that
North Korea did, right, Sony was targeted because they made
a movie that the authoritarian
government in North Korea felt was insulting to them.
And so they hacked all the executives'emails, they went after
Sony in particular. We are seeing much less
of that type of approach now.
It still happens for sure. But the
much more common methodology
of the hacker these days is to first
look at public facing endpoints for
vulnerabilities. So it really doesn't matter who you are.
I mean, we know from the capital one breach that that's
how she discovered a vulnerability in capital one. She wasn't targeting
that bank, she was targeting anything with a vulnerability
to assemble a list for her. And this was done through automation.
Coming back to we're asking about programmable global infrastructure.
Now, youll need to be using it in its most
effective and rapid way and correct way
in order to build systems, compete, and stay safe.
But hackers are using it to their purposes, right?
So they'll search for vulnerabilities, get a list of these things,
of that list, pick a target,
and then very often do a very brutal,
almost instantaneous smash and grab exfiltration.
Just take all the data and go. And very often,
as was the case in the capital one breach, or in
two of the Uber breaches, this is stuff that the
exfiltration was not detectable on the customer facing
TCP IP network. It had to be understood in the form
of API calls.
So your traditional perimeter data center
security watching packets stuff would not help you
mean it might help you at the margins.
But if you look at all these breaches, the twitch breach,
capital one breach, et cetera, the Uber
breaches, the security
cloud security company whats got breached a couple of few years ago,
Imperva, their database got hacked.
When you look at them, there are some very common traits both to
what happened in the breaches and also how those
things are described incorrectly by the press.
Okay? And therefore people start thinking about the wrong things.
So in Twitch's case, this huge 125 gigabyte data
and source code leak, it says due to server misconfiguration.
Nonsense. Was a server that was misconfiguration involved
in these breach? Yeah, often there is, but that's not
why the hackers got 125gb of data from
them. It was due to a poorly designed set
of access controls and permissions based on identity.
No misconfigured server should be able
to connect and download all the source code for
all the applications you have, including some source
code from your parent company, Amazon. That is a design
mistake and there are probably a bunch of reasons for it,
but that is not due to a misconfigured server. You're going to
have misconfigured servers. You don't have to shoot yourself in
the foot with bad architecture. Okay,
capital one breach more complicated than it looks. People attributed
whats to a misconfigured waf yet again, the misconfigured server
was the foot in the door and the hacker didn't care about
that misconfiguration server. They went after s three storage,
which is an abstracted storage
service. The server didn't matter
that much, right?
So what these folks are doing is they're
going cloud, cloud control plane compromise attacks control plane.
What we mean are the APIs that
allow modification, creation, deletion,
read, describe operations against cloud
resources. That's what they're going after. They're going after endpoints
that are hosted by the CSP, by Amazon,
by Microsoft, by Google, using stolen,
typically credentials that they're getting from somewhere.
So that initial penetration, the misconfigured server,
who cares as long as that server doesn't
allow for discovery and movement.
All right, so if all the way on the left youll get into,
maybe you have a cloud misconfiguration, a dangerous port is left open during
a maintenance window. Maybe you have an application vulnerability
like log for shell or
something like this. Maybe as in the case of Uber,
if you get to GitHub, and I suspect this is probably
the case in twitch, that we don't know API
keys stored in source control repos and
that aren't rotated frequently like long lived API keys.
So that's the initial penetration, but then what's done with that?
The goal is always to get to a bunch of other stuff,
typically storage,
typically data persistence of one form or another,
databases, object stores, et cetera. That's kind of
the norm. And so the automated detection
of the misconfiguration that you've got this bot that's out there looking
for anything that has a certain version of
Apache running because it has a known CVE, or you have a bot that's
looking for public facing IP addresses
with port 22 open, or whatever it is,
it discovers it. You then get
a toehold in that initial penetration and then
you start exploring from there.
The vast majority of asking, as is the
vast majority of defense, is knowledge.
It's understanding what's dangerous,
understanding what's vulnerable and not making those errors,
and understanding what you have the hackers
is going to do discovery and movement, and that typically leads
to data extraction. I mean, there are other kinds of breaches
where Stuxnet was tapping the side effectively.
Through controllers of uranium centrifuges,
you can get defacement
kind of attacks like anonymous will
do, but most of the time, your economically motivated hackers
are going to tend to steal data
from you. Okay, so here
at sneak, we've identified among our
customers the ones who are really successful with this stuff,
five fundamentals of cloud security.
And for the remainder of this presentation,
I'm just going to walk you through these steps I promised you up front,
a methodology that would help you deal with the kinds of
threats I just described for the last 20 minutes or so.
All right, so these five fundamentals, there are really four
things youll do, four verbs here, and those are on
the outside edges. We'll go through them one at a time. And in
the center is this big noun. Policy is code. Policy is code
is because the cloud is software defined,
is programmable. We can express security
not in Excel spreadsheets and lists of rules in
English or French or whatever human language you speak, but literally as
code, as executable code. And this is a
massive leap forward for security. So policy as code
is essential. It is the method by which
these other things are accomplished and by which you can secure your
systems. If you're not doing policy as code,
the hackers are faster than you because they're doing exploitation as
code. So you can't use
those old manual processes. Okay? So step one,
know your environment.
Much easier said than done, especially when a
reminder, you've got these dynamic and ephemeral resources,
and there are hundreds of thousands of them in a medium to
large cloud environment.
But that's just at any one moment in time.
They also went through the software development lifecycle
to become deployed assets. And so as you think
about this, you have to understand in all the contexts
if you want to understand what's safe and unsafe.
So, for example,
we know from a department of justice filing
that in the capital one breach, s three list permissions
were left on to a running virtual
machine with a set of Im API keys.
Well, you have to have list permissions for s
three. Somewhere in youll organization, like when I go to the console
or whatever it is, humans need to be able to see what's
out there, right? But you really don't want a
public facing asset, compute asset,
a container or a virtual machine,
even a serverless function, to be able to just get a list of
all the locations in s three, that's extraordinarily dangerous.
It's only dangerous because of that combination of things in these context,
a compute instance, whats has those resources that is connected
to the Internet. Okay,
so you've got a number of dimensions here. Youll have to know
at any given moment in time the state of everything, the list of everything
and what it's doing and its current state. And then you have
to track change over time if you really want to understand what's
going on. And by the way, the hackers do this,
right? They are really good at
discovery. That's why they are good at hacking the
successful ones anyway. Okay, the next
step here is to prevent error. And that
may sound a little strange,
but the only way you're going to
get in front of cloud security issues
is by changing the way you build software,
okay? You can't put devices
on the network to solve the problem.
The imperva breach. Another example, using identity.
All right, so these are design issues, these are architecture
issues. And what that means is you need to be using
policy as code to check things like
infrastructure as code, like terraform templates or cloud formation
templates before they're deployed, and give those
developers who are writing that code the
feedback that lets them act on things and prevent
those errors from getting out there into the
live system. And this has to be integrated into
the CI CD pipeline. Okay?
If you really want to make this a practice,
if you really want to get safe and secure on cloud,
a big part of your effort is integrating your security tools.
And of course sneak does this with all of our tools,
not just these cloud oriented ones, into that CI CD
pipeline for prevention and to
educate the people building things. That's a nice side
effect of that. All right?
And this gets to empowering your developers. So in
one of our customers, there are over
2000 application developers
in the various business units writing new
applications for running their
business. And the cloud security team and the platform team
is like three people, all right? So when
you have that scenario, and everyone does,
whether they're fully aware of it or not, I guarantee you this is
what's happening in your organization is the majority of people
by a very large margin are much
more concerned with shipping software and hitting quarterly
numbers or mission goals or whatever,
if you're a business or a government entity,
than are concerned with securing it. And what that means is
the security teams need to act more chief architect and
provide their knowledge
in a way that can be absorbed naturally by
the people building stuff, which means in an automated way,
right. So IAC security looks which give
feedback in the code editor through the CI CD pipeline.
You need to provide the knowledge, the guidance as to
what's secure, what's insecure, but not in emails and
not in written form. You need to do it as policy, as code.
So when they're actually building a system,
your developers are building a system.
Their tooling are telling these when they're making errors,
and of course, complete integration to the DevOps
workflow. So right away if you look at
our five, first one is know your environment, and then immediately we're
going to prevention and secure design,
and then to empowering the developers. So this
is all the things we've shown so far contribute
to stopping digging the hole that you're
currently digging in your organization, right? It's stopping future
mistakes from being made.
And all of this is being done with policy as
code, as the mechanism. And if you're not doing this with policy as code,
it really comes apart at the seams. It really becomes vastly
less effective because the
scales we're operating at and the short time frames in
which we're operating necessitate
automation. If there is any human in
the looks, what you are doing is slowing yourself
down to being slower than the hackers,
and you will lose. So this really needs to be
expressed as code and then measure what
matters. How much risk are you taking? This is going to be
different for every organization. Okay.
There are very small data sets that exist. You might have some
that are extremely damaging in terms of the
blast radius if they were to be exposed. And there are very large
data sets that don't matter that much.
So you need to be measuring what matters.
As you're fixing stuff in your cloud
environments, you need to be quantifiably tracking that.
I mean, that's one of the things we spend a ton of time on,
is giving you that ability to know kind of where was I? Where am I?
How am I doing? What's the list of stuff we've accomplished?
And of course, investment is a big piece
of this as well.
And this acts as a virtuous cycle.
Right. Policy as code is the facilitating
technology. But as you go through this and measuring
what matters that contributes back to understanding youll environment
and back around the horn,
we hope these five fundamentals
are helpful to you. It's a very complex topic unless
youll kind of start breaking it down.
We are having on May 5
a cloud security masterclass. I will be hosting that
with my Fugue co founder, Andrew Wright.
We also have some really cool resources for
you over on our website. Fugue co resources
the state of Cloud Security 2021 is the
last big market survey we did.
We do this every year on the state of cloud security.
There's tons of interesting stuff in theyre, and then
we also have an engineer's handbook
on cloud security, which is a great place to start for
engineers. And you can also, of course, find in
resources there a lot of classes we've taught, videos,
et cetera. So I hope this was useful to you in
understanding cloud cloud cloud cloud
control plane compromise attacks fundamentals as a
methodology to try to prevent bad design,
and bad design is the principal enemy in cloud
security. So thanks much for your time.
I'm around to take questions. Take care.