Everyone. In this presentation we'll talk about
how the history of software engineers has
and will continue to shape the improvement of in
practices. Then we'll introduce newer concepts
like environment as code that will help further
the craft of managing infrastructure beyond
infrastructure as code my name is Ada Shah.
I am the founder and CEO at Zlifecycle.
We as software industry has always learned from
other industries like Waterfall, who remembers?
Waterfall came from construction,
lean came from how Toyota used to do their
production and still do it.
And we are learning how to handle software incidents
from industries like airlines. This has
helped us grow and helped us
improve as an industry.
In this talk, we will look at history of software engineering
as overall and then we will see what
of these practices have already helped us manage infrastructure
and how we can evolve this into using
other aspects. We'll start with version
control, which around 1970s is when
we started using that. I can't even imagine
a world without version control now, but back
in the days, the latest code used to
be on an engineer's machine.
After that we'll talk about deployment pipelines around
1990s 1991 is when we started
using deployment pipelines that gave us more predictable
deployments. Then we'll
talk. But microservices around 2005
is when we realized that we need to start breaking our
monoliths into smaller services to gain
faster feature lead time.
Taken around 2013 ish we started
using continue. We'll look into that and how
that helped software engineering and taken how that
can be applied to managing infrastructure.
From there on, Kubernetes is what became the
de facto orchestration engine.
So around 2014 we started using
that and then let's see how we can apply the same
to infrastructure. And then the latest
one here is Gitops. Around 2017 is
what it came in, and then from there on we started
using that to deploy applications. And then we'll see
how that we can use to deploy infrastructure.
Before we get started though looking at those aspects,
let's define what an infrastructure as code is, because the
first three topics that I mentioned in the history are
all achieved through infrastructure has code.
So I'm sure you all know what infrastructure as code is.
It just helps us automate provisioning of infrastructure resources.
It is one of the key DevOps practices that enables
teams to deliver infrastructure rapidly
and reliably.
All right, so before version control became ubiquitous,
determining the latest version of an application might
be a matter of asking what code is on an
engineer's local machine who deployed
it last. We realized this is unreliable,
error prone, and makes collaboration difficult.
Version control has allowed application code
to scale and engineers to collaborate better.
Infrastructure continued to be managed manually long after
application code left those days behind,
whether from a cloud provider's UI or
the command line from developer's machine. Managing infrastructure
manually makes it difficult to make changes or
troubleshoot regressions. Infrastructure as code made
it possible for infrastructure changes to be stored in version
control, and it has saved engineers the toil of
tracking the current state of your infrastructure
and made troubleshooting easier. As you
can see here, you should put everything in source control,
even your bash script if you're using once in a while,
and then make it available to everyone so that anyone
in your organization can see how their infrastructure
is deployed.
Initially, it was not uncommon for applications
to be deployed with a bash script, or even manually copying
from a team member's laptop with
tests run ad hoc, if at all.
The frequent and reliable deployments of today
were made possible through pipelines that have continuous
integration and deployment.
So this helps stabilize and made
those deployments of your application more predictable
and repeatable.
ISE has also benefited from the use of pipelines.
With pipelines, infrastructure changes can be tested,
deployment becomes repeatable and auditable,
and managing dependencies and secrets is made easier.
This diagram shows an evolution
from running infrastructure as code on an engineer's
machine to a shared environment using pipelines.
Let's dig deeper into an ISE pipeline.
So as you can see on the left, we have the continuation
integration bit, which means that
we can run some static analysis against the ISE.
We can run any unit tests,
see if those things pass before pushing
our changes. After that's
done, we do testing
and validation, and for that we can provision temporary
environments using ISE, run compliance
tests, integration tests,
any security checks that you want to have, and any smoke tests.
This gives us confidence that our changes will work in
production. And then if that works, then we
go to the last step. These is we deploy those changes and
provision our infrastructure in production, and then
we run some smoke tests to validate that production
is what we want. So this is how
we have been using pipelines with infrastructure as code to
achieve more reliable provisioning of infrastructure.
As applications grew more complex,
deploying the entire application as a monolith can
become a bottleneck to continuous delivery. A bug
in one part of the code base or infrastructure prevents
the entire application from deploying.
Domain logic and tech stack decisions are
often tightly coupled throughout the code base.
Because it's all a monolith
code base, you have everything deployed
as a single unit. They all are tightly coupled,
so you can't use different technologies. There teams
began being monolith applications into smaller
self continue components or microservices that
could be managed and released independently. This helped
them go to market faster, reduced the feature
lead time, and it
made working with applications more efficient.
Similarly,
basically here's an example of monolith to microservices.
If you have a retail application where you have
a website that allows people to
list down products, they can check out, they can make payments
or billing, has shopping cart aspects,
you have the monolith application on the left.
And then with microservices architecture you
can start being those into separate services. You can even have
your UI layer or data access layer and all
of those as separate services.
The same can be said for infrastructure. Using a
single infrastructure has code like terraform
to deploy all the infrastructure needed becomes complex
and hard to maintain as you scale. To avoid
that, we started breaking the IAC into various pieces
which help with collaboration and reduced feature lead time
for infrastructure breaking ise into loosely
coupled components, taken it easier to understand and
maintain it. So here's an example where you,
let's say have a monolith infrastructure as code, where you have
your networking platform, EC two and
s three bucket and database and all of that together in
a monolith with this. If you run your
terraform, you have a single state file. If you make any
changes, you have to run that again and again
and that becomes slower as you scale.
So in case of micro IAC, you basically break
each of these components into separate terraform
runs. So you would have a separate networking which
you would run separately. After networking
you would run, let's say your EC, two instances,
terraform or Kubernetes terraform or postgres
terraform. And then after that you would run your kubernetes
add ons terraform. So breaking these separately
allows you to have these loosely coupled
components and you can make a change to one, just run
that and have a more efficient way of provisioning
infrastructure.
So this has been working great, right? Well,
not actually, because ISE
is powerful and crucial tool.
However, if you have ever managed many divergent
environments, something like this one where
you have your networking separate and you
have bunch of these different components with your databases, let's say you have sage
maker, let's say you have kubernetes, clusters and
s three buckets and all that with
existed tools, you know, there is still a long way,
a long road ahead in improving developer
effectiveness with infrastructure as code.
And that becomes painful.
So here's how you would actually provision an
environment like that, using existing
tools, you'd basically hand roll pipelines. So write
a lot of logic in your
jenkins or Circleci or whatever pipelining tool that you are
using and that logic will basically run your various
ISe components and then you'll manage that complex
dependencies within the pipeline. So while your ise
is declarative and idempotent, these pipelines are
not. You have to write a lot of custom code to provision an
entire environment. So for example, logic for executing
networking layer first and then executing the
Kubernetes layer and then kubernetes add ons layer,
all of that logic needs to be written in your pipeline.
Code tear down must be supported as
well. If you have any failures that impact the environment,
you need to account for that as well. And a
lot of that just comes down to then manually solving
these problems outside these pipelines. So as you
can tell, these options are inefficient, costly,
and typically it requires a dedicated team.
Again, we are talking about more complex
environment deployments. If you have a very simple setup,
you don't need to worry about that. Just having some
simple IAC and a pipeline would do the job.
So since infrastructure as code is great,
it helps in a lot of ways, but has becomes limiting as
we scale. We need to start thinking beyond infrastructure
has code. We need to start thinking how we can use
infrastructure as code for things that it's powerful for.
But how can we add on things on top of that to
help us achieve scalability,
achieve something in production that is more efficient.
So that's when code the right side of
this history of software engineering. So there are other
practices taken, version control, deployment, pipeline and
microservices which we are already using in infrastructure.
How about using the other practices that are out there like
continue or package managers or kubernetes?
That has worked pretty well with applications and Gitops,
that has worked well in recent years.
So now we'll look at those practices and how they can
be applied to manage infrastructure, and we will use
environment as code as a mechanism to achieve
those. So before we dig
in deeper there with those, these, let's actually define
what environment has code is. It is an abstraction over
infrastructure as code. So you're still using infrastructure
has code under the hood. This provides a
declarative way of defining an entire environment.
It works well with a control plane that manages the state
of the entire environment, including any relationships between
various resources. It detects drifts as
well as enables reconciliation. It supports best
practices like loose coupling, item potency,
immutability, et cetera for the entire environment.
ESC allows teams to deliver entire environments
rapidly and reliably at scale. I know it was a
long definition, but I think it was important to kind of read through it.
So now that we kind of define what environment as code is,
and we'll look into it deeper as we go into these
various topics. So let's come back to
one of the practices that has worked well for us in
software engineering, working with applications. So yeah,
the adoption of microservices made managing individual
services easier, but added complexity to application
dependencies. Managing dependencies between various
microservices can put even a most robust continuous
delivery pipeline to the test. This makes
deploying an entire application environment a
pain point. Similarly for infrastructure
as code. Code creates complex
dependency graphs that can be difficult to navigate.
So several tools have gained popularity after
microservices because they help simplify complex
deployments. Containers is one of
those tools that helps organize dependencies so
that an engineer doesn't deploy a
server and then deploy their applications along with that.
On top of that, helm charts
and customize taken that concepts even further.
Serving has package managers for a suite of many
services. So these tools have kind of helped us
improve developer effectiveness and
helped us deploy to production with more confidence.
Similarly, environment s code applies
the same concept to an entire environment by packaging
all components within an environment,
along with the dependencies between those components.
Let's look at how that an example code
for environment as code looks like. But before we
do that, let's kind of just at a high level show the difference between
environment as code and infrastructure as code.
So infrastructure as code automates various Lego pieces.
If you take the Lego analogy, you have various
pieces which in this case are infrastructure resources
or could be a group of them. Infrastructure has
code automates those and is good at doing that.
What environment S code does is it automates how
those various Lego pieces are connected to make up a
Lego toy, which is where the most value
is. Getting your entire environment, your databases,
your networking, your kubernetes,
clusters or EC, two instances or s three buckets. All of that
together is more meaningful and useful
to a product teams.
Now let's dig a little deeper into provisioning workflow
using environment as code. So as we can see at the top,
you declare your environment as code, and we will look at an
example in the next slide. Once you push that to your source
control, there is a control plane associated with
environment as code that picks up the change. It sees there
is a drift because you're doing it for the first time or maybe there is
a drift on an existing environment and it starts reconciling.
But it also manages state for your entire environment.
So all these dependencies that are there and what their status
is so that you can make intelligent decisions
or make provisioning as and when needed.
From there on, control plane kind of starts reconciling
stuff at the top node, like networking, being here
first, then your Kubernetes cluster, your postgres database
or Kubernetes add ons after that. So control
plane runs these various infrastructure as
code components in the right order.
As you can see in that box it says terraform. And each of
these boxes, the networking, the platform
kads and postgres and all of these are terraform
code that have their own state. But what environment
s code does is it also maintains state at an environment
level because you want to know what's the state of the entire
environment and how those various pieces are connected.
So yeah, here's an example. This is our custom format,
so you can use other formats as
well. So as you can see from the top we are
using custom resource definition, the Kubernetes custom resource definition.
And as I mentioned, this is our format. So at the top we
have your environment name, your team name,
some other parameters. But as you can see
that we have various components,
various Lego pieces that make up the
entire environment as part of this file.
And then you will see here on line 54 and 55 that
each component will have a type. In this case we have terraform as
a type because we are using that to provision platform
eks. And then you also can specify dependencies.
That's how you kind of tie everything together.
So in this case, eks depends on networking.
So this allows you to define an entire environment.
This allows you to push things desired state to code
to source control. And then environment has code kind of
picks it from there and then provisions your environment by going
through these components one by one in the right order.
So with increase in microservices adoption, it became clear
that containers make it easy to manage
those microservices. But then we had the container
orchestration war that Kubernetes won and became the
de facto orchestration tool. Kubernetes made
it easier to manage microservices. These applications,
especially due to its controller pattern that watches
the state of your cluster, then makes changes
where needed to bring it to the desired state specified
in the code. So it does a lot of those things
for you and makes it easy to manage.
Environment s code applies the same logic to infrastructure using
the controller pattern from Kubernetes Environment
s code has a controller that tries to move the
current state of these environment to the desired state in
the code. See in the diagram that we have
the desired state. On the left we have a control loop. It kind of
observes and detects drift and tries to move
the desired state to the current state. Current state
to the desired state. And then there is this reconciliation aspect
there as well. With environment has code though
we would recommend having an approval step that
shows you the plan first and you make a decision and
taken this is based on what?
Because you might have some destroyers there, right? You might be destroying something.
And especially if you have a database, you don't want to just destroy
anything without actually checking the plan and
approving it. So this
is how applying Kubernetes concepts and
using Kubernetes to provision infrastructure helps.
Yeah, we looked at this, but quickly. This control panel
part is what we were talking about just now. This control
panel running in Kubernetes helps you do that
drift detection and reconciliation and allows
you to bring back your environment if
they are out of sync from your desired state back to the
desired state.
So far we have talked about improvements made to close the
gap between an engineers, an engineer
adding work to a code base, and that
code base working and scaling in production.
Turning to code submission itself as a
tool for deployment is a natural next step.
Kubernetes has already replaced a large
portion of deployment pipeline logic with declarative
configuration. Gitops on this
concepts Gitops as a concept
and it makes the entire deployment process configurable
in code. It uses the git pull request workflow
so that you can have a pull request, you can get it approved
from someone, and then once you merge
your changes, it picks it up and deploys those changes based
on once it's merged to trunk.
So here's a typical workflow from weaveworks
that talks about deploying
your changes using Gitops. So as you can see on the left
you have your dev environment. Let's say
you create a pull request, it gets approved and merged to
git and then it picks up the change. You run some CI
and then eventually you push your changes to container registry
and then from there it gets deployed to
your Kubernetes cluster.
Similarly you can apply Gitops for environment
has code. So if we start on the left, we push our environment
has code to a branch, we run some validation,
maybe some static analysis or best,
and then we create pull request. One of your team
members can approve the change or reject it and ask for
a change. And then once they merge the PR,
the control plane observes that repo picks
up the change and it starts reconciling and give
you your environment, your various infrastructure components.
So that's the talk.
Thanks for listening. The software industry
has made great strides in improving software engineering.
I'm hoping that things talk helped demonstrate
how we can continue to build on existing software engineering practices
to achieve similar gained in productivity
and performance with respect to managing infrastructure.
Infrastructure has code has already piqued the
interest of many teams. Environment has code
is on the horizon. Thanks everyone for listening.
Hopefully this was helpful. You can find related content
about the topic at the bitly link below.
Please feel free to reach out if you have any questions.
Thank you. Have a nice day.