Quantum machine learning is a research area that explores these
interplay of ideas from quantum computing and machine learning.
As you know, machine learning revolves around algorithms, model complexity
and computational complexity. Whereas quantum computers offers
parallel processing capabilities which are essential to build efficient
machine learning solutions, quantum phenomena such as superposition
and entanglement are helping the industry to build efficient
machine learning algorithms. Applications of QML QML
is becoming a base building block for many scientific
solutions on built on quantum computing.
The classification we can use for classifying nanoparticles
subatomic scale because here the data itself available in quantum information,
not a classical data and molecular modeling for drug
discovery and prediction, weather forecasting, geometrical differences
in recommendation space exploration, large language
systems like chat GBT. So when you hear
the quantum applications, you may wonder what are the techniques
offered by quantum machine learning these
days it is very fancy to prefix the word quantum in front of any technique
or any tool. So that's what first we look like when
there is a support vector machine, quantum support vector machine neural network quantum
neural network. But QML has their own approaches also like
quantum binary classifier and even the grower search algorithm
is one of the fundamental technique for most of
the quantum machine learning solutions. Quantum enhanced
reinforcement learning, quantum sampling techniques, quantum neural network,
quantum convolution neural network dissipative quantum
neural network,
hidden quantum oracle models,
explainable quantum machine learning quantum transfer learning and these
quantum generative adversary networks then fuzzy cognitive
mass FCM. These are all various techniques used for
QML based solutions. What are the
platforms or software tools available to build QML
systems? IBM Kiskit is one of the prominent
quantum computing framework. Kiskit has QML
libraries to build quantum support vector mission
nearest neighborhood neural network
and there are some special functions like ZZ feature map
and those Kiskit based
libraries are helping to build a
counterpart for their classical machine learning models.
And Xanado is having a special package
called Pennylan. Pennylan is can again Python package which can
be imported and installed in your Python environment. These connect it to
the various quantum computers and Pennyland
has more QML specific
functionalities functions libraries
to implement your quantum machine learning solutions.
And if you are from Tensorflow based classical machine learning
solutions, you can use Google's Tensorflow
quantum for building Tensorflow
quantum based QML solutions. Dwayve has their machine
learning libraries and then PYQL. They are offering grower
search based QML solutions. Apart from these
things there may be more framework
or software tools which I may not aware. If anyone knows, please share.
It is growing every day new libraries are coming. There may be many
advancements in the QML so you
might have found better QML solutions. Also. If there is,
please even I think qsharp is also having a QML
package and bracket. So almost
all quantum computing platforms have their QML
capabilities. You hear QML
is not the new technology. Even the research theoretical researches started 1995
itself. There is a biological inspired QML
work by CAN 1995, but in 2009
d wave demonstrated a QML capability to predict
cars in the digital image processing. In 2013
Google and NASA jointly started
quantum artificial lab. Then 2014 all
optical fiber classifier was built,
a perceptor model was built. Then powertrain
modeling and optimization of dual motor driving
systems for electric vehicle that also build in 2014,
2015 to 2018 multiple use
cases enhancements happened like train their probabilistic
generative models with arbitrary and
pairwise connectivity for handwritten image generation.
Traffic flow optimization using quantum annealer which
is then in 2019 2021
there are experimental demonstration of quantum speed up of
learning time of the reinforcement learning. Then quantum neuron
was built, even tensorflow quantum was released since
2022 multiple chain.
This timeline is not exhaustive. There are a lot
of new researchers,
papers are published and if you see the number
of papers published on QML, it is an exponential cow. The last
four years we have seen thousand 200
peppers per annum. So that is the growth
of QML. So QML is promising more
powerful and then efficient algorithms to
build quantum
systems which are utilizing these QML capabilities.
Thank you.