You. Hi everybody. Welcome CTO.
This talk at Conf 42. My name is Liran Haimovitch, and I'm
the CTO and co founder of Rookout. Today I'll be
talking about software understandability and what it means for us as
software engineers. I'm an advocate of modern software methodologies
such as agile, DevOps and Lean, which taught me a lot about understandability
and the importance of that. And before founding, Rookout spent about a decade
doing cybersecurity as a software engineer,
team leader, product manager, and group manager.
Rookout is a platform for live data collection and
debugging, and rookout lets you collect any type of data
on the fly with no extra coding,
redeployments and restarts. Working with engineers or
using rookout to debug various problems to learn more about their
software and CTO get things done, we became exposed the
concept of understandability, and understandability is
so very important. I'm sure many of you software engineers are
familiar with the mundane tasks of the basic
stuff, like read a JSON from file and parse it and
verify it, or solve a data structure.
And those are so basic stuff we've been doing since day one,
since the first lessons in intro to computer sciences.
And yet, if you gain the similar task in a very large system,
in a very complex system, sort a data structure within a
database or within an output, all of a sudden,
the same very simple task can take days or even weeks,
because there are so many intricacies and so many connections,
and quite often what's making it so complex. It's not even
that the task itself is complex or long. It's the fact that
you actually have to spend so much time trying to understand how
to do it, trying to understand where to do it, and trying to understand how
does it comprise with the entire system, and that's understandability.
How do we manage the complexity of the tasks? How do we walk our way
through it? I love this quote by George Bernard Chow where he's saying imagination
is the beginning of creates you imagine what you desire, you will
what you imagine, and at last, you create what you will.
Now, this quote is nowhere true, has much as it is in software engineering.
Imagination is truly the limit for so much of what
we can do. There is so much, it always surprises me how
much we can achieve using software engineering. And yet we get this report
by the DJ who's saying 68 of organizations experience flying
blind or trying slow. So while imagination might be the limit of
what we can do, sometimes we find ourselves achieving it very very
slowly, and that's a big problem. You either fly slow
because you're trying to keep things certain, trying to slowly understand,
or you fly blind without understanding, tracking potentially dangerous
changes without knowing the impact. This is where software
understandability comes into play. The term understandability
we draw from the finance industry, but it was originally about having
service providers such as insurance providers and pensions
funds empower their consumers to read the reports they're sending out.
And drawing upon that definition, we define understandability as
the concept that a system should be presented so that can engineer
can easily comprehend it, essentially how hard or easy it is for you
to understand the system in front of you. Now keep in mind, a software application
is comprehend of many things. Obviously you have source code
and that's the first thing you're going to think of. But there is so much
more that goes into creating an application as it makes into
having the application run. You have the configuration and state whether
it's stored in a database or in a file or anywhere else.
You have the runtime environment, whether it's a cloud environment. Youre have the
various node or Java functions that are running your application.
Are you using spring boot? Are you using micronaut? Are you running within a
weblogic server? There are so many different options,
as I'm sure you arent all well familiar with. Each of those
make a very significant difference to how the same code
plays out. We have the service dependencies, whether it's open
youre and closed source dependencies within our code, or it can be
other dependencies, other microservices within our organization,
or even third party dependencies such as stripe. Potentially most important,
hardest to predict inputs and outputs of the system. Our system
doesn't walk in a void, and the way our clients interact with
it are going to make a huge difference. Think about it. You're seeing an
endpoint that receives JSon as an input. That JSon can be virtually anything,
and only by knowing the expected input of the system can you truly
make sense of the function that handles that input. Only by
truly understand all of those five elements can we understand
our software and operate it and maintain it accordingly.
How do we know if a software is understandable or not? So there are four
criteria we're drawing again from the finance industry. The software has to be
complete. The information we have has to be complete. We need to have full
access, CTO, the source code to input examples and so on and so forth.
We need information to be concise. Just because there are a million lines
of code doesn't mean we can go tough, all of them. We need some sort
of summary, shorter presentations that we can go through. We also need
information to be clear. We need those summaries. We need those
snapshots to be made very clear. We obviously want the full
source code as well to be cleared and documented, and we want
everything to be organized. We want to be able to shift from the short
summary to deeper summaries to the source code itself. We want to be
able to easily shift from source code to input samples that show us how
it's going to be used and to example configuration that shows how it's going to
be configured in production. Once we have documentation on the system,
once we have the information about the system available in a complete,
concise, clear and organized manner, then we can go ahead and say
the system is understandable. You might be wondering about a few other terms out there
that you might have heard that might come to term, so let's think them
through. Understandability is closely related, but it's not
complexity. Obviously a more complex system is going to be harder to
understand, and a less complex system is going to be easier to understand.
And yet at the same time think about this way. I can provide you with
a script that Java application is going to be about reading a file.
I can either provide you with a jar. Ready? Here's the jar. Go ahead and
tell me what it's doing, or I can provide you with the jar and the
youre code and documentation and input examples. Obviously it's going
to be much, much easier to understand the same application with the full package,
even though it's just as complex. Second, we can think about readability youre
we want the source code to be readable of youre. We want the documentation to
be readable. And that's going to have a clear impact, a very big impact
on the clarity criteria which we've just defined. But just because
something is readable doesn't mean it's complete, doesn't mean it's concise,
doesn't necessarily mean it's organized. And there is much beyond readability to
understandability. And last but not least, we have observability.
Observability is a term used often to define how we
monitor the system in production. How do we know if it's up or down,
if it's serving our customers or not? And understandability goes a step
back. It's not about just whether the system is up or down, whether it's working
properly. It's about how it's working, why it's working, and what's
it doing all of those three elements very much interact with understandability
more often than not. By improving complexity, readability and observability,
we're going to improve understandability as well. But that's not always an
option and that's not always the best approach to improve understandability.
How do we go about improving understandability?
There are five key ways I like to point out for improving understandability.
The first, which I kind of briefly touched on, is minimizing complexity
by creating a less complex application that is going to be less to understand,
making everybody lives easier from the first time we were
introduced to software engineers through any experience,
everything we're taught in many ways is but minimizing complexity.
So you start out by cutting back on requirements. The less you have to
do, the less complex it's going to be. This applies to both functional requirements,
what the system is going to do, as well as to nonfunctional requirements, how it's
going to do it, nonfunctional requirements such has availability, security,
performance, arent all going to have a significant impact on complexity as well.
Hire the best developers. Better developers are going to find simpler
solutions to the same problem, reducing the complexity of the solution.
Utilize the highest level building blocks by using cloud,
by using open source software, by using prepared solutions,
you are offloading much of the complexity to somebody else and
creating a simpler, neater solution. Overall with better
abstractions, apply software engineering principles such as encapsulation,
such as abstractions are all there exactly for that purpose,
to minimize complexity and to make it more manageable. And last but not
least, practice agile and DevOps. Build a software step by step to
make sure you only introduce complexity where it's necessary and avoid
over engineering and over planning, while at the same time make sure
to reduce tech debt and keep the system understandable. Keep the system
simple as issues crop up. And by going through all of those five
elements, you're going to minimize complexity. Unfortunately, there is a big
drawback here. All of those are very, fairly easy to do or
fairly straightforward to do when you're developing a new systems, and you can take
all of those into account. But unfortunately, when you were working with an existing system,
one that has been around for 510 or even 20 years,
making those changes is so much harder. I mean, you can't cut back on requirements
on a system that has been written for 20 years, and you can't change the
engineering team who originally wrote it. Naturally, you can and
should strive to make those changes long term, even for existing software.
As long as you're tracking with it. But that's a much harder journey. So what
we can do is we can create knowledge, we can curate knowledge,
we can build the knowledge around what's already there to make it easier
to understand, to make the knowledge accessible. Start out by learning about
the system. Chat with your colleagues. Find previous engineers who
work on the system who formally walked in the system and learn from them.
Buy them a cup of coffee, read through the source code,
go through production, collect has much information as you can.
As you collect this information, make sure to document it, write it down,
record your conversations, whatever it takes, so that both for yourself
and for others, some of that knowledge is going to be captured in a way
that's easier to understand. And then go ahead and share
that information. Give talks, write it, create tutorials,
have meetups, whatever you need to do internally so that knowledge
spreads. And keep in mind that as you share the knowledge, youre probably going
to get feedback, you're going CTo get corrections, youre going CTO get new
insights and you might even get new questions that should be
answered. But over time, as you practice these three steps,
learning, documenting and sharing, you're going to create a body of knowledge.
And this body of knowledge is going to significantly help you handling
that complexity and making things more understandable. Third on our list,
we have development environments. Nothing allows us better to
understand things than blind able to take them apart and put
them back together in a sandbox. Now, development environments have a few important criteria
to make them effective. The first, you have to replicate your tech stack. If youre
using Java twelve in production, which you probably shouldn't because
it's not a long term support version. So let's say Java Eleven. If you're
using Java eleven in production, make youre to use Java Eleven in the development
environment. Don't go for Java 14 or Java eight. They're going
to behave differently. Use the same companies, the same open source,
comprehend the same operating system, use the same database, everything you
can replicate, replicate it. If you can replicate the scale, do that as
well. Second, use high quality test data. We've mentioned it before,
configuration, state, input and output.
The more youre can get them from the production environment,
the better it's going to be for you. The more you're going to learn about
how the system is actually going to operate rather than just running
the code with dummy data and getting results that may or may
not matter. Keep in mind that today, with compliance and security,
using production data for testing and development is a big problem
and there are ways to generate fake data and there
are ways to buy data and create it, but it's a
big problem for many of our customers. And keep in mind that this is not
a one time process. Environments drift as you introduce
new databases to production. As you make upgrades
to production, you have to make those in the development environments as well. As you
create new APIs, you need to make sure those APIs have input examples
has well, the way the software is used changes, you have to adapt the input
samples you use to reflect that as well. And overall, this can be quite
a lot of work, both setting up the development
environment and maintaining it. It can take a lot of effort,
but it's a great tool that will help you improve the understandability of
your software. Next, we have observability tools. As I mentioned,
observability tools show us the state of the system and not so
much exactly what it's doing and why, but it can definitely provide us
with some insights in what's going on that we can use. And so if
your organization uses observability tools such as logging,
tracing, metrics and error tracking, then you should definitely
ask to have access to them so that you'll be able CTO use them.
They're not going to provide you with all the information you need. But often if
you're asking yourself what's happening, a log or a metric or
an exception you can track, that can all provide you with some visibility
into what's going on and help youre make better educated
guests. Now last and definitely not least,
we have tools that are always there to help us
understand our software better. I like to categorize them as understandability
tools, but I guess most of you would categorize them as debuggers.
Traditional debuggers have always been about enabling us to
understand our software. You run your application and then the debuggers
allow you CTO take it step by step and see what's going on. They allow
you to go back and see what's going on. They even allow you to inject
variables, change values, and so you can literally explore
the application as it's running and truly understand its inert.
Unfortunately, traditional debuggers are not so good today
for many of youre environments. If youre working on kubernetes,
if youre working on serverless, if you're working on a very large monolithic applications,
if you want to see what's going on in production, traditional debuggers are
not going to be there for you. Fortunately, next generation debuggers such
as rookout allow you to take the debugger experience and
use it anywhere. Next generation debuggers support debugging
in kubernetes, in serverless, in production, regardless of the scale,
regardless of the size. Using nonbreaking breakpoints, you can go
anywhere you want and see exactly how your code is behaving. Now,
whether you prefer the traditional debuggers or the next generation debuggers,
those are definitely the best options for engineers
looking to quickly understand their software. And I think the biggest benefits of
that is how easy it is to set up youre can get started in a
matter of minutes and get real insight into existing applications
without overly worrying about what's going on. I hope this talk has
been beneficial for you. I hope you learned a bit about the importance of understandability
as well as what can be done to improve it and why you
should care. And I would love to hear from you whether on Twitter or
on GitHub. So please reach out to me and I would love to continue CTO
discussion and maybe show you a bit about truecode. Thank you very much.