Hello, my name is Joe Carlson and you
are here for an introduction to IoT Internet
of Toy. This is supposed to be a gentle introduction
to the Internet of things or like how to get started
with programming with hardware, with JavaScript
and Nodejs. What quick introduction?
We don't have a lot of time here today, but I thought, hey, my name
is Joe, I work for a company called MongodB and I'm a developer
advocate and software engineer. If you want to hang out with me, I'm going to
be posting at the end, but you can find me on Twitter. It's the best
way to get a hold of me. And actually this may be the first time
you see this, but I'm also on TikTok. Who knew?
If you want to follow along with any of the resources, include the slides,
recording of this video, any resources, and the code I use in
this deck. You can totally check that out at that QR code in the upper
right hand corner, or at that bitly link.
And most importantly, if I say anything controversial
today, just know that those opinions are my own and not my employer. Please don't
get me fired. And let's jump in here.
So what are we going to talk about today? First thing, I just want to
introduce IoT, like what is it? How do we use it? Then I want
to talk about why you should be considering JavaScript and node for your next IoT
project. I'm also going to be talking about a practical project
I recently built. It's my Internet connected smart
kitty litter box. What?
And then lastly, I love making wild speculations about the future.
So we're going to be talking about my predictions for the future of IoT.
So stick around if you want to check that out. You can
play this back in five years from now to see how embarrassingly wrong
I was about all these two, which is fun. So what the
heck is IoT? What is this thing? What is this Iot thing? Well,
basically it's just anything. It's basically anything you put a chip in.
Anything you put a chip in. It's just the Internet, but we put physical hardware
and stuff on it. You've probably seen a bunch of it.
Fitbit smartwatches, rings, google nests and homes, whatever,
right? But my favorite part about IoT,
it's the stupid shit. I love the stupid parts about IoT.
I love the weird little dumb project.
I love straddling that line between something that's kind of like totally ridiculous and
dumb and totally smart. I think that there is
actually kind of a new wave of art coming
about from Internet connected devices, and I think us as developers and programmers
are uniquely positioned to explore that space.
A lot of artists don't know how to actually do programming, but we do.
I think that that's fascinating. I think that's absolutely fascinating,
and I love exploring that line. I have a bunch of projects,
you can check those out on my website, joecarlson.com, if you're curious. We don't
have time to get into those today though. Okay, so why should
you be considering Javascript for your next IoT project?
Let's dig into it together.
So did you know that actually 58%
of IoT developers self identify as
node JS developers? What? It's huge. That's a quorum.
I think that's what that word means, but that's a lot of people, right?
I would also argue this is total opinion, but JavaScript
makes a great choice for new developers. A lot of developers
are coming out of boot camps and colleges are learning node and JavaScript. It's a
great language to learn. I know there's Python and Java heads all over the place
too, but traditionally embedded software
has typically been programmed with a lower level programming language like C
or C plus plus or now with rust. And these
are really difficult to develop for because you have to worry. But memory management JavaScript
has a garbage collector built into the language, so we don't have to worry about
that, and it makes it a great choice for new developers to pick up.
So if you want to learn hardware, JavaScript is a great place to start.
And you can build IoT devices, servers and full
service web pages on top of that.
Let's talk about updating. So traditionally with an embedded
device, you have to actually secure the actual device, plug it in,
and reflash that with a new code on it to get it updated IoT.
So with JavaScript, right, with JavaScript all I have to do is do a git
pull and NPM install and boom, it's done. If it's connected to
the Internet already, if you have a git client installed on there, which with a
raspberry PI is totally doable, it's mega easy to do updates.
Internet's already speaking JavaScript, this is my opinion. Right,
but why not just use the language you're already using for
speaking on the web and transfer to this new
frontier of devices? I think that's kind of exciting.
And did you know there's actually a vibrant ecosystem
of JavaScript tools, libraries and APIs available to
make hardware projects? The two big ones on the market today are Cylon
Js and Johnny five. For my Internet connected smart kitty
litter box, I'm actually using Johnny five. We're digging into that hello world
together as well. I wanted you to
think about a typical use case for a IoT device.
Typically what you have is some sort of Internet connected chip or hardware
that has a sensors out in the real world. And when that sensor detects some
sort of event, something happens. For example, maybe you have a luminescent
sensors that determines how bright something is. And when
it reaches some sort of level of luminescence, then you want to have something
happen, like a light bulb turn on or off or something like that.
But if you think about it, it's an event driven app
node. At its core is an event driven app programming
language, right? We use callback functions and promises, and now async await,
which is just async tactical trigger for promises, right?
But for handling asynchronous events that
are happening even on the front end, right? We have some sort of click
event triggers, a callback function to do some sort of thing.
JavaScript and Nodejs core structure directly
translates how we develop applications with hardware and
sensors. It's a perfect marriage,
honestly. Okay, that's a bunch of great reasons
why I personally think that Javascript is a great language for using it.
And there are other considerations too, like memory management, other things which
you might want to consider other languages for. But if
it's your first project, just do what you know, just go out there and try
it. Okay, my favorite part,
let's talk about my Internet connect litter box. I love
jumping into some practical projects while doing these presentations,
but what does things thing actually look like? Here's actually the real
finished product. I've got a little mid century fancy little box,
and you can see a little cable coming out of the back of that thing,
but it's actually pretty hidden in there, right? Like I said,
I'm obsessed with the stupid ideas, but I did some homework after I built
this, and it turns out this actually might Iot be a bad idea, right?
People actually are spending up to $500 on decently well reviewed
Internet connected smart kitty litter boxes. Mine's not quite as fancy as this,
but Iot could be with a little bit more effort, right? I don't
know, I think that there's something uniquely special about that. Okay, so what
does my box actually do? So how does this work?
There's a switch on the door, and when that lid is lifted
off it goes into maintenance mode. Maintenance mode basically means I'm either cleaning or
adding additional litter to the box. This basically means that the box weight
is going to be changing when this lid is open. So once I put
that lid back on, what I do is I have basically a really
fancy Internet connected bathroom scale. And what IoT does is
it reinitializes the base weight once that lid has been back on the box.
Then we do the waiting game and we wait for some sort of cat size
object to enter the box. I'm not smart
enough to determine if it's like an opossum or raccoon or whatever, a small
human, I don't know. But we're waiting for a small cats
sized object to enter that box. We're waiting for that weight to be
placed on the actual litter pad to detect it. So let's
assume we have an actual cat and it's detected in the
box. We have that weight gain on it. It does its business,
and it does two things. It takes a passive measurement of my cat's weight
and a timestamp of when that bathroom event happens.
So I can passively keep track of my cat's weight over time, and I
can keep track of the number of times he's using the restroom to see if
there is drastic changes over time with these health
indicators. Right. So once the cat has evacuated
the box, done as biz, what we do is we reset with a brand new
base weight of the box, and then we just wait for a new event,
whether it is a maintenance event or a cat or cat
size object entering the box. Again. Oh,
let's check out some code. Nice. All right, again, if you
want to check out all the code, bitly link or that QR code in
the upper right hand corner. So, hello world, it's our first thing we always
do with a Internet connected device or IoT device.
An IoT equivalent of a hello world is just making that dang
led blink. And this is actually my real pie, making a real led blink
with a real Johnny five code base just blinking on and
off. That's all we do. You can see my sensors and stuff all the side
getting ready to go, but we just have that initial making
sure everything's set up correctly. But what does that actually look like with the code?
So we're requiring our Johnny five package. Johnny five works a bunch of
different chips and cards and hardware.
So we're actually telling Johnny five, hey, you're going to be interacting with a raspberry
PI today. I said, okay, cool. So we want to initiate instantiate,
a brand new instance that board of a raspberry PI board. So we can start
working with that board in memory. And we have a callback function,
an event driven right. And when that board has been ready to start receiving
events, we instantiate a brand new led. And on the P
113, I have no idea what that is, but I have to google every single
time. Literally, I'm messing with a PI. But it's what GPIO pin
or the general purpose input output pins? Those basically allow us to
interact with the real world on a pie. But we're saying on
the 13th pin, on this pie, what I want you to do is just blink
on and off. Johnny five is a built in functions for leds
that can do a bunch of different stuff. But all we're saying is there's an
Led on the 13th pin. Make it blank easy.
Right? That's it. That's it. That's how you get
an Led to blank with Johnny five on a pie.
That's all it took. Super easy. Okay,
let's get to some fun stuff, huh? We gotta go through this again.
All right, let's make a toilet. So we got the hello world.
Our board's initialized. We good, right? We good. So what do
we do? We got to wait for our board to be ready. But all I'm
doing now, instead of an LEd, I'm using that switch, right? That magnetic
switch on the door that determines whether it's in maintenance mode. And when that event
is either open or closed, I just change the state of the application whether
it's in maintenance mode or not. So let's actually see things in practice. Sorry,
this is a terrible video, but it's all I got. I'm so sorry. So you're
going to see the little white thing on the board there. That's the magnetic switch
I got screwed into the side there. And I'm opening and closing the door.
And on my laptop, you can see that those open and closed events are being
triggered by Johnny five. Woohoo.
Right? Okay, here's the fun
part. I love this. I learned a lot. It's going to have to go fast,
so we only got 10 minutes left. I'm so sorry, y'all.
But load cells again, this is a fancy Internet connected
bathroom scales type things that measures the cat's weight. I actually couldn't find
a node package that could interact with the load cells I bought.
Whoops. But I did find a python package. And I've messed around
with a bunch of stuff for a long time, but I actually got to play
with the spongehold. Process nodejs function. It's a core
function, right? It allows you to spin off on a separate thread, other stuff
that's not even node. Right? I'm spinning off a python script from
the main event loop on a separate thread to
run this constantly. And what it's doing is this python
script. It just reads the weight
from the load cells every 10th of a second,
and you're sending that out as standard input on the python script, and it is
received by the process that spawned it on node as
data. And I just parse the int or parse the float,
and we update the weight for that thing every 10th
of a second, constantly reading it. You can
do error enclosed states, whatever, not a big deal, right? But the cool part is
using that spawn child process and mixing languages to get this actually work. It's a
little bit of a hack to admit, but it's super cool. And I love that.
I got to explain things for real this time.
Okay, so let's see what this looks like in practice. You can see the actual
piece of plywood has the load cells underneath of it. That's why we put the
box on. You can see here it's reading numbers. And I'm pressing
on there and I'll show you. Just a second. Press. Right,
press. And you can see that those weight measurements are being registered on my laptop
every single time I'm pressing on that board.
Not the greatest for you. I'm so sorry, but those load cells
are being received by our node application. So now we have the maintenance
mode, that switch, and we have that load cells registering weight from the
box. Awesome. What are we going to do with all this
data? What I'm doing is actually, I'm going to show you quickly an
IoT time series data. I'm saving this,
obviously in a MongoDB database because it works super well for IoT time series
projects. And I'm saving it in a time series project because typically if you think
about this, most IoT projects are being saved and
reported on some sort of dashboard, so you can see real time results of
whatever's happening. I'm doing the same thing. We have a web application that shows
you a real time stats of my cat's bathroom behavior over time.
I design the schema based on how I'm going to be reading that data,
and the time series makes a lot of sense. So what does it actually look
like with a MongoDB document? I'm glad you asked. We have a bunch
of metadata about what's going on, but I make a brand new
document in MongoDB every single day. And what
I'm doing is I have an array of events, right, that events thing there at
the bottom. And I'm keeping track of a timestamp and a weight and the type
of event that's occurring, whether it's a maintenance event,
a bathroom event. And I want to keep track of, passively keep track of my
weights, my cat's weight, and the time that he went
to the bathroom. And this can go as
much as possible, right? We're going to probably only have a couple
events per day. We're not going to have infinite amount, but the something's probably seriously
wrong. But this is a perfect use case for how I'm reading that data.
The other thing that works really well with this too, is MongoDB has a flexible
schema. So I added that additional door sensor to keep track of the maintenance
weight. I just updated that time series schema and it was
super easy. I didn't even care about the old data.
From now on, if I added additional sensors in the future, I would
just update the time series data. It takes literally seconds,
right? I don't have to worry about the old data. I can if I want
to. I could update everything else if I wanted to, but I don't have to.
And for a time series day like this, it makes so much sense that I
don't have to do that. Okay, let's see the whole
thing put together. Iot.
That raspberry got that
sliding doors back on and plug it in and you're done, right? I think it
hides away pretty good. It's pretty easy to see, and it looks great.
You could use a cheaper box if you wanted, but like, hey, I'm extra
and I wanted something fancy for my cat, so sue me.
There he is at the end. I added bribe matrix to sit on there.
There he is at the end. I added bribe matrix to sit on there at
the end of the photo shoot. Okay,
time for some wild speculation.
We're using to see smaller and more powerful hardware devices. I think this
is going to mean that we're going to see additional compute power on the edge,
which basically means right now what's happening. A lot of our devices are
sending the raw data back to a central server in the cloud somewhere
to actually process that data. I think we're going to actually see more of that
data processing happening on the edge in the actual IoT devices in
the field as they get more powerful. It's already happening.
I did it with this project, we're going to see a continued increase in that
happening. I think we're going to see Javascript more optimized for hardware
devices, right? Smaller, lighter, smaller footprints, easier to
run. I think there's incentive because there's just such a massive
developer community devoted to JavaScript that it's going to continue to
get more optimized for these specialty use cases. We'll see additional
hardware support. I already ran into this issue with the load
cells not working the way I expected them to. I think we're going to see
additional support growing in the future as more and more developers are
using node and JavaScript to interact with hardware. And lastly,
this is true for just hardware in general.
The batteries are and will continue to be the bottleneck. It will not be compute
power. As the devices get more and more powerful, we're going to
see continued reliance. It's going to get hotter and hotter and do more stuff,
and it's going to require more energy to do that. We're seeing but their cell
phones too, right? Like they're getting more and more powerful, but battery
life is not getting better. There's optimizations of software to make them
last longer, but it's still enormously difficult. And bottlenecks
continue to be on the batteries.
All right, we're almost done here, but let's say hypothetically,
I've inspired you to want to try but some IoT and some hardware
for your next project. How do you go about doing that?
I might have a weird brain, but how I do it, I just do it.
Get out there, pick a dumb project, just go buy a raspberry
PI flex $35 and just try making an led blink. Try making
a plant moisture sensor. Make something Google.
There's a ton of raspberry PI projects out there, but try to make one.
And every time you get stuck in something, just google IoT and try to figure
it out. I think the best way to learn how to do something is to
program and actually get your hands dirty. Also,
if you are planning on using a project, you should totally
check out MongoDB. It's so optimized for IoT
types of data, including time series data and schemas.
If you have any questions about things, stuff or want to chat about it,
Twitter is the best way to get a hold of me and I'd love to
talk about it with you and try to figure out your situation.
But I just want to say thank you so much for having me here.
I so much appreciate being a part of this community. It's incredible and I'm so
honored to be invited to be here. It's incredible. And I'm so honored to
be invited to be here. You again. If you want any of the resources I
chatted about, including slides, this video code,
whatever, you can check it out at that. And please,
please, best way to get a hold of me is on Twitter, so I'd love
to see you there and resources.
But thank you so much, everyone. You're the best. I had so much fun.
Hopefully to see you soon.