Welcome all to my presentation at Conf fourty two today.
What I want to talk to you about are the four reasons comp
1234, why digital transformations usually fail,
and how you can be successful. My name
is Zach Gardner. If you didn't already know, somehow I'm
the chief architect here at Keyhole Software. I get to work
with some amazing people day in and day out that help
solve real world challenges for real world applications.
We don't do embedded software, we don't do
guided missiles, none of that stuff. What I do is
I help companies digitally transform by
focusing on user centric applications. Now,
what that means to everyone is completely different. What that means for a hospital is
different than what it means for a utility company. But I've had the privilege and
the pleasure of helping different companies figure. But what digital
transformation means to them and how they can use that to
empower their customers. Full disclosure,
I'm not here to sell you a product. I'm not here to sell you
anything in particular. I'm here because I care about this
subject passionately, and I think that we as software practitioners
have really done a disservice of explaining what digital
transformation is and how it can positively
impact the lives of real people. This presentation
is a compilation of the things that I've learned. After doing this
two or three times, I kind of lose count on how many times
it's been. And what I hope you'll get out of it is
to understand how you can, I guess, not have
a successful digital transformation, but also how you
can have a successful one. So with
that, let's get started. Now, it seems like every
couple of years there's a topic that comes along that simply everyone is
talking about. Chat GPT seems to be the flavor
of the day. A couple of years ago it was microservices,
before that it was service oriented architecture. The list
goes on and on. In the past couple of years,
what we on the keyhole software side have noticed is that digital transformation
seems to be on the top of everyone's minds, all the way from the CEOs,
the CIOs, the CTOs, down to the managers,
the directors, the people leading software development teams.
And you can tell just from these clips that the
term digital transformation is becoming more and more ubiquitous.
Now. The industry has taken notice and
it seems like everyone is offering a service on
how to digitally transform your applications, how to digitally transform
your business. I can go on. And I can go on.
I actually have more slides that I didn't include in this.
The first reason why a digital transformation do
not succeed is because there is a fallacy
in how a lot of companies approach it.
There is no single tool that will allow you
to digitally transform your business. There's just not.
Every single business is unique. Every single business
has very specific constraints, specific things that it's good at,
things that it's not so good at. And even within a particular
industry or sector, one company to another can
be radically different. They can be neck and neck, number one and number two,
and they could do things entirely differently. How do you have
a single product that you can buy off the shelf
and customize to any degree that will somehow
work between these two and digitally transform
it? If someone tells you that,
it's because they're trying to sell you something. And what's funny
is that this fallacy is not specific
to this particular kind of transformation. In the years
that I have been the software development field, I have seen these
trends become, and I have seen these trends go.
But they all share one interesting characteristic,
the fact that there is always one particular way of
looking at the world that will somehow make everything better.
The oldest, and probably the first that I really dealt with was SOA,
to where we were going to have these beautiful services that completely
modeled our business. And all these services were going to interact
with each other, and somehow that was going to allow us to
compose applications on top of them and not have to
write any custom code anymore. Well, I think we
all know how that one went. The next one that I got to
was an enterprise service bus. Where? Well,
from SOA, we kind of figured out that there are all these different
business rules that need to be in the middle, and we
need to have some way of orchestrating calls from here
to here to here. We put the smarts out of the edges and
we put it into the pipes. Well, we all know how that went.
It got to be too complicated, and we didn't understand it anymore.
Well, what did we do next? We have microservices, and this
is the trend that we are seeing. Not to say that any of these
approaches that I've talked about so far are inherently wrong, in much
the same way that a hammer or a saw can't
be wrong. It can be applied to the wrong job.
It can be used improperly. But it in and of itself is
not necessarily wrong. It is how you apply it to
a particular problem. That's the part that I think we're
getting wrong in a lot of these cases. So with microservices,
we all know that these are independent services that
can go in and out of production at different cadences.
Theoretically, they could be written in completely different languages,
though kind of behind the curtain. I don't know if I've
ever actually seen that happen at any large organization.
It typically is pretty homogeneous, but that's a different presentation
at a different comp 42 for a different day. So we have
all these different services. They're talking to each other and they're
going, and they can communicate asynchronously.
They have high cohesion and low coupling.
Well, what happens is usually one
of these services goes down. We didn't properly plan for failure cases,
or what can also happen too, is we realize that our business
services, we've defined them a little bit too granularly.
So we actually need to combine microservices together in
and of itself. This is not a failure of microservices. What it
is a failure of in all the three that I've mentioned up to this
point, is the fallacy that somehow there's one particular
approach that will help us solve our problems. And it's a lie
that we keep telling ourselves over and over again, that even
though we've seen this never work before in the past,
we felt it. We have scar tissue. In some cases,
I'm talking but abortly, but we have scar tissue. We remember what it
is like. We always tell ourselves this lie, that sometimes
this new thing that I'm trying, it will be different. That if I just purchase
this one product, it will digitally transform me,
even though I have never seen that happen in the past.
And we tell ourselves, this time is going to be different.
That's reason number two. This time will not be different.
You are going to wake up exactly the same
team, exactly the same people with exactly the same idiosyncrasies,
the same worldviews. Everything about the teams that
you will be working digitally transform, everything about your customers that
you are trying to transform, they will be exactly the same.
This time will not be different. So what do we do?
We have to plan accordingly.
Here's the fun part. How do you do that?
How do you plan for a digital transformation where,
you know you're going to need to do something different than you're doing right
now? You're going to need to figure out different ways of thinking about things
that maybe you haven't thought about in the past? Well, first of all,
you need to define what a digital transformation is. And honestly,
if you've never jumped to it before, it's kind of like that
first year of marriage where raise your hand if you made a few mistakes during
your first year of marriage. I am very culpable
of that. You kind of have to figure it out as you go.
But we can look
for how other companies that have gone before us have done things and not
always emulate exactly what they've done, but try
to figure out why it is that they did the things that
they did, why they chose that path, and what
made them successful. And from that,
let's work backwards. Let's figure out how it works in our particular industry,
our particular business, our particular problem. So the first case study
that I want to bring up is DHL. They did
market research on their customers, and they figured out
what made their customers choose them instead
of one of their competitors. They tried a couple different things. They saw
some things that worked, some things that didn't work, the basics
of agile. In any given organization,
you kind of got to figure out what works and what doesn't work. One of
the things that they discovered was that people like to know where their
packages are, which, as someone who occasionally orders
things through DLL, excuse me, DHL, I can attest to,
but what people don't like is having to talk to
other people. We live in a digital age. We like to be able to
do everything that we possibly can on our phones.
I have very a couple of members of my family that if they
could get away with never talking to anyone other than their immediate family, they'd be
totally happy. So let's stop saying these people are wrong
and let's embrace it. Let's figure. But how to bring them into the fold?
How do we engage these kind of people? Because they're becoming
more and more ubiquitous. What DHL found was
if they create a chat bot, something on their website,
it can be both on desktop as well as mobile.
And that's an important point, because they found out most of their customers actually preferred
mobile. They could have the chat bot interact with
the user. The user could tell it, here's my shipping number. Can you
tell me where my package is? And it could even tell them where their
package was. They can schedule on demand deliveries
where you could say, oh, you're projecting it to deliver it on this
date, but I'm actually going to be out of town. Can you maybe deliver it
same day next week? Or is there any way you can move that delivery day
up? They could even have people, the chat bot,
generate QR codes for labels so that they don't
have to go to the post office, they don't have to take extra steps.
You know what's funny is when they did that, they found their customer
satisfaction scores increased and their
profits increased. People had a more pleasurable
time dealing with this new digitally
transformed DHL than they did with the previous ones. Now they're still
experimenting with new things. They're actually one of the companies that are really
on the forefront of using blockchain,
which in their particular domain, it makes a lot of sense. They have packages
that go all over the place, and having an immutable ledger
of where these current packages are, that's a pretty
compelling use case. But not every company is
going to be able to get away with a chat, but it really depends.
This is kind of a sneak peek of what I'll be talking about in a
little bit. It really depends on who your customers are,
where they are, what they want, and what you can do to
meet in the middle. Now, the second company
in this case study is Disney. They have done
a ton of work in the digital transformation sphere,
and I can attest to it. I was at Disneyland at the end of
2021. There were so many new offerings
that we almost had to find guides online to figure
out how to use all these different features, all these different
apps just to get in there and get in the park.
We found good tips about making sure that we had battery packs
and solar chargers and logging
into the same accounts ahead of time. Genie is one
of their best enhancements that they've ever done because it allowed us
as consumers to plan our day. We could say,
well, we know we have two little kids,
so they're going to get tired around noon or 01:00
so we're going to have to go back to the hotel. So let's figure out
how much walking we can do in the morning and what are
the rides that are closest to us that have the lowest wait
time? Because they were seven and
three at the time, my daughters, and we knew that
they would get bored really quickly if we were standing in a line.
Disney spent enough time to figure out that
that has one of the critical features that that was built into
the mvp. I'm sure that they have a huge laundry
list of things that are on their backlog that they could have implementing,
but because they understood their customers, they went through
and they only implemented things that were the absolute most critical
that would provide the best value. Disney, along with other digital
transformation features, they actually have a program that not
a lot of people know about where their executives have to spend time
every single year dressed up has a cast member, so you never
know if the person that you're taking a picture next to that's in a goofy
suit. I mean, not like Goofy has in silly,
but goofy as in Goofy, the character
that might be a vice president or a senior vice president.
They have to go and they have to live in the lives of
the people that they serve. They get to interact with the customers. They have
to stay in character all day. They get to really understand what
that experience is. Now, not every organization
has the luxury of doing that, and that's totally fine.
There is one, however, near and dear to the heart
of a lot of people that I work with, because they get gasoline from there
and they get pizza from there is Casey's.
Casey's, if you haven't noticed, has gone through a rebranding and
they're looking holistically at all the different aspects of their
business. And there are two things that they found in
particular that apply to a digital transformation.
The first is that they had a lot of different systems
that tracked their customers and none
of these systems were talking to each other. So they
drew a line in the sand. They said, we need
one particular platform, whatever it is,
where all of this transformation is going to be gathered, so that we can run
reports off of it, so that the light of the people that need to
do analytics and business intelligence aren't so painful.
They chose Salesforce, and I'm not being paid by Salesforce to
say this. I'll just say it's a very popular tool that I've seen a lot
of different organizations that I've personally worked with use for this particular
type of digital transformation. There's other ways of doing it.
You could have single pane of glass applications where even if
you have an EMR and an ERP and
a CMS, they all tie together and they all appear to the
user as one particular, very unique, very atomic
application. Even though under the covers it might be
retrieving data, it might be sending data,
it has that layer of abstraction that allows us as humans
to focus on one thing and one thing only,
and leaves it to the technology to figure out how to do
this kind of reconciliation. The second thing that
they learned is that once they had all this information,
what are the things that their customers really care about? You know
what people at Casey's really like even more
than gas that is cheap, they really like
the pizza. I can't tell you how many times we have gone,
and this is not an advertisement for Casey's.
It's totally not. I'm not being paid by them, but they want to send me
some bitcoin. I'm not going to complain how many times people
have gone there and raved about the breakfast pizza.
That pizza in particular has a ton of love.
So how can they lean into that? They don't need to diversify.
They don't need to go into all the other pizza derivations
like calzones or hot pockets. But how do
they maximize on people's love of Casey's
pizza? You know what they did? They came out with a triple
pepperoni pizza. Now, you might not
think that's a digital transformation, but it is
because they were using technology to figure
out how to transform their business.
And the insights and the analytics that they gained
from having that single pane of glass allowed
them to increase their revenue.
And here's the fun part. In all those three examples,
you'll notice I didn't name one particular director,
I didn't name one vice president, I didn't name one CTO,
one CEO as the rock star.
A digital transformation, yes, I will
agree, has to start from the top, be agreed
to. This is our new priority, full stop.
We need to figure out how to do this, and it
has to be implemented on every single level below.
But when you get to the very, very last level,
that is where the digital transformation is actually felt.
So it's sort of a paradox. The CEO and
all the leadership has to agree this is what we're going to do.
But the people that are actually at the center of
a digital transformation are not the people at the top.
It's the people at the bottom, so to speak. It's the
customers. The end user is the star
of the digital transformation. Because every business no
better if you're in b to b, b to c if you're in fintech,
if you're in web three, if you're in AI. We're only
here because there is an end user that has a
problem, and they are willing to pay us to solve that
problem for them. So we need to,
as an industry, stop thinking about ourselves as these
amazing people that have been gifted from on high, that are
allowing people to communicate in new and exciting
ways. No, the end user, the customer,
the person that is actually using your software,
is the one that you need to be focused on, and you need to be
borderline obsessed with learning, has many things
as you can about these people, about what it is that they want,
about probably what it is that they don't want, about what you do better
than all your other competitors, and you can use technology to
do that. That is the heart of a digital
transformation, you can do it in many, many different
ways. Probably the most popular way is through user experience.
You can go through, and this is an investigative
report that Forbes did. For every dollar
that you spend on learning about user experience,
this could be in reasons, this could be in write alongs,
this could be any number of different ways that you're learning about users.
But every dollar that you spend in user experience,
it's a hundred to one return. I mean, you'd be silly
not to do it. Now, in the three examples that
I gave previously, DHL,
Disney, Casey's, they're all in different sectors.
They've all done completely different things. They all have potentially different
customers. But they
found at the very core of it, the fact that the customer
is the one that truly drives
their innovation, and they are the ones that are getting into the customer's
head, figuring out where it is they need their business to go.
Software, as much as we don't want to
admit it, it is a game of catch up. We are always going to be
behind the ball. We can try to figure out where the
industry is going, but we are never going to get in front of the business.
So let's stop telling ourselves the lie that we will
somehow get in front and instead think about what
are some of the different ways that we can embrace that. What are some of
the different tools that we could use to get into the
heads of our users. Write alongs are honestly my favorite.
If you ask any software developer what their favorite part of the process
is, I can almost guarantee it's going
to be the times when you've gotten to sit with a user that
is using what you're producing. We have
metaphorical blood, sweat and tears in the applications
that we build. We spend hours of our lives. We spend time away
from the people that we love the most, our families.
Unless you have the privilege of working from home. My two kids,
I mean, it sounds like a war is happening when I'm
at home, so I have to work from an office just to get any work
done. But even for those of you that work at home, you still have to
focus. You're taking time away from the people that you love to
work on an application. You're sitting behind an ide
for 30, 40, 50 hours a week. You care
deeply about the products that you deliver and being
able to see someone use it, being able to see someone delighted or
see someone frustrated. There's a level of empathy
that we need to tap into as software developers and software practitioners that
we aren't and doing ride alongs is one of my favorite.
Carmax actually does this really well.
They do studies where they have their development
teams and everyone sort of sit and just go on mute and
let the end users talk. But what it is that they like and
what it is that they don't like now there is the potential for a Rashimon
effect where everyone can have completely different interpretations
about what it is that the users liked and what they didn't. And that's
okay. Software is great. Not when it's a
lone wolf developing in their basement encoding all through
the night with too many red bulls or that new panera enhanced
lemonade that has 1200 grams of caffeine.
No, it's done by a team. And so even if you
have conflicting views, that's fine, embrace it.
Figure. But how you can get to the root of what the user was actually
talking about. And there is no one single role that
is responsible for this. I'm a firm believer
that the earlier you can have software development product owners
and architects and be has involved in the process, the better the project
is ultimately going to be. But no matter where you involve them
in the process, it's something that we all have
to do. It is 2023, as I speak to you. We have
rovers going around on Mars. This is something that we can do.
This is not rocket science. This is extremely simple. It just
has to be prioritized. And we have to understand that
a user is at the heart of everything that we do.
There's many tools, there's many techniques, if you've seen the slides that have
been going on as I'm talking. But at the end of the day,
it's the software development team that is the one that is responsible
for delivering the digital transformation. It has
to be prioritized. Don't get me wrong, it's the development
team that actually does the work. And this unfortunately
is the fourth reason why I've seen
digital transformations not work. So you have the wrong people
on the bus if you have not to pick
on them. Managers that have been in the business for 2025,
30 years, maybe they grew up as being
developers on a mainframe. And their entire
mental model is revolved around the mainframe.
The mainframe and the mainframe, if you talk to them, and all they
can talk about are the glory days of the as 400,
they may not be the right people on the bus
because what we're talking about with the digital transformation goes
beyond any particular software stack, it goes beyond
any particular language, it goes beyond even any particular SDLC
be it safe or agile or scrum or waterfall.
It goes back to what we're doing here.
It goes back to why we are even here. We are here
to serve an end user. If we don't understand
who that end user is, if we don't care if we think that the end
user is at best an inconvenience,
we got the wrong people on the bus.
So we really need to take a hard look at what are the strengths
and understand what are the weaknesses. What are
the mental models of everyone on those low level,
I say low level closest to the client teams,
and if we have people on there that maybe
their mental model can't be stretched to
understand what we're doing, we might need to have some difficult
conversations. Now, in any large organization,
there's inertia. Inertia, I would honestly say,
is another word for culture. This has always
been the way that we're going to do things, and any derivation
thereof is not allowed. People,
we kind of get in a groove. We like to do things the same way.
You talk to someone who's been developing software for 30 years,
chances are at around year ten or 15, they found a way that they like
to do it, and that's going to be how they want to do it from
here on out. When you do a digital transformation,
you have to leave that kind of childish mentality behind. I say childish
because I have that mentality sometimes too, so I totally get it.
You might have to get the wrong people off the bus,
and you might have to get the right people on the bus.
Now, no matter what it is you choose to do,
I can guarantee you that it's not going to be easy.
But once you get the people that are
not going to move you forward off the bus,
and once you get those people that are going to help you,
the people that are going to be obsessed about who your clients are,
the people that are going to spend night and day thinking about
what are the things that really work well and what are the things that
don't work well. When you have people that truly care, that have
an enormous amount of empathy for your end users,
you're going to find that almost everything else
will sort of take care of itself. So, to recap,
when you hear digital transformation, don't buy into
the hype. Don't just look at what
other people are doing. Don't just look at what other tools people are doing
and think that if you somehow purchase those tools, you yourself will
be the rock star of the show, because you're not.
Because if you're doing a digital transformation for yourself,
you will never be as successful as if
you focus on who the truly important people of
the digital transformation are, because it's your customers,
it's your people. And until you can get the wrong people
off the bus, get the right people on the
bus, you're always going to be hitting up against that inertia
day after day after day. So we have to, from the
top, understand that this is going to be a priority.
Make it clear constantly, possibly over
communicate the fact that this is now a priority.
We need to embrace the fact that people are on mobile devices.
We need to embrace the fact that our customers want us to do things that
we're currently not doing. And if we don't, our competitors
are going to do it better than we are. Once you
get to that state of customer
nirvana where you are constantly thinking
about what is their life like, what process
can I solve for them? It doesn't always have to be technical. As I
mentioned with the example with Casey's having a pizza with
not one, not two, but three different types of pepperoni,
that kind of insight, that kind of knowledge, that increase in
revenue was only possible because they had
a digital transformation that allowed them to see it,
to see it so clearly that they could go out and reach it
and potentially taste it. I haven't had one
yet, but from what I hear, they're fantastic.
So again, my name is Zach Gardner. I'm the
chief architect here at Keyhole Software. I've helped two,
three organizations with their digital transformation. I've seen
it go well. I've seen it go not so well. I hope you found this
presentation insightful. I know I've had a lot of fun delivering it,
but I need your feedback. So scan the QR code,
let me know what are the things that I'm doing well.
What are the things that I need to work on? And if
you agree with me, scan the QR code. Let me know if you disagree with
me. I also want to know as well, because there
is not enough time in the day. I wish there were more than
24 hours, but at last there is not. And our
customers, we are real people. I am
a customer and I am also a provider of software services.
I want to help solve people's process through software.
I think it is such a unique opportunity that we have and
a lot of these other presentations at Conf fourty two that you're going to be
listening to, they kind of touch on this. Software is
one of those unique fields that allows us to
do things that we thought potentially were impossible. We can scale
solutions to business problems to be able to solve people's
problems while we sleep and as far as I know there's very few
other fields unless it's the building of roads and the
building of buildings that can anywhere close to
how tactile and how tangible
we can get with these solutions to our problems and allow
them to scale and we owe it not just to ourselves
and honestly not just to our bottom lines because if you're thinking like that
you're going to fail. We owe it to our
customers, we owe it to the real users to
stop thinking about things in the way that we used to
just because there's momentum and truly start to
understand what it is and where they need us to
go what are their problems and how can we provide those solutions
again my name is Zach Gardner, chief architect at Keyhole Software.
Thank you very much for my presentation and I hope you enjoy the rest of
42.