Hello everyone, thank you for joining us today at
this conference. I am excited to share with you
the importance of empowering sectors readiness
with quantum solutions. Today, we are here
to talk about quantum computing and
how it can shape these future of sectors
across industries. Let's begin our journey
into quantum computing readiness with an overview of
our agenda. In this presentation, we'll cover five
topics. We'll provide an overview of
why quantum computing is gaining significant
attention in various sectors. We will discuss
why sectors need to be prepared for quantum
computing and the potential impact
on their future success. We will also explore
the advantages that quantum readness
brings. We will dive
into practical strategies that sectors can
take to prepare themselves for the quantum
era. Last thing we will share
our recommendation for quantum industry
that leads to quantum computing readiness.
So let's get started on this exciting journey
together. Quantum computing offers incredible
power to solve complex problems that are
impossible for classical computers to solve.
Today, it's crucial for sectors to preparing
for the opportunities that quantum computing brings.
Understanding the risks and benefits will make
sectors take a step forward associated
with these technologies. To achieve
success, it's essential for sectors to be
proactive and preparing if they want
to stay ahead in their fields.
So, how to be safe?
Consultation services provide knowledge,
tools and guidance to become quantum
ready. Now, let's delve into the need
for quantum computing readiness.
There are list of reasons why
sectors must prepare and I will just mention
some of them. First one, quantum computing can disrupt
industry and markets. It has the
power quantum computing solution. It has these power to
transform the way we operate today.
Offering new computing
capabilities being preparing ensure we
can or sectors can leverage these advancements
efficiently. Empowering proactiving
preparing a proactive preparation
is crucial to avoid falling behind.
By staying ahead of the curve,
we can maintain our competitive edge
and size opportunities that arise from
quantum technology. Specialized experts and consultants
provide guidance. Accessing the
knowledge and experts of professionals
in the field is invaluable.
They can guide sectors through these
complexities of quantum computing and its
applications to solve complex problems,
understanding quantum technology and its
application is essential.
Sectors must develop a foundational
understanding of quantum computing concepts
and their potential applications. This knowledge
enables sectors to make informed
decisions and identify areas where quantum
solution can have the greatest impact in their
industry. So what are the benefits of
quantum computing readiness? Quantum computing
readiness offer numerous advantages
that can greatly benefit
sectors in various ways.
First, enhance competitiveness by enabling
informed decisions,
cost reductions and the exploration
of innovation applications. This empower
sectors to gain a
competitive edge in the market.
Second, quantum readiness ensure improved
sectors through these implementations of
robust framework, risks assessments and
governance solutions. These measures
protect data from potential
risk posed by quantum computing
and ensure complaints with security
regulations. Last reason
quantum readiness facilities structures data
by computing it for quantum
algorithms. This enable accelerate
processing, empowering hidden
insights and enhance efficiency
in handling big data.
It open up new
possibilities for sectors to drive meaningful
value for their data.
Now that we understand these benefit, let's explore
how sectors can achieve quantum readiness.
The first method is to establish
dedicated quantum computing office within
the sectors. This in house team will
be responsible for developing tailored
strategies, ensuring confidentially
and fostering
collaboration within the sectors. So it's the
team inside these
sectors. The other method is sectors can
partner with establishing quantum computing or
existing quantum computing companies through contractual
agreements. These allows them
to access improved technologies
and proven solutions that existing,
accelerating their progress and
assess their specific requirements.
The last available method is engaging with
quantum computing organizations, both national and international,
so the engagement is crucial. These organizations offer
valuable services and insights.
Examples for that the National Quantum
Coordination Office, the MQCO
in the United States. The other example is the European
Quantum flagship and there are several
organizations in many countries focused
on the advanced quantum technologies
worldwide. These organizations provide guidance
and support sectors to prepare for
quantum risks and opportunities.
Collaborating with them ensure these sectors
stay up to date with the latest advancement
in the field. To further
accelerate quantum computing readiness, I would like to
propose two recommendations that's not available today
for sectors to achieve readiness,
but is available to do for
sectors and governments.
And it's still a recommendation. First,
the establishment of governmental standardization
for quantum computing fields.
This will create a
good ecosystem by provide
guidance, mitigate risks,
fostering collaboration and facilitate knowledge
exchange. We don't want two
companies work to solve the same solution.
So the governmental standards will let
the organizations or the sectors or the companies
exchange their knowledge to solve different
problems. It ensure that everyone
is working towards the same goals and maximize
gains. The second one I
recommend the creation of an
international organization called,
I name it the Quantum Computing Standards organizations
QCS similar to ISO BCARB
SDG from the United nations.
The QCs would publish standards,
then provide guidance and then
offer certificate to sectors who meet
the requirement of these standards. By aligning
with the responsible research and innovation
the RRI principles,
it can address challenges,
anticipate potential conference
and encourage sectors to develop quantum services.
This will build trust, stimulate computations
and drive the overall development
of quantum computing. Despite the challenges
improved despite the challenges
involved, establishing the
QCs is significant step
toward effective and safe implementation
of quantum computing across sectors and countries.
We have reached the final slide of our presentation,
let's recap the key point we have
discussed today. We discussed the importance of quantum
computing readiness for sectors. It gave them
competitive edge and open new opportunities.
Quantum computing readiness brings several
benefits. It increased competitiveness by enabling
informed decision, cost reduction and innovative
applications. It improves security through
robust frameworks and risk assessment.
It also helps structure data
for efficient processing and handling big
data. To achieve quantum computing
readiness, sectors should establish
quantum computing office, contract with quantum
computing companies or engage with quantum
computing organization in their countries. Our recommendation
includes governmental standards for
quantum computing field. This foster
collaboration, mitigate risk and facilitate
knowledge exchange. Additionally, we proposed
the establishment of QCLS
quantum Computing standards organizations to publish
standards, provide guidance and offers
certificates to sectors.
Thank you all for being here today.
It has been a pleasure sharing insights
on empowering sectors readness
with a quantum solution. I appreciate your
time and attention and I'm excited to witness
the remarkable advancements
that lie ahead in the world of quantum computing.
Thank you once again and have a nice
and great day.