Hi, my name is Ismael Hommani. I am cloud cloud native developer
GDE Wescale. In today's talk we are going to present you with
clement a comparison between Argo and Flux, which are two
GitHub's tools in the Kubernetes landscape.
First of all, we want you to be aware that it is not a
basic comparaison we want to make, but something that go
beyond a simple benchmarking. It's about describing
these difference of philosophy when it
comes to consider Githubs in the
flux mind or ArgoCD mind.
So our comparison criteria will first
be based on the model, that is to say the different entities and relationship
with one another. It will allows us to
deeply understand how flux and ArgoCD consider
the GitHub's approach and will give you the
right insight when it comes to make the choose
between those two tools. Then we will present you the
different user experience you can expect. Is it easy
to install, how to do it, how to update it,
how to debug it, and so on.
Last but not least, benchmarking will give you a quick
overview of what kind of expectation you can have in terms
of cpu and memory consumption.
We wanted to compare flux and Argosidoi because when it
comes to Githubs in Kubernetes landscape, we have two
clear winners, ArgocD and Flux.
They have a wide recognition and community and
adoption. But the question remains,
what tools should I install? And usually we see
comparaison in terms of performance and not
philosophy. That's why we wanted to compare
Flux and ArgoCD today.
Before comparing those two tools, let's recap what Githubs
is. Traditionally, we consider the CI CD approach
with a monolithic pipeline where a file will imperatively
describe how two deploy inside a target platform,
which means that the runtime will need to provide
the different tools we need to interact with these platform.
First point, let's say for instance Kubectl.
Second point, we have to provide these
tools with credentials inside the pipeline,
which means potential data leakage. And third
point, if we want to deploy on another platform, we would
have to provide with new credentials and
modify neroprone file,
which is rather not really good. In fact,
we oppose this approach two the CI and
CD. That is to say GitHub's approach,
which is a continuous
deployment pattern where a deployment agent will take in
charge all the deployment step. We at
no point describe how to deploy our manifests
onto the platform. It is up to the agent to
do it, and that's why we say that the
GitHub's approach is purely declarative.
It will fetch from your sources the different
manifest and apply it on the platform,
although that it is not linked by
definition to the Kubernetes platform.
We can say that Kubernetes is well adapted to the GitHub's approach because
first, it provides a declarative model through the
different resource definition that we
describe in YaML file manifest.
And second, we have infinite
reconciliation loop that these deployment agent
can rely on when it will apply
the different manifested watch
from the repository into the platform.
In terms of credential. By design, when we
install a deployment agent, we provide it
with the credential to access the
platform so that we don't have any more
the issue of providing into the pipeline
the credential.
So let's have an overview of Argo CD and
Flux. Both are open source and donated
to the CNCF respectively by WeWork
and intuit.
Both are graduated and both
have broad community on GitHub
in term of stars. Last but
not least, we strongly discourage you to install
both on Kubernetes cluster.
What we may find on the Internet when
we compare two tools is that okay, they are complementary and
we can take both of them to make the
perfect tool. But no, don't do that.
It's not a good idea.
Let's focus on the model. So what we understand
by the model is the different entities and relationship that
would be considered by a given tool, flux or
Argocd. It is important to have it in mind because it
will help you to understand the deep
philosophy, the deep understanding of how
those tools understand Githubs and will help
you later in the usage of these tools and especially
in these decision of whether flux or argo.
Before going into the description,
let's remind you what is an operator pattern on
Kubernetes. Kubernetes is a platform that allows you to
industrialize the deployment of your application through
different entities like pod
deployment, job services and so on.
Which means that Kubernetes understands
its business logic. Business being deploying
an application. Now what if you want kubernetes to
understand your own logic, your own business logic, for instance
githubs. Well, with the operator pattern
you are able to define your own custom resource
with an associated controller so that each time
you create a manifest foo,
you will trigger a controller that will
later interact with Kubernetes to do
this and that. That is two say Kubernetes
is now able to understand your own logic.
It is interesting to know about this operator pattern because
both Flux and ArgocD relies on it.
The flux model an overview is this schema,
but it has not many sense if we don't know about
the different customer resource definitions. So let's go back on this schema
later. The first resource
to consider is the source. The source is where
flux should be monitoring the synchronization.
To do so we have several kind of it several types,
git repositories, bucket OCI repository,
and also ELM charts and repositories.
We can describe it through basic manifest
with their own API version and own kind.
It's quite obvious in term
of specification. Here we define URL
corresponding to this git repository and tells Flux
to cons it at the master branch every five
minutes. We have the same kind of consideration for
an ELM repository and for the elm shard kind
we have this specific sourceref tag
which points to another ELM repository
here, a repository named Pod
info that we can find here,
but alone a source is not enough,
it only tells Flux where to watch
but not what to synchronize. And for
this we have the customization which relies on the customized
Kubernetes tool to not overcomplicify
this presentation. I will only tell that the
customization is a way to specify to flux
what path to consider in the
previous source. So for instance here we
have a customization telling Flux that you
have to synchronize the entities
you will find into the pod git repository
under the path customize.
Of course we also have resource corresponding to an
ELM release which is a wrapper of
an elmorelize and you manipulate it
through Yaml file which
definition is quite basic.
You have the specific API version and kind
then a spec that will tell you the interval of
installation, the version and most important
the source reference which is here.
And of course you have the values needed to
render the chart template in
terms of organization of those
different custom resource definitions. We have at
higher level a source which
will be pointed by a customization but also an
ELM release. And the customization will
tell Flux where to find the different Kubernetes
entities and custom definition to synchronize
with your cluster. An interesting point
is that inside those entities
we can find also other sources
and you begin to understand that in fact we can
create a directed acyclic graph that
would represent the entire state of your Kubernetes
cluster. Something that
we have to watch for is that we can create cycle,
and if cycle is created, the customization that
is at the origin of these cycle,
the synchronization of this synchronization of this customization will
fail. We also
have the capacity to define explicitly
dependencies between same sort of kind.
For instance, we can say that a customization two
depends on customization one, effort flux.
It means that customization one
should be installed before customization
two. And we have the same kind of relation with
the nmolis also.
So we are back to our overview and
what will happen in normal flow flux
flow is that you will push source on your
repo source kind which will be
pushed on the Kubernetes API by flux.
The source will trigger a source controller
which will read the
specification and see that it has to clone a GitHub repository.
The cloning will happen inside the pod under
the source controller. Then we
also pushed a customization that is
referencing these very same sources at
a given path. So the customized controller
will read these cons repository
and explore at the path specified in the customization
the different manifest that
it would find and each manifest will be applied
to the Kubernetes API and a namespace controller
will take action, airbag controller take
action, and so on. And we can also find a
releases that would trigger a name controller
which reference a name repository and
would be able to fetch the right
version and install the right release into
the cluster.
Let's focus on the ArgoCD model. The ArgoCD
model is a very different one from the flux model.
In this model we only care about one central CRD
called application. The application represents the
synchronization part of the GitHub's approach.
It's an all in one CRD where
you define sources which can be plain YML files,
customize Elm or chisonet, but also
the target which can be defined as a different
cluster than the one where argoCD is installed.
In a sense we can say that this model is
simpler than flux because we only have one CRD,
but because we have much more parameter to
play with. We can also say that this model is
more complex than the flux one.
As usual, we have manifest with
its own API version and kind here
application these we define
a project which is a notion we will see later,
but most importantly the source these
a git repository with a path to
explore in order to synchronize the sources
we will find into, and a
destination which represents a Kubernetes
cluster. Where to make these synchronization wave.
On the right side we have an alternative
specification where we specify a
NAM repository and
we want to synchronize a dedicated chart called
Argo.
Sometimes you may want to specify another kind of sources.
You can enhance these application capabilities
with config management plugin
that would allows you to specify other kind
of resources. And this is
interesting because you can benefit from the
community which provide many ArgoCD
plugins. You also
have the capabilities to synchronize
these synchronization of different applications.
That pattern is called app of applications where
you define a root application,
which sources will point to other application CRD,
so that once you synchronize this root application,
you will trigger the application of the subservices.
An interesting point is synchronization hooks.
In fact the synchronization have a lifecycle
with phases and each phases can be hooked
with a job computation so
that for instance you can has a precinct job
create a database needed for
the sync phases.
If you remember, in the last application manifest we
has this default project setting which
in fact points to an application project
resource definition which represent in a
way the federation we want to apply on
a group of applications. These federation means
what kind of permission we would apply
on the synchronized resources, but also where
we can deploy in term of namespace or
cluster or what kind of entities the
application under these project are allowed to
deploy. So in term of dependency model
we have this CRD which
is to my opinion secondary,
which will point to so a project
which will point to application which is a central customerial
definition of the ArgoCD model
and which represents the synchronization.
And an application we have seen can
points to other application, it's an app of apps pattern,
but in these end an application, a leaf application
will point to Kubernetes entities, or ELm
charts or Gsonet and so on.
So now we understand the model of both tools,
let's wrap up our findings. I like to
say that Flux and ArgoCd are
an answer to the same question, which is how do you implement
Githubs on Kubernetes? If you ask
someone which is interested and well versed
into kubernetes, it will tell you flux,
because flux is keep it simple, stupid.
It already depends rely on
existing entities from the Kubernetes environment.
An enrollment release is nothing new, a customization is nothing new.
And now that we have a terraform operator also on flex,
it's nothing new. On the other hand, we have
ArgocD, which provides you with a new
model, a kind of logical
layer that render kubernetes
as a detail of implementation in the
GitHub's padding. And this is interesting for
people such as developers who are not interested
into kubernetes. And also
I think it explains why by default Argocd
has a user interface because it really needs
it in order to express these
model in term of application and app project,
contrary to flux which already rely
which purely rely on Kubernetes
entities that we already can handle through
knnice in term of user interface.
So it is interesting to have it in mind when
you want to choose between flux and ArgoCd.
Let's conclude our comparison with multi clustering and multi tenancy.
First, multi clustering we understand from
a GitHub's perspective these multi clustering has the capacity to synchronize application
on several clusters while using a single tool application
for flux. This is not possible because each
cluster we want to synchronize has to be installed
with a flux instance, meaning that if
we want to deploy application synchronize deployments
on cluster one, cluster two, cluster three of
all of these three must have a flux installation on them.
But we can emulate the multiclustering
approach by creating a central flux
installation root repository that would contain
the installation source of each flux
installation. That way those installation would
be able to monitor themselves and
later we would have inside the same root repository
sources and customization that would point to application
repo that would later replicate on each cluster.
So in a sense we have a control plane which
is distributed, but still that we can
centrally manage through a flux installation
root repository containing the source installation of each
flux clusters on
Argocd we have the multi clustering approach. By design.
We have a single cluster on which Argo is installed
and the target of the applications we define could
be very well other clusters. My Argo
installation has access to multi
tenancy. Now let's call a tenant a segregation
quantum multitenancy from a GitHub's perspective would be a
tenant bonded to a namespace and also to permission
to that namespace only from a
flux perspective we don't have by design,
once again the multitenancy, but we can
also emulate it by reusing
already existing entities from Kubernetes but
also from git. Basically we would create
repository, a git repository where only operative
would have access two, and inside this repository
we would define tenants as namespaces,
Erbac, but also sources and customization
that points to other repository which
contains the infrastructure of a specific application.
But this time this tenant repository would
only allow a dev team to have access
to. So we see that the multitenancy
rely on two notions. First one being
Kubernetes Rbac and second one being
the GitHub or GitLab Rbac.
From an ArgoCD perspective, it is
already rooted inside the tool,
as the app project gives you the necessary
tools to create your tenant, in what
kind of namespace your application can be deployed on,
with what right, what kind of entities
kubernetes, entities you can manipulate, and so on.
And also we can note that airbag and
single sign on is supported by the
user interface of argocd.
So now we are going to see the user experience
which will be presented by Clement.
You are live.
Thanks ismail. So now that we have seen how
Argo and Flux were designed, let's see how this relates to
the user experience.
We have two kinds of users for GitHub tools. These administrator
team in charge of deploying and maintaining the infrastructure, including the
GitHub tools, and the user team, mostly composed
of developers who are not expected. Two have as
deep knowledge on kubernetes on the GitHub tool than the
starter team.
Before installing or using or even choosing our GitHub
tool, we must first talk
about different things we need to implement on the GitHub's
architecture. We must talk about,
for example, whether we want a multi repository or a mono repository
for the deployment code. If we want a multi repository,
what scope should each repository have?
We should also talk about how the code should be put into each
repository. For example, do we want multiple
folder for GCP, Azure or a
single one? We must also talk about who owns
the code for the repository and who has the right to modify it.
For example, the developers will probably have the right to
modify the code in the GitHub repository to deploy
on the old cluster. But also these SRE team should have
access to this repository in case something went
wrong in production and they need to fix it quick.
We must also talk about how can we protect the production.
By that I mean how do we implement for example, or git
flux or git flow? Like if
we want to deploy first in these development, then QA,
then production. That's something that needs to be discussed before
and implemented if you want to, but some protection on the branch.
So these issue is that these really need to be discussed before putting a
GitHub solution or you may need to refactor these
code base in the future. They're not mandatory
I would say, but it's still nice to do it before implementing
it.
So let's begin with flux. A Redmissrazer team wants
to install it on these cluster to do so
they have two official choices. Either install flux with
a CLI which will bootstrap the installation on
the cluster and create the initial synchronization between the cluster
and these provided root repository provided by you,
I mean. Or you can use terraform which do
the same thing has in CLI but with terraform which is
useful. When for example, you are using managed cluster
on AWS or GCP.
There also exists a community mshat that will
install the core component of flux on your cluster,
but will not create any initial synchronization between
the cluster and git repository.
So like I said, flux manifests will be committed to the root
repository. That means that if flux detects,
for example, that there is a change between the git repository, only its own
installation flux can correct this change by itself.
So now that you have installed flux on your cluster
and that flux is doing the initial synchronization
between its root repository on the cluster, you should know that
you can put your manifest on the root repository before installing
flux. That means that for example, if you have
all your manifests already on your GitHub repository,
for example from a production cluster, and you want to put them on a pre
production cluster, you can do so really quickly.
So we have installed flux on the cluster. We have the initial synchronization
ready between git repository or root repository and
the cluster. Now we want to add over
multiple application on the cluster to
do so. It's quite easy as long as you follow the documentation.
You have really four custom resources that will Internet you
the git repo, the customization, the amplitude and the
narrative. And using these four customization custom resources,
you will be able to deploy all your application on the cluster quite easily.
Like the CRD, they really
only do one thing, but they do it really well. There are no
option on the CRD to really drastically
change the way they function,
but you can still do some minor configuration. For example,
change the synchronization interval used by
your different custom resources.
So now we have our flux installation
ready on the cluster. We have all application running on the
cluster by flux. Let's see what
happens if our developer teams want to
modify something in the cluster.
So to do so, it's quite simple. They really only have to commit
a change in git on flux will handle everything else.
So if you want to do an update, you write your commit, you merge
it in the main branch. For example, influx will detect
the change and apply it on the cluster. If the
change is not up to your standard, you can revert
the change using a git revert, commit it once again on
the main branch and the flux will change the modification
of your cluster. Now like I said,
flux really only does one thing, it's one thing,
it is synchronizing.
So now we have flux running in the cluster. We have the
different developer application also deployed on the cluster using
flux. Let's see what happens if the developers want to modify
one of the application. So the developer for example
created a new version of the application and want to deploy it
on these cluster two do so they will create a commit on one
of the GitHub's git repository,
merge the commit in one of the master branches and flux
will detect the changes and apply it to the
cluster.
So to deploy a change on the cluster release,
developer only have one tool to know it's git.
They only need to know about a git commit git revert.
That's all they need to know.
If for a reason or another you want to pose
the flux synchronization for a component between git
and the cluster. For example, you deployed manually a change on the
cluster and you needed to stay that way until you've committed it.
Two git well you can use an annotation
on the cumulative object of flux.
So now that the developer has released its new version
on git, he wants to check what is happening in the cluster.
Well to do so, flux does not provide any UI out of
the box. So these developer will need to have access to the cluster
and check what is happening with flux and with its application.
If there's an issue with the deployment, he will need to go
check on the flux. Custom resources what is happening for example on
the customization there may be an issue if one of the Kubernetes
object is malformed.
If the administrator team has properly
configured it, the developers can use Grafana to check
what is happening on flux with their application.
There also exists web UI developed
by withworks that will allow these developer to check what
is happening with flux and whether its application is deployed on
these cluster. Quite simply this web UI is not included
in the box, but you can deploy it quite simply using Elm.
So now from these point of view of the administrator,
when you want to upgrade a flux installation,
the way to do it depends the way you install it.
If you install it with a CLI, well there is a command CLI to
upgrade your application that
is quite simple to use, but you need to remember
the arguments you pass to the first command to
the flux install command.
If you're using terraform, it's quite simple, you just need to upgrade
the version of the data source you are using and flux will do the
rest. I want to put these little
point of intention on the fact we use githubs
to upgrade the Githubs tool. It can be dangerous to use
GitHub to upgrade the same tool that is monitoring itself
because if something were to run wrong in the update,
well the tool will not be available to do a
revat on itself and you would need to go on the cluster to upgrade
it. So if you want to upgrade
GitHub using GitHubs, I would recommend to use another
GitHub tool to upgrade the first GitHub tools.
So now let's see how ago CD works.
So our team wants to install Argocd on their
cluster. To do so they can use either helm or
directly use Kubernetes manifest. It can be
installed with Kubestall applied or customized.
There is no initial git repository required when you are installing
argocd. That means you only install the RSD core components and there
is no initial synchronization done. There are
three installation type that you can use, either highly available installation
type, a nonlivariable insertion type,
or a core only installation type that does not
include the web UI. I would recommend using the non
reliable installation one.
So like I said, the OCD will not monitor
itself. So that means that if you remove one
of AGD components from kinesis it would not auto.
So now we have our ArgoCD installation completed
on the cluster. Let's see how we can install a different application.
So IOCD will only use one custom resource
to deploy these object on your cluster. It's these application
so the application can deploy everything customize Internet
catanet it's nice, but that means that there is a lot of different
options you can use depending on your application on what you need to do.
That means that the configuration of this custom resource can
be quite complex. For example, by default
these application will not remove anything from your cluster even
if it's removed from git. Or if you remove the application from your cluster,
you should also check which wave your
application should be. That means whether your application depends on these one
or not. So there is a lot of different options to
use. But that can be simplified when you're using the web UI
provided with AgoCD.
Now our ArgoCD cluster is running on the Kubernetes
cluster. The different developer applications are
running using ArgoCD and the developer wants to upgrade
one of its application to do so. He will need to commit
his change to one of the monitored kit branches
and then depending on how the application is configured on ArgoCD,
it will either be automatically applied on these cluster
or it will require human
interaction. So a button to deploy it.
The button will be quite nice for example for production scenario.
So now the user has deployed these application on
the cluster and he wants to check what is happening.
Well, he can use the ArgoCD web UI to see if
its application is deployed as he wants or not.
It will indicate, for example if the application has
issues running, for example if a pod is failing.
Now from the point of view of the administrator,
if you want to upgrade an ArgoCD
cluster, it's quite simple. You can upgrade it
using either Elm or customize.
You really just need to apply the new version of
the ArgoCD manifest and it will be modified as you want.
I just want to remind you that when you are applying an upgrade on Weatherflux
orgo CD, you should really read the release note to
check if there are any breaking changes.
So to summarize, ArgoCd is quite easy
to install using standard Kubernetes tools.
To configure, it is a little bit more complex since its customer
source has a lot of options that will modify its behavior to
use. From the developer point of view, it's quite simple. The web UI
will help a lot in that regard.
Also, AGC has a lot of sane options that will
prevent it from breaking your cluster. For example,
it will not remove anything from your cluster
and it will always require an human interaction before applying something
on the cluster.
For flux, on the other hand, it's a little bit more complex. To install
you need two give flux permission to access your repository
to commit things in it, etc. To configure.
It's simple. Each customer resource does one thing and it does
it without modifying its behavior.
Two, the usage. I would say it's still simple to use for
the users, but it requires your users to be a little more experienced
in Kubernetes. As there are no safety ads in flux.
Everything committed in git will be deployed in kubernetes and everything
kubernetes is in git. So what that means is that if you were to
remove manifest in git, it will be removed in kubernetes.
All right, so now let's talk performances.
We wanted to see how angle CD and flux would handle a medium
sized cluster of 200 deployments.
These two Android deployments will come from both distinct git repositories
and different embraces. That it will really match these
standard Kubernetes installs that you can see in the wild.
The different point of comparison we will use will be the time to deploy
an object on the different processes used in the different lifecycle
of the tool. We're talking before installing everything,
when we've installed everything and it's monitoring the default object,
and when it's removing these object,
only the core components will be considered for the benchmark. So we
didn't install any other tool than.
All right, so our setup we are
testing our benchmark on an AWS lacks cluster and
everyone of our GitHub tool has run git repository
already synced into which we will push our default changes.
In terms of installation, ArgoCD has been installed
with a non highly available installation,
so that means we still have the web UI available. We are
using these version two 60 for aquacid.
For flux we used the standard installation with CLI
and we are using the latest version available for us which is
00:38 these in
term of initial resources taken when
we did not deploy anything else other than the initial git repository,
we can see that they are both nearly identical in term of
resources. So first the
timelines. We can see that flex before the
installation of all our components is not taking a
lot of resources. Then when we're installing these components we can see a little peak
in both cpu and memory usage and that taken average
out to not a lot of resources before the removal.
We can see that for flux the components taking the most resources
is these Elm controller for
COCD, same thing I would say we do not
take a lot of resources at the start of ArgoCD then
insertion a huge peak we are averaging.
But again our cpu and memory memory consumption little
peak at the end when we are removing things.
Fargo CD the component that is taking the most resources is the
application controller.
So let's compare our deployment. We can see that
as a first synchronization. These ArgoCD will take nearly
twice the resources in flux does.
The time to deploy all objects is identical for both of
them. So it's not here a good comparison point I
would say on the day to
day operations we can see that now obviously on
flux both have reduced their resources usages
and now they both have the same point.
I would say in term of CPU consumption, but ICOCD now consumes a
lot more resources in term of memory than flux does.
So this metric is the most important to you I think since
this is what will be on your cluster 99% of the time on
the production side, we can see that ArgoCD took a
little bit more time than flux, but it's not consequential
I would say, and that once again ago CD
took more resources than flux.
So the results we can see that in terms of deployment speed,
both ArgoCD and Flux are fast. These will
be faster than anything you can code in your CD pipelines.
In terms of resources consumption, we can see that ArgoCD is
taking a lot more resources than flux. We think
it comes from the architectural choices Daco city took in that
its application is doing everything its application custom resource.
I mean in our experience,
this memory consumption of ArgOCD
is really impacted by the number of objects it is tracking in Kubernetes.
So if you are having a large cluster ago CD will be
needing a lot of memory.
So we have arrived at these end of our talk. I hope we've
given you the necessary point to compare both OCD and flux.
So two recap OCD will be better suited
for you. If you need to ensure that your users need to
use a button, for example to push two production. They don't need a full auto
GitHub CD pipeline. If you want to give
your users a rich web UI so that they can see what
is happening on the Kubernetes cluster under the CD pipelines,
ArgOCD is a better tool and if you want
to protect your production, by that I mean ensure that only some users
can push the changes to the Kubernetes cluster
and that these changes will not remove anything from the Kubernetes cluster.
ArgoCD is better suited for you. On the other
one, if your users are experts in Kubernetes,
if they understand that everything that is happening on
the git repository will be reproduced
to the Kubernetes cluster, and that these git and Kubernetes
airbag are good enough for you, well then flux will be
better suited for you.
We want to end this talk with some encouragement.
Two, the whiskey team that helped us a lot to
create these talk on these.
Mainly Basin Fergie who gave us a lot of advice
on how to handle ArgoCD on orchester.
I hope you've learned something today. Thanks for listening two.