Hello everybody. Become to this talk. This treasure related
to the intelligent business agility. So before to
think about intelligent, we needed to understand why this can be
very, very important for your organization,
for your company. And the
idea here is that you need to find a way
to align, to create a bridge between the
strategy and the execution. Those is very important because sometimes
in the real world, it's very, very hard to transform
your ideas, your approach
to the market in a way that can be really executed
by your organization. And this can create a very gap,
a very problems between what you think
to do and what you really achieve during your
activities and in the way in which you can support
your customers. And for that, it's very
important to have in your mind that your
organization must follow, must achieve
what we typically call business
agility. What is business agility? Business agility is an
ability of an organization to fast adapt
itself to the market. And those ability
related to those ability to change in a very fast way,
but in a very cost effective ways.
Those transformation of your environment shows also you need
to have a great focus, a great capability
to produce a very, very good product, a very
quality product. And in case you must focus
your attention to the technical agility. So business agility
is built on
process agility, enterprise agility and technical
agility. This is a great point.
Sometimes in the lecturer tools you can find
that business agility is the same than enterprise agility
or process agility is not true. Business agility is
those full vision of agility of your company in relation to the market,
in operations, to your customers. But you needed to be focused to
make a great attention, to also have all
of these three pillars, agility themselves.
In that way you can try to create the right mix,
the right balance between them and between all
the activities, all the initiatives that you can approach to achieve
those final results. So enterprise agility means that
you can have your organization focused on
what really is important. And you can do that
having for example, grid leader inside your company,
thinking about to going beyond budgeting.
So thinking about how I can founding my solutions,
my budget teams without have a so bureaucracy
plan. So bureaucracy approach to the budgeting. Something like okay,
we needed to create the budget for the whole year, but we
have no way to change it. That's not correct.
We needed to have a flexible way to adapt
the using of our founding to create our budgeting
in relation what really happens during the day by day
activities and supporting what really create value
for our customers and our company.
We needed to be agile, we need to be lean, it's important that
because actually agile lean can be the
most powerful tool that you can use to achieve
the enterprise agility in relation to business agility. And sure you must
think about value stream before projects because value stream is
something that it's very very continuously
live in your company. It's not something that starts
and ends in a specific time, but it's something that
continuously is attention inside your company to create values,
continuous value for your customer. And the second point, technical agility.
There is no way to achieve the business agility without technical
agility. This means that you need to be excellent in
what you do and the way what you do something. So you
can use different framework,
different practices, but it's very important to
create your own approach, your own mix
of all of these to really, really achieve technical
agit. And also you must be excellent in technology.
Select the last solutions and so on.
That's very, very important. And list but not last process
agility. You can identify how support
in a practical way this transformation using
frameworks inspire yourself to toolkit
create a mix also in the way that you really,
really apply those concept of
a culture, innovative culture, learning culture in a
very pragmatic way. For example, you can
decide to use scrum or kanban or something like this.
It's not so important to
be the best in the world to adapt, for example scrum. But it's very important
to create a tailoring of all of that in
the way that can really support your
goals like company. And here
the idea is that you needed to innovate,
you needed to transform your company, you needed to start to think
in a different way, how you can
guide your organization and you can lead your organization to
achieve these results. And we
need to change, you need to change. And to do that,
one of one model that can support you
is related to the eight steps process for
leading change suggested by Dr. Cotters.
These are a set of eight steps, but the
most important for starting the flame
for start a new transformation is the creation
of a sense of urgency. When you can create, when there
is a sense of urgency, every time that you
are sure that you view that something that you are doing from a
lot of years is not helpful,
it's not still helpful for you. So you need to think something different,
a different way to work.
And sometimes when all the things are okay,
is very difficult to
have a real commitment in a transformation
because those people doesn't understand why change if all is okay,
when different products,
different actions doesn't go well,
you can have more support for those I'm
not suggesting to create a problem problems inside your company,
but I suggest you to have a very good
attention to what happens in your company. Identify when can be a good
time for start and when is the moment to really
reinvolve the company, the organization to something
different. Because change have a cost and you need to motivate
that. And you can measure to
use a disciplinary job approach to change. What it
means with that is an idea that there
is no right model for everyone. There is not the
right framework for everyone. But you must think something like
creating options inside your organization.
And you can use those until
metaphor for that. For example, you can imagine that in
your company, every one of you is an ant.
And every one of you and everyone of those ant,
every ant transport an option transport something
that can be helpful to improve your antil.
If something is not correct, if something is wrong,
no problem. Because you have your colleague and yourself can select
a different option to have a very
real improvement. Not one improvement, but a real
improvement. In this way you can be fast in change. You can be sure that
one local failure is not so big, but you can
learn from it. And you can select in a fast way a different
approach coming from a very, very restrict
number of selection, because you are learned from your failure
before, from your experiment. So small experiments are
better. Yes, that's true. And you can imagine that you have a pragmatic
approach for that. Define a starting model, defining an idea,
identify the first candidate option to
adopt, presenting an MVC,
a minimum viable change that you can use for
experiment something different with a metrics that's very
important that you can use to measure it.
So after you apply this MVC, after you experiments this MVP,
you can measure the outcomes and identify if the new
idea, the new option is in line with your expectation.
And if yes, you can accelerate the adoption of
those new option, these new practices and so on.
If not, you can go back identify new
MVC or if needed, you can change the plan because you
are totally out of the scope that you
before image to follow for improve your organization.
And you can best
all of that with the using of the artificial intelligence.
I yes, that's true. Because if we go back to this
slide, one of
the steps is related to measure outcomes.
So that means that you have data and you needed
to analyze this data. And you know that people are not so
good in analyzing a very, very big amount
of data. So in this case, you can use I to
improve your capability to
analyze this data and reduce the number of
options that you must consider
for your new improvement. The heart
is to succeeding fast, succeed faster.
That means that using machine turning,
using big data, using ie,
you can receive suggestion from models,
algorithms and so on that can be useful for be faster,
identify the right option to achieve the
better results in aless time. And that's very,
very interesting. So for that I
created the idea of the intelligent business agility.
And this IBA does mean that you can use all
of the data that you can collect inside your company to
support an organization achieve its
business agility. And the right definition
here is that IBA represents the ability
of organization to develop an adaptive corporate
culture supported by intelligent
agents that are able to support people to enable more
fast decision. And that's very important because it's not something that
remove the needs of people, but support
the people in their decisions.
So how IBA supported in the presenting
GDT, collecting information coming
from customer, so we can have more data from customer, coming from example,
I don't know, from social networks and so
on to support, how to
support in presenting how customer are
looking for us and what is
our brand reputation in their minds.
So we can use this data for supporting innovation
because we can select
new ideas, new products in
relation to the data that we collect from a lot
of sources and in the commitment. Why this? Because in those way
we have a total sharing of information,
data, different point of view collected
in different analysis,
used for different analysis that can support different people inside the
company. We can use also
ie for supporting the technical agility, because we can use
that to align your technology choice to
the real needs needed solution. So we can really understand
measure in some way if we are in the right path to
use in an efficient way our technology and if
this technology is the right one to achieve the right goals
and create the right products. And also we can use for
example, data for
maximize the capability to use better way
our technical skills and improve
step by step, all of that. And we can use
also a to support process agility. Sure,
because we can use it for monitor what happens inside
the different teams, how their
mature level improvement, for example,
across different iteration, across different sprints
and so on. We can use that for accelerate their
growing. For example, they can measure, for example an
IBoT can identify
view the different trends for I don't know how time
you need to create to have a daily inside your team and suggest
you few standard approaches to use better the
time and to reduce the wasted
time inside it. And it's very important to have
accuracy so you can have a really important
way to really identify step by step
what is your real possibility to achieve the IDL
goal. And I suggest you to
few practices that can improve the
opportunity to improve yourself in the right direction.
Two principles are at the basis of IBA,
empowering and inclusive and data driven.
Empowering inclusive means that you must
create a learning culture and a culture based
on sharing and collaboration. That's very important because you needed to share
and you needed to also
use the data, not just for
the personal,
just for the personal goal, but in relation to holistic
goals, company goals. And it's very important that also
you use in the right way
with the respect those data, this data with the respect of the other
people and for protect their
privacy, their identity and so on.
Also you must be sure that
you trust this data to transform them. Not just
something like an additional tools,
but really base your decision on them and
on the other side, data driven. You must be sure that all the
company people can access in a very fast way, in a very simple
way, all the data across the organization. And you need sure
to have rigorous data practices to be sure that the
data that you are using during your analysis and for support
ABI are good data and not the bad data.
So what can be four Edel
steps to go
ahead with your implementational journey in relation to ABA.
So you can start but those foundation from the foundation
point. At this point you are asking yourself
if you have those good
data and if your expectation
are satisfied or not, what is
your level of digitalization and what
are your capabilities, analytic capabilities
to use this data to create real information,
not data but information for supporting decision inside your company.
The second step is the approaching step
in you can start image
what can be the promises that can be
outside from the using of this approach. So you can
starting create the right platform, the right digitalization
inside your organization to use those information.
You will start looking for how you can
increase and optimize the process. And sure you
must be also aware in how you can
distribute in some way. You can give
the right information to the right people. Those next step is
aspirational. So in this case you will experiments and apply
to really a BA at all level
of your organization. And in this case you can identify
how you can use that to improve your lifecycle,
your management and so on and building and how
to build the foundation for that architecture. At the
fourth stage of your journey you
can imagine that you will be mature and you have
really created a continuous learning organization with
a high digitalization
and a real, real trust in
the BI, IBA and for this you
will trust the information. You are sure that your system will
give you a real important
information to support your organization, to improve
itself. And for this you will have
two main guidelines to implement your journey. The first
is those stair guideline.
So security and privacy, this is very important.
You must be sure that you will have security
and privacy about your data.
Transparency, accountability,
inclusiveness and reliability and safety.
So security and privacy, how I said before
is a very, very important point because you need to be sure that data
are managed in the right way and you must
be sure that you protect your data from external
attacks, from misuse of them. And that's very, very important
because if you grant this, you can be sure that
your people will trust it. And we collect a
good amount of data and the right data to support you in
the business. Intelligent business,
agility, AI and those transparency.
This is another important pillar because you must be sure that
you are very transparent in
using your data, in how you can
share the key elements of that. And you must train your people to
use the suggested action
coming from bots and other type of ie
just for support them. But the final decision will be theirs.
Not coming, not automatic decision coming from these
tools, accountability. So these people must be in
charge for maintaining the
responsibility over ever decisions that we
will take based on this data, on this information.
So it's not remove managers,
it's not remove team lead, it's not remove developers
here. The point is that you need to use that to
give to these rules, those people new tools
on which they can take
their decisions in a better way, in a more informed way,
in a more specific way. That's the point,
inclusiveness. So you need to remember that
it's very important to have
a respect for all the sources and use
all the information in a holistic way. So it's
not a way to divide people, separate people, but it's
a way to clue people, to link people between
them. And every information coming from the different people
are very, very important to grow in a very,
very inclusiveness way and the reliability and safety.
That's true. You must be sure that you are using the right data
in the right way with a good supporting
systems that can assure you that the system will
be available when it's needed, and not
just one time every week. For example,
something like this. The system must
offer you a
good slA, a good availability to support you every
time you need its support. And also give you few
pushes about something that you forgot
or something that you doesn't see your own.
So the second guideline
is to use the agile a approach and
this is based on four main experiments.
Get started with those pre built I doesn't create
from scratch your solution, please select a standard
solution coming from the market. Identify the right one. For example,
you can use a lot of machine learning algorithm
coming from a lot of cloud services provider and so on.
Leverage development tools. That means that when you start
in the implementation of your absolutisms or you are
starting in the customization of prebuilt
solutions, your point is to invest on these
tools and be sure that you can reinforce
them. You can support their evolutions
because this is a very important investment for your organization
and you must be sure that you will
take all the Roy that you can extract for
them. Develop by people, for people. Remember that this
approach is not related to create automation without people.
Is thinking to create tools
that can suggest to other people how to use
data, how they can improve
those company activities, company roles,
company improvement using data
coming from internal, coming from the internal environment and from
the external environment. So when you create these tools, when you select
these tools, you must think that these tools are for people,
not for machine. And you
also must be sure that you create that
your I must be ready for data state. And that's
another good point because it's very important to have the right data
and can data in
our activities because without that we can have the
risks that we will select too
much time, the wrong choices, the wrong options for
transform ourselves and that can create not
an efficient way to improve our
organization. So thanks
to listening, thanks to arrive at the end of this presenting.
If you have a more curiosity about that,
you can contact me on LinkedIn, on other channel and
enjoy the conference. And I hope to see you soon in
other conference and also in presenting if this is possible.
Thank you so much.