Hi everyone, I'm Steven Kolawole all
the way from Lagos, Nigeria, and I'll be speaking on Streamlit,
the fastest way to build data apps. Let's get started.
Here's my table of contents. I'll be explaining the problem
being faced by data scientists and machine learning engineers in
building web apps today. Then we'll move on to
Streamlit. I will explain what Streamlit is all about and
what it does afterwards. We'll play around with
the storage process and we'll check out them. And then we'll
move on to building the step by step process of building an
interf and then I'll be showing you
the building blocks that streamlit
makes youre in the building of a data hub. Also, we have in a
sneak peek at the different use cases of Streamlit.
Finally, I'll be taking us to the console streamlit.
Why? Streamlit might not be the ultimate solution to all data apps
problem out there all right, so here's
my profile. I'm currently a machine learning engineers.
I'm currently looking for my next gig. I'm a computer science undergrad at
Federal University of Agriculture Abiocuta.
I'm a finalist. I mean, I'm in my final year of school and also
I consider my skill set to be somewhere in the intersection of software
engineering and data science. I'm also a Liverpool citizen
since I've been a kid. And yeah, I'm a python freak. I use Python
for most of my stuff. I use Python for web development,
for data science, for machine learning
at home. Yeah, I'm also a foodie. Yeah, I like my food.
Okay, so let's get down to business. What's our
problem statement? If you've asked to build a
data hub or a data driven web app before, this is
the issue process, right? The first step is usually the
data processing and data analysis, which is done in
iPOIMB files, right? And then if
you want to share your findings with others, you might want to do that using
notebooks, right? Or better still,
if you want to reach a wider audience, that you might want to copy
all the relevant functions into a Py scripts
into a Python script. You can then create an app
using flask, right? And then if you're using flux,
you need to build a front end part too. And for you to do that
you need to use HTML, CSS, JavaScript and JSON.
At very least you might want to use a JavaScript framework also,
right? But let's say your work is part of an organization process.
So it is an organization, then you most
likely have a dedicated software engineering team,
right? So that means you don't have to build the web app yourself. So you
could give the requirements, the specifications
to the engineering team. And of course
the engineering team will take care of the designing. And of course
let's say in a week or two you might have a state of
the heart hub and then the team lead for the engineering
team might probably tell you able only be able to
carry out updates on your hub in let's say two or
three months, right? So that leads us to the pain point.
Now, depending upon the software engineering team
to do this for you is nice, but also take up
a bunch of our time,
this sort of back and forth and they need to get
the specification right. Communication can
really be stressed at times and you probably won't want
that. And also you won't be able to create new features
and updates on a web, right? Because youre
need to talk to the software development team. And of course doing
that take time and software development team. I also have lot of stuff
on this page. Yeah we'd rather create this apps ourselves. But for
one, most of us are not particular athletes. If you're like me, I can't
recognize a blue color from a yellow color.
I suck at UI designs. Of course creating
web apps means you'll be spending a huge amount of time
and most of us will rather use that amount of time to do something
else. Also, if you're using Flask for your app, it also
means that youre have to bother with JavaScript, with HTML,
with CSS amongst others and of course learning. Those also
take a while. And finally, most of us prefer to use our code
to generate insights or building model. And then I use our
code to provide user with a blizzard experience.
And that leads us to the million dollar question, what if we can build
apps as easy as writing Python script? That will probably change
the world, right? So that leads us to streamlit.
What is streamlit? So let's just say that Streamlit is the
app that data scientists have been waiting for.
Building apps with Streamlit is as easy as writing Python
script. Let's say you have a particular Python script
here, then you write in your functions, you sprinkle in a few public
API call and calls and of course then youre go
back to your browser. Of course you'll be able to see your
new beautiful web app. Is that easy, right?
Yeah, and it covers most UI used in data hub think.
But the check the select post you
have in a chart you have in a drag
button, right? And all this would probably take
minutes or hours. You try to implement them on the front
end side, but with streamlit they already made functions,
not even functions ready made. Readymade. Okay, lets me use
methods. They are readymade methods that you could use.
You could do them in less than maybe a line or two of code
and I think that's quite fun. Also, streamlit supports
multiple interaction visualization libraries. Talk of plotty
bokeh, Pydec or mathplotly seaborne.
Yeah, streamlit supports every one of them. And also your
favorite machine learning tools like pandas, psychics, all of
them are fully supported by Streamlit. Having said that,
let's go through the installation process and maybe play with it then.
All right, so for you to install streamlit you need to do
app stop pp stuff streamlit. And afterwards you
can best on it using Streamlit. Hello.
I'm going to try it out. So I already have
streamlit installed. So I'll just do streamlit. Hello.
So it's coming up and got
this up on my browser.
You can see the documentation. Feel free to try this out on your phone later
and just have fun with it. So I could
just to play analyze the demo. I'm going to try this plot and demo.
Okay. You can see it's loading up and you can see the nice animation over
there. And I can zoom in. I can zoom but
so you could try this out. It's quite nice.
And the animation is just for 5 seconds,
I think. And let's go further.
Let's go down. Yeah. So everything youre seeing up there
is implemented with this, I think less than 15 online
support. I think that's pretty amazing.
Feel free to try out all the other DevOps.
So let's move on. Now I'm going to walk us through the process of
getting the data upstream. Let's assume that we
have a file called hello Py file. And of
course you have to input streamlit it as ST and then style.
Now then you go back to your bash or your command
prompt on windows and try streamlit on lo PI. And of
course it's going to bring this up in your browser automatically.
And I think this is pretty amazing because if you are doing this in flask,
you'll be doing it in I think, five or seven lines of code.
I feel this task quite wonderful. Yeah. So moving
on, let's try that part. All right, so I'm
going to open up the other five,
but I think it's straightforward. So I'm not going to try it
out. I'm going to try out a slightly more complex
example.
Here we are. Now, this file you're looking at, the idea behind
this is this. I have a younger sister who is starting
with data science journey. So she
was busy with the statistics and probability part, and I
felt that it would make much more sense. She gets to see
what she's learning. She gets to see it
in parties and get to
know and see how it works. So that's the idea
behind this scripts. So of course, I have to import
it as sd, import numpy as mp. I expect most of
you to be familiar with that. Numpy is a numerical
computational library, Python. All right, so ST
title, I think that's self explanatory. We are going to have a pick
title distribution test as the words and
ST threads means that we might have a line of code with
this particular test. Pick a distribution from the list,
and we shall draw the line chart from blah, blah, blah. Okay?
Yeah. So here's another line of code. We have the
keys, which is actually a list and number. We have number
and uniform elements in the list. I have
this key, which is actually a symbolic
method, and it's a select, but you can see a sticker select,
but which distribution do you want to plot? And I passed
in the key list variable as an argument.
Now, if this key is equals to
number, right, I'm going to have nums. And nums is going to
be a randomly generated number within the range
of zero to 1000.
To 1000. Of course, if this key
is uniform, right, they're going to have a list of range
zero to 1000. Then it's going to be a
randomly generated number. It says zero to one. Now, the highland line of
code is a line chart, right. And we are passing in the
nums list or elements as
an argument. All right, so I'm going to go over to
my browser. I'm going to go over to my terminal and run
this.
All right, so let's see what comes up. Now,
you can see the editor, you can see the line of code. You can see
our select boss right. Now it's at number
by default. Now, let's say I change this to uniform.
Let's see what happens.
Okay. You can see the difference between
normal and uniform. And it's quite amazing that we're
able to come up with this little app in less than six
lines of code. I think that's pretty amazing. I know the
amount of code I'll probably use on this if I'm
on flush, right? Yeah. So let's move on so
let's have a look at the different use cases of streamlit.
Here's the streamlit demo that lets youre perform the
semantic search across the entire odor city self driving car
for the data set. And you can run a complete neural
net in real time from within the app in less
than 300 lines of code. I think that's pretty amazing.
Yeah, but we get to see that later. All right,
so let's come here.
So if you want to try it out, I think it's here.
I'm going to open it up. Okay. Yeah, so it's actually
build by the streamlit itself.
You could check it out on your own. All you have
to do to run it is just copy paste
this following comments in your browser all right,
so I want to show you another demo. This is an
apartment pricing app and it was developed by a friend of
mine, Moyo. All right, let's check
back on this later. I'm going to open up this. This is another
use case. This is streamlit gallery.
And the gallery contains app built by streamlit developers all
over the world. I'm going to open this up. So the outstandwise
an app is build for major cities in Lagos. Lagos State is like the financial
capital of Nigeria and
the data was created from Propertypro ng.
And you can select the particular city you
want to live in. Lackey is I twelve
city in Lagos states. And let's select Lakey. And of
course you can choose the type of area you want to live in and
you can choose the number of bedroom, number of bathrooms.
So I'm picking two for youre number of toilets and device.
Do you want to live in an estate? Do you want to live in
a Tegus apartment? Do youre prefer a new apartment?
All these are choices that you can make so that the
apartment is tailored to your preferences. Now, once I press evaluate,
so it's going to give me an estimation of
all that particular kind of house is going to cost,
right? So I have
an estimation of 1,050,000.
Then it's giving me the range of
outfits you can see
5 million for the ones that cost quite
much, and then youre could have 1.5 million for
those that cost lets.
And I think this is actually a nice use case of
streamlit. And don't be surprised the amount of code that is needed to
do this particular evaluation to build this app in
a space Daniel of 100 lines of code.
So let's move on. Now, looking at this gallery, you can see
apps that have been built by sending developers all over the world you
can see New York City, Uber right?
Sharing. There are lots youre can see computer vision,
images, finance and business, and others buying Tesla
predictor. I think this was which I think commodity
market price predictor and others.
I will include a link in the comment section, so feel free to check
out all of this on your own account. And I particularly feel that
Student is awesome. Yeah, so let's
move on. What are the cons of Streamlit?
Why Streamlit might not be the ultimate solution to
all our web problems, but there, number one
is the convenience. Let's make it fade up. This means that most of those
checkboxes, most of the uis are automated,
right? You don't have to worry about them. So that means that you
can't make custom changes to them. I mean, you can't just decide to
place the chart side by side. Actually strength
of stream rate, but what you get in terms of time and speed of
execution, you have to compensate for it
in terms of flexibility. And also there is a cap on
the size of data impute and it's 50
megabytes. Yeah, that might be a con
for youre too. Also there's limited support for video and animation.
Finally, you can build an app with functionalities with complex functionalities.
Think of user dedication, newsletter subscription,
chatbots, you can do that. If you're thinking
of building a web app with functionalities like that,
you might want to consider flask or jungle for that.
All right, so moving on. Even with all the consoles streamlit,
it is simple enough to use for every Python program, which is portable with Python
Basic, and it's superb if you want
an interactive data very quickly. I've done this,
me working on an NLP projects. I just want to see how my model is
performing. So far it's easier. I mean, I could spin up
a web app in less than 30 minutes and I feel that's actually
quite good. And also, if staff flux
developer, you need flask, you need JavaScript, HTML,
CSS and JSON. At the very least,
you might still have to bother with JavaScript frameworks like angular.
And I think that's quite a lot, might take a month or maybe years.
Master all those, but with Streamlit,
all youre ever going to need is just streamlit it. And then
if you're thinking of containerization, that you might need docker too.
Having said that, thank you for taking your time to listen to my
talk and that youre feel free to say.
Also you can buy.