Hi everyone. One thank you for coming to my presentation. Today we'll be
talking about Hono, a multi runtime web framework for the edges.
But first let me take a moment to introduce myself. My name
is Nikolay Pryanishnikov. I'm a full stack engineer at Station Labs.
We develop some cool stuff on the blockchain with NFTs and regular
tokens. In my free time I like to contribute to open source projects
and develop my own. I also do security
research, some bugbal, TCTF and things like that.
Previously I was an original full stack contributor at Lido Finance,
one of the largest blockchain projects by TVL.
Before that I was a startup founder and the founder of a small web
development studio. What's common between all of my developer experience
is that I've been building a lot of APIs. Recently I stumbled upon
a really cool new web framework called Hono. Today we'll be taking a look
at it, and I'll explain to you how it's able to run on different runtimes
and different cloud services. So the plan for today will
be in two parts. First, we are going to be discussing JS
runtimes. We'll understand the differences between a JS engine and
runtimes. We'll have some examples of standalone
and cloud runtimes, and we'll be discussing API interpretation
of runtimes in general. Then we'll be switching to hono.
I'll explain to you what Hono is, why it's awesome, and why
you should consider building your next project with Hono. So let's begin
with JS runtimes. First we need to understand what
a JS engine is, and this is quite simple.
An engine is a software that executes your code.
However, it's not enough for a good developer experience,
and a runtime is the environment in which code
is being executed. It provides some nice features for us, like the event
loop, so we don't have to manually schedule when
a code is being executed. Then it
provides some runtimes libraries for us and APIs. So for
example, we don't have to write low level code to access the file
system. The most popular engine is V eight,
pictured here. On the left it powers Chrome. On the
right we have at the top JavaScript core, which powers
Safari on iOS and macOS for example. And then
we have Spidermonkey, which powers Firefox for
runtimes, in this case the standalone runtimes you probably heard
about node Js. It's the most popular and the
oldest runtimes. But we also have newer,
more modern runtimes. On the right here at the top we have
Dino and the newest one at the bottom,
bun node Js runs V eight,
Dino runs V eight as well, and bun runs JavaScript core.
Then we have a lot of service runtimes,
and your service needs at least one runtimes
to execute your code. AWS actually has two
lambdas and lambdas at the edge, Cloudflare has their worker
D runtime for their workers offering,
and Purcell also has two runtimes, the code
Js runtimes and the edges runtime runtimes
will have different APIs, and it's clearly visible
for standalone runtimes. In this example,
we are trying to open a file for node
Js. You will have to import a module called read file. You will
have to specify the file and the encoding for Dino situation
is different. Dino is globally available,
and you also have some nice helpers. So for example,
you have a read text file helper, so you don't have to specify encoding.
In our case, service runtime APIs are
also different. So for AWS Lambda
for the handler you will have an event object and a context object,
and in order to return some data to the
user, you need to use a return. For Versailles Node
JS runtimes, you have a request and response object. To return some
data, you need to call send on the response object.
Ideally you would want to return here as well, but it's not necessary.
It's going to be working either way. Next, we are
getting a problem that one service does not actually equal one
runtime. So Versaille, for example, has two runtimes,
and you can't migrate from one to the other without code
changes. Node JS is an
older runtime. Edges is a newer runtime built on
modern web technologies, but it's also more limited.
And speaking about limitations, one of the service
runtimes limitations is limited NPM package access.
Back in the day there were runtimes when you couldn't even
import NPM packages at all. Today's situation is much different.
NPM package access can still be a problem. For example,
you could be importing an NPM package which tries to access some
API which is not available at the runtime. Which brings us
to the second point, limited API set. Modern runtimes
potentially can have web standard APIs only,
which we'll be talking more about in a moment.
Also, for service runtimes,
direct database access might not be possible
at all. So if you wanted to directly
connect to your database and get some data from it
or insert some new data, it might not be possible. You would need a
proxy, or you can migrate to different runtimes.
For Versailles edges as an example,
we clearly see that although you can import NPM packages,
you can only import ESM packages,
not CGS. So if you're relying on CGS
dependencies, then you are out of luck. You will have to change
your runtimes from Versaille Edge to Versaille Node JS runtime,
and then it wouldn't be using the latest web technologies and
it's a separate problem. So Windows G came
along. It's a community group created
with all the industry leaders
in the space from Cloudflare to Vercell.
From standalone runtimes we have Dino, we have Node JS,
and they have their mission as
increasing the interoperability of runtimes. And for the
end user, it means that ideally you would have the same
code being able to run on different
runtimes, different cloud services. If you
don't like one service, you could easily
migrate from one to the other, and so on and so forth. But how
is it possible? And it's possible using the web standard APIs,
and those are these standard APIs which will be
available across runtimes. So you can
have the same code running everywhere. And examples of such
APIs is fetch.
You can bun fetch not only on the standalone
runtimes, not only on services, but also in the browser.
You can write your code once and run it everywhere.
We're talking about fetch specifically because it has the request and
response object which you can now reuse in modern
runtimes. So for
Versailles, in this case, for the code JS
runtime, you would get the API with a request and a response
object. You would be setting up a status code for
the response. You would sending some data and returning
with the newer API for their edges runtime,
you will actually get the request in form of the request you
are familiar with from fetch. It's the same request in order
to respond, you will be creating a new response object,
the same from fetch, and you're going to be returning it
inside. You can specify the thing to return to
your users, you can specify the status code, and you can specify options
like headers, for example. This API is much
cleaner, it's much more error prone,
and it's much better to use it. One example
why it's better is the situation I
ran into multiple times, even myself,
even with workplaces I've
been working at. What would happen is that you would be
setting a status code, returning, setting some data
to be returning, but then you would forget a return and then
the rest of the code will be executed and in production you will
run into errors and your
handlers won't be working as expected. So you would have to spend
time finding out the handlers which have this problem,
debugging, fixing it, and just adding a return after
the logic and adding an if statement.
The newer API prevents this completely. If you are returning,
you must return something, and if you're returning something then
execution will stop and this situation will no longer happen.
Let's switch to Hono. Hono is a new web framework built
on the latest web standard APIs. That's how it's able
to run on multiple runtimes and on multiple
cloud services. Hono is flaming Japanese.
It was created by Yusukiwada, a developer advocate at
Cloudflare, and we've been talking about its
flexibility, but it's actually very simple.
It's small, it's fast, and it provides
just a fantastic developer experience. Overall, it's been gaining
a lot of popularity, and I think that's because so many developers
are finding out about it and starting migrating their
projects to Hono and developing new projects with
Hono. Hono API is very simple.
You simply import Hono, you initialize your app and
you can start straight away setting up
the endpoints. So in this case for our app, we are setting
up a get endpoint at hello and we are
setting up a handler
which would return some Json. In this case we are returning a
message with a simple string hello. As you can see, the API
is very straightforward, it's very easy to get started.
And if you are migrating your old project
to Hono, there's basically nothing new to learn. It's so simple that
you can get started straight away. Now let's get to the main
points why it's awesome and you should use it ideally.
First, it's very flexible. We've been talking about flexibility
a lot, but Hono can actually migrate from server
to serverless environments and vice versa. You can switch standalone runtimes,
so you can migrate from node JS to Deno, for example if you
want to, and back. And you can also switch hosting services.
So if for some reason you don't like AWS, you can
migrate to Cloudflare or the other way around. One of my
favorite flexibility points is that it's so flexible that you can actually embed
it in your next JS project and you will have one
repository where you would have your front end and
your backend in the API folder versaill will deploy everything for you.
If for some reason tomorrow you decide that Versaille is
not the best platform for your API, you can just take all
the code from the API folder and deploy it
in a standalone way without any code changes whatsoever.
It's fantastic. So for flexibility you can
deploy hono. You can run it on node JS,
on Dino, on bun, pretty much any standalone runtime.
And for services you can choose from a
lot of different runtimes. So for AWS it even
works on both the lambda and lambda at the edge. Same goes for
cell. You can run it on the node JS runtime and
the at runtime. For node JS runtime you will have to use an adapter,
but it's simply one edit dependency and
one or two change code lines.
Hono is very fast. It's got the fastest
router for cloud web workers and for Dina. Also,
if you're using a node JS adapter, it's still going to be three
times faster than express, so massive performance gains.
Hono has different routers for different applications.
By default, a smart router number three will be
used here, which will automatically select the best router for you from
a regular expression router and the tree router. Regular expression
router is the fastest in the JavaScript world. Tree router
is slower, but it supports all patterns.
If you are running Hono in a one shot environment,
in serverless environment, for example like fastly compute,
then it's best to use a linear router.
If you're using Hono in an environment with
very limited resources, it's best to use a pattern router number
five, it's the smallest one. One of my favorite features
of Hono is that it's completely type safe. Everything you
do, everything you touch has got types.
It's very easy to see what kind of data you
are dealing with. We're going to be talking about data
validation as well. It's very easy to do with Hono as well.
Everything inside Hono will be typesafe. It's a very good developer
experience because it completed typesafe.
It can deduct types for your application and you can create
an auto generated client with Hono.
Just in my mind, it's the killer feature of Hono.
You would set up your app just as you would
with other clients. Then you could deduct the types in here.
App type from the app and this will
store all the information about your API,
all the endpoints, all the inputs and outputs
of your endpoints as well. Then you would import a
Hono client, initialize it with the app type,
specify the base API path and you will have
a completely typesafe client for
your API with all the inputs, outputs, all the endpoints
in a completely type safe manner. With my example
with next JS you can actually have your API
and your front end in one project and you
can generate a client and use it on the front end. So you can
interact with your APIs very easily and when you change your API
it will be synced automatically. Nothing to do to
your front end and you can change the way you interact with
the API. Also, if you have a public API, that also
means that you can export your client as
a separate package so user can install it from NPM and get
going straight away. It providers a very
cool web developer experience. All the
endpoints of your API get autocomplete and
you never have to worry about what type of data is
my API returning. Let's talk about
middleware, one of the most important features
of any API library.
Hono has a very simple API for middleware.
If you just want to use a login service,
for example, you can just say app use and specify the
middleware logger. In this case you can also specify the path
where your middleware should apply to.
In this case we are setting some course headers for post
and you cloud also specify the method and pass.
In this case we are setting basic authorization for
just the post request. So get request
will not apply this middleware, but post ones would.
Middleware is very easy to develop with
Hono and you get a lot out of the box. Here is a
huge list. So the included middleware is
everything you want to do with authentication, caching course headers,
logging and so on. And there's a lot of third party
middleware as well, like sentry error integrations,
zot validation, open API and stuff
like that. Pretty much everything you would need has already been
developed and you can use today.
But if you don't actually find something that you
want, you can easily create it. All that you need
to do is to have one function with the context
and the next function. In the first example,
you can lock anything from the request
or the response objects. When you're done
in this case dealing with the request object,
you just call next. So the next middleware will
be triggered or the request will end.
It's very easy to adjust some
headers, for example AWS. In the second example
you just need to call next and set the headers you want.
It's very easy. You can get even very complex middleware
done with Hono in a very easy way.
Another one of the most important features of
API libraries is validation. And basically you
don't want to be dealing with data,
you don't know what's inside of.
And it's best to use a validator. You can
use zod. It's the gold standard for data validation
in the JavaScript world. Hono provides a zod validator
for you. Here is just my personal example.
What I like to do is to specify the schema. First I will say that
I'm expecting an object,
a name, we see string type.
Then I would set up my hono endpoint.
I will say that the endpoint will be hello,
I'm specifying the middleware here, in this case that validator,
and I'm specifying the schema I just created. And you need
to also specify the part of the request you are actually checking.
If the format is wrong, users will get immediately an error
so they can correct the data. But inside the handler you
see the data is already validated, you just need to
access it from the context request valid and
specify which part of the request you
are checking. And then it's going to be completely typesafe.
So the name we're accessing here, it will be deducted
that it's going to be a string. And we can say another
major features of API Libraries has
automatically generated documentation hono
covers you here completely. You can just import the open APIs
Hono package module.
In this case you would initialize open APIs hono the same
way you would do with regular hono. But then every
route you set up will actually save the
information. So like in this case we are returning an ID,
an age which is a number, and a name which will be
a string or the exact thing over here.
Then you would set up a documentation on the dock endpoint.
You'll specify some metadata and that's it.
The documentation will be available on this endpoint.
Users will just have to go there and everything will be present to them.
You don't have to run any generation steps.
Everything will work out of the box. Nothing left to do.
Here are some takeaways from this presentation. First,
standardized web APIs are great.
We are using in our handlers for our
server software the same request and response
objects from fetch. We are just completely reusing
them. Developers are already familiar with them, so they know what
to do with them. This increases interoperability
of runtimes. This means that you can migrate your
API or your handlers from one service to
another, from one standalone runtimes
to the other. Thank you very much Windowsig for Hono
it runs everywhere. It's very easy to migrate
from runtimes or services
without any code requirements, code changes requirements.
It's got excellent developer developer experience.
Everything is typesafe. Data validation is excellent.
It's very easy to get going or even migrate your
existing projects. Because API is so simple,
it's easily extendable. So if you don't see a middleware
you like, you can easily develop it.
Please go and try hono. It's fantastic. It makes your
life easier. And in case you
don't like a service, for example, where you've been
running Hono, you can easily migrate to another one.
If you want to know more about Hono, here are
some links. First three are for the Hono
project. The last one is for Yosuke, the creator of
Hono. Thank you very much for listening to this presentation.
In case you have any questions about the presentation,
or any feedback or any questions about Hono,
please reach out to me and I will share my experience with.