Hello, my name is Jeanne Grana, and today we're going to talk about Elm,
which is a delightful language for front end development.
When you want to do front end development today, you have to use
JavaScript because it's everywhere. If you want
to use react, angular, viseo, Vanilla JavaScript,
you have to use JavaScript to have interactivity on your website.
And the biggest advantage of JavaScript is that it's backward compatible.
That means that if you have a website that is working today with JavaScript
on it in 20 years,
50 years, one century, it should still
work because the web platform is backward compatible.
It's a big advantage, I think. But for me it's also its
biggest disadvantage, because if you can break
compatible, you can deprecate things. That means you can't
remove things from the language, even the
things that are bitwell. For example, in JavaScript, if you
try to compare null and zero, null greater than
zero is false, null equals to zero is false,
but null greater or equals to zero is true.
So a little weird,
but as this is in the language since
the beginning, you can't remove that, because if some
websites have dependencies on this, it will break.
So if you have a look at the JavaScript syntax size over
time it will only grow because you can remove
anything that you add to the language. So each time you add a new
tiny functionality, new tiny feature to the language,
it will remain forever inside the language, especially during
the new ES six version where we've added
a lot of things. So everything is here to stay, and it will never
be removed from the language,
even the mistakes and badly designed API,
if there are any.
So there is a lot to learn because we're not using JavaScript the
same way that it was conceived. So we've added a
lot of features to the language, and the language
has become quite complex. There are a lot of ways
to do the same thing. For example, if you try to use
asynchronous operation, you can have callbacks, you can
have promise, you can have generators, you can have asynch
await functions. There are a lot of things to
learn, a lot of way to do things, and once you've learned them,
you need to learn when to use one over another.
So a lot of things to learn. But even after you've
learned the language itself, you have to learn its ecosystem,
because usually you will want to use some framework,
some library, because the standard library in JavaScript is pretty poor.
So you have to learn react angular view enough
to know which one to use when, or if you even
need to have a framework like that.
And once you learn all of that, if you want to go to production,
you need to learn a little bit about tooling in JavaScript.
So how webpack works, how you can configure it,
parcel, et cetera. So there are a lot of bundlers,
but you have to learn this also.
Another drawback of JavaScript is that it's by essence dynamic.
That means you can reference some part of the code dynamically,
making it hard to statically analyze
the code. So it's hard to optimize. You can
really do a good bitcode elimination or tree shaking
because you're never sure that a chunk of code
is not used. With ES six modules, you can now
know for sure if a file isn't used,
but you can't know if inside a file that is
used, everything is used or not. So you have some
assets that are bigger than expected because you're
forced to use something to
have some chunks of code that you are not using,
but still you have a complex build state because we still want
to eliminate everything that we can. So it's
pretty hard to optimize as a language.
But for me the main drawback
of JavaScript, it's low confident level because
for many reasons, for example because
of new learn undefined values, you can have a runtime exception in
production. I will even bet my house that the
majority of bugs in JavaScript are
caused by null pointer exception. Undefined is not a value,
et cetera. So we will see that in elm it's a
bit different. You have really
minor editor assistance because as the language is dynamic,
a tool can only assist you to
a certain point, and after that it's
up to you to fix things leading to painful
refactoring. If you want a comparison, just have a look
at the Java ecosystem.
I'm not very fond of Java, but I have to admit they
have a really wonderful ecosystem for tooling.
You can do a lot of refactoring from your editor.
It's pretty nice. The feedback
cycle is pretty slow because often you
will need to go to runtime to see if something
is working or not. Even if you're practicing TDD
test driven development, there are a few things that you won't
notice until you try to actually run your code.
So it's a pretty slow feedback cycle.
And the main drawback
for me is that dependencies in JavaScript are risky.
I can talk about that during an entire session,
so I won't go into further details
right here, but I have got you two links that
you can check. In NPM a package
can do almost everything. So it can
call another server, it can do
whatever it wants. So installing
a dependency is always risky.
In NPM everything
leads us to M. So what is M? Elm is a
type functional language, create fast and reliable web application.
There are a lot of things in this definition we will try to
break things. So first we can notice that
it's really domain specific. In the definition it
says it's to build a web application.
So it's not used as javascript in server
or for your coffee machine or for your raspberry.
It's only focused on websites and web applications,
so it's really specific and it does
only one thing and it does it well.
Also it's something that is statically typed. We've talked
about Javascript being dynamic in
Elm it's not. So everything can be analyzed
by your tools. That means many bugs don't
even compile, so you cannot send some bugs
to production because it won't compile. The editor
can really help you with every refactoring.
And when you try to refactor your code it's always compiler
driven because you will change something
and the compiler will throw nice and helpful
errors to help you fix what
you've just broken. So refactoring is compiler driven
and the feedback cycle is really fast because as
you get your errors instantly when you type your code,
you can know if something is wrong. In fact,
in arm we're saying that once it compiles it means
it work. So pretty nice.
It is safer. Don't trust my word.
I have a graphic right here showing
the runtime exception encountered by Noradink,
which is a pretty big website elearning platform and
a big user of Elm. So during three years
there are like 62,000 Javascript
runtime exception against
almost zero runtime exception with m,
which is quite impressive.
Of course they have like 17,000
line of code of JavaScript, so it's pretty
dingling number, but you have to
balance it with 200,000
line of code of m. So 17,000
line of code in JavaScript can trigger 62,000
runtime exception while 200,000 line
of code elm production almost zero exception.
So it's a language that is by design really safer
for your production.
So it's a functional programming
language. So functional programming is blah blah blah.
In fact, I don't care about the academic definition of functional programming.
For me, functional programming just means that it's
honest. It's being honest. Let me explain my
point. So in JavaScript,
for example, if you have a send
email function here, when you're calling
this function, if you don't look at the body, you don't know what
happens, anything can happen. And for example,
you don't know that if the user email is not provided,
it will throw can error. And if you
don't know that, you don't use try catch around
your code and you won't catch this error in production.
So in production you have something that can be broken just because you
don't know how the send email function is implemented.
But it could be even worse. For example, you could launch
a nuclear missiles on somebody or
transmit your credentials to someone.
So with functional programming you wouldn't
be exposed to this kind of things, because in
Elm side effects are
explicitly declared. So if your function can produce side effect,
for example sending something over network or anything
else, your function will
show that it does something, so you can't have unwanted
side effect. That's why I talk about honesty, because a
function says exactly what it does and
it doesn't do anything that you can ignore.
The language is really fast, everything is static, so you can
eliminate every chunks of code that is not used. You know
everything that is used in phase language, pretty nice.
Everything is pure. So you can have further optimization
from uglyphage. Yes, so you have smaller
lets and you can have some comparison
on Internet. So it's really fast.
If you have a look at the guide of Elm, you can see
this sentence that is quite important to me.
Elm has a very strong emphasis on simplicity, ease of use and
quality tooling. And behind this simple sentence you
have all the philosophy of m focusing on simplicity,
so the language will decrease in syntax
over time. It's really easy to use and everything is
done for newcomers to not be lost. And the
tooling is really good. So simplicity and ease
of use, because it's focused on one purpose, so you don't need a lot of
features inside the language. You have a
very small list of features and you
can learn it really fast. Even over
time the language has lost some syntax
more than adding more syntax.
So it's simpler and simpler. The API
are really well thought because you can break things because the
language is compiled. So when you compatible things,
you don't care about what was original source code,
so you can deprecate things between versions.
It's not a problem. In Elm everything is
explicit, meaning that there's nothing hidden.
Like in JavaScript, everything is honest and explicit.
The quality stooling when you install,
for example, Elm, you have a compiler install, a project
starter, a package manager, a dev environment,
a ripple to execute some Elm command in
the terminal, and a Doc tool and
the test runner. There are two test runners in Elm,
but they are compatible with each other and everybody is using
the same test library. So it's
really nice. The documentation
is enforced, meaning you can publish a package without having
a documentation with it, and it's all available
on the website, on the end
package website. So it looks like that it's pretty nice.
So you're never lost with someone else's code
because you have some documentation. The versioning is enforced.
I don't know if you're familiar with semantics training,
but it's this triplet of numbers representing
the version. The last one is called the
fixed number, and when you increment it, it means
that nothing has changed for the outside world. So anybody
that relied on your package can update safely
without breaking anything. But as soon as
you've added something to your API, you need
to increment the second number that is called the minor.
That means something was added, but it won't break
any people's code because it's only something that was added.
But as soon as you have a breaking
change, so you remove something, you change a behavior
or anything else you need to increment the major version.
So in NPM this is used, but it's only a
convention, so it depends on the maintainer of the
package. If they make a mistake or ignore this rule,
you can update your dependencies and break your application.
It's not possible because the compiler will
decide which version your package has. So for
example, if you try to break something, the compatible will
say okay, it's a major version, so you need to increment the measure version.
So when you update your dependencies,
you're sure you won't break anything. So it's pretty
nice. The community is awesome.
In fact, if you have a look at the talks of the creator
of the language events applications, you can see that it's
mainly focused on how to build a community, how to animate it,
how to build trust in the community,
and a reflection on what is success on
the online communities. So these
threadholes are really nice. So if you
want to have a look, we have the links to the slide at the
end of the presentation. This Community gathers
on slack and on a discourse which is
a forum for m.
So let's have a look at the syntax and for that we will go
to the terminal and use
elm repel. So as I said, when you install elm you have
access to many tools. Here we will help
use the repo, which will allow me to type
some elm command inside my terminal.
Lets me just move that.
Okay, perfect. So let's start with something
really simple. So for example a string,
if you have a look at the return, it returns
the value. So hello. And here you have the type of
the return value. So here the type say it's a string with uppercase
s. So let's try a number.
First thing we can notice is that the
type is a bit different. Here it's a number with lowercase
n, because number only represents a type
variable, meaning that the compiler
knows that it's a number, but it don't know exactly what it is.
Because in arm you have two types of number. You have float and
you have int. So here the number is just a compiler saying
okay, I know this is a number, but I'm not sure if it's float or
an int. That's why we have a lowercase n right
there. So you have some basic operation,
for example the
entire division. Here we have an int,
so we can see an int, we can concatenate
things maybe. Hello?
So let's see something
simple. Here we have some error from
the compiler, because I've tried to,
let's see the error. I cannot do addition with string values like this
one. So in arm you don't concatenate things
with the plus operator like in JavaScript,
but you have to use the double plus operators.
But if you have a look at this error, it's pretty nicely done,
because the promise location
of your code is displayed with a really great explanation
of what happens and how you can
fix that. So it's pretty nice. In elm
the errors will guide you to
working code, so it's pretty nice.
So let's see, what do we have else we
can have some variables. So for example,
I can say is 42
equals to true. So declaring
a variable is just assigning a value to
a name. And here for example, we have some conditions.
So if 42
so if you have a look at the syntax right here we don't
have parentheses, we don't have brackets, only if
the condition then here this
is value that will be returned if it's true. So hello.
Then you have a health and there you can return the
value if it's false. When you
try to press enter you can see that it returns a value.
So in elm conditions are an
expression and not a sentence like in JavaScript. In Javascript
a condition doesn't return a value. In elm it
does so this expression is
equals to hello conf
42. Okay,
so we have foundation. It's a functional language. So let's
create a function. To declare a function, you just
have to write the name of the function, the parameters.
So here let's say we have two parameters, a and b,
and equals to the body of the function. So here it
will be a plus b. So as you can see,
the syntax is really simple, really straightforward,
not a lot of characters to type. So pretty nice.
If you have a look at the function signature, you can see
that it's pretty new. That means that it's a function
which takes one number, another number and returns
a number.
So this is a function type signature.
What do we miss? So for example,
the arrays in m are called list.
So it's a list of a.
A is like number tie variable. It's a compiler
saying okay, it's a list of something, but I don't know yet what is
inside. So it's a list of a. But if you
put something inside like hello, it will say okay, I know,
it's a list of string, which means you can't use different
kind of value inside the list. If you try you will have an
error from the compiler saying okay,
the second element is a number. The previous elements were string,
so there is something wrong. And if you want to do this
anyway, you can have a look at this link to know how
to do that. If you are trying to convert
this isnt to a string, you can use this function.
So as you can see it will try to
learn to teach you how to fix your mistake.
So that's really helpful.
We also have some tuples which is two or
three values when you want. For example,
to return two values from a function you can return a tuple.
Okay, you can have three value inside the poll if
you want. If you have more complex data
structure you can use something that
isnt, sorry, you can use something that looks
like objects in JavaScript. So for example I
can say that I have an object with a login being Jordan
and the password being password.
Wait, I need to be safe right
here. Perfect. So this is a record.
So this is a record, sorry.
With two elements, a login and a
password. So perfect,
sometimes, often in arm you will try to type
your value. So you will have to type this and as
it's pretty long you will often use
type aliases. So you can create a type alias and
say okay, the user is the same
thing that exactly this.
And then you have access to a new function that
was created with this declaration, which is the user function
that can create a user. So the user function
is a function that is expecting one string, another string, and returns
a user. So if you do something
like that, you will have a user with
a login jordan and a password. So this is
the first kind of type that you can create a type alias.
So it's helpful, but it's not revolutionary.
But in arm you also have custom types.
So custom types are very
much like an enemy in typescript or Java.
So for example, let's take
a JavaScript example. You want to retrieve something
from the server. So a string,
so you will declare a
variable like that, for example, that will
be new at first, then a boolean
that will be false. True, sorry,
you want to know if it's an error, so you have another boolean,
okay. And you have three variables to represent
only one thing. It's a remote string that we
will fetch on your server that can be loading, that can be on
error. So you have three variables
only for this concept. And for
example right here is loading is true and is can error is true
also, which is kind of weird because if there was an error,
it shouldn't be loading or not. So you have some incompatible
states that can happen. In arm you will
create a new type and say okay, my rematch string is something
that is maybe not loaded or maybe
it's loaded. So here it looks a lot like can enume,
but you can also say that it's loaded and it contains a
string. So this variant of the enume
can contain a string, but you
can also say for example, it's an error as it contains
one error code and one error message.
Oh, sorry,
it's coding. So as
you can see, the error is pretty nice too.
So after that I can say okay,
my remote string is equals to not loaded.
So you have a remote string that is not loaded. When it's
loading, you can say okay, it's loading. Or you
can say okay, you've retrieved the string.
So it contains the string. Hello, it seems something loaded.
Or you can say there was an error 400
bad request.
So this is kind of like can enumerate
but with values inside.
So it's pretty nice to really represent what you
want to represent.
Okay, do we have null?
We don't have null inside the language maybe undefined now.
In elm we have something that is called nothing.
So pretty nice. I've just renamed it. In fact,
if you have a look at the null reference on Google,
you can maybe find this quote
from Tony orr. I call it my billion dollar mistake.
So Tony orr is the inverter of the new reference.
So it says this is my billion dollar mistake.
This has led to innumerable errors,
vulnerabilities and system crashes. So Tony Rose
advised to not use the null reference because this is what can
cause runtime exception. So in l we've not
just renamed undefined
it to nothing is something quite special. If you have a look
at the type, it's something that is
a maybe of something. So this is a type variable, we are getting
used to that. So this is a maybe. A maybe is a
custom type defined like this. So maybe of a
is nothing or just something
of type a. So for example, you can say my
string is nothing, meaning it has no value,
or you can say it's just hello.
So it contains a value which is hello.
So the main difference with Javascript is that the compiler
knows because of the type of the variable
that it's can ab and it can be nothing.
So you have to handle every case in arm, so the compatible will force
you to handle the case where it's nothing. That's why
you can't have any runtime exception because of undefined values
in elm. That's pretty nice.
I think we've seen almost all syntax, just two things
we haven't seen. If you have a complex expression like here,
you can use a latin block to split it.
For example here I've split it into two variables,
24 and 1624 and
16. In the in you can use the
variable that you've declared right in the lip block. So pretty simple.
And you have the case of expression, which is kind of a
switch in JavaScript, except that
you're not matching the value itself, but also
the pattern, the structure of this
value. So for example here I can say if it's equal to zero,
okay, I will return zero. If it's equal to one, I will
return one. But if it's anything else, and here anything
else is a variable, so it can catch every
structure. Because a variable can contain anything,
I will return that. If I'm not using this
variable, the convention is to use an underscore to
say I won't use the value. You can
also use case of on custom types it's
its main use case. For example here I have a maybe of string.
I can say if it's nothing I will return my string maybe.
But if it's equal, for example to just hello,
it will match with this member and
it will say okay, my string will contain hello. So my string is
a variable that will contain hello and then you
can return hello inside the body of this
member. Okay, so to go further,
we will build a really simple application in elm,
which is head of tail. So really simple.
If you have a look, we can start a new game.
Here we have flipped a coin and we're asking
the user to choose between head and tails. And maybe it
will be right, maybe it won't.
So if we have a look at the current version,
this one, it's not doing anything. We only have the
starting screen. So let's see the code.
Looking at the code, so we have an index HTML file
which will import the compiled program.
So ElM compiles JavaScript and you can import
the JavaScript inside your HTML, and then you will
instantiate your application with the init method.
So let's have a look at the code. Here we have the module declaration.
So each file is a module and is declared with a
name. It can expose something to other modules, then you can
import something from other modules. So here we are
importing some things to under a browser application and
HTML. We'll see that later. And main is the
earth of your program here. It's a program, as you can see
with the type annotation.
So it's a program which is an element. It means it will take
control over an element inside the dome, and you
have a few elements. So during
application in Elm, we've noticed that we're always using the same
pattern that was standardized under the helm architecture.
So the ElM architecture is basically one
data flow. So you have a model. A model is
a type that you defined, and this type can
contain every state of your application. So any variables
that you can have inside your application is stored inside
this type, the model that you define. So this model is
given as parameter to a view function that you declare. So you
have a view function that receives this model as
argument, and you return some HTML to
the end runtime. So you have a view function that returns
the HTML that will be displayed. The runtime will
display this HTML, and every time something happens,
for example, when the user clicks on something, the runtime
will generate a message, which is a type that you undefined
yourself. So it will trigger a message. This message
will be sent to another function that you declare, the update function. The update
function will receive the current model, this message,
until it will return a new model,
a new updated model. This model will be transmitted
to the view function to display the new view, et cetera.
So it's a circular data flow that
looks like a lot like redux if you're used to using
redux because redux was inspired by Zelma architecture.
So going back to the code,
so we have the init function, which is the initial
model. So here we can see that it's the first model of our applications.
We also have something that is a command, we will see later what it is.
We have the update function. Now let's start with the view function.
So we have the view function. The view function receives the model,
the model that we have declared right here. The model is a
custom type with only one variant. It's in the first state
of the applications in the game.
So the view receives this model and returns some
HTML. So in Elm, HTML is
created by using n function, taking two arguments. The first
one is a list of attributes, for example class id and
click, et cetera. And the second is a list of child
elements. So here the only child is a button with
a class button primary containing
the text start a new game. So if you have a look at the
application, it's this button.
Okay, sorry.
And we have the update function which takes a message.
The message is the type that we've declared here. We don't have any kind
of message, so I've just put a
placeholder or a message, so it receives
a message, a model, and it returns a new model. But here,
as you can see, we are always returning the safer model. So it's not
doing anything. So our application cannot do anything because
the update is not doing anything. So let's try
to implement this second screen. So this one, so here it
doesn't work. We need a second state in
role model. So let's add a new state which is
again state, meaning that we have
started the game. So now what
we need to do is check
what is the model inside the view. So we will use case
of and if it's a no game we can display
what we were displaying for the
start screen. But if it's a game,
we need to display the game view. So I have a little
helper right here. So when it's a game we
can display the question and the two buttons.
Let's try that. It doesn't
work because if you have a look right here, we are not sending
any message to the runtime.
So here we need to create a new message to say
okay, we need to flip the coin, so it's a
message that you can create. And when
we are clicking on the new start button,
we will send this message.
So on click, we will send this message to
the application. So if we have a look, clicking on the button not trigger
some messages. So we have some messages that
are send it to the runtime.
But if you have a look at the model, it never changed because update function
is not doing anything as we said earlier.
So let's have a look at the update function here. We need
to know what has happened. So let's say that if
our message is a flip coding,
then we need to change the model. So the
model was in the game and now we need a game.
So let's have a look. And now it works.
As you can see, we have a flipcoin message that is
triggered. The flipcoin message is sent to the update function
that will change the model to. Again,
earlier I said that when you click on the button,
you flip a coin. So here we need to store the
coin state. So let's add a parameter to the game and
say that it contains the coin state.
So let's create a coin state model which is
either head or tail. So as you
can see, you can really represent what you want to represent. You don't have to
use a boolean to implement things like that.
So it contains a punch state. I have an error because
my variant is wrong. So let's go to the error.
So right here I need to give it something. Let's say I give it
and here I don't care about what is the value. So I
will just use underscore.
It should compile. Yeah, it compiled so it works
okay if I have a look now,
my model contains again head, but here
it's always head. So it's not very nice because the game would
be pretty easy. So we need to generate a random
coin. But in elm, remember it's a functional
programming language, meaning there is no side effect. You can generate
a random value because that will mean that the same function will return
something different when you call it with the same parameters.
So we need something else.
In elm you don't execute side effects, you let the
runtime execute them. So in the update function you can return a
command, and the command is basically an order
that you will give to the elm runtime to say, okay, I need
you to do something, please do it and use
a message to return the result value.
So for example, here we want to generate
a random coin. So we'll create a recipe
to explain to the runtime how to generate random coin.
We won't generate it, and the
runtime will flip the coin according
to the recipe and return the result
inside the message. So the recipe is called
a generator of coding state. So it's a generator that
generates coinstate and then runtime will
receive a command of type message that
it will use to generate your value.
So let's have a look. First we need to
create a coding generator. So let's create a random coin
which is a generator of coinstate.
So for that we will use the random package.
So we will say that it's a random uniform,
so it's a uniform probability of
ed or tail. So it will generate either
ed or tail with a uniform probability.
Here we cannot just give this argument because
remember I said that the APIs were really well
thought and what will happen if someone was
using it like that? Here you're asking to the
uniform method to generate a random value inside
no value, so it cannot actually generate a
value. So random universe needs a
non empty list. And what is a not empty list? It's in fact
a list with at least one element and another
list that can be empty. So an unlist
is one element and a list that
can be empty. So it has always at least
this element to generate. So here
we have a random coin generator, and here in the
update we need to tell the compiler
that we want to generate a random coin.
Once it has generated this value, we need to get it back.
So for this we will create a new message
which is coin flipped,
which will contain a coding state.
So we can give that as argument to nonhandled the generate.
So once the coin is flipped, the compiler
will return a new message that we
need to end up. So here the coding has been flipped, so we can store
it inside the state and we
don't need any more side effects. So let's return command
none. Here we haven't really a game
add. We still have a new game waiting for the coin to be
flipped. And now it will work. So if we
have a look at the application, now we have a random value
that is generated. Perfect.
Let's create the third screen, the result screen.
So let's create that with
a game state. Once again we
can create a type for the game state and say it is a win
or loss. Okay,
in the view function you have an error because you haven't under this case.
So let's create the result view.
Sorry. So perfect we have the result
view. And now when we are clicking on this button,
we need to decide what to display. So let's create a
new message which is a player bet. So the player
will bet on funcoin State.
So here when we are clicking on ads, we want to generate
a player, but on Ed.
And here when we're clicking our tails want to generate
a player, but on tail,
so perfect, we have an error in the update because we
are not handling the new message here. We will just say,
okay,
if my model equals
to game has a coding state that the player is betting on,
it's a win. Else it's a loss, sorry,
else it's a loss.
Okay, and we will use that and say this is a result
containing the result and
no command. Perfect. It compiles,
it will work. Let's have a look where it is
right here. So let's start a new game. As we can see,
it's a tail. So if I click on tail, I win.
Here it's tail again. So if I click
on add it's hyper. So this is how
you create application. In elm, you create some state,
some model, then you have some message that can
change the state of your application. And in the update function
you're just updating your state accordingly.
So it's pretty easy to understand and the compiler
can really help you implement things because it will only
compile when everything is done.
So let's have a look at the advantage of Elm. So Elm
has a really great developer experience because of the error messages,
because of the tooling, because of the community, you have no
runtime exception, which is pretty nice,
very good. It has a great debugger, as you
can see. I can see exactly what happens inside my application.
I can go back in time to different state,
I can export this to someone.
So it's pretty nice. The type system is really powerful.
It will always try to reduce
the possibilities of your variables to handle less
and less case. So it's really nice. The performance is really
great and the community once again is amazing.
It has some drawbacks, for example the governance
model, it's basically a one man project because events
API key is the one decided for everything. So if you're not
happy with what he wants to do with the language,
it's not good. So it depends
on what you want. And some
people find it a bit verbose because everything is
explicit. So for example for navigation or something like that,
you have to explicitly do something.
But for me it's an advantage because you understand everything that
happens, nothing is hidden. And the asymmetric
Javascript communication can be a bit destabilizing.
The debut at first, sorry,
because you only can communicate with JavaScript through
messages, so you send a message and you wait for an info.
So it can be surprising
at first. Why should you use them?
Because you have a complex UI or complex model.
A lot of change happening inside your application and you want to
understand what is happening. Elm is really good for complex applications.
You have frequent refactoring because ELm really
shines during refactoring. You care for dogs?
Of course, if you don't want your production
to be full of dogs, Elm will help with that.
If you want to go into programming functional programming language
like SQL, ELM is really a gentle introduction
to these languages. If you want
to write better code, because since I've started Elm,
my javascript has become more readable and better
for me. You can start today working
with elm with my workshop. So it's a workshop on GitHub that you can
clone and then follow the steps. Everything is described inside
the readme and if you want to have the link to this slide,
they are available right here. Thank you for listening.