My name is Artem. I'm a software engineer with experience more
than ten years. Currently I'm working at Microsoft and today
I would like to give you a short overview of serverless programming,
the most popular platforms in this area, and some
challenges you can face during developing your application with serverless
programming. So what is the cloud computing?
Cloud computing refers to the library of computer services
over the Internet, enabling user to access resources and applications
on demand without the need for local infrastructure or
hardware. In cloud computing, data,
applications and resources are hosted on remote servers
maintained by cloud services providers, allowing users to
access them from anywhere with an Internet
connection. Azure cloud computing platforms are
Amazon Web Services, Microsoft Azure and Google Cloud
platform. Let's talk about
each one. So, first in the list,
Amazon Web Services is the most comprehensive and
widely used cloud platform in the world,
with customers in over 190 countries.
OS, which works with over 5000 educational
institutions and 2000 government organizations,
accounts for more than half of the global public. Cloud share
OS offers more than 200 cloud services and
products in industries such as computing, storage,
databases, analytics, networking, mobile developer tools,
management tools, Internet of Things, security and enterprise
applications. Below, we'll describe the most popular of
them. So here are the top five for
Amazon. EC Two is a
compute cloud web service which allows users to rent virtual serverless
instances and run various application and workloads on
them. RDS this is a cloud service to create
various database instances like relational
databases, nonrelational databases and many of others.
S free is a scalable cloud storage
service which is designed to store and retrieve any amount of data
from anywhere over the web, offering highly durable
and available object storage infrastructure. It's really, really a
reliable one. Amazon Lambda
Service is a service to support serverless computing.
We will talk more about these kind of services a bit later after
overview of the most popular
cloud computing services. Cloud Front
this is a content delivery network which is, in a simple
words, improved website performance by providing access to cloud
based data in more efficient way.
Let's go to the next one. Next one is the Microsoft Azure.
It's a cloud computing platform developed and operated by
Microsoft. Includes over 200 products, same as
Amazon and cloud services designed to easily build,
run and manage applications across multiple clouds.
Using a variety of tools and frameworks. From DevOps to
business analytics to the Internet of Things, Azure offers scalable,
cost effective solutions that bring together everything you need,
related products, services, third party applications,
modern nowadays, open eye resources which you can use to leverage
power of large language models in your applications.
So let's move on to the top five Microsoft Azure
services first and
similar to Amazon Service,
Azure VMS and web applications support. You need to handle
different computing tasks, web applications,
different workloads. You just create instances there
and run your code. Next one is Azure Blob
searches which supports your needs to store any portions of data
for your applications. Very useful in data lakes and things
like this. Next one Azure Kubernetes serverless,
would offer you managed Kubernetes environment to support your continuous
delivery work with your cluster and to ease
your day to day life. Azure functions
similar with AWS Lambda serverless computing
service and next one azure
active directory or azure identity.
This is a service to support many features based on
access control such as user siding, authorization authentication
and control over access from one application to another.
Let's move on to the third one in this list.
Google Cloud platform is a cloud computing platform
used by Google to power all of the tech giants,
services and products including Gmail and Google Search,
on the other hand, offers over 100 products and services
under the GSP brand to millions of customers
worldwide. The lineup includes a wide change of
cloud services such as computing storage,
machine learning and data analytics.
Here we have top five for Google Cloud platform compute
engine. This is a Google analog for cloud computing
similar to Amazon EC two or Azure Web services.
Cloud storage allows highly durable
and available storage infrastructure.
Bigquery is a fully managed, serverless and highly
scalable data warehouse and analytics platform provided by Google Cloud platform.
It enables users to analyze large data sets using SQLite
queries quickly and cost efficiently without needing
to manage infrastructure or worry about scalability.
Google Kubernetes Cluster Kubernetes engine
same as Azure Kubernetes services support your Kubernetes
with environment infrastructure to
help you process your continuous deployment and other
stuff. Google Cloud platforms, AI and
machine learning includes tools for automated model training and
AI platform for simple model deployments.
Let's now talk about serverless computing.
Serverless computing is a method of obtaining on demand backend
services. In other words, we only pay
for actual code execution for actual function calls instead
of paying for maintaining service or infrastructures.
As we told before, Amazon, Microsoft and Google provide serverless
computing at their cloud computing
platforms such as OS Lambda, azure functions, and Google Cloud
services. Here are some benefits which we can gain
from serverless computing. First in the
list is scalability, the ability of application to automatically
adapt to changing workloads.
It means that cloudless serverless
computing allows us to smoothly
go through traffic spikes to increase
capacity of our resources
on the demand. Next one is
cost effectiveness because users are built based on
actual usage. Serverless computing can save
a significant amount of money when we have low traffic or we
don't have traffic at all. We just don't pay if we don't
use and the last one in the list
performance serverless Pro platforms provide tools and services for
monitoring and optimizing applications performance at scale.
Let's talk about some real use cases of cloud computing and serverless
computing. First example, Amazon, which leverage benefits of
serverless computing to handle spike traffic
during different events like Black Fridays or
other promotions, so scalable design helps to
provide smooth shopping experience for Milan of customers.
Amazon relies on cloud computing to effectively manage its
massive online retail operations using the benefits of its
cloud platform. The leading cloud platform, the online retail agent,
gains scalable infrastructure capable to handle traffic spikes.
As I said before, it relies on
such technologies like EC Two for web hosting, Amazon s
three for storage, which I also mentioned. It's really
reliable solution and also they use
lambda functions to serverless functions let's
go to the next one. Next one is healthcare.
Kaiser Permanent, one of the
largest healthcare providers in the United States, has been actively
incorporating Microsoft Azure's cloud computing services
into its operation to improve patient care and efficiency.
Care teams in particular use Microsoft Azure
solutions to collect and analyze data from medical devices
in order to ensure data driven decision making and personalized
patient care. Azure also powers telemedicine
services, allowing patients to access healthcare services from
anywhere. With Azure's comprehensive set of
cloudbased services, Kaiser Permanent is now capable of providing
timely and personalized digital experience to
its massive patient base of more than 12 million
patients, as well as equivalents medical personnel to
make more informed decisions and a little
bit different area from previous two gaming.
Supercell, the developer of maybe popular mobile
games such as Clash of clans, relies on cloud solutions to
handle traffic spikes during the game launch and updates.
Supercell requires thousands of servers on a continuous basis
because each player starting a game necessates
a session on the server side and the number of servers must
grow concurrently as more players join in.
So Supercell's entire game infrastructure is built on
Amazon Web Services, the same as Amazon.
It use EC two instances distributed across multiple availability
zones to increase availability,
storing up to ten terabytes of game event data per day.
With the ability to scale server capacity based on player demand,
they can efficiently handle traffic spikes while minimizing cost
during quieter periods. So let's
now talk about what challenges we can met
with cloud computing, and first in
the list would be the protection
of personal and sensitive data such as personal information financial
information or health records is critical in
cloud computing. In a serverless architecture where
the servers are managed by the cloud service provider,
protecting this kind of data becomes a difficult task.
Compliance with the regulations such as health insurance portability
and accountability acts, or GDPR general
data protection regulation is required to fulfill it.
Following the security guidelines provided by cloud service providers,
conducting regular security audits, and implementing
strong identity and access management,
we can mitigate this risk.
Amazon, Azure and Google Cloud, each of them offer
different security guidelines, tools to monitor
your applications to assist in the security of cloud based application.
Regular assessment of cloud infrastructure to identity
and correct potential security vulnerabilities aid
in the maintenance of a strong security posture.
Username identity
access management controls framework to ensure that only authorized
and authenticated users have access to specific data or
applications. Next one is
vendor lock in. What is the vendor lock in?
Vendor lock in occurs when a user loses ability to
switch to a different vendor. So for example, we lose
ability to switch from Amazon to Azure or to Google
Cloud platform. It may
occur by different courses by using
vendor specific logic and things like
this. So how we can
work with this one, so we can work with
implementing cloud agnostic technologies like contrization
or microservices architecture. These strategies make it
easier to switch cloud providers if necessary,
reducing the impact or vendor lock in so
we can save ourselves from these risks.
And the next one in the list cost
management. So it's really important to understand how
much we pay for our services for our infrastructure we keep
in cloud provider and analyzing
serverless cost is essential for cost management and tools such
as AWS, cost explorer or Azure.
Cost management help organization track and understand
their serverless spending, their budgets
on the infrastructure. To optimize serverless cost,
organization can implement resource cleanup practices, set up
budget alerts to monitor spending, and regularly
review usage patterns to precise
resources and reduce unnecessary expenses.
Cost optimization is crucial for maintaining a cost
effective serverless environment. So let's talk
about trends we have in this area right now, where we'll
be developed in the next decade.
So one of the trends we can see, it's edge computing
and the Internet of Things. Edge computing is gaining popularity
because it brings computation closer to the data source.
Reducing latency and enable real time processing
is critical for Internet of Things devices, autonomous vehicles
and remote monitoring. Serverless computing is being extended
to edge devices, allowing organization to run lightweight serverless
functions directly on edge devices, enhancing their
ability to process and respond to data locally.
One of the most significant on my opinion trend,
it's machine learning and artificial intelligence machine
learning and AI are increasingly being integrated with cloud and serverless platforms.
Microsoft Azure provide you open
eye resources which you can use to get an access
to GPT, four Dalia different models which
you can use and leverage the power of it in your application.
Other cloud providers as well provides specialized
services and frameworks that enable organization to efficiently build
and scale AI solutions. AI and machine learning are
being used in a variety of fields, from healthcare
diagnostics to self driving cars. Natural language
processing and computer vision are two examples of AI driven services
that are transforming industries and spam. New applications
right now and the next trend hybrid
and multicloud solutions hybrid
cloud environments, which combine on premises infrastructure with
public and private cloud resources, are becoming more common.
They are adaptable, allowing data and workloads to
move seamlessly between environments. Multicloud strategies
employ multiple cloud providers for various purposes,
providing redundancy and flexibility. In other words,
you use the best each cloud provider can
offer you. Multicloud deployments are expected
to play a significant role in the future of
cloud computing as organizations seek to avoid vendor locking and
optimized performance. So that
was my overview of the current cloud computing
services of the serverless products
they have, and the conclusion here
that the rise of cloud computing is reshaping the digital
world. I think it's also reshaped right now,
creating new opportunities for scalable and cost effective
deployment cycles, allowing organizations to
scale easily while focusing on
code rather than infrastructure management measure.
Multinational corporations such as
iOS, Microsoft Azure, Google Cloud platform provide
hundreds of cloud services and products that transform virtually
every industry from e commerce to healthcare and gaming.
Despite some potential security concerns and serverless architectures,
these technologies have a promising future.
Cloud computing is rapidly evolving with new technologies
and services operating on a regular basis.
It involves new products like,
as we told before, tools for machine learning,
for artificial intelligence, who are using power
of the natural language models and
all other modern stuff. Yeah,
thank you for the listening me today. Thank you for your time.
Hope you enjoy the conference. Have a great day.