Our name
you. Hi, I'm Tanya Janca and I
am at Comp 42 and I'm going to talk about adding
Das. Now that's a dynamic application security testing
tool to a CI CD pipeline.
But first I want to tell you a story. So I
added the Das to the CI CD pipeline and Batman says it's
too slow. The this
is very reminiscent for me of when I first started adding
security tools. I wants part of an open source project called Owasp
Devswap, like swappy DevOps. And I
had added a dynamic scanning tool and our app did almost nothing.
And it took nine minutes. And I was like, nine minutes isn't that
long? And my other person that wants working on the project with
me said, tanya, it used to take 1 minute. So you added
900%. And it only worked at nine
minutes when I really rushed it and the app didn't really
do anything. And so as the app build and build, it wants
longer and longer. And he's like, dude, what are you doing? And I was like,
you're right. And so I want to talk about how we
can add dynamic application security testing to a CI
CD pipeline without losing any friends because
I realized if I wanted people to, one, let me do these tests, and two,
not kick me off my open source project. I had to go
faster. And so we're going to talk about how I did that. Okay, so I
am Tanya Jenka. I am also known as she hacks purple.
And yes, that's me on my sweatshirt. I am that nerdy that I wear my
own shirt. I am the director of developer relations and
community at Bright. I am the CEO and founder.
We hack purple, which was acquired by Bright.
Again, I already told you this. I wrote a book called Alice and Bob Learn
Application Security. And I'm actually currently writing
my second book, Alice and Bob learn secure coding. So it's pretty clear that
I'm a big nerd. I advise at some startups.
I've been in it a very long time. It's basically the
only thing I know how to do. And I am a nerd
at large on the Internet. That is basically the main key
takeaway. I'm very excited about the security of software and I do lots of content
and stuff. And when I brush my hair, I can look pretty good.
Okay, so what problems are we solving?
Because this presentation isn't about me. It's about us doing
better. And so insecure software is causing
breaches, data breaches all over the world. You already
know that this is a problem. It was about a $6
billion problem in 2020, and it has only grown since
then. It is a
very big problem. I'll just leave it at that. And so DevOps
has some requirements. So if us security folks want to work with
DevOps teams, which we do, we have to follow their rules.
And so that means when we do tests in a pipeline, I've learned
we need to be accurate. We can't have tons of false positives.
We need to go fast. And whenever possible we
want to automate as much as we can. And the reason for this is
because that's what DevOps is. And it's the first way of dev.
Anyway, you should know this. Okay, so devsecops,
so that's us security folks working in a DevOps environment.
If we want to get it right, there's requirements for that.
So we want to test from multiple angles, not just
one. We want to have good relationships between the security
team and whether you call it the dev team and the ops team, the DevOps
team, the awesome, super cool people that make software, whatever you
call them, where you work, us security folks need to have a good relationship
with them if we want to get our jobs done. And then lastly,
we want to have bugs fixed as soon as we can in
the system development lifecycle. So we don't want to find things at
the end. We want to find things as early as we can so they can
be fixed sooner. When it costs less money, it's less difficult.
And also that makes sure they don't accidentally end up
in production. So what's with the acronyms?
Tanya? So dast stands
for dynamic application security testing.
It's an automated, there's so
bright makes one, but a whole bunch of companies make one. Obviously ours is by
far the best. But basically what dynamic scanners
do is they interact with your application while it's running on
a virtual machine or a container or wherever it's running.
And what it does is it sends requests and responses in an automated
way to try to find vulnerabilities.
Most of them, they'll make you a really nice report. And then at the
end it's like, these are the things that are wrong. This is how we suggest
you fix each one and then we hope you
fix them. And so that is the gist
of what a dynamic scanner does. So why
do we need to do this? So there's lots of different ways you can do
security testing if you can only do one type of test.
I personally always start with Das. One is because it's the first
tool I learned so I was a software developer. I learned how
to scan things. I found it really fun. Honestly, the first time
I got to work and I found all these vulnerabilities, I was like, pew,
pew, pew, pew. I'm a hacker. Yeah.
Immediately went out and bought a black hoodie. I did not. But the
point is that of all the security
testing tools, dast and other
variations of tools that do dynamic testing.
So sometimes there's slightly variations on the
name, but basically, if your app's living on the
Internet, any moron can learn how to use a dast
in, like, an hour or less, point it at your app,
and then find vulnerabilities. And most of us
don't have, like, a shield in front of our app, like a content
delivery network or a waf, a web app firewall
or a rasp, a runtime application
security protection tool. Most of us don't have that. Most apps
on the Internet don't have a shield. And so you can't just say, no,
go away. Stop that. And so if
any moron can learn how to use these very quickly and then are very
able to point it at our systems, I feel we should fix
those bugs first. Other bugs where you require a copy of the
code or you have to have lots and lots of time, et cetera, et cetera.
I still think we should fix those bugs, but not at
the same speed and with the same urgency. And so that's why
dast. So you're at a DevOps conference. So I'm
going to assume that, one, you kind of know what DevOps is.
Two, you're very aware that it is not paying one person
to do two jobs. When my cousin, she's like,
my boss told me, we do DevOps now because the ops guy failed.
Like, he left. And so I have to do both jobs. Now, I didn't get
a raise, but apparently I'm a DevOps engineer. That's not what
we mean, and we all know that. But basically,
DevOps is a more modern way to build software. It's also
about the culture and the way that you work. It's about
having better processes to get things done more efficiently.
It focuses on automation, efficiency,
accuracy, and creating rugged software that delight
our customers. Usually we use a CI CD and a whole bunch
of other cool things like infrastructure as code. But the main point is,
it's a very modern way to build software, and I am all
for this as a security person. So, very briefly,
CI CD means the pipeline software that
we use to test and release DevOps has
requirements. So we want to have efficiency of the entire
system. We want to give fast feedback that's accurate
and that actually gets to the right people. There's no point in having a lot
of feedback that's all wrong or never gets to the person who needs
it. And lastly, continuous learning and improvement.
Last point. Not all security testing needs to be in the pipeline.
Okay, so let's talk strategy for putting a dynamic scanner
into your CI CD. So the first thing you can do is you
can put your dynamic scanner in, you check all the boxes,
you click, let's go. And then you lose all the new
friends you made on the nice DevOps team. All those people
are like, you are no longer invited to coffee time or lunch. You broke everything.
This is a bad plan manually when you're first testing
and playing with it, yes, but in a CI CD you're not going to go
fast if you do that. So let's talk about ways you could do better.
So first, refine your scope using
a Har file. So har stands for HTML archive.
And so whatever the name of your file is, it's har.
When you are going to, let's say you're doing your work in sprints
and you are going to be releasing a feature, this Sprint, another feature.
Next sprint, you could record an Har file, shove it
into your dast, and then immediately it is
like a laser focus and it's only going to test those things and that's it.
If you have a QA team that uses har files for automation,
for instance, let's say they use selenium and they record themselves doing things,
you can just plug that into your dast scanner and it is very, very quick.
So that's one way. Another way I think of that
song. Don't worry, be happy, only test what you want.
So this sounds ridiculous, but most security teams,
especially appsec people, they have certain
things that are the end of the world that are very bad. And we
want to make absolute sure nothing like that gets to production. And then
for everything else, we might say, you know what, that can go in the backlog
or that can be fixed within five days or
whatever, but there are certain things that absolutely cannot go to prod.
And so you just test for those things in the release pipeline
and then you test for everything else, either in another pipeline
that no one's waiting on. You overrun it overnight,
all sorts of other things, but just in the release pipeline, just test
the emergency things. So this is another way that you could do it.
This is the way everyone should do it.
Don't check off the boxes. So uncheck any box for a
technology you're not using. So if you made a super awesome ruby
app that has a NoSQL mongo database
attached to it, you don't need to run WordPress tests,
you don't need to run SQL server tests, you don't
need to run Java tests. So uncheck everything that
doesn't apply to you. And although that won't make it 50% faster,
it'll maybe be 10% or 15% faster.
Every bit of speed helps. Okay,
so those are the three things that I would suggest to start with when
you're tuning your system so it can go faster.
Next, you don't have to put everything in a CI CD
to be doing DevOps. So just because we
have this beautiful, shiny pipeline that has lots of cool tests
and all the cool kids are doing it, does not mean every single
security thing needs to go there. So I'm going to talk about
other ways that you can use a das that's also good,
that respects the rules and processes of the
DevOps team. Okay, so you
could do scheduled automated regular scanning.
You could have a dynamic scan run every Sunday on 100%
of your apps. You come in Monday with a whole bunch of reports.
You prioritize, you put things in backlogs, and you go,
you're like Jira tickets for everyone. I'm Oprah. So you can
do this. And this is not that hard. When I first started,
as soon as I realized scheduling was an option, I'm like, oh, I'm always just
going to schedule this late at night so I don't have to wait on it.
I just arrive in the morning with reports.
Another thing you can do is do a one off or a manual scan.
So last year, one of my clients said, oh, yeah, we're going to buy this
company. Could you just do a two or three hour
assessment of this company's web
app? Because we just need to know if it's a disaster or not. And so
I just ran a couple of scans on it manually and then gave them a
report, and then they could renegotiate the price accordingly
because they knew there were some problems that need to be fixed.
Like whenever you get a tool, the first thing you do is play with it
manually before you put it in a CI CD. But sometimes there
are reasons that you need to do things manually, like contracts or
short term things, et cetera. Guess who use
lots of dast tools? Pen testers. Pen testers use all
sorts of different tools. They do also manual testing,
but they'll come with like an entire toolbox worth of stuff. They'll have like 18
2030 different things that they'll test with because they're trying to find
literally everything that's wrong. And you can't do a pen test in
your pipeline. You just can't automate that. You need a really
super duper, well trained security expert. And so that
is another way that you can use a dynamic scanner.
And if you recall, I said just one tool
is not enough. So I work at bright, we sell dast.
That's awesome. But that's not all you need. You need more.
So other types of security tests I'd like you to think about are
static application security testing. So it analyzes
the code that your team wrote for problems,
software composition analysis, or SCA.
This is where basically they look at all the different components you
have in your app. So nuget packages, ruby gems,
libraries, anything that is code you didn't write, but it's
in your app, it checks that to see if it's known to be
vulnerable. Some of them also tests to see if the way you implemented
it, if the vulnerability is exploitable. And that's new and
very cool. Interactive application security
testing, where you put a binary inside your app and it
tests it from the inside out. Secret scanners, these are super
easy. You just run it over your code base and it tells
you anything that looks like a password or a hash, an API key.
And basically it looks for mistakes. So there's so
many types of testing. There's even more than this.
Although I would start with a dynamic scanner, I wouldn't
stop there and I don't want you to either. And so very briefly,
where do we put a dast in the SDLC so we
can do security regression unit testing with
some dynamic scanners. We could test against our
dev server. So as soon as we are able to deploy code or even in
local host, you can aim a dynamic scanner at that and get some
results. When you're in the testing phase, if you're doing a
pen test or you're just trying it out, you could either automate
it in the CI CD or just run it on full blast manually.
You could have a manual pen test done. You can have it tuned in
your CI CD pipeline from then on. So every new release,
it checks for all those emergency things that are really important to you and then
also scheduled weekly tests.
So these are the places in the CI CD
pipeline that you could add it. But how
does dast feel how does it feel to run a dast?
So I personally feel it's like this for
me. But one of my other friends told me for her, it sort of feels
like this. I know twins and they told me it's sort of like
this because they both do testing. It really depends on the person
because everyone feels differently. But the key takeaway is
that I am ridiculous. Okay, so, conclusion.
It's really important if you're going to put an app on the Internet
that you do security testing. Dynamic security testing is where
I would start. I would like it if you also did it.
Automation is all of our friends. Whatever we can
do to automate more stuff, our life is better.
Dynamic testing in a pipeline must be fast
and it must be accurate. We can do dynamic testing
outside the pipeline and still be DevOps friendly.
We're not disobeying all the DevOps rules. If we do
more testing that's more thorough and slower outside the pipeline. If anything,
we're being more respectful of the DevOps processes.
Other types of testing are still needed to find as many vulnerabilities
as possible to make your app very tough and rugged.
The people at bright we can be a little silly sometimes.
Okay, so I have some resources for you. So, first of
all, I have a podcast. It's called the we Hack Purple podcast.
And we're actually now on season three. I just realized it says season two,
where it's just conversations about application security and how to
make more secure software and what tools exist and what are some
good strategies for this or that. And so it's on YouTube,
or it's on any podcast platform in audio only formats.
Awesome books. So there's the DevOps handbook,
the Phoenix Project, accelerate the Unicorn project, and if
you are at Comp 42s DevOps conference, I have a
feeling you've read those. My book is in here. Me and my mom
both agree it's basically the best book ever. We might be
biased, but I'm not sure. I would like to invite
all of you to join the we hack purple community. So this is an online
community that I founded in early 2020,
and basically we have a
whole bunch of free courses, even courses about this topic,
secure coding, how to secure your infrastructure as code,
cloud security appsec. Anyway, it goes on and on and on,
and it's free for you to join. The next thing is,
every Monday on Twitter I use this hashtag,
cyber mentoring Monday to help people find professional mentors.
If you're a Twitter person, please feel free on Monday to check
this out. And maybe find a professional mentor for yourself.
Bright has a blog that is highly technical. If you're
trying to figure out how to fix something and you're not sure, we probably have
an article on it. And so brightsec.com blog
is a good place to learn more stuff. And then lastly,
me my stuff. That's me. I'm me and I'm
shehackspurple everywhere basically if you look that up that's
definitely me except for shehackspurple dev.
Someone took that and it's not me so that's awkward but also
flattering. Imitation is flattering. So I have a newsletter,
YouTube, all the stuff. And lastly, thank you.
Thank you to the organizers of this conference who worked very,
very hard to make it a success. Thank you you
for giving me your time. There's a lot of cool cat videos
on the Internet and instead you chose me. So thank you.
I'm Tanya Janca and I hope you enjoy the rest of the conference.