Hi all, and thanks for being here. Half an hour is
very little time, so let's dive into the talk.
I'm Francesco and we will take a quick ride
through the tool we use the most, our trusty
browser. It helps everyone surf the web,
but more importantly, it allows everyone to
serve through our artistic creation.
Well, but first, let's do a virtual show
of fans. We are not in person, I know,
but this will do. I bet if I ask it
all of you right now, how many times have
you gotten frustrated with your browser not
responding? Or how often have you seen or
closed the page with laggy animations or
a bad user experience? Well, I can
picture an infinite number of age dance at this
moment. Well, it's time to understand why our
dear beloved browsers sometimes act
like this. Well, but what
is a browser, you ask? Everyone uses it,
but you really know it really works.
So let's start by learning how it works and
what challenges it faces.
Okay. If we try to simplify things,
it's an application that requests data from
the web servers, sends a network
request to the URL, retrieve resources and
present them interactively. Sounds simple,
right? Well, in reality there's
nothing simple about it and it's one of
the most complex processes you can imagine.
Browsers are the most widely used
software ready to run any kind of application.
Everything today is web based.
They helped us navigate for decades
and they're build with millions of line
of c plus plus code and a bunch of other
hardcore starts. They need
also to adapt to the ever growing demands
of users. Trust me,
they're a concentrated mix of technology
and algorithms that makes the bad mobile looks
like a regular car. And trust me, you should know
that I'm Batman enthusiast. Well,
okay. But those
who write browsers have a little
has to manage. Users love to
see pixels on their screen has quickly as
possible making a web application fast.
Okay, you might be thinking,
why should I care? I'm not a browser code developer,
right? Oh, a little disclaimer.
If you are from the Kramer team,
please be merciful. Okay, thank you.
Okay. Has fence quad goes. As web developers
we must understand some of the mechanics of
browsers so we can make better decision
and grasp some things that sometimes seem absurd.
Actually it's not Femiscott, it's mine Chicho
from Valdemon, a national name of
place in Sicily. But I
hope that it will be very famous quote
and you can help me. Okay, we have confirmed
that it's complex stuff, but worth knowing
about. So let's dive into how it's built
and look a bit inside the architecture.
Well, currently there are no standard specification
for browsers and approaches could
change from other to another, from one to another.
Well, however, today a multiprocess
architecture is commonly used where
each process handles specific task or
logic. Moreover, these processes have
a main thread and dedicated thread for more specific
tasks to manage more specific tasks. To get
a clearer understanding of the concept of
processes and threads, we can define them very
high level as follow a process
is a running program that includes the executable
code, data, program state and other elements
required for the execution. Each process has its
own address space and is managed by
the operating system Lida, an independent
entity. A thread is a single unit of
execution within a process. A process can
contain one or more threads which share the same memory space
and resources of the parent
process. Well, since browsers use
multiprocess architectures, processes must communicate
with each other. So using the interfaces
communication APC the APC is a set
of mechanisms and techniques such as pipes,
socket, shared memory and blah blah blah, that enables
separate processes on operating system to exchange
data and communicate between them. IPC is
essential when coordination and sharing of information are
needed between separate processes,
such in a multitasking system
or a distributed application, for example.
Well, a browser is a
multiprocess application and these processes manage
to communicate with each other.
Well, but what exactly are these
processes and how do they collaborate?
Whoa. Don't be scared. It seemed complex
and indeed it is, as we can
see in this wonderful, beautiful low zone diagram made
by myself, our brother, is divided into
various processes. Okay, the first one,
main or browser process, is the browser's
primary process, responsible for managing the user interface,
address bar, menus, tabs and so on. As well
as coordinating interaction between others
processes. It also handles the creation and
termination of tab rendering processes. Okay,
one moment. Well then we have
the rendering processes. Each open tab in
the browser is associated with a separate rendering
process. This process renders web page,
process, HTML, execute javascript, and interfaces
with the dome. Each tab has dedicated process and sometimes
different contexts, like an iframe for
example. You can think
that each tab having its own
rendering process right now is good enough to understand.
It's not perfect like a concept, but it's
good enough. Well, the network process manages all
network requests, including resource
download like image, style sheet and so on. It isolates network
operation to ensure security issues or crashes,
so don't impact the entire browser experience.
It's basically responsible for communicating with
the network with the Internet. The GPU process
handles hardware acceleration for rendering pages and works
closely. Yes, closely with the rendering processes.
It provides better graphic
performance by separating graphic work from tab
and user interface management. There are also
others processes like storage,
extension and various minor processes,
but it's not important for our session. Okay,
as you can see, each process has a priority
showing how important a process is to the operating system.
DOS balances process priorities to
ensure efficient use of system resources
and a responsive experience for our application.
Okay, it's important.
Well, like everything else, multiprocessor architecture
has its pros and cons.
Talking about pros, sandboxing is like
a security bubble that isolates processes
and underlaying the operating system.
So if one process gets hit by malware,
for example, the image is contained.
So that process without messing
up the world browser operating system is a very
important thing. Blackship detection nice
name. Consider this a way to spot processes
that are consuming too much resources like cpu or
memory or ones that might be blocked, for example.
This feature helps prevent a single
tab or process from destroying your browsing.
Experience optimal memory fruit in another one.
This is about ensuring your browser uses memory
wisely. Nobody likes a memory hog.
Okay? Privacy data this feature can ensure
sensitive stuff like cookies,
private browser data and so on are handled securely
and privately. And the last one set isolation
that ensures web pages
from different sites load in separate
processes for the same reason.
But there are some counts. It's normal.
We have got to deal with extra memory usage, for example,
creating lots of processes and a lot of chitchat
between them using ABC. Okay,
well we understand what happens when we browse
then. Okay, well,
when we enter a URL or a search query in our address bar,
the input is evaluated by the browser process and
the end navigation begins. The browser process
communicates with the network trader process
to execute the request and then
manage the response handle the response.
At this point, a render process is activated by the browser
process and navigation is taken over by the render
process. Finally, the document loading phase begins,
maintaining the dialogue between the render
and browser processes.
It's very weird, but it's true.
So the user types in the address bar.
The browser process asks the network process to
go fetch the information of the Internet.
Once it is received, the browser process
instantiates or look for the best is
another concept render process which
communicates with the browser process and TaDA.
The page is served. So it's not magic,
but what happens inside the rendering process.
Well, let's try to understand it together. The rendering
process taken care of by the trusty render process
is certainly the most intricate and exciting
part, and it's where we encounter the
much clearer critical rendering part.
Great concept, but what exactly does it entail?
What does each rendering process need
to do to render the requested page?
Well, here is the
entire journey that the rendering process has
to do to render a single frame fira,
a very common gesture in Italy. You know,
Italians are known for the expressive gestures,
and I'm sicilian, the best one for the expressive
gestures, trust me. Okay,
let's remove the expression of terror from our
faces and take a look at the main phases of the rendering process.
Tense is a considerable part to the main thread,
which we'll discuss later. The rendering process needs
to handle parsing, style, calculation,
layout, painting and composing.
Okay, hand composing.
Let's go through them one by one. Well,
when we send over the Internet, data travels
as packets, and when retrieved by the network process,
the data is nothing more than row bytes.
The first thing we receive is the HTML
also received a simple bytes. What's necessary
is to execute a parsing phase that follows
a well defined process. It transformed bytes
into a sequence of character that are then
tokenized. Tokenization means converting
them into a sequence of tokens.
A tokens is a piece of text representing
an HTML element, an attribute text, or other content
within the HTML document. For example, a tag
like opening div tag becomes
an open token, while closing
div tags becomes a closing token,
as you can see in these images,
by doing these, what were once bytes become analyzable.
Structure and the tokens are analyzed by
Alexer, Alex analyzer to understand the
language, to identify their type and
relative information, such as the tag name or attribute value
or so on. The lexer
breaks down the tokens, the token
stream and recognize their structure.
So the browser can finally create
nodes and dom using these tokens and
information extracted during tokenization
and relaxer works. Finally, the DOM
is like a tree like
representation of the page's structure, and each
node represents an element in the HTML document
and contains information about the relationship
between elements. But we should read it
now this, and I'm sure you know this well.
After creating the DOM, the browser builds another
free knows as CSSOM.
The CSSOM, a very difficult
name for an italian guy like me,
represents all CSS rules declared in the document,
including selectors, style declaration and their specificity.
It uses similar
parsing techniques,
not the same, but similar for the CSS
files and retrieve information found in
line during parsing. In fact, references to
CSS style sheets are identified and the rendering
process, or better, the main thread, fetches the relative
CSS files or extract styles directly
from the HTML documenting line. Okay,
well, CSS style sheets are parsed and
we get the CSSOR.
Well, this phase and another phase is
completed and the process is ready to create
the layout or render tree once
the DOM and CsS Som are created. In fact,
the main thread traverses through the DoM and styles
making the layout or render tree.
This tree contains the information such
as the coordinates and dimensions of
elements. These structures represent
the visible elements on the web page and their relationship.
Non visible element will not be included in this
tree in the render tree. Okay, the layout process
is quite resource intensive for the browser
because it has to compute the exact position and
size of every element on the page.
Every element on the page, the exact position
and size. Well, this is a slide I'm
very proud of. Quite a notable quote.
I hope you catch the quote
and it's animated too. I'm expecting a virtual
and great applause. Okay, the dome and CSS
on fusion. Whoa.
Well, he obtains not a super
science, but the most powerful layout tree.
Well, during the layout phase,
the browser calculates the size and position of
element in the box tree. This process is known has reflow
elements are positionated based on
their type, dimension of their content, and the computed styles
values on the x and y
axis two dimension axis. This has considers
factors such as viewport dimensions,
browser windows resizing, and other variables
that can affect the position of the element. Okay,
I hope this video help you.
The video is clear enough, but watching it
give a good sense of how much work is
required to position element by element on the page.
It's a great work and very hard
work. Okay, well,
once we have positioned the element on the
x and y axis, a new face come into play,
the paint phase. However, to be able to draw every pixel
on the page, it's also necessary to know how the
elements are arranged on z axis.
So what's in front and what's behind.
Okay, the painting has is the process in which the
browser draw pixel on the user device screen
based on the calculated layout and web page
content. During this phase, the layout tree is traversed
to build a queue, a queue of paint records
which helps detect pixel colors, drawing orders
of element and their overlapping. Okay,
the content is divided in two layers
traversing the layer tree, and it is useful
to generate the layer tree.
Okay, the compositing phase is
the next step after the painting phase.
It's a very important phase. During this,
the browser combines the previously prepared layers
into a single compositing mage
that represent the final visual appearance of
our web page. This phase,
and it is very important, is handled by an
independent thread called compositor thread,
and some of the more resource intensive operations such
as scrolling are managed by this thread.
Before compositing begins, the content is divided
into layers by traversing the layout tree
to generate the layer tree, another structure,
another tree. The information is then received by the compositor
thread, which handles the rasterization of each
layer by breaking them down into draw quotes and
sending them to the raster thread. Draw quotes a portion
of pages like quotes for
our page. After the draw quotes
are created, the compositor trait gators around
the world the information to create a composite
frame.
It is like a
collection of information and
is then sent to the browser.
The browser process, I'm sorry, via pc and
then to the GP U for display
for display to our display. Well,
for example, if there is a scrolling event,
the compositor trap creates another compositor frame
to send it to the gpu. Okay,
so we finally have our
rendered frame. When a user
gesture like a touch on the screen occurs,
what we have to do okay, when a
user gesture like attach, for example on a script on a
screen, I'm sorry occurs, the browser process is
the one that receives the gesture at first.
However, the browser process only knows where
that gesture occurred. Since the render process
handles content inside a tab,
so the web process sends the event type
touch start, for example, and this coordinates to
the render process. The render process handles
the event appropriately by finding the target and
running the attaching listener, the attached listener.
Okay, this work is
made by the compositor thread.
The compositor thread marks a region on the page,
one or more region or more regions on the page
with the event handlers attached,
and these regions are called non
fast crawlable region. This information allow
the competitor thread to send input
events to the main thread to
manage this event only if the event
occurs in that region. If an input event come
from outside this region, the compositor
thread continues compositing a new frame without
waiting for the main thread. And it is
wonderful and sorry, there's indeed
a lot to do and every step is critical.
Critical the World Series of
step is often called CRP
critical rendering, but the entire
process has to manage an aspect
that makes it especially critical.
It's crucial for the browser to render
about 60 frames per second to
ensure smooth animation. So the
entire pipeline I saw I talk
has approximately ten milliseconds to
complete its task, and it is crazy or
it's critical. Okay, if the browser fails
to maintain this frame generation frequency,
we'll see those infamous logs that
are so detested by users we
often refer to as junk
in technical jargon. But we are
sure no user wants a poor experience,
so avoiding it is crucial.
It's important to know that you can skip
specific steps in the rendering process through
some optimization. You can skip the layout phase
when the dimension or positions aren't changed.
For instance, if only color of the text
changes, there's no need to redo this has or
you can skip the painting phase. Use specific CSS
rules like transform and opacity that works
directly on the gpu.
Skipping any of these phases will help
the browser render the correct number of frames
for asmooth experience.
Okay, well, so we
need clarification on a concept we should
all be familiar with, but it's
very important to clarify web
application use the main thread to execute
most application logic and user interface
tasks. We are really familiar with the concept of
the event loop, I'm sure. However, it's crucial
to understand that it lives within the main thread and
its behavior also help us in the rendering
phase helps browser or us
in the rendering phases haven't loop is basically
an infinite loop responsible for selecting a
task from the task queue and placing it
on the main thread for execution until completion. And I'm
sure you know, but sometimes selecting
a render steps task instead of reading
from the task queue to generate a frame.
So we need to be careful
not to overload it. This task
to execute comes in various states
that include all the render steps performed
on the main trait well,
so looking back at the recap slide now,
we should understand better, or at least I hope
so. It's essential to grasp how
much work the browser has to do
frame by frame, and how crucial it
is to achieve those famous 60 frame
per second. Okay, so far what
I have told you aligns with what happens in
chromium based architecture. However, it's important
to remember that various rendering
engines work depending on
your browser on your choice. Okay,
so our browser don't have
such an easy life as we could see,
and it's a good idea to start thinking about how
to make their job more manageable.
Well, some ideas,
some stuff we can dig into include request
animation frame and request idle frame API.
Use it, use them. Use the wheel
change, but be careful.
CSS rules to create a layer of
rendering to create another layer
of rendering, use the async and deferred tag
attributes to
load our script in a synchronous way.
Please use workers workers
is an incredible technology not so young.
And this kind of technology is
helpful to move a lot of work
out of the main thread. Okay.
Manage the priority of the resources with preload or
check out CSS and API triggers that
force the layout and paint faces
well to ensure a smooth experience.
Let's try to help the tool that takes us
through. Billions and billions and billions of pages full
of things to learn and kittens every day.
Well, I do it in my way. I use the bad computer,
which is powerful and I don't care no like
that, but by trying to
write better code. Okay, well,
this is a collection of link. It is always
handy links and more and more and
more. Okay, well, I'm Francesco Shudi,
a developer by choice and patient. I'm a Google developer
expert at Microsoft MVP. I'm also a partner
in an italian company that specializes in front
end mobile development and provides training in this field.
So thank you all very much
and here are some links to reach out to me or my company.
Thanks again. And now it's feedback
time. Thank you so much.