Hi everyone, I'm Stefania Chaplin, a solutions architect
at GitLab and I'm going to talk about implementing true devsecops
with people, processes and technology a
little bit. About me I'm Stefania Chaplin, I'm a solutions architect.
I've been in the devsecops space for a very long time. You can
find me on my different handles or email. I used to be
a python developer. I'm part of OWAsp dev silos.
When I'm not doing tech stuff, I quite like yoga,
tropical plants, and I'm a big advocate for diversity
in technology. But enough about me.
So people, processes and technology,
if you think of it as overlapping Venn diagram. So when
we have people and process, what we end up
with is we can scale. So if you think about manufacturing
and services, they have a fairly standardized process. For example,
if you're going to get a McDonald's, you're probably going to receive a similar
service depending on where you are in the world,
maybe different products, but that's a different story. When we
have people and technology, that means we can innovate.
So if we think about the World Wide Web and what it looked like in
1994 to 2004 to 2014,
it was very, very different. And it was a great combination of people,
technology and innovation. The final one,
when we have the bottom two, process and technology,
this is where we can automate. So if we look at all the
AI, machine learning, how we take our technology and
we give it a process, all of a sudden we can get things done
a lot faster. So what happens when you're
missing certain elements? So for example, maybe you're not fast
enough, maybe you've got a good process, good people,
but maybe you're not using processes and technology efficient enough and you're not
automating. If you're not efficient enough,
then this probably means that you haven't quite standardized your people
and process. So maybe you haven't found a way to scale yet.
And okay, you're scaling, you're automating,
but maybe you're not creating value.
So this is where the people in technology is missing, and maybe you're lacking
the innovation. So these are all things to think about as you think
about your people, process and technology in
terms of business impact. There's some great books I'd recommend.
So Jean Kim, first the Phoenix project, then the recent sequel,
the Unicorn project. And what we can see is improved
information flow. We also have an increase in
other areas. For example, culture. I talk about culture a
lot because in terms of DevOps devsecops.
It's not about a tool changing. You could buy all the tools and all
the platforms in the world. If you haven't changed your culture and
you're still operating in silos, you're going to have a little
bit of a problem, similar with job satisfaction,
identity of users, well, of employees,
because ultimately you want to reduce the team burnout. Because if you're lacking
scale, innovation or automation, people are probably
potentially getting burnt out. There's going to be frustration.
And once you start to fix this, you're going to get lower levels
of deployment. And I say pain because it
can be a bit painful sometimes, getting from code
to production and also unplanned work. So when I mean
this, I mean the red alerts, the firefighting,
the problems that can arise when you have a very segregated
tool chain and a lack of unison with people,
processes and technology. So what we're looking
for is software delivery performance and
also organizational performance as well. I think the Unicorn project
is a really good example of this. If you haven't read it, I would recommend
it, because in the example, the protagonist,
she joins a new team which is struggling.
She's just trying to do a build, and that's a significant
portion of the book. Just the process of her, like chasing
support tickets, trying to find what scripts to run,
the mix of languages, scripts, executables, et cetera.
So if you have a culture or a process similar to
that, you're going to end up with potentially a lot of frustration
and lower software delivery and organizational performance than you
would hope for. So Devsecops
is transforming how companies deliver
software. So when I say that, what I'm really
talking about, security, changing vulnerabilities,
everybody's favorite job, right? I used to be developer.
I've worked in security a long time. I'm going to
present to you two examples. So number one,
what happens when you find 10,000 vulnerabilities
at the end of your software development lifecycle?
So maybe going into production,
maybe it's in production, maybe it's just as you're about
to hit deploy, when you're already behind schedule,
behind budget, behind. Maybe there's a bit of tension
in the room that's not when you want to discover these vulnerabilities,
because especially if you've got any higher criticals, that could definitely be a
showstopper. So I'm going to present to you another opportunity.
What about if you empower each developer
to deal with each one at the point
where it's introduced, be proactive give developers
the opportunity to play around, maybe in their
own feature branch. Maybe they discover they're introducing a vulnerable library and
then maybe they just upgrade. Maybe they use a different library,
but having it as shifted left as possible,
empowering your developers, a lot better I would
say, than dealing with all of your problems right at the very
end. So why do this?
It's not just about the culture burnout, the happy
fuzzy feelings that we as developer and security operations want
to feel when we deploy. It's also about the cost.
This comes from NIST, which is the
very popular framework for security, and what
we can see the cost to remediate. So say if we find a problem in
requirements, maybe we're doing some threat modeling. That's going to be fairly easy.
Well, easy, quick or easy to fix, because maybe we haven't quite
started with still, we're still requirements gathering. Similarly, as you're coding,
it's fairly easy to make code changes before you've started the
development process. Once you start getting into
testing, which is normally when we find vulnerabilities,
that's going to still fixable. But what you can see in this chart
with production, it's very expensive to fix in production. And also if
you're fixing stuff in production, it means it's already out there. So your
application and your business is vulnerable. So it's definitely
worth taking a shift left approach to security.
So what it doesn't mean because you
don't want to look like this poor woman here, hand in your
eyes, which I'm sure everyone has those days, but hopefully
not with dead suck ups. So there's a lot
of misconceptions and a couple of myths.
So what we are not asking for, we do not
want to disrupt workflow. So if
you're asking developers to run scans outside of
their existing workflow, that's going to cause a problem because you want to make
it as seamless and transitional as possible.
Similarly, expecting developers to understand what tools
to run, when and how to interpret the results. This is a big knowledge
gap we see because the way that developers DevOps talk
and the way that they prioritize versus security and the lexicon
that they use, there can be miscommunication sometimes.
So when we think about security, this is kind of the old
school approach and you can kind of see a loop. If we start at
the top left at the repository, we commit, do CI
merge, CD deploy, maybe you have a
test environment, do some dynamic application security testing or
maybe on the infrastructure, then the security team come along
and then they're like right, here's your list of problems you
can dismiss or create. The issue goes into the ticketing system
and back to the development team. But you can see here,
security is an afterthought and security as an afterthought
is never a good idea because we really want to be
releasing secure applications.
So a more modern workflow,
similar, same component, slightly different order. We have
our repository on the top left, we commit our code, then it goes
into the CI system. We have something called a review
app. This is an ephemeral instance, which means you can do,
a developer can do dynamic application security testing
as part of their feature branch,
what this also means, so they can do well, not only das a lot
of other security that I'm going to talk about, but this gives the developer the
chance to dismiss or create the issue, but they
have a lot more control. If you think about as well the number of developers
to security, you've got a lot more developers.
If we could make every developer 1% better in security all of a sudden
that would be a massive improvement. So now
once you've got your CI and you have your merge request, so maybe you're merging
back to your feature branch, CD will come along security team
and at that point you have significantly lowered the number
of potential vulnerabilities being released and you're able to
deploy in a much safer manner.
So advantages for the developer.
So a couple of contextual, what do I mean by this? So within CI
CD, everyone's accountable. For example, you could have a merge request
pipeline for each developer. So this means that
you've got your sandbox, you have the ability to play around, but you're
not necessarily, I'm going to say polluting the main branch congruent
with DevOps processes, so it gives you the chance to
iterate. DevOps is very much about iterating.
So if you can test with every code change, you can immediately
see the cause and effect. So instead of on the first diagram where
I might not know there's problems for a while, if we do
take a more devsecops approach, we can integrated
a lot faster. Similarly, having it integrated
with DevOps tools, whether you're creating issues,
autoremediation, you can get production feedback and efficient
and automated. So what you're trying to do is
eliminate work wherever possible, reduce context
switching because no one wants context switching no matter who you are.
And finally, less tracking and triaging because you've got more value added security
and you have it at the right time. So really simplicity and
integration win advantages
for security. So there's some automation,
it's consistent. They've also got earlier visibility into risks
and remediation. If you could have a imagine
this, you could have a development pipeline,
you could get security results into there. You could then have a security
dashboard where you could see all that might be going on in the pipelines,
but mainly in the main branch. And then when you do create issues, you can
see who's working on what. So it's really about visibility
with this. When you get visibility, you can also potentially
have predictable costs, because even if you have more testing, more testing,
you're going to uncover your problem. You want to shift that left and that makes
it a lot cheaper. So there's also reduced friction with development
because you are empowering them and you can also give competitive feedback to
the development. Maybe you want to give them a bit of security training as part
of that ticket, for example.
So what we have here is an example pipeline.
So this could be as part of, for example, a merge
request. A developer has an idea, they're going to write some code,
they then create a feature branch, and then what they can do
is as part of that, have all of these different scans.
So I mentioned dynamic application security testing earlier. You can
have static code analysis, looking at the written code,
software, competitive analysis, looking at all the open source
license scanning of that open source, looking for secret detection unit tests,
et cetera. You can have all of that within a
pipeline before a developer has even committed
the code. And security as well can have visibility
of this if they choose to. So what
you end up with, here's my example, you are moving your
security testing as close as possible
to the developer. So as mentioned, developer creates
an issue, create a merge request, so then they have the feature branch,
which you can see along the top, commit the changes, run the pipeline,
have some security scans, and the developer can get the results
and then act on them. And this is all happening
within the feature branch. So once you've done that, you can review,
you can approve the changing and then close the merge request.
And all of a sudden all of your amazing code is back in the
default branch as secure as possible. So when your CD
pipeline runs, you get some more security scans and
then this all goes to the security dashboard.
So when shift left is done,
well, you can celebrate, as you can
see here. So what does it mean? You can scan
all code every time.
A lot of tools out there, especially historically, maybe they
charged per scan, maybe they charged per app.
The reality is, if you
are pricing per scan for example or per app, it's going to mean less
scans. Whilst if you could can all your code every time with
the incremental changes you could then see if you're introducing vulnerabilities.
You want to make it seamlessly for devs. I used to be one. We like
our tools, we like our idE, we like the tools that we need
to use. Maybe we use handful issue tracking for CI CD, but we
really want to use fewer tools. If a dev could live in their idE,
I promise you we would. So what you really want to
do is you want to combine, you want to have development, security and operations on
the same page, maybe even using the same interface
to have your CI CD, to have your security result,
to have all your permissions hierarchy, just having one interface
for all this and also happy compliance auditors
which I will talk about in a moment.
So compliance, this can be very
important for a number of companies. So we try and make
it as easy as possible. So one
define and manage. So you're probably going to have specific
settings. You're probably going to want to meet specific compliance controls.
Depending on the industry you're in and depending on what compliance is necessary,
you might want to do audit reports so you can export them very easily.
It's a little right click. I can't remember off the top of my head if
it's CSV or I think it's CSV,
but it's very easily done, especially when it comes to compliance.
I'm sure a lot of people have spent a lot of time and effort collating
different results from different tools to produce audit reports.
GitLab have it all in one place and traceability
audit events. So you want to log
everything? I hopefully don't need to tell people the
importance of logging, but especially when it comes to instant
response. If there is a malactor
within your estate, you kind of want to know what they're
doing. So logging and monitoring is an
excellent way of doing this. So what you want to do, you want to have
the traceability audit events and then you can identify adherence
sorry eventify incidents and also adherence
to compliance rules. So in terms
of desired outcomes. So where are we looking to
get to so greater efficiencies
for both security and dev? We have to remember we are
all on the same team. Sometimes it can feel with
development, security and also operations that
we have different language,
different priorities. It can definitely be a case of pointing
the finger and we really want to kind of reduce that. So efficiencies
is a great way to start and then we can start on the digital
and especially cultural transformation.
We also have consistent compliance to policy. As mentioned
in the previous slide, compliance and policy are important,
so being able to adhere to a consistent guideline can
only be good. Thanks. Reduced security
exposure. So back to one of my earlier slides.
Would you rather have ten k of problems at the
end, or maybe one or two problems on each commit
that can then easily be fixed pre commit, allowing developers
to be proactive. What's also worth noting is
with the reduced security exposure,
what are you scanning? How are you changing it?
Are you changing everything? There's a lot of different types of
application security. GitLab. We have something called
DevOps. It's a YamL file for our
CI CD, and you can literally plug and play and you can decide what you
want. So maybe we want SAS and gast and SCA software competitive
analysis for this app, or maybe this one.
We want all of them, and we want secrets protection. So with
this security exposure, it's not only when we're doing the
security, but also what type of security,
and most importantly, what are we doing with the results?
Because I've worked in a few organizations, you might have security,
they produce a big list of reports. Back in the day, it was probably even
on paper, and then give it to developers. They might
look through, okay, the first five or four positives, and then that pile
of paper goes into the bin. That's not what we're
looking to do. We want to empower developers, we want to lower our
overall security exposure, and we want to give visibility so that
developers and security can interact within the same interface
to see what each other are doing, to make sure the bugs are being fixed
and given opportunity to communicate and collaborate.
And what happens with this?
You end up with predictable costs.
So as I mentioned earlier,
you don't want to have a cost per scan or cost per app. You want
to be able to have your whole devsecops interface in one
platform. Predictable costs with all your security scanning
within the pipeline and also integrated within as well, which can
lead to much more predictable costs. And when I say this, I also
mean cost of tool chain, cost of scan, but also if you've
taken all the steps I've described and you've reduced your security exposure, guess what?
Your costs if touching all the woods, if something bad
does happen, that can also have a massive cost in terms of brand impact,
et cetera. So how do we get there?
Scan results, allow developers
give them their security information and do it when they're
committing code. So really take that shift left approach,
you also want to have a robust set of application
security testing capabilities. So I spoke about that a few minutes
ago. In terms of, I should know the number. I think I know GitLab
would do about seven or eight different types of security scanning,
all just within a pipeline as we're producing an application. And this could be
whether you're producing a Java app, a swift app,
or even provisioning terraform as well. With this,
you want to have your security policies automatically applied
and exceptions documented.
So what this means is when you're looking at your apps, for example, you might
have a hierarchy, you might have your tier one apps, you might be a little
bit stricter with what you allows out in production versus potentially lower
tier apps or internal. If you are using incumbent
scanners, you want to have those integrated. And as I've
mentioned, just one cost, regardless of number of scans
and apps scanned. So coming
back to my people, process and technology,
when you have people and process you can scale
when you have people, technology you can innovate and process,
and technology you can automate. When you have all three,
that's when you can drive true business value.
And what I mean by that, you can improve
your operational efficiencies, you can reduce your security
and compliance risk and fundamentally deliver better
software faster. And what this means is, if you
have an idea, maybe you speak to a customer, someone in your product
team, you have an idea, okay, how quickly
can we deliver that idea for our customer and outperform our
competitors? How quickly can we improve our software based on feedback?
How quickly can we iterate? How can we drive true business value?
So thank you so much for listening.
My name is Stefania, I work at Git.
You can find me on these different handles. Please feel free to connect with
me. This is also part of QCon. So thank you so
much for hosting and whether this is live or watching the recording.
Thank you everyone for listening and look forward to catching up in
the future.