Everyone welcome to comforted to cloud native.
Today we will see the power of serverless computing with cloud functions.
This is Nielsha at Evox Community Guy building various
DevOps communities like Google, Cloud, NCS,
Docker, Hashico Bank. I build a 15 plus hackathon
and I help people, more than a thousand plus
people to to the source. Let's understand
what is serverless computing? Serverless computing in
a layman language is execution model where
your infrastructure will be scaled and
maintained by the service provider. You just
need to set up the small infra, it will automatically scale
infrastructure by the service provider.
This is just a definition for handling.
So let's shift from the traditional model where
we were giving a lot of time to scale our
infrastructure when the user, when the traffic is
more. So let's focus on the core things
apart from working on the scalability.
It takes a lot of time. So why do we waste our time?
So let's shift what are the advantages of serverless canvas?
It is cost effective. When you have lesser traffic, you have
a smaller consumption,
the cost would be small. When you have a higher traffic, the consumption
will be higher, it will have a higher cost, so it
fluctuates. Next is scalability.
So when the traffic has raised it
will automatically scale up your product and it will
trigger that, to scale up that scale up your application.
And the next thing is focus on code, not on the infrastructure.
Eventually we do a lot of things
to maintain our infrastructure in a very good position.
We do scale, we do monitor scaling.
Purpose installed by it. Next is the evolution of serverless
1800. Let's say sorry ninety s
to the era of physical machine and there were a huge computer,
there were huge OS, it was utilized. Then it
came an era of virtualization where VMware
and all the companies partitioned from the
OS and utilized two different things on the same
computer. Then came the era of cloud computing
where people are storing their data on cloud and hosting
their applications on cloud.
Then came container, try to automate and
try to containerize everything and have shifted to
microservices and
all the people are shifted to serverless. As serverless
is everywhere. All the big cloud provider
are providing their serverless services. As some of the
companies utilize it in a better way.
You don't need to take care about the infra besides
service provider do that.
Next is what are the key concept. So it's
eventive execution, automatic scaling and paper execution.
So let's discuss what was event driven. Event driven is if
something is changed in your code or if some
event has occurred. So after that event made call
some of the function or some other thing then this sort
of thing is called event driven execution. Next is automatic
sharing as I already told and paper exhibition be only
what you own with serverless. Serverless people
will say why serverless? So there are the major reasons.
It's cost effective, scalable, time saving,
event driven model computing to cloud functions
the cloud functions is a serverless
service provided by ECP. That's Google cloud platform and it
offers all the things which we discussing until now also
cloud agnostic.
Language agnostic. Why I say language agnostic because it
allows various languages like node, Js, Python, Joe,
Java, net and nowadays UV also
to write their serverless function code in these
languages. We will see all the things in a demo
later on. What are the use cases?
Here are some of the best use cases. People are utilizing in two ways
are enough that is bad hook and API integration.
Let's take one example, simple example, if we
had integrated Jenkins, if we
had deploying another deploying failed, then there
would be alerts and apparently alerts. If we want to call some other
function which will redeploy that by sharing something,
then we can do that with cloud function. Next is
real time beta processing. Let's take an example of
a live cricket match, football, basketball match,
anything. And the application owner would
be showcasing some,
let's say like a game or poll on the screen
and from the data of that the admin,
the owner of the application would trigger something because
he will ask which team will win.
Or let's say if the match
was interesting or something. So the answers
of the users it will change something and
make if this match was liked by many people then
it will have that in the first order.
So these are small things which can be implemented with real time.
Next is image and video processing. So for this
when we store images and videos in
cloud, it gathers a lot of storage.
It needs a lot of storage, so why
not we optimize them? Let's say we
need to just store the image in
the minimum format of two MB and store
them. So if anyone has uploading
that photo in our application, then we can trigger this and
customize the size of the photo to two MB.
So this way it will work. Next is microservice architecture.
So how does it work? When we have our whole application,
we try to modularize them to break them in smaller parts.
So in microservices it can help to
easily automate the things. Next is integrating
with third party service API. You can just see this
is normal example where we are pushing
some comments on GitHub, the GitHub webhook that's a
third party API integration on the cloud platform.
So the webhook will trigger with cloud functions
and it will trigger to slack. So there is two
third party apps and the intervention of them is done by
the cloud function. This way it cloud also helpful
for us next is serverless mobile backend.
So as I already told you an example
of preclaired or basketball game. So similarly
as something is live from the
answers and from the responses of user,
the owner of the application knows which
thing is better and
how to trigger them.
The application could boost about have more user.
So this way the serverless functions are
helpful for it. So serverless I have to back in.
Nowadays the home automation thing is on boom. Everyone is
utilizing their smartphones to spin
up their span, spin up their lives, everything there.
Also this function intervention
would help them. So let's see the
sensor how it works. So when the temperature
doesn't have directly temperature
sensor but eventually from coding perspective
we can utilize the function to integrate the two third party sensors
and have the automation in IoT directly.
So it plays a good role in IoT.
So yeah the thing which I told you directly so
you had a good length of video and then
if someone is uploading the video on your application then
you can figure out how much storage or something should be
done on the video and just store them in the cloud storage.
So it will be to basically help you to optimize your
storage. It will eventually help
you to optimize the cost. Some of the best practices for
cloud functions are design state lab functions.
State lab means independent functions which are
not dependent because sometimes what happens is one
function is triggered on the cloud function and other dependent
other function is dependent on that. So it will wait till
the first function is triggered. So if first function
goes out the next function won't be able to do
its work recurrently. Try to use
states like design state lens function.
Next is handling dependency efficiently to
minimize the dependency, to minimize the parameter
library package sort of thing. Use lightweight
libraries so it will help you to boost
your efficiency and to boost your time. Next is
setting up monitoring and logging. Eventually it is
a good way to monitor and log because sometime
you need to have the minimum storage
or some sort of thing. You have a minimum bandwidth.
So how you will decide that so something is some
thing has gone up above your bandwidth
then you should be notified securing function
code and dependencies. So even if you are utilizing third party
libraries then you should have a least privilege with them.
Because sometimes if I use a third party library
and it has security concerns, security vulnerabilities,
and I had it bigger in my live project and the whole thing will
be gone to have security scan before that and also
to give them least access, least privileges.
So it will be benefits for us because as a security person
we should also, sorry, as an infrastructure person we should also
consider security as one of the core major things,
optimizing cloud function performance. So cloud
starts involved strategies. So sometime what happens is the
serverless function is working on a low end,
low end is minimum end, it is going at minimum.
And from almost one month and something,
some huge traffic has came as some good sale
is there in Amazon or something, then a huge traffic will be there.
So how to optimize them,
because when cloud starts and strategies are not there,
it could break the like
in this technique, what you can do is every
day takes a time where you are infecting a traffic,
good traffic, or every month, every monthly or every weekly
you can figure out as per your perspective. So it
will help you to optimize your function
whenever it is in need. Next is minimizing
function execution time. So it is really important
to optimize them because we need to try and test them.
How we can get the idea, let's take the
execution time of function is 10 seconds and we are figuring
that we have figured 16
seconds, so it is not a good use case. How we
will figure that we need to test drive and then
we can figure it out. Next is fine tuning
of time out of values. It's same as inner keys
with the execution time. But yeah, we need
to figure out that ensuring security in cloud functions,
so security is also main concern in each and every aspect.
So utilizing IAM rules and giving the
minimum privileges to the app. Next is
securing function code dependencies. So try
to avoid giving your password, your passcodes
or app codes and your functions
and store them some other parallel, some other way.
We have key management systems
in every cloud provider and some of the projects we use
vault also to store our secrets. So yeah, try to utilize
the various secret tools handling consider data
and script all the data. And also there are many services
by the Google provider so you can use them.
This is the shift which is there.
So firstly,
how human has shifted as a
human from the animal sort
of thing, the physical,
virtual, virtual continuous. Then came the
serverless. So you can understand the whole thing,
whole economic specs like diplomacy.
I have
made good resources for all the cloud people.
You can do visit this on GitHub
and it's public, you can utilize the good resources.
You can connect me tag with me for inquiring
and now we will go ahead for the demo. So yeah
I already made the demo. So go on to Google
Cloud, search for power functions and then create
functions. You can write the name,
you can then select the
region. Google Cloud also supports
to reduce the carbon footprint so it is showing low carbon in that.
And here are the types, these are the HTTP
curbserve cloud storage firestore so
if something so if something
HTTPs requests are there then it will be good. The password
is public and subscribe. They are the different
techniques you can use and you can also customize the thing.
So these are the allocated and then you can set all the things.
You can also set how many instance you want for auto
scaling. These are the all things you can figure out once
when you are on the cloud function.
After making the cloud function you can see
you can select many languages over here you
have python node react
and. Net java all the over here I'll
choose python over here and we have your HTTP request
over here. We can upload the file from local
from the cloud storage and we can also edit the file over here seen
on the right hand side we will customize and you can test
the function over here. The name is given in hello.
We will just check them and change, try to
change that. It will take one or two
minutes. Cloud that now
I have changed hello world to my name and it should
work perfectly. See the function is ready to test.
Functions is ready. Yeah that can be on both the
things here also and on the console also. Hello Neil
it's there. You can try and figure out
you can connect with me.