Hello everyone. Let's talk about CI CD,
but a little bit differently than just usually we
do. So we will not talk about the tools, pipelines,
integrations, at least not about the
specific tools, pipelines and integrations, how to
use them, how to configure them, et cetera. We will do
something different it. So let's
get started. My name is Pablo Pivosch. I am DevOps Institute
ambassador, AWS community builder, and also CD foundation
ambassador. I work as
lead, lead systems engineer, EPAm systems.
So on the beginning, let's think about
how we usually create our
CI CD, right? And this is,
I would say, most common approach. And I found it everywhere
during the discussions after talking
with people about CI CD itself. So we
have some code, we know
what kind of environments we want to deploy to,
and we know some specific tool,
Jenkins, azure, DevOps, teamcity, whatever.
And those three elements together creates
for us the pipeline.
We use this tool to provide or
to deliver this code to these
environments. And that's it, right? And we
consider mainly the environments,
as the previous slide showed, we consider
the tools, we consider the tests. Sometimes, if we are
advanced enough, those of us
who are seniors considers
even releases, how we do the releases. If you
are even above this level
of senior, you will think about branching and
some kind of jedis during
inside the team will think about the
reverts, because this is also the part of the CI CD.
Of course, I'm kidding a little bit, but not that much.
All right, so let's think about
this from a different perspective, because what can
go wrong with this specific way of
doing things? Is there anything what
should be done a little bit differently?
So today we will look on CI CD from
different perspective, from the helicopter view, we will go back in
space and we will look on it from completely
different point of view. So we will not look on
the topic from the engineer perspective, but from the organization,
not from the pipeline perspective. Pipeline itself, how it is
designed or implemented, will look
on the process, right. And in order to start
it properly, we need to, as a first
point, we need to take organization.
Why is that? Because a couple of things really,
and this is very important, something what we very
often maybe not
forget, but we don't see it, we don't
have it in our minds when we do
our daily work. So why organization?
Because of a couple of elements. And one of the most
important is Convey's law. What is Convey's law?
In simple terms, to explain
it in simple terms, I will say that the design of the system,
so what we developed and how we develop it is
a mirror of the communication structure inside
the organization. What it means,
it means that if two components in our
application have to be very
close together, have to very closely and very
intensively communicate with each
other. And those teams who
are responsible for those components will not talk together, it will
not work. Okay. Those teams need
to be also in that
kind of communication pattern like system
is, right. And this conveyor's law leads
us to some great book and some great
concept called Tim Topologies. And this is based
on the book
of two guys,
Mr. Skelton and Pai. And they created
an approach where we can see all those elements,
how they work together, right? And we see here, for example, platform team
and the platform engineering right now is a hype, but this
hype is because some kind of misunderstanding what the platform
team really is, right. We will not go into details
here because we have only 25 minutes left. And so let's
go further. So what we need to consider
when we design, when we talked
about CI CD, the first element,
we already discussed quickly,
shortly, but we discussed organization, what else?
For example, branching strategy, right. Delivery strategy,
artifact management,
SDLC quality, gates capabilities,
constraints, responsibilities,
releases, and we are in
the middle of the list at this point.
Rollbacks. KPIs, yes, I know,
all of us love KPIs.
DevOps as a practice, monitoring and
measurements, those two things are different.
Monitoring is not equal. Measurements or measurements are not
part of the monitoring. We will go into details a little bit later.
What kind of environments we have value streams
also more and more popular element. But honestly
speaking, as DevOps is emerged
somehow from lean,
the value streams should be in our blood all the time,
because value stream is one of the important part of lean,
what tools we use. And last but not least,
the security. And I always have the fun to talk about security
on the end because,
yeah, why not, right? Something need to stay in our
head. So most often it is the
last topic, last element, right? So let's
go through the details, right? So we have environments and
here we can say it's easy, right?
We have dev, we have QA, we have pre prod release, candidate production.
What's the problem is here? What is
the problem? And the problem is very easy to touch,
because we have many environments,
this number can change. We need to
understand what is the ownership
of each environment, what is the structure of each environment,
what kind of access we have to each environment. Because it
may happen that you have the full control on dev
environment and QA environment, but no
control at all on production.
Production is deployed and monitored only by automated structures
like CI CD, like infrastructure, as code, like monitoring
platforms, et cetera, et cetera. So those
elements areas important to understand. And also,
as we know how many environments we have,
we know what is the transition between them. We are
able to design our test strategy through
the chain where specific lets
will be executed. Next part,
branching strategy. This is like a most common,
most understand element,
definitely more than just the environments.
And the branching strategy means generally
what we do with the code in our
version control system, right? So this is where this
CI CD somehow starts, right? This is the first point
where the code from different developers meet together.
And we have a couple of strategies, right? We have trunk, we have Gitflow,
we have stories, tasks,
kind of strategy. We can have even environments,
right? If you are not familiar with this approach, please think about git
flow and multiply it by number of your environments.
And yes, it goes crazy.
What is the code structure, what is the repository design,
how we provide access to the code
there. So for example, who is
and how we design pull requests,
how we design the communication about
pull requests, how we provide approvers to
those pull requests. Do we have protected branches?
How we do escalations? Because yes,
again, we all love escalations, but let's be honest with
each other, right? Escalations path is
needed because if something happened,
and it will happen in some point, we need to know
what to do and who to notify,
right? What kind of integrations we have,
do we use feature toggles or not? And how we design
those feature toggles, do we do tests? And here
I'm not thinking about unit testing like this,
but more like TDD, BDD approach, et cetera, et cetera.
Because this also will somehow influence
how we code and why this is important because
for example, if we have very small
code, do we want to use Gitflow?
Maybe not, right? If we use specific
tool for our deployments, like for example,
AWS code deploy, probably we would
like to go with specific branching strategy
and those are interconnected somehow. So,
branching strategy, this is the first or the one
side of the stick, the opposite side of the stick
is the delivery strategy, right? And here we need to talk about not
only delivery itself, but also the CI, right? What is the
trigger, what is the build process,
what kind of steps we have inside? What are the
responsibilities of team members? What is the communication pattern?
Do we use continuous delivery on continuous or
continuous deployment? Small change, but really,
really big difference. Small change in the wording
at least. Because continuous delivery
means that we have some stop inside
the process when some manual action can be taken,
continuous deployment means that there is no manual action,
no stop. You commit the code, you have it on production,
right? So this
also influence
other choices. What kind of testing strategies
we have? Do we have manual testing? If we have manual testing,
we will never have continuous deployment, right?
Unit test, integration, end to end smoke acceptance performance.
There is a lot of different tests, right? What are the environments, when we
need to deploy our code,
what we do between stages, what will happen between,
for example, QA and release candidate,
release candidate and production. This is also important,
what kind of deployment strategies we have. Blue, green, blue, violet.
Probably you could hear blue,
something else, some other color. For me it is Violet,
for me it doesn't make any difference because
I have tendency to be colorblind. So who cares ab
a deployment strategy, canary rolling, even recreate,
right? And now think about if one team,
we have these two components, which are talking with each other
very closely, and one team deploys using canary
and second deploys using recreate,
right? What can happen?
Because something may happen. So how you
will deal with that? All right.
In between somewhere we have artifact management. And here it's
important, what kind of tools we use, how we create the
naming conversion, how we version our naming conversion,
how we version our artifacts,
how we inform others about artifacts,
what is the access management to those artifact storages, what is the integration?
And here I was thinking
a lot about that and I found that the best description for
the integration in terms of artifacts management
system is to say that it can be loosely integrated.
Like for example, you have code pipeline,
code deployment code deploy and you keep
your artifacts in the s free storage, right? This is not part
of the code pipeline service itself. Or we
can have highly integrated, like for example in Azure
DevOps, where you have the
part of the tool itself is this artifact management system.
And this may be also important because if you have this
loosely integrated, probably there is
a lot more actions
needed. Let's say this as actions, right? Security access,
et cetera, et cetera, et cetera, SDLC.
In other words, do you use agile
waterfall? What is the approach?
And is this approach valid for your CI
CD lifecycle? Is the CI CD itself
treated as an internal or external product
platform part, right. So this is also important
to know, quality gates. This is quite simple,
right? So what kind of type of quality gates we have? If we have manual
quality gates, we do not have continuous deployment. I said that already.
How we notify how we test
stuff in gates, what kind of metrics we
provide from those tests, what kind of delays we
can allow, because some tests
which are in quality grades, can be quite long and
time consuming and even resource consuming. And if
we have, let's say, the project to deliver
every five minutes, we cannot allow to have 4 hours
long tests, simple like that.
So quality gates, understand the quality gates is also important,
what kind of capabilities we have. And here we talk
about the team composition, about the team maturity, team knowledge,
it means experience, knowing of tools, et cetera,
et cetera, collaboration between the teams and between the people
inside the team, the topology of the
organization, right? We talk about this in terms of organization,
people constraints, what kind of tooling we have.
So those are elements which we need to consider
before we even go to the next slide,
which is constraints, because honestly,
all of those elements can be also your constraint.
So your business type can be constraint. Probably you
will have different approach to CICD when you own
the company who presents the pictures of the cats
in the Internet than you have,
for example, I don't know, space mission
company, right? And you are responsible for some kind
of space mission when
you cannot just use exactly the same tooling
and the same approach or different
constraints. For example, you need
to keep your artifacts, you need to keep your backward compatibility
for 20 years, because why not,
right? Or your delivery process is quite heavy.
For example, you need to deliver new software to all IoT
devices in cars,
and you have like millions of cars around the world. Your CI
CD probably will look a little bit differently than just new part of
the code in your PHP script for your site.
For pictures of cut.
What is the time constraint? This is also important,
right? What is the security constraint?
Tooling constraint, technical constraints
for security. For example, if you are not
allowed to use cloud based environments,
you will not go with Travis Circle, CI, et cetera, et cetera, et cetera,
because you cannot simple,
what are the responsibilities? And here we talk
about people, we talk about processes, we talk about contact
points, escalations, path policies,
times, procedures, et cetera, et cetera, et cetera, everything.
What prepares us to
act quickly and effectively, let's say this way
releases. So release.
Please have this in mind. Release doesn't mean
deploy, right? Because you can have
the SDLC constructed in that way that you, for example,
have some kind of committee who accept or
reject the changes, right? And if you have something
like that in your SDLC, it will mean that you will never
have continuous deployment. Simple rollbacks.
And this is interesting part, because rollbacks generally we
understand, like we have the code in version X,
we have the code in version X, plus one, we deploy
the version X plus one and something happened.
We just come back to version X, right?
And yes, this is correct. This is something,
what we called rollback back, but we also have rollback
forwards. That's interesting, right? And that
sounds a little bit scary. Roll back forward,
but okay, now if
you have two microservices and one is
treated with rollback back and second we roll back forward,
right. You see my point here?
But this is not only, but this, this is about rtos,
rpos, restore time objective restore point objectives.
Are we allowed to have any data loss?
Do we need to have zero downtime event for rollbacks?
What kind of granularity we have, right. Do we roll back everything
or do we roll back just the one service or part of the service?
What we do with databases, those questions we need to
know and those questions should be answered
on the organization level, really KPIs
and here this topic is quite again
beloved by us. Generally it means about,
it is about the service level agreement, service level objectives,
service level indicators, right? So if
our process allows us to restore, for example,
something or do some action in 4
hours and there is no way to have
this shorter, or we need to
use these 4 hours for SLA, or we need to
change our approach to fulfill shorter
SLA, right. Simple like that.
DevOps. And here we talk about composition of
the DevOps part, let's say. So do we use this, what I hate
really, DevOps engineer. So do we have DevOps engineer in
the team? Do we have like a separate DevOps team
outside the single teams? Maybe there is no
DevOps at all as our role, what should be done.
But anyway, what we do with automation,
right? What we do with cooperation,
feedbacks, how we treat feedback loops. Feedback loops and
how we work with them. What kind of measurements in
terms of DevOps, we have monitoring.
And this is quite simple, how we monitor our pipelines, how we
monitor the effectiveness
of our pipelines, how we monitor stability
of our pipelines. So here we talk about
metrics, tools, responsibilities as well, what kind
of events, actions, alerts and how we areas logs
and metrics, right? And this part
is technical when measurements
are operational. Okay. And here we talk about something,
what is called for example, Dora. So this
is quite nice set of metrics created
to measure DevOps. And Dora has four metrics, form based
metrics which we can set up into two
categories. One is throughput and here we have deployment
frequency and lead cycle time. And the
second is stability, where we
have time to recover and change failure rate,
those are taken from the monitoring
stuff, partially at least, but are treated
a little bit differently and the value stream.
So generally if you look on
CICD in most of the organizations and
you will map your
process, the big part of this process
will be taken by CICD. What means really that
you need to look on the CICD
as a very integrated part of your
whole chain of your value stream.
So looking for all wasters,
looking for all bottlenecks,
problems, et cetera, et cetera, here will help you also
to improve the value stream itself. All right,
tools, it's quite simple,
right? So what kind of tools we use,
but not only that. For example,
if you have three teams and those three teams areas using
completely different tools, and what even worse,
those free teams pay the licenses for
those free tools, probably a
lot of money is wasted. First of
all, you have the kind of disintegrated
common knowledge because all teams are using something else.
And also you pay for three different licenses where you
can pay only for one potentially,
right? And this brings us back to
convey slope to organization, to setup of
everything around communication, et cetera.
Right. Security. Finally,
I published, not that recently, a couple of weeks ago,
an update to my framework, this framework which I'm talking about
right now, and there is a lot
about the security, it becomes the biggest
branch in this framework.
But security is really important, right? And we have
a couple of aspects here and
this is the aspect of the security of the tool
itself, of course, and this is the most obvious for us.
But there is something else during the
or inside the chain, we are
somehow forced, at least part of some of us
which are working for us government, for example,
we are forced to generate s bombs,
right? So software bill of materials and
as this is already a law in us, this will be spread,
this will be spread and more
and more clients will expect
to generate this kind of document
into the pipeline. Inside the pipeline,
what else?
How we deal with the pipeline to secure
any kind of injection, any kind of issue during
the pipeline execution,
how we deal with all required
dependencies, how many of
you are checking your dependencies in terms of security
and dependencies of those dependencies,
you know what I mean? Right. Especially when we talk about
Python, when we talk about node js or JavaScript.
In a broader perspective, there is tons
of dependent libraries which
you need to download, how often you check them,
if they are secure or not. And all
of this provides us into
kind of mind map. And we can use this mind map
to talk about the CI CD on the
organization level and to
see all elements which are
needed to be taken into consideration, needed to be taken into the focus,
needed to be improved, et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.
And why I say that this is kind of architecture of
the CI CD because it is very simple
as we have on this side,
all of those elements
we discussed very shortly, but we discussed, we have
also all of the quality attributes
of the architecture,
all those ETS capacities,
scalability, interoperability,
usability, security, et cetera, et cetera,
right? So we can architect
the vision from
different perspectives, right? So the CI
CD itself can look completely differently from different
point of view. And why
we would like to use this approach. And believe me, I use this
a couple of times in real environment,
in real action, let's say. And it works.
It works perfectly fine. So why this approach?
Because we can architect the vision, right? We can
put all those points together in
some relation to other points,
to align the projects, to align the stakeholders and business together,
to build a common understanding what is possible and
what is not possible, right? And to unify the tech
stack knowledge and to unify the people. And please
remember, this is not about ordering all teams to use Jenkins.
No. Right. It is about to think
how we can improve the collaboration in
terms of tooling as well.
And I tend to call it as kind of Rosetta Stone of CICD.
And I see that they have typo here because
this is a translation point. This is translation point for business.
This is translation point for the stakeholders, for engineers,
for architects, and also for the security. And you can
bring all those people in one room and talk with
them at the same time. All right? And this is also
what I've done and this is very
valuable here to have the broad
understanding on, let's call it
enough level for all those
parties which are participating in your organization success.
Because on the end of the day, it's not the team or
DevOps or QA or whatever, the one team who sells
the product organization does it.
Right? So thank you very much. I hope it was
useful for you. If you have any questions, you can
reach me on my LinkedIn. And if
you are interested in this framework, if I make any
thinking process happening in your minds right now,
you can go into WW CICD
run and there is this framework where you
can download this mind map in the most current version.
So thank you very much and enjoy rest
of the day and see
you somewhere else very soon. Thank you
very much.