Hello everyone, thanks for joining us. Today in
this rapidly evolving digital era, businesses are continuously
seeking ways to leverage modern technology g's
to enhance their efficiency, stay competitive
and accelerate their growth. A pivotal aspect
of this transformation is digital modernization.
Today, we embark on a journey into the realm of
digital modernization on public cloud platforms,
examining its three key facets,
application modernization, infrastructure modernisation and
data modernization. We'll also look into the strategic
use of tools like terraform and Packer,
crafting a resilient platform that empowers us
to unlock the complete capabilities of the public cloud platform
through streamlined deployment and resource reapplication.
As we embark on our exploration for digital modernization
today, it is crucial to dispel the misconception
that it merely involves migrating applications
to the cloud. The landscape of modernization extends
beyond a simple relocation.
It encompasses a holistic transformation that
integrates three essential elements, application,
infrastructure and data. These three
facets synergize to form the comprehensive concept of
digital modernization. Now let's break it
down a little further. Application modernisation involves
optimizing and enhancing existing applications,
making them cloud native, scalable and agile.
Simultaneously, infrastructure modernization focuses
on refining the underlying it infrastructure
to harness the full potential of cloud resources.
Finally, digital modernization addresses
the strategic management and utilization of data,
ensuring that it becomes a valuable asset for
informed decision making. Together,
these interconnected components redefine the digital
landscape, creating a symbiotic relationship
that goes beyond simple migration.
It is a transformative journey towards digital
modernisation. So remember in this
equation, the combined force of application modernisation,
infrastructure modernization and data modernization
provides the true essence of digital modernisation.
Now, there are many benefits of application modernisation
and some of these benefits include increased agility
and scalability. All the cloud based applications
are much more agile and scalable than traditional on
premises applications. This means that businesses
can quickly adapt to changing customer demands and
market conditions. It also provides reduced
costs. All the cloudbased applications can help businesses to
reduce their it costs by eliminating the need to purchase
and maintain on premises hardware and software.
Improved security and compliance cloud platforms
offer a number of security and compliance features that can
help businesses to protect their data and applications.
Cloudbased applications can also provide a better user
experience than the traditional on premises applications.
This is primarily because they can be accessed from anywhere
on any device and they can be updated more frequently.
Cloudbased applications can also help businesses to innovate
more quickly by providing access to new technologies
and development tools. Now, before we dive in,
let's clarify the concept of digital modernization.
I believe digital modernization is the process of
harnessing advanced technologies and platforms
to transform IT infrastructure, data management and
application development. In the context of
Google Cloud platform or any other cloud platform for that
matter, we'll break it down into true core categories.
Infrastructure modernization it is the foundation of digital
transformation. It is basically transitioning
from legacy on premises infrastructure
to agile, scalable and cloud based solutions.
Google Cloud platform also offers a wide array
of services and tools for modernizing infrastructure.
Then comes data modernization, which is
unlocking the value of data through cloud based storage and
processing capabilities, empowering advanced
analytics, real time insights and
intelligent decision making. Similar to
the infosec modernization, Google Cloud provides powerful
solutions for data modernisation as well for
data warehousing, data lakes, analytics and machine
learning. Third in the list is application modernization,
which is basically the process of updating application architecture,
design and functionality to leverage new technologies
and cloud platforms, enhancing scalability,
agility and user experience of the application.
A transformative process that goes beyond simple migration
to the cloud infrastructure modernization forms
the bedrock of any digital modernisation.
It involves migrating from traditional on premises setups
to dynamic cloud based infrastructure.
It refers to the process of updating and migrating
an organization's IT infrastructure to the cloud.
This can involve moving servers, storage networking
to the cloud, as well as adopting cloud native technologies
such as containerization and serverless computing.
The key elements include virtualization and containerization
by utilizing tools like Kubernetes and compute
engine for scalability, profitability and efficiency.
Infrastructure as a code which is automating infrastructure provisioning
and management through code based tools like terraform
serverless computing which is leveraging platforms like cloud run
cloud functions for automatic scaling and cost
efficiency. Then we have network modernisation which
is Google
Cloud platform's high performance network infrastructure for
fast, secure and globally connected applications.
From a data modernization perspective, data is a
very valuable asset and modernizing data management unlocks
its full potential. Data modernization
refers to the process of updating and migrating
an organization's data into the cloud. This can
involve moving data from on premises data centers to
cloudbased data lakes and warehouses, as well
as adopting cloudbased data processing and analytics tools.
Some of the key concepts include data warehousing
which is migrating to solutions like bigquery for
handling large volumes of structured and semi structured data,
data lakes and analytics where storing,
managing and analyzing diverse data types using
cloud storage, dataflow and dataproc.
Then we have data streaming and real time analytics which
is ingesting, processing and analyzing data
in real time using tools like cloud, pubsub,
machine learning and AI. Harnessing AI services like
Automl AI platform and Tensorflow
for innovation and efficiency.
Lastly, application modernisation. It is all
about more than just migrating to the cloud,
it is about enhancing applications architecture and functionality.
Some of the key concepts included in application modernization
process are breaking the application into
microservices architecture. As I mentioned,
it is basically the process of breaking monolithic applications into
microservices for agility,
scalability and independent deployment.
API based integration which is fostering interoperability
through seamless integration with other applications
and systems. DevOps and CI CD
which is embracing DevOps practices and CI
CD pipelines for automated builds,
testing and deployment employ something like
domain driven design. If the core businesses are aligned
with specific domains, decouple the
applications from any specific technology.
Isolate business logic from technology stack now
whenever we talk about migration to the cloud,
we have heard of the R's. Depending on the
vendor it can be 5 hours, 6 hours
or 7 hours, but on a very high level the
R's. Here are the process
or the methodology that we are using to move the
application to the cloud. So first one
in the list is retire. This is basically the
process of where after application
discovery you can decide that you don't need these applications
in the future, so you are just going to retire them.
This is just getting rid of them as you are not going to use them
anymore in future. Second one is retain.
You can decide to keep applications exactly as is before
a reevaluation sometime in future is required.
An example of this application migration strategy could
be unsupported authentic system and applications
legacy applications that do not have a business justification
for migrating to the cloud. The next one is rehost.
One of the most basic ways of migrating to the cloud is simply
to rehost something and this is sometimes also called as
lift and shift. This means to take your applications
or systems and move them exactly as is into the cloud
environment. This approach is great for organizations
that need to migrate quickly. For example, the data
center lease is coming to end soon. For the
majority of applications, this type of strategy is
also the first step because it's easier to optimize
or rearchitect them once they are already running in the
cloud. An example of
this kind of strategy could be a VM currently running in your
local ESX cluster which is copied to
a vsphere instance running on cloud,
something like GCP VM instance.
Some of the pros of this approach is speed
of migration. Reduced risk of
migration could be automated or assisted by cloud native tools.
Then we have real platform which is sometimes called
as lift and reshape because you can potentially
take advantage of some of the spatial capabilities
of the cloud. An example of this app migration strategy would
be replatforming leads to cloud optimization
due to some cloud platform adoption while
keeping the application core architecture the same.
Often, replatforming is used when replacing
database backends of application with a corresponding
pass database solution of a cloud provider.
The next strategy in the list is repurchase.
Repurchasing, also called as replacing, is the
strategy where the legacy application is fully replaced
by a SaaS solution that provides the same or similar
capabilities. This involves abandoning
the existing software that you have and migrating to
a cloud first application. An example
could be changing your web application firewall to
something like cloud armor web application firewall with managed
rules, or swapping a self run email
system for an online email as a service offering.
The last one in the list is rearchitect or refactor
for highly critical applications that require cloud
native characteristics or applications that need
thorough modernization due to outdated NAS or performance issues.
Rearchitecting, also called as refactoring or rebuild,
is the strategy that usually leads to the highest transformation
cost. However, it allows optimized use of
cloud, leading to cloud native benefits and making the application future
proofite. Rearchitecting an
application often comes along with the opportunity to
even break down the supported business processes into fragments,
which greatly improves simplicity and makes a business process
more agile. This is the most advanced application
migration strategy. Put simply, it is a redesign
of your application in a more cloud native manner.
In general, you create a serverless version of legacy
application. An example of this approach could
be migration of your on premises
oracle database to something like cloud spanner.
You can choose to modernize your monolithic application
by breaking it down into smaller microservices and
leverage services like cloud run or cloud function.
Some of the benefits are highly increased
efficiency, agility and improved cost,
eliminating dependency on custom hardware or proprietary
technology platforms and no infrastructure
or service to maintain. Just a call out
here that it's the last approach which is refactor
or rearchitecting which is basically the application modernization
that we are going to be focusing on now.
Just to reemphasize application modernisation is
the process of updating and refactoring existing
applications to take advantage of new technologies and
cloud computing platforms. This can involve
a variety of changes such as migrating applications
to the cloud native services, refactoring them
to a microservice architecture, or adding
a new feature such as mobile support or artificial
intelligence. To summarize, everything that we
have discussed the three facets of modernization.
Google Cloud platform, along with Hashicoff product
suite, offers a wide range of services and tools that
can help businesses to modernize their application.
An example of such an architecture or such a
solution could be something that's shown on this
page here. I'm not saying this is the only solution,
but a combination of different services that are
displayed here could be used to achieve a complete
digital transformation for our business.
So on the very far left,
top side, we have externally facing applications
configured with cloud load balancing and cloud armor.
Tools like APG API platform or cloud endpoints
are used for interfacing with applications
via custom developed API endpoints.
Then we have native tools like cloud build in conjunction
with third party tools such as terraform and Packer that
are used to define infrastructure as a code.
Application secrets can be stored
securely in secrets manager or hashicoff vault
data encryption address is provided to
multiple services via key management system or KMS,
in short, container image deployment using
artifact registry and securing that with
signature validation via binary authorization,
which is basically the process of only deploying the images
from verified sources.
Then we have application compute components replatformed
and are rearchitected into containerized
platforms, things like cloud run or GKE
or even cloud functions.
Then we have on the right hand side, in the middle
of this whole tier data where
we host data on cloud native services such as cloud
storage, cloud SQL firestore or
memory store event driven interaction
using services like pub sub or event arc.
Then at the very far right, we have cloud
operation suites utilized for application observability and
then we have tools like Bigquery and Google Data Studio
for analytics purposes. So as we can see
the whole spectrum from left to right, there are a number of services
that we can use to optimize the infrastructure,
application and data to provide the complete digital modernization
to any business. Now, to distinguish between application
modernization and cloud migration,
I'll put together some of the key focus areas
here. While these two are closely
related, application modernization and cloud
migration have distinct focuses and scopes.
So from a focus perspective, application modernization
enhances application architecture,
whereas cloud migration primarily involves
shifting to the cloud, moving your application from on premises
to the cloud. From a scope perspective,
application modernization encompasses infrastructure,
data and application architecture, whereas cloud
migration centers on application and infrastructure
transition from a compelling moment
or trigger point perspective. More often
than not, application modernization is
considered when there are issues with the application performance
or when you want to include new capabilities and the functionalities,
how the application is run or behaving.
Whereas for cloud migration it is primarily when the
data center leave is coming to an end and we need to
move our application off to another
set of servers or we need to renew the lease.
So that's when the cloud migration is primarily considered.
From benefits perspective, application modernization fully
leverages cloud technology's potential,
whereas cloud migration primarily taps into
the scalability and flexibility that is provided
by the public cloud platform. Now,
in the quest to harness the power of cloud technology,
application modernisation is a pivotal strategy.
By understanding infrastructure modernization,
data modernization and application modernisation as
interconnected components, businesses can embark
on a comprehensive journey to transform their applications
and fully embrace the potential of the public cloud application
modernisation, infrastructure modernization and data modernization
are all essential components of a comprehensive digital
transformation strategy. By modernisation,
all these true components organizations can
improve their agility, scalability and efficiency
to gain a competitive advantage in this digital
economy. Remember, it's not just
about moving to the cloud, it's about optimizing
applications for success in the modern digital landscape.
Thank you for your attention.