Hey, friends, I'm going to kick things off today with a story.
Well, an embarrassing story. So back when I
was working on my master's degree in computer science, I had to write a thesis.
And a thesis is this massive paper where you explain your research
and how it contributes to the larger body of work. Now,
I diligently worked on my thesis over time,
and looking back, I should have sent it to my professor every time,
finished a chapter. But I was never really
thrilled with what I had written, so I just kept chipping away at it on
my own. Now, eventually, I finished the
first draft and I had to send it to my professor.
I needed to know if it was any good. My graduation depended
on it. So I sent it to her.
The whole thing, all 83 pages,
and she didn't reply. I knew she had it,
but she was a busy professor with lots going on, and she didn't have time
to read an entire massive paper all in one night.
So I anxiously awaited her reply.
I don't even remember how much time passed, but I got more and more
nervous by the hour. I was totally in my head. I was asking
myself questions like, how much was I going to have to rework?
Was I going to be able to graduate on time? Was I just bad at
this whole grad school thing? Now, eventually she
replied, and she liked it. She had
recommendations, of course, like, it wasn't perfect, but her
overall review was positive. I wasn't going to have
to redo my research or rewrite the whole thing.
Graduation was within my grasp. I was absolutely
thrilled. So I was so excited.
And I'm a millennial who's very attached to their mom.
So I decided I should forward this email to my mom. I started typing out,
mom, I'm so excited. My professor liked it. I'm going to
graduate. Book your flight. I'm going to graduate. This is great.
Now, I initially threw in a little shade about someone else, and then
I deleted that part about the other person and I pressed send.
And that is when I realized my mistake. I had
not forwarded the email to my mom, I had forwarded it to my
professor, and there was no way to stop
it.
And so off it went into her inbox,
and I was mortified. And I was super glad that I'd removed
the shade about the other person. Now, luckily,
my professor was very cool about the whole thing and she didn't hang it over
me. But I remained embarrassed.
And I also learned about Google's undo send that day because
for some reason, mistakes become so much more obvious. When you actually
press send.
So let's have a moment of solidarity together.
Just think about it. Has your writing ever gotten you into trouble?
Maybe you sent an email or a chat message that didn't go to
the person or group you intended. Maybe your tone was
a little snotty, either intentionally or unintentionally.
Or maybe you missed an opportunity because the reader just didn't
understand what you meant. The written
word is powerful. It can get you into
trouble if you're not careful. But it also has the power
to level up your career.
We're all writing every day. A recent study found
that knowledge workers spend about 20 hours a week. That's roughly
half our work week on written communication.
Writing is super important, and it's hard to get it right.
Much like writing code, if you use the wrong word, you misplace
a character. Youll can get it all wrong,
but when you get it right, it feels so good
and the impact can be massive.
Your writing has the power to improve your personal success
and your personal reputation.
Over the next few minutes, I'm going to share with you five concrete strategies
for writing to level up your career. And then
I'll share three ways that you can improve the quality of your
writing. Okay, so let's just dive right in with strategies
for writing in order to level up your career.
First, strategies write to help your
users. So, jumping back
a little more backstory on me. After grad
school, I started working as a software engineer. I chipped away
at my coding projects at work. I started getting comfortable with them,
and then I asked my manager what I needed to do in order to move
my career forward. He emphasized the importance
of demonstrating scope I needed to show that
I was influencing and helping others.
So he recommended that I begin answering questions on
our user forums. Now, I got to tell you, this was
a little scary to me at the time. I certainly was not an expert
on our products, and I didn't want to look dumb in front of my colleagues
who would be reading my public answers.
But I decided to try it anyway.
So I set a goal for myself to answer one question each
day. In the beginning, I had to really
search for a question that I had a clue how to answer.
I often had to code the solution myself to figure out if what
I thought would work would actually work.
The first time someone marked my answer as correct felt amazing,
like I, a new grad, had helped a professional like
out in the real world. That was so cool.
Now, I'm not going to pretend I always got my answers 100% right? I mean,
sometimes my colleagues would drop in and add suggestions to my answers
and sometimes I wouldn't receive any feedback at all and I would have no
idea if my answers were helping other people.
But over time, I learned more about our product
and I got better at answering questions.
So I kept at it and I continued to try and answer one
question a day. My reputation points grew
a little bit each day and I eventually ranked in the top 1%
of users on our forums in terms of reputation points.
End users, as well as colleagues from other offices
who I'd never met, began to recognize my name.
Writing was starting to give me visibility,
and I just share this to show that little bits of writing every
day add up over the long term.
Once I was somewhat confidently answering questions on our user forums,
I went back to my manager and was like, hey, what do I need to
do to progress my career? And he suggested that
I start writing posts on our company blog. Once again,
this was new and scary. I remember
just staring at a blank screen and thinking, oh my gosh,
how am I going to sound competent when I have to write so many
words? But I pushed through the discomfort
and I published a post and then I kept
going, becoming a very frequent author on our blog and these
activities are part of what led to my current role as a developer advocate at
Grammarly, whose mission is to improve lives by
improving communication. I was able to take the writing
skills I developed over my years as a software engineer and then
turn them into a core part of a career that I love.
Writing to users improved my career at a company where I was
working and then helped me pivot to a slightly different career at other companies.
All right, that's enough about me. Let's look about you and how you can
write to help your users. Your users might be internal at
your company or external users of your product.
Whatever the case, write to them. Help them.
There are so many ways you can do this, and what makes sense for you
will be customized for your company and your role. But let me give you
some ideas. You can answer questions in
forums. You can write blog posts and tutorials
on your company's blog. You can write documentation.
You can respond to users bug reports and requests for features.
You can write reason for outage reports.
You can email your users.
You can chat with your users on platforms like Slack or discord.
Or you can even curate a newsletter.
Perhaps you're thinking, why bother?
This seems like a lot of work. Well, these are
the sorts of things that can impact your company's bottom line.
If your users are unhappy or confused or frustrated.
Your role, your team, or your company may not
be around for long. Now, you might also be thinking,
well, this sounds great, but writing to my users is not one of
my core responsibilities. How can I possibly make
time for this? I encourage you to take a look at your career
ladder or talk with your manager to discover what you need
to do to progress to the next level. I've looked
at a lot of technical career ladders, and almost all of them require
you to demonstrate scope and influence.
Showing that you're impacting your users through personalized help or more
broadly on a larger, less personalized scale is a great way to
do that. All right, so write
to help your users. Second strategy for writing
in order to level up your career is to write
to educate the tech community. I believe that
everyone has a story to tell. Seriously.
Maybe you've worked really hard to become an expert in a technology.
You've got a story, you can share what you know.
Maybe you're in the process of learning something new.
Share as you learn. This is a great way to reinforce
your learning. Or maybe youll have failed spectacularly.
Share your story so we don't make the same mistakes.
You can share your technical skills as well as your
soft skills, or some people call them core skills.
I've written about a variety of topics on everything from
data modeling to how to be successful remote employee
to how to theme the Grammarly text editor SDK to
match Taylor Swift albums. One of
the great things about the tech community is that we are lifelong learners.
We want to continuously improve and grow.
So share what you've learned. So here are
some ways that you can write to educate the tech community.
You can answer questions on sites like Stack,
overflow or Dev. You can participate in
discussions on open source projects.
You can chat in tech communities on platforms like Discord and Slack.
You can share micro content on platforms like Twitter,
LinkedIn, or Instagram. You can
write tutorials or thought leadership articles on your own blog
or on platforms like Dev Medium or LinkedIn.
Or you can really go for it and write a book.
So why do this? Well, I think there are two main
reasons. First up, you can help others.
It feels so good when someone comes back
and tells you that what you wrote helped them solve their problem.
But two, a little more selfishly, you can help yourself.
The more you write, the more you will become known as the go to
person on a topic that's going to help you demonstrate
scope and influence in your current role. And it's going to
get your name out there for potential new roles.
For me, writing to the tech community is probably the scariest suggestion
that I'm going to make today. And from talking with others,
many people also fear writing in public. Not just
speaking in public, writing in public. I've been asked
questions like, what if I write something dumb or wrong and
people call me out on it? I mean, people on the Internet can
be mean. Chances are
good you're probably going to get a few mean comments. There's no getting around that.
You're going to have to focus on the positive comments and learn to
let go of the negative and to be transparent.
It's easier said than done. It doesn't matter how many
kind comments I get, one mean community will wriggle around
in my brain for days. So if
you start to feel dragged down by the mean comments, just go back and reread
the good ones. But you can also work to
prevent some of them by having a trusted friend or colleague
read your work before you publish it to spot check it for any glaring
technical errors. You can also use a human or
a tool to spot check your writing for spelling grammar mistakes.
Getting both a technical review and a copy edit review
will give you more confidence when you go to click publish.
In the end, writing for the tech community will be worth it.
Okay, third way to write to level up your career.
Write to document team knowledge I
love this gift from parks and rec where the mayor says,
if there's praise, I will humbly accept it, but if there's blame,
it's your fault. Have you ever looked at code and asked yourself,
who wrote this nonsense? This code doesn't make
any sense and there are no community to explain what's going on.
And then you checked the git blame and realized that it was you.
Yeah, me neither. Moving on.
We all have opportunities each day to improve the daily
work of our teammates, and potentially for our future selves
by documenting team knowledge. So here are some guidelines.
If you find yourself answering a question more than once, either verbally
or in a chat, find a way to document it.
Maybe you drop it in a readme, or maybe you put it in a team
wiki, but drop it somewhere that others can easily
discover it. Point people to it, and then ask them
to improve it if it doesn't fully answer their question.
When you make a decision on your own or as a team,
document the decision and why you chose it.
This doesn't have to be a big, huge document. I mean, if it is,
that's great, but it can also just be like a quick paragraph that summarizes
what you chose, with some bullets below it about other options that you
considered and why you didn't choose them. Future teammates
and future you will appreciate this context,
and it can prevent you from having to revisit the same decision again in
the future.
Finally, document team processes it's
nice to feel needed, but it's not nice to feel needed at 03:00 a.m.
When the person on call can't figure out how to fix a problem in your
area, so they call and wake you up.
Document team knowledge and processes so that your team can easily
keep moving forward, even if a key person is offline.
All right, fourth strategy. Write to
encourage your teammates have you ever
worked with someone who's a natural encourager?
Kindness just seems to ooze out of them.
They're always ready to compliment your latest pull request or
the way you ran a meeting, or how cute your shoes are.
It feels so good to be around them right
now. Most of us are not natural encouragers.
We might occasionally remember to say something kind when someone goes above
and beyond, but otherwise we just stay focused on our jobs.
I am very much the second type. My husband will tell you that
I am quick to criticize and slow to praise.
He loves that about me. I'm very task
oriented and I tend to focus on accomplishing my tasks.
When I feel overwhelmed and behind on my work, I go even
deeper inside this bubble of solitude.
When I was at my previous company, I decided to be more intentional about
celebrating the successes of my teammates. When someone shared
something they'd accomplished in our team chat, I made sure to celebrate it with them.
When I saw someone doing good work, I complimented them publicly
in our team chat. And when someone did something to help
me out, I made sure to thank them through our company's platform
for recognizing others. To be clear, this was not something
that came naturally to me. This was something I chose to intentionally
do. Shortly after I left that company,
a former colleague, Megan, tweeted this. She said,
we still talk about youll and how amazing and brilliant
and kind you are. And I was like, what,
me kind? They had noticed
and appreciated my efforts to be kind.
Tell your teammates that you appreciate them and that they belong.
They are going to thrive in this environment.
I encourage you to be intentional in encouraging your teammates.
If you're likely to forget, set a reminder on your calendar every Friday
to encourage a teammate. When someone does great work,
celebrate it and let others know about it. If your
company doesn't have a platform like bonusly or lattice for sending
public compliments. You can post them in team chats
or send an email to the person and CC your manager and
CC their manager. The person you're thanking
will appreciate it, and it's going to give both managers
visibility into what you're working on.
All of these efforts can help create a culture of compliments on
your team. When you start recognizing other strengths,
they're likely to start recognizing yours. And that's a win for
everybody. Which leads to my last point in this
section. Write to record your accomplishments.
Now, I don't know about you, but I have to write a performance
review every year. And every year I kind of dread
this process. Here's the thing.
Your performance review is your chance to make a case for yourself as to why
your manager should give you a bonus, a raise, or a
promotion. Do not waste
your performance review I know you'd rather be doing something technical than
working on your performance review. But do
not waste your performance review. I write
the longest, most detailed performance reviews. I format
them. I bold the key points. It's possibly a bit over
the top, but it works.
Managers are busy. It's easy for them to overlook or forget
your accomplishments. Your performance review is your chance
to remind them of all the amazing things you've done so
that they can go advocate for you. So here's what I recommend
throughout the year, regularly document what you've accomplished.
If you typically track all of your work in your to dos in task tracking
software like Jira or Asana, you're good to go.
But if you track the main step from your team in one place and then
you end up tracking other to do's in a list that ultimately gets
deleted or thrown away. Set aside time,
weekly or monthly, to document what you've accomplished and who
you've helped. Whenever you get a compliment,
drop it in a doc dedicated just to compliments.
When it's time for your performance review, you can group items together into bigger
themes. Then copy and paste in any relevant compliments
and state what you've accomplished. Don't undersell yourself.
This is not the time to be humble. Tell your manager
what you've accomplished, the impact it had, and how
it moved your team's or your company's goals forward.
Make it super easy for your manager to make a case for your raise
after you've done this. Update your resume, your CV, your LinkedIn,
whatever you use to show potential employers what you've accomplished.
You're probably not going to remember the impact you had three years from now when
you need it updated, so write it down now while it's fresh in your mind.
Over time, your resume is going to become really strong if you do this regularly.
Now, for me personally, LinkedIn has been huge for my
career. I got my last two jobs through LinkedIn,
and I've also gotten speaking opportunities through LinkedIn.
Taking the time to document your accomplishments and your impact can
help you at your current company and help your career prospects
at other companies as well. When you're
having a down day, maybe you're feeling like an imposter or
that your work isn't living up to your standards. You can open up your
compliments, doc or your performance review. It's a
great pick me up to see the amazing things you've accomplished
and all the nice things people have said about you.
All right, so let's recap five strategies for writing to
level up your career. Write to
help your users. Write to educate the tech
community, right to document team knowledge,
right to encourage your teammates, and right
to record your accomplishments. And I
encourage you to pause and think right now. What strategy
can you try over the next month?
Write it down. Make a commitment to yourself. What do you want to
try out now?
Now that we've talked about the ways that you can write to level up your
career, you might be concerned about the quality of your writing.
How are you going to make sure you write in a way that people understand
what you're trying to convey? I'm going to share with you three ways
you can improve the quality of your writing.
So this might seem super obvious, but it's super important,
so I'm going to share it anyway. Don't be a jerk.
I've created this very scientific scale of being a
jerk. So down at the bottom, we have those times when you
intentionally act like a jerk. Perhaps it makes you feel better to
put others down. Up at the top, we have those times
when you're unintentionally accidentally being a jerk.
Maybe you don't realize that the words you're using negatively impact
others, or that others may misinterpret the tone in your writing.
Now, to be totally transparent, I've done things all over the scale.
I'm not proud of it, but it's happened. So what
can we do to not fall on the scale?
Well, be empathetic. Put yourself in
your reader's shoes. They don't want to feel dumb or
that their technology of choice is somehow lesser than yours.
As the old saying goes, you catch more flies with honey
than vinegar. So don't put others down because you're likely to
lose them as a reader. Now, up at the top of the scale,
we have those times when you're unintentionally accidentally being a jerk.
It's kind of easy to unintentionally be a jerk in your writing.
The words you choose matter.
So use inclusive language, even if you
don't care about being inclusive. For the sake of being inclusive,
be inclusive for the sake of getting your message across.
I recommend perusing Google's developer documentation style
guide to get recommendations on words to avoid.
Now, full disclosure, I'm a Grammarly employee, but I feel
like I need to throw out there that there are tools like Grammarly that provide
suggestions on inclusive language. Your tone
can also get you into trouble because you know exactly what you're trying
to convey, but your readers may not. So this is another
case where having someone else, either a human or a tool like
Grammarly, can really help.
Last point of not being a jerk every time you write to someone
else, either privately or publicly,
is a chance to make their day a little bit brighter or a little
bit crummier. So I encourage youll to
use your words to make someone else's day a little bit brighter.
My former teammate Mark Smith included a fun gift whenever
he accepted someone's pr, and this always made my day a little brighter.
I have a colleague now who uses emojis to share his appreciation
and when he thinks someone's done a good job and it makes us all feel
so good. So use your words and
youll gifts and your emojis to make someone's day a little brighter.
The second way you're going to improve the quality of your writing is to practice.
Just do it. I encourage you to regularly set aside
time for writing. At about the same
time that I started writing technical blog posts at work, I decided to
start a personal blog where I wrote about anything that interested me.
Now, ultimately, my blog never took off. I never became Internet famous
because of it, but I got a ton of practice writing.
My goal was to write two posts a week, and I did that consistently
for a little over a year. Were my posts good?
But my blog allowed me to develop my personal voice,
which I still use today. In my professional writing,
I'm able to write higher quality articles and write
faster than I did years ago, and that's because of all
of the practice that I have.
So I encourage you set aside time to write regularly.
Now, earlier in this talk, we talked about five strategies to write
to level up your career, and I encourage you to pick one way
now. Put a block on your calendar to do that.
Maybe you want a daily reminder for shorter content,
or maybe you want a weekly reminder for monthly content.
But set aside the time and follow through.
You will get better just by practicing.
All right, my final recommendation for you today is to educate
yourself on how to be a better wider there are a few different ways you
can do this. You can use an aipowered writing
assistant like Grammarly that will teach you as it
reviews your content. Another way
to educate yourself is to find a writing partner. You can
set up regular writing reviews to get feedback. This will help you
improve your writing and hold you accountable to following through on
your commitment to write, which is a win win.
Look for patterns in their feedback, identify your weaknesses
and work to improve.
There are so many ways to learn to be a better writer. You can
read a book. I know I've got docs for developers. It's on my current
reading list. There are excellent articles available
for free online. You can attend workshops. Megan Grant and I led
a workshop last fall on how to get your first technical article published.
Or you can take an online course. Lots of options out there, so see
what works for you. Give it a shot.
Let's recap. So at the beginning of this presentation, I shared five
strategies for writing in order to level up your career.
And then I shared three ways to improve the quality of your
writing. Don't be a jerk.
Practice and educate yourself.
So those are ways to improve the quality of your writing.
Once again, I'm going to encourage you to pause and think,
what do you want to try over the next month? And commit
to doing it?
If you want to dive deeper into these strategies,
get a quick overview. Later this week, share it
with a colleague. You can check out a blog post I wrote on the Grammarly
for developers. Blog covers the same content, so check
that out. Share it with your networks. In closing,
use the power of the written word to level up your technical
career. I cannot wait to read what you write.