Hi, thank you for coming to my talk. We will look at functions and
how to use them in Python programs. If you
haven't heard of functions before, this talk requires
no prior knowledge of functions or category theory. The talk
is for Python programmers and is designed for ease of
understanding. There will be places where we will choose to
simplify things at the expense of skipping some math details.
The code examples are based on an open source Python
package called Funklift. The links to the GitHub repositories
of funklift and its tutorials are shown on the
slide. Before we move on to the meat of the talk, a quick
introduction of myself. My name is Char Wu. I'm a software
developer, grew up in Taiwan, and I'm based in
the San Francisco Bay area for the past 20 years.
Now, today's agenda is very simple. We will
start with a motivating example and then we will introduce
various functions with even more examples.
Let's start with a simple function, get price, that takes an
item and returns the item's price.
To visualize the code, we can draw types as dots and
functions as arrows. Item is a dot in the diagram
and int is also a dot. Get price is an arrow
that goes from item to int. Now we have
another function is pricey and we can
draw it as an arrow as well. This time
the arrow goes from with those two functions,
what interesting things can we do with them? We can
compose the two functions to form a new function.
The composition of functions corresponds
nicely to the composability of arrows in our diagram.
A diagram like the one we are seeing here represents a
category in category theory.
Essentially, a category consists of dots and arrows,
plus some properties about how arrows compose.
We will call our category here the category
of types. In this category, the dots
are Python types and the arrows are Python functions.
Now let's move on to
see how functions are related to categories.
Here we have a function is even that goes from int to bool
and we have a list of numbers. 1234 we
want to map is even over the numbers. One way
to achieve that is by using this comprehension.
Another way is to use the CDS class of the funklift
package. As you can see from the code here,
the CDis class has a method called fmap.
Fmap takes the function is even and maps
it over the list of numbers behind the scenes. On the
outside, we can think of fmap as lifting
is even to a function that goes from
c list of int to c list of bool.
If we put the is even function and
its lifted counterpart side by side we
can see that c list is actually a mapping from
a source category to a target category.
Such a mapping is called a functor if
it satisfies certain properties. In our case,
C list is a functor. The source category
and the target category of C list are both
the category of types. A functor is called an
functor when its source and target categories
are the same. Now that we've introduced the concepts of
categories and functors, let's see some functions,
and let's also see what problems they solve.
It's common to have code that performs some kind of
input or output. For example, we might have code
that sends a request over a network,
reads a file, or writes a record to a
database. Such I O functions are side effects
that make our code harder to reason about because they break
referential transparency. Here on the side, the function
get number side effect on the left has side
effects because it reads user input from a console.
To avoid such side effect, we can wrap
the I O action into an instance of the I O class
when we call the get number function on the right,
no actual reading from the console.
Rather, we simply get an I O object that represents the
I O action. The code here shows what we can
do with the I O object returned by the get number function,
even though no actual I o has happened yet.
When we call get number, that does not stop us from
mapping the is even function over the nonexistent
number when we are finally ready to incur
the actual I o by coding the
unsafe run method on the I O object.
Although our example here is simple already, it shows that
with the I o function we are able to keep the kernel of
our code free of side effects and push
the actual I o functions to the boundary of our program.
Now let's look at another example here.
At the top we have a function that takes an integer and returns
ten modulo that integer. The function
is a partial function because it's not defined when the input
integer is zero. We can write the function
at the bottom. The function at the bottom is now defined
for all input values. However,
we now have a different issue, and that is the new function
is not very composable with other functions.
Here's an illustration of the lack of composability.
The code on the right tries to compose the two functions
on the left. Because the ten mark by function returns
either an integer or none, it is not very
composable, and we have to use if else statements
when we try to compose it with other functions. Is there
a solution that can turn a
partial function into a total function while retaining
composability. That solution is the
option functions. As the example here shows,
the ten mark by function now returns an option of int.
The option class of the funklift package has
a subclass called nothing and another
subclass called sum. Nothing represents
the absence of a value. Sum represents
the existence of a value. By the magic
of functions and their fmap methods,
we can compose ten map by with other functions,
without any if else statements in the code.
Just like how we visualize c list as a functor,
we can visualize option as a functor.
Map starts and arrows from a source category
to a target category. So far we've been
composing functions. It turns out that we can
compose functions too. This diagram shows
that we can compose the option functor and
the c list function. The result of the composition
is a new function, and we call that new functions
c list after option. Like any other function,
the new functions is a mapping between two categories.
It maps dots to dots and arrows to arrows.
If we can compose functors the way we
compose arrows, does that mean functions are arrows
in some sort of category? Notice that in this
diagram, each rectangle represents a
category. If we collapse the rectangles into dots,
we will get a category whose dots are smaller categories
and whose arrows are functions. Here's what that
category looks like in a diagram. We call
it the category of small categories. Of course,
we don't just look at theories, we want to see some code,
right? The code example on this slide shows
how to compose functions in Python. Here,
the variable nums is a C list of option objects.
If we call fmap on nums, we will
not be able to map over the numbers inside the option
objects. In order to do that, we need to compose
the two functions first, and we do that by
using the compose class of the funklift package.
Once we have the compose function, we can call fmap
on it, just like we do with any other functions.
This is really fantastic. In this diagram,
capital f denotes a functor. The functions
we've seen so far are called covariant functions.
Here, covariant basically means
that the two vertical arrows in the diagram point
in the same direction. When a functor
maps a source arrow to a target arrow.
If the mapping does not change the direction of the arrows,
then the functions is covariant. If the
two vertical arrows in the diagram point in the opposite
direction, then the function is contravariant.
For contravariant functions, we have the fmap method.
For contravarian functions, we have the cmap method
similar to fmap. The cmap method
lifts a function from type a to type b to
a function that goes from f of b to f of a.
Here's an example of a contravariant function called predicate.
A predicate is something that is either true or false.
In our example, we first have a predicate that
will be true if we give it an even integer,
and as the diagram shows, we can use cmap
to convert that predicate of int into a predicate
of str. With the converted predicate
we can pass it the number six as a string,
and it will tell us if that's an even number
or not. The next type of functions we will look
at is called applicative functions. Before we
introduce applicative function, we need to first get to know
a special kind of categories called closed category.
In the diagram on the side, there are two categories.
The category on the left has a dot for
type a and a dot for type b. If the
category also has a dot in gray for
the function type a to b,
plus some other properties, then the
category is called a closed category. An example
of a function type is into bool, as shown
in the blue box. Now let's turn our attention to
the category on the right. The category has a
dot for the type f of a and a
dot for the type f of b. Because it's also a closed
category, it has a dot for the function type f
of a to f of b in green.
Between the two categories we have a functions that maps
dots to dots and arrows to arrows. In particular,
the functor maps the gray dot a to
b on the left, f of a to b on
the right. In blue, it may be the case that the blue
dot and the green dot are not related at
all if they happen to be one and the same dot.
Then we say that the functor preserves the structure of
the source category, and we call the functor a
strict requiring the blue dot and the green dot to be
the same dot is a rather strict condition.
A somewhat more relaxed not require the
two dots to be the same, we merely require that there's
an arrow between the two dots. We call
the functions a lex closed functions another
name for lax closed functor is applicative
functions, the arrow between the blue dot
and the green dot app. That's a lot of theory.
Let's see an example in code. Here we have a curried
function for summing two integers.
Currying means if a function takes multiple arguments,
then the current function will take one argument at a time.
In this example, we start with sum of 20.
Then we f map the current function.
What we end up with is an option of int
to int, which is shown as the blue
dot in the diagram. Because our option functions
is an applicative function, we have the app arrow
that takes us from the blue dot. The green dot is
essentially a function that takes n and
returns another option of int. So if we
give that functions sum of 30, we will
get back sum of 50 as the result.
Next, let's turn our attention to a kind of functions called
functors. If we have a type a and a type
c, we can form the tuple type
a comma c. If we have a type b and a type
d, we can form a tuple type.
And if there's an arrow from a to
b and another arrow from c to d,
we can take those two arrows and form a tuple
of arrows that goes from a comma c.
Now, if we have a functor that maps a comma c
to f of a comma c and b comma d
to f of b comma d, and the functor
also maps the tuple of arrows to a lifted
tuple of arrows, then we call such functions a
functor. In python code, a functor
class takes only one type argument, whereas a
functor class takes two type arguments.
Let's see an example of a functor. The functor in the
example is the either class from the funk devt package.
As its name suggests, either represents one of
two possibilities. We represent those two
possibilities with two classes left and
right. In the co example,
we take two functions, add one and negate.
We by map them over an either
object. Because the either object is a write object,
the negate function will have no effect, and the add one
function will be applied to the number five.
Like functor, there's a kind of functions called profunctors
that also takes two type arguments. The difference
is a functor is covariant
in both of its type arguments, whereas a profunctors
is contravariant in the first type argument
and covariant in the second type argument.
The diagram here is very similar to the diagram we
saw earlier. For functors, the only difference is
that the arrow between type a and type b
a. Perhaps very helpful way for visualizing how a profunctors
works is through a diagram like the one at the bottom.
We can visualize a profunctors p
of a comma c as a box that
takes an a and outputs a c. When we call dimap
under profunctors. We get back a
new profunctors and outputs a d.
There are many different profunctors. One of them is called forget
it always returns some value of type r,
type of input value you give it. Star and
costar are two other kinds of profunctors.
The symbol f here represents a functions.
So star f takes an a and returns
an f of c. When you die map on it,
you can turn it into a new star f that
takes a b and returns an f of d.
Here's a co example of the star profunctors.
The star profunctors takes an integer.
If we give it integer three, it will give us sum
of one because ten mod by three is one.
If we pass zero to the profunctors, it will
give us nothing because ten mod by zero is not
a valid operation. We can take the star profunctors
and die map on it with the
stir to int function on the way in is even
function on the way out. What we end up with is
a new profunctors that takes a string and returns
an option of bool. The code example we have
starts to look like some sort of data pipelines
that can be chained and composed in flexible ways,
and that's indeed a good application of profunctors.
Congratulations for making it to this point.
We've covered a lot in a fairly short amount of
time. We've introduced the concept,
then we covered covariant,
contravariant applicative functions,
as well as functors and profunctors.
Hope you all enjoyed the talk. Thank you.