Hey everyone, and thank you for watching my presentation.
Today. I'll tell you about the Mlsecops framework for protecting AI
systems. And before I jump into details, I want
to tell you a story how I started in this field and
actually witnessed how the entire industry was born.
And like many of you at this event, I am a cybersecurity
guy. And for more than ten years I've been doing security research in
various product startups. And after a few years in application security,
I became a product leader for security monitoring and threat detection.
And we've decided to use machine learning for enterprise
security monitoring. And we were quite successful with the models for
insider threat detection. But closer to the release, we tested
our product for vulnerabilities and we have realized
that it's easier to fool our own security models.
So we started diving deeper into the world of AI vulnerabilities
and discovered the entire field called adversarial
machine learning. And during that period, I was interested
in devsecops practices, and at the same time I
was also building an Mlsecops engine for our security platform.
So I have created this name, Mlsecops,
which was quite obvious from my two interests to
separate these two work streams. One is for
operationalizing our security models and another one is
for protecting our own models. And then I witnessed
how the field of AI security was growing with many new attacks
and tools and regulations. So we decided to start
a research company focused exclusively on AI
vulnerabilities and we founded Adversa in
2019. We were the first commercial company
researching AI vulnerabilities, and it also happened
that we did many other things that could be called the
first in the industry. And we started on a mission to protect
AI from cyber threats with applying all
the latest attacks from academia to the industry,
to the real world. And I won't go into details here,
but if you're interested in this topic, I encourage you to visit our
website so you can read a lot of research materials there.
So in this presentation, I'm summarizing my ideas
from years of research, and I'll tell you
why. AI is almost certainly the future
of software. What are the security threats to large
scale AI systems and how to implement security in AI pipelines,
all while shifting security left with Mlsecops
framework as an example. So why
do they call AI as the most likely future of
software? Well, you already can easily find
many exciting AI applications in almost every industry,
and many of them offer quality improvements and
large scale automation. And the simple example here
is that AI is widely used in cybersecurity
so instead of writing regular expressions and signature rules,
we can use machine learning for deciding whether a binary
is malicious or benign, or whether security events
are normal or anomalous. And I believe that
in the next five to ten years, most tech companies will become
AI companies. Similarly to how many
traditional businesses had to go online and become
tech companies just to stay relevant.
But also, AI enables completely new ideas,
like generating visuals or even writing real programs.
And many unexpected things at the intersection can happen,
like turning speech into text,
then this text into visual arts, and this visuals into
code, which essentially becomes a really well designed
web page. And similarly to how the
most popular applications that we use today didn't
exist ten to 20 years ago. In the next
years, a similar shift will happen with very
new types of companies that we cannot even predict now.
So why does this happen? If we dive deeper, we can
see that AI offers not just cool applications,
but a paradigm shift, and that's entire new way of
developing software. With the traditional software,
we create clear algorithms and behaviors
with programming languages. But with
AI in the form of machine learning, we can train the algorithms,
and instead of defining all the rules, we can reduce the
number of instructions and replace it with the trained model.
So a deterministic algorithm designed
by software developers is replaced or augmented
with a probabilistic algorithm designed by AI
developers. And of course, it comes with
the new roles and processes. For example,
data engineers collect and prepare data,
then data scientists do experiments and model training,
and then machine learning. Engineers focus on
model packaging and productizing, and finally, operations handle
deployments and monitoring. And this requires
a whole new process, which is called mlops.
There are many similarities with the devsecops and even
some shared infrastructure and tools. But if we zoom in,
we can see that models and data sets introduce
new types of artifacts, like data set files, model weights,
model code metrics, experiments, and so on.
And all of these things increase complexity and could be
potential attack vectors. So attacks could happen
against data models or against a system in
general. And the field of attacks against
AI is called adversa machine learning.
And as you can imagine, with so much value locked in AI systems,
it's very valuable target for cyberattacks. And in fact,
attacks against AI are already happening.
You can read in the media or in incident
databases of how hackers bypassed
malware detectors, spam filters, or smart firewalls.
And our own projects, penetration testing.
AI systems have 100%
success rate with industries such as automotive,
biometrics, intranet, or finance. And just
recently, we at Adversa, together with our partners
organized the ML Sec AI hacking competition.
My team has created the facial recognition track and
all the top ten contestants used very
different strategies and all of them successfully
fooled AI models. And if you're interested
to learn more about this contest, you can read the blog
post with technical details.
So in adversarial machine learning today, there are
over 5000 research papers about attacking and
defending AI systems. In this presentation,
we don't look at individual attacks, so if you're interested
in details you can watch one of my previous talks that covers
the past ten years of AI vulnerability research.
But I want to give you a quick idea about such attacks.
So you know what we should protect from the
most common AI threats that we see are infection.
That happens at the development stage when
attackers maliciously modify training data with
poisoning attacks or simply trick devsecops to
use infected models.
Then manipulation happens at runtime when
attackers full model decisions or bypass
some detections with adversa examples,
or simply perform a denial of service attack.
An exfiltration happens at the runtime
stage as well when attackers steal model
algorithm details or extract private data
from the model with various types of inference attacks.
So if you want to know more, you can read our report that covers
all known AI vulnerabilities and explains
them from different angles based on industries,
applications, data types and so on. And I just
want to conclude this section reminding
that essentially AI expands the attack surface.
On the one hand, AI systems are just yet another example of software.
That's why you can expect them to have all the traditional
types of vulnerabilities, such as problems with input
validation, access control issues, or misconfigurations.
On the other hand, AI systems have new types of behaviors.
So on top of the traditional vulnerabilities, we should worry
about unique AI threats like infection,
manipulation or exfiltration.
So, as you can see, the security of AI
is a fundamentally new problem, and current application
security and other security solutions cannot help
with AI vulnerabilities. So the new approaches are needed.
But despite these unique problems, the core
security principles still apply here.
Security should enable AI teams build and scale
AI software reliably and with more trust.
And as AI is fundamentally vulnerable,
when you scale it without security, you actually scale problems for
your company. So instead, AI teams should be confident
in AI reliability because it's backed by preparation
and security processes, and then they can scale it successfully.
Similarly to how security shouldn't slow down
AI development. Also, the manual model validation
shouldn't slow down deployment. So automation,
playbooks and best practices are also required here.
Essentially, we want to build security into
the way software is built, not after software
is built. So that's called shifting left,
because we start doing security earlier in the pipeline,
which is technically on the left side.
And this idea is also very practical because
for AI systems it's deeply connected to the levels of complexity
added after each stage. For instance, if in later
stages we decide that the model should be fixed with the
retraining, then it will require redoing all the stages,
starting from the data packaging,
redoing all the experiments, choosing the best model,
and so on and so forth.
So the earlier you start, the more reliable AI
systems you can build because you dramatically decrease the
number of problems at later stages. And it's
beneficial to use combinations of security controls at
different stages over the model lifecycle as well.
So now I want to give you a high level overview of my
Mlsecops framework. I'll focus more on concepts
rather than on technologies, so we could build your intuition about
this topic and based on your knowledge of devsecops.
Later you can do your own research on specific tools.
So first I will visualize original Mlsecops
tasks this way. Then I will highlight
key security problems like this, and finally I
will suggest solutions for MLC Ops pipeline.
So the first stage is planning, and here you collect
all types of requirements to understand what you are building
and why, including business and technical requirements.
Then cross functional dependencies across departments or
even across companies. Then internal
and external policies, regulation and compliance.
So the final outcome of this stage is a set of plans and
policies shaping all the later stages.
What is often overlooked during the planning stage
is understanding of risks and security requirements.
If you don't do risk assessment, you don't know what assets
worth protecting from, what you want to protect them, and what
risks you can accept. Sometimes you won't even
think what assets you'll create during development, and therefore
you'll not be able to plan protection for it.
If you don't do threat modeling, you'll be blind about
what attackers can do to our system. This step
doesn't apply any advanced knowledge about attacking algorithms
or ability to perform such attacks. This is about
finding the weakest links and bottlenecks in the AI
system design and how users interact with the AI,
how AI outputs can impact users or business
decisions. And finally, if you don't manage security,
you basically don't have it. So depending on the scale,
it could be just a team level or system level security process,
or a wider program affecting multiple teams,
departments or entire company.
So when you start implementing the practices of
risk assessment threat modeling and security governance.
You'll start producing some artifacts which will affect the
entire Mlsecops pipeline. Like risk
register helps you track AI risks and
mitigations, and it keeps you up to date with the latest potential
threats and helps you make decisions later
during development.
Knowing your attack surface means having
all the parts of your models, data sets and user interactions analyzed
for attack scenarios, and this could be linked
to the risk register or tracked in the
model management system with some notes and references.
Having security baselines essentially means that you know
how to quantify security risks and can decide
whether these metrics go or no
go situation for deployment.
The next stage is data collection and preparation,
and the process starts with understanding business requirements
and what data should be collected for it,
and then understanding existing data and whether something
is missing. Then, according to the requirements,
the data is collected, cleaned and enriched.
Alternatively, it could be sourced from data vendors or
partners or contractors. And finally, all this data
is packaged for reusing later in the pipeline.
So the outcome of this stage is basically releasing a data set as
a little product and it will be used for model training
later.
Clearly, not knowing your data and business requirements
can get you into big trouble, especially in regulated industries.
You should be very knowledgeable about the structure of your data.
Very often you have some private information that
is absolutely not required for model training,
but brings many privacy and compliance risks.
The next common problem is unreliable sources of data and
essentially supply and chain risk. And regardless
whether you collected it on your own or sourced from
data vendors, often you can't guarantee the correctness of
methods for data collection, whether it was collected without violations,
and whether the actual data matches the data specification.
And another more advanced risk is data poisoning
that injects some malicious entries in the data set.
It could happen by working with compromised data set providers
or by injecting individual examples that
eventually end up in the data set. So the risk could be
that you don't verify the integrity of individual entries
and don't confirm or cannot confirm the data sets
were not maliciously modified. The main
overall principle here is careful curation of
data sets. So for data privacy,
the main piece of advice is to think whether you need this
private data at all. Often it's absolutely not required
for model training, so sensitive entries can be
just removed. And if it's not feasible,
then private details can be anonymized or tokenized.
And sometimes other methods like differential privacy
could also be helpful. Then to address supply
chain risks and ensure data integrity, you should use
reliable data sources, those that you can control
or verify and data should also have verifiable
quality based on specifications, and you
can verify it with individual entries, with metadata, with metrics.
And finally, against data poisoning, you should avoid
inconsistencies in your data.
Like first is like filtering out anomalous
entries, and also filtering potentially
malicious entries that are often anomalous
too. And you should use secure
data set version control to ensure that the data was
not maliciously modified. If you checked that, it's correct previously.
The next stage is model building. At this stage,
we take a specific data set version and start
building a model, including experiments with processing
data in different ways, known as feature engineering,
and also experimenting with model parameters and
architectures. And it's important to remember that we
are working with the data set that was previously supplied.
So technically, it's kind of an external artifacted model.
And also in many cases, for highly effective
big neural networks, there are already pretrained models,
so the model brains could be also external.
And this model building stage essentially becomes writing
code for connecting data set and the model.
At the next stage, we focus on training the model
and hoping that results meet our expectations. Otherwise,
we'll repeat experiments with features and architecture,
and train it again until the results comply with the
business requirements. And finally, for model packaging,
we are finalizing code from the early experiments and
model training, and if necessary, we convert
it from Jupiter notebooks to production ready code.
The outcome of this entire stage is that
the model is ready and could be reused.
Essentially, it could be imported into the main application and used
just like any other module.
So this stage is probably the most dangerous one
because it's so easy to make expensive mistakes here.
So let's start with the model itself. If you're using an
external model, you should be really mindful where you take it
from. Just like with external data sets, you can just download a big
model from GitHub and hope that it's reliable.
And it actually becomes quite common
to use models released by big corporations like Google and
Microsoft, who spent millions of dollars for training those
models. And it's very realistic scenario for cybercriminals
to spread malicious models that look
like benign. If the model is created
from scratch, it's also quite easy to get into trouble.
Production level machine learning is a new area for many teams,
and sometimes due to lack of resources or role misunderstanding,
data scientists are expected to write secure
and production ready code, which is often disconnected from
reality. And on top of this, there are many tools and
frameworks that emerged from academia that
were not designed for production and that were not designed with
security in mind.
One of the most widespread examples is importing
a model with Python pickle files, which is
object serialization, and it's a well known
insecure practice. Also,
the core machine learning frameworks like Tensorflow
and other libraries may have their own vulnerabilities.
And finally, one of the most unique problems to the security
of AI is a non robust training of
models that enables model manipulation
and data exfiltration attacks.
There are various fundamental design flaws
of neural networks that like weak decision
boundaries, lack of diverse data examples that
affect nonrobust learning.
So to address all these risks, the main principle
is to work with external models, as with external code,
and conduct your own due diligence. Here, for model
integrity to address supply chain
risks, you should use only reliable sources
of pretrained models to reduce the risk
of backdoors and validate that models you downloaded
match like hashes of original models.
You should also use secure model version control to
ensure that models were not maliciously modified,
because it's easy to hijack model artifacts,
especially when you work in different environments and switching
back and forth between experimenting and productizing.
Next, secure coding is actually the closest
to traditional application security.
Model code is often written by experts in data science
who are not necessarily experts in software engineering.
And the most common place where problems arise is the
process of converting experiments code to the production
code. Then you should avoid known
unsafe functions like insecure pickling, object serialization,
and other things. And you should only use
known good libraries and diversions and check dependencies
for vulnerabilities. And finally,
for robust and secure machine learning, you should remember
about algorithms based threats
scenarios. So if your primary concern is manipulation of
decisions with adversarial examples, then you should
think about training a model with adversarial
examples. And if you care more about privacy,
you could try training with federated learning or even train on
encrypted data. The next stage is
model validation. At this stage, we take the model built
from the previous stage and conduct model evaluations
and acceptance testing in terms of model accuracy
and business requirements. And if it meets the target baseline,
then it's usually all. In some rare
cases, we see robustness testing that is mostly focused
on some non standard inputs or back testing.
And our experience shows that the most mature
industries are the banks in the United States because of
the model. Risk management regulations also
self driving companies because of the obvious safety concerns,
and we see that some biometric and Internet companies
also fighting some real attacks.
Finally, some companies do compliance checks,
but again mostly in regulated industries,
and the outcome of this stage is essentially a
green red light for deployment based on test reports with
the evaluation metrics. The most common
problem in productizing and protecting AI
systems is that they're barely tested because there is very
little knowledge and no actionable frameworks or best practices.
And it's very rare that testing goes beyond model performance
metrics. Next, even when there is robustness
testing, we still see few problems
here, like not all models are covered by
tests. It could be a limited number of
tests or limited depth of these tests,
and the formal approach happens even
when companies do it for regulation or safety
concerns. And it's even more rare that they do adversarial
testing, which is obviously very dangerous.
Another common problem is that AI heavily relies
on traditional infrastructure and software environments,
and unless companies use some proprietary
end to end platform, it's very common to put models into docker
containers and hosted somewhere in the Amazon cloud.
And as you know, most containers are vulnerable by default
and most clouds are never responsible for your security.
There are several ways this could be addressed.
To work on testing coverage, you really need to have security
governance, so the testing should be informed by asset
registers with models and data with assigned risk
levels and based on security specification,
including attack surface and
threats models that we created before the development started,
and also check for compliance with the functional
specification like model
cards or data sheets or service information. All of these
artifacts define the AI system behavior and
should affect the scope of security testing.
For better security validation, you should have testing playbooks.
Scenarios I can suggest include basic adversarial testing,
like a sanity check. If it fails on the most
basic tests, you probably shouldn't test further.
Then you can use a bigger repository of attacks with
the most common tests, similar to how application
security has OS top ten attacks,
and finish with custom and threat based scenarios
for the kind of real world penetration
testing. And of course you
need to secure the
environment and infrastructure. As for any other application,
and it depends a lot on your AI system design,
but commonly you should scan containers for
known vulnerabilities, be conscious about
any external dependencies in the system,
and ideally scan the entire infrastructure as code
for security and compliance.
The next stage is model deployment. If the validation stage
gave us a green light and the model code with fixed
weights, probably packaged in a container,
is deployed and ready to accept connections. Here,
the model inference step is essentially the
model runtime processing inputs and responding and outputs
that AI users incorporate in their decision
making. And by model serving I mean
like general operations of the AI system.
So the final outcome of this entire stage is that a
concrete model is deployed, the model behaves
as expected, and the system is in a good condition.
Let's see what can go wrong here. First of all,
the model that is actually deployed could be different from what you
wanted to deploy before the deployment. The model
could have been maliciously modified in the model store
by changing its code or replacing its weights. Essentially, you could
deploy a Trojan here, not the model you developed.
The next problem is the classic problem of adversa attacks.
The three main attack groups here are manipulation
attacks that include evasion, reprogramming and resource
exhaustion, which is essentially a denial of service attack,
then exfiltration attacks that steal model
algorithm details, extract private data,
and infection attacks. And even though infection is usually considered
as a train time attack, it's possible that those infected
examples are received during model runtime.
So essentially the system collected all the inputs and
later used in updating data
sets. And finally, unrestricted access
can help develop various types of attacks.
It could be absence of any access controls, or absence
of user accounts at all, or just unlimited model queries
or unrestricted data submissions, and many other things.
So what could we do here? You obviously should check
model authenticity. Depending on the system pipeline
configuration. This could be a verification of model artifacts
from the model store or code hosting.
Or it could be a wider model governance approach
where you track the entire model lifecycle in
a single platform. And on top of this you should control who
can roll out models to production to
protect from attacks against AI algorithms. You should keep in
mind your threat model, because it's impossible
to have a model that is fully secure
against every existing attack, but it's possible
to harden the model against concrete threat
scenarios. There are three main directions you can go
here secure training in the first place
with adversa data sets or differential privacy,
then runtime defenses like input preprocessing
or output postprocessing, and also what I call operational
defenses, things like rate limiting.
And the last point is about secure communications and access controls.
The first piece of advice is to control authorized
usage based on the intended model usage,
so you can introduce some rate limits by design,
then mutual authentication of requests and responses
so you can check the requests come from eligible users,
and also you can protect users from man in the middle
attacks and encryption of model
inputs and outputs. Intransit should also
protect both parties from eavesdropping,
and the final stage is model monitoring. So after the
model started producing predictions,
you should carefully monitor it. And not just because every
serious system should be monitored, but also because of
non deterministic nature of AI systems.
Basically, it can change its behavior over time or
with unexpected inputs to the model.
That's why the model performance monitoring should
be a good start. The common use cases include tracking
prediction accuracy and detecting model drift. That essentially
indicates that the real world data is now different from the data we trained
on. Then anomaly detection in
model inputs and outputs, or in some general
request patterns can be another indicator
of model health. And all
of this should be looped back to AI development teams
for continuous improvement. So the outcome of this entire
stage is kind of peace of mind when you know
that things are working as expected. So the
most common problems here are lack of monitoring
in the first place. And I'm talking not just about basic logs,
but also about usable monitoring infrastructure.
There is no way you can do something useful with logs that are only
written in API or proxy log files
or saved in container storage.
Another problem is analytical capability.
So when you have all those logs, do you really know what to look for,
how to group or correlate incidents, and what is normal
and what is not? And finally, with all
those monitoring capabilities, are you passively watching or
actively protecting your a system?
So what you should start with is activity
login with some usable and
actionable dashboards that includes monitoring,
model performance and metrics, metadata from requests,
input and output errors, and you also should
monitor requests at the user level for access control and
behavior anomalies. Then when
you have those monitoring capabilities, you need to add an analytics layer
so you could act on this data. And the basic advice is
to have event becoming so you could filter events
by importance and prioritize investigation. Then it's useful
to have error types so you could identify and group events
for correlations. And ideally you should have more
advanced stuff for incident forensics and
for traceability like sessions,
request hashes and other types of profiling
behaviors inside your AI application.
And finally, the most advanced step is automated
detection and one possible automated response.
So for regular performance incidents it could be as simple
as alerting. And for some input trash unexpected
outputs, like with the recent prompt injection attacks,
it could have some safety filters or custom
responses with custom errors. And for some classic adversarial
attacks it could be either activation of some defenses
or custom responses, or even account blocking.
And of course for all these activities it's important to have feedback
loops. So not only the AI system
issues immediately addressed, but also best practices and
processes updated and some additional trainings conducted.
So now you can see the whole picture of how Mlcikov's
pipeline should look like. And of course I've simplified some
things for introducing this topic the very first
time. And it's also worth mentioning that I didn't
cover things related to traditional cybersecurity that
are obviously also important. For instance,
during work with the data and models,
which happens on data scientist machines, it's important to secure
workspaces. They often have collaboration
tools like Google Collab or Jupyter notebooks that have
remote shared access and could expose access to the
operating system and some other critical system functions,
or provide direct access to data.
And there are known ransomware attacks against Jupyter
setups. And also it's a well known cybersecurity
problem that entire data storages could be exposed at
Amazon or elastic instances,
and then the security of the pipeline itself is
an important topic. What you should pay attention
to is access control for who can commit code,
publish models and data sets, pull artifacts,
approve releases, promote models for deployment and
so on. And of course, secure configuration of
machine learning infrastructure is also important, like the code hosting
feature stores, experiment trackers and so on.
So after this presentation, I want you to remember a few key
ideas. First is every AI system is
vulnerable by design and it expands the attack surface
of software. There are real attacks against AI
systems already in almost every industry and
every application and every data type, so you
should deliberately work on protecting from these
threats. Then. Traditional security
solutions cannot protect AI systems, so don't expect
your firewalls or vulnerability scanners to solve
the problem because the problem of AI systems is
very unique. And last, you should
think about securing the entire AI system,
not just an AI algorithm as often discussed
in the context of adversa attacks.
And also remember that defenses are often more
operational than algorithmic. So start building this
internal infrastructure and best practices sooner.
And if you work in devsecops and you have
AI in your product or in any other product
teams, you should definitely share your security concerns with
AI developers because they rarely know about the real
threats landscape. And if you find this presentation
useful, I ask you to share it with your colleagues and I hope
it will be useful for them too. So this
is it. I appreciate your attention. If you're interested
in this topic or in any form of collaboration on Mlsecops,
search my name on LinkedIn or Twitter and make sure you drop me a
message. Thank you.