Hi folks, my name is Yasir and I'd like to invite you to my talk
positive and constructive feedback and how you
had it all wrong. Here is a quick glimpse at
the agenda them I'll start off with an introduction of myself so
that you know who's talking to you and why you should listen to me.
I will introduce the concept of the standards devotion matrix
and say a few words on inquiry and feedback on different cultures.
I will then reframe the word feedback
into slightly different terms. Afterwards, I will summarize
the learnings from this talk and send you off on your way with
some homework to put those learnings into practice.
So first off, a few words about myself. I have over nine years
of professional experience with the past five years
spent as a cloud engineering manager at Pega.
I am a graduate of the leadership consortium, which is a course
taught by Harvard Business School professors with very practical learnings
for your professional and daily life. And I rely
very heavily on this talk on the learnings from that course.
Last year I was named as top 100 women in
cloud computing in Poland. I hold a master's
degree in machine learning, which is such a catchy topic
recently that I felt compelled to include this information.
And privately, I am an avid natural language learner
with seven and counting and a proud bomb to a beautiful son and the
cutest cat. So let's now get into the meat of
the talk. Let's talk about the standards devotion matrix.
This is a concept that is going to help you locate yourself
in relation to the people around you in terms of your
standards for them, how high your standards
are and what you expect from them, and in terms of your devotion
to them, essentially how much you care about them
being successful, or how much they feel
that you care about them being successful.
And we're going to go through each quadrant
one by one and to see some of the behaviors you might
exhibit when you land in each of the quadrants.
So let's start with the bottom left quadrant.
Your standards are low for the people and your devotion
is very low. This is called neglect. The behaviors
you might exhibit would be essentially not paying attention,
not caring about what work they're doing or how
they're doing it. And I'm not going to spend time
here because this is a situation that arises very, very rarely
and is not necessarily a place where you want to end
up in far more frequently. You will end
up in the top left corner, which is called severity,
which means that your standards for the people around you are very high,
but your devotion to them is very low. So they
do not necessarily feel that you are deeply devoted to
their success. And this is a situation
that you frequently have with your peers. There is this phenomena
called peer bias when you expect
far more from your peers than from someone on
higher or lower level than you. Oh, I'm working so much.
I'm doing so much. Why aren't you
you doing as much as I'm doing? On the opposite
side is the bottom right quadrant, where people
feel that you are deeply devoted to their success,
but you're not necessarily setting very high standards for them.
This is called fidelity, and honestly,
this is a little bit too kind.
So you're not expecting them to do a lot
of work. You're making sure that they're comfortable. And people
tend to stagnate with you when you
fall into this quadrant because they're not growing
as individuals, they're not growing as professionals.
The situation you want to end up in is,
of course, as in any matrix, the top right quadrant.
Valerius Maximus, a greek philosopher, called this
justice, and Anne Morris and Francis Fry,
whose book you will find in my sources, called this love.
This is a place where you have high standards for
people and they feel that you are deeply devoted to their success.
Ideally, you will end up in this category with your direct reports,
but human nature has it slightly different
things, making things hard for us. So normally people
oscillate between these two categories, oscillate between severity
and fidelity. It goes something like this.
You might start off in severity having very high standards
for people, and then people complain,
oh, you're pushing me too much.
I'm tired, I'm burning out. I can't take
this anymore. There's too much on my plate. So subsequently,
you try to make people feel comfortable, you lower
your standards, you try to make sure that they're not overworked
and that they feel very at ease with
you. You're lowering your standards, and little by little you
end up in fidelity. Until one morning you wake up
and you say, okay, this is enough. No work is getting done anymore.
I need to increase my standards again. And boom,
you end up back in severity. So how do
you break this loop? How do you move along the axis of devotion?
And how do you move along the axis of standards where there
are two components to this? If you want to increase your
devotion, you do that through inquiry, and I'll
talk about that in a second. And if you want to increase your
standards, you do that through feedback. The main
topic of this talk, which I will delve into in
a couple of slides. So let's start off with the devotion
axis and inquiry.
So when you want to reveal your
devotion, you essentially are going to ask people questions,
how can I help you be the most successful or best self?
How can they provide more opportunity for you?
More and more and more questions you ask, the more they're going
to feel that you truly, really deeply care
about their success and about them as individuals.
And remember, the currency of love is attention.
So before we move on to talking about
feedback and different components of feedback, I want to say a few
words about the cultural aspect. So Erin
Mayer performed a lot of research in terms
of culture and the role of feedback in different cultures.
And she drew this axis with direct
negative feedback on one end and indirect negative feedback
on the opposite end. So essentially, you will
have some countries, some cultures where
straight off the band, people are going to be very direct and
they're going to tell you straight up what you're doing wrong.
Netherlands is going to be on the complete
opposite end of indirect negative feedback, sitting very hardly
indirect feedback. A person from Netherlands
is going to tell you very, very clearly what you're doing
wrong, and they're going to do that in front of a group of
people. And nobody's going to consider this route.
Japan, for instance, sits on the opposite side
of the spectrum, where a japanese
person will never dream about telling
you something directly negative,
but you will have to listen in the things they're
not saying for the things that you need
to improve on. And us sits
somewhere in the middle a little bit, leaning into the
indirect negative feedback, for instance, with the very,
very famous compliment sandwich technique,
which, by the way, you should never use.
But this is not quite the topic of this particular talk.
So I want to reframe this a little bit into
terms that will allow you to give feedback
very accurately, no matter
the culture. So we're going to divide
feedback into two categories. There's positive
reinforcement and there's constructive advice,
and I am going to portray the difference between the
two right now. So essentially,
positive reinforcement is catching somebody doing something well
and telling them, do more of this. And constructive
advice is catching someone doing something
not quite well and telling them,
you know what? Do this a little differently.
And when it comes to timing, for positive reinforcement,
usually 12 seconds is sufficient to provide positive reinforcement.
And for constructive advice, at most 10 seconds,
it has to be very short. 10 seconds is quite enough.
Positive reinforcement is going to be very specific and sincere.
And constructive advice, again, has to be very specific.
Can't be, oh, this is all terrible.
You have to pick up on a specific action
or activity with the people that you're talking to,
and it has to be non judgmental but developmental.
So essentially I am telling you this for the sake of
your development, for the sake of your success and
positive reinforcement, you're going to give all the time and
constructive advice you're going to give ASAP after
you have noticed that particular activity
that you want fixing. And the reason why I'm saying
give positive reinforcement all the time is that there
is a specific ratio of these
two between these two that is needed
to make this successful. And the ratio is
five to one. So essentially, in order to
be able to give constructive advice that is going to guide
the person, to stir the person in the right direction,
you need to have built a foundation of
positive reinforcement to give yourself credibility.
If you're going to only give constructive advice, then the person is
going to say, oh, they're never noticing
the good things that I'm doing, they're only focusing on the bad.
I'm not going to take this very seriously,
but if you give positive reinforcement very
frequently, this will give you credibility.
This will give your worst credibility that,
okay, this person is noticing not only the difficult
things but also the positive things.
And essentially the five to one ratio means that if
you want to give constructive advice once
a day, you have to give positive reinforcement five times
a day. If you want to give constructive advice once a
month, you need to give positive
reinforcement once a week and so on.
But the reason why you need to start giving
positive reinforcement straight away and all the time is
because you need to give constructive advice as
soon as possible. And if you do not have that foundation built
up, it is not going to be effective.
So be very keen
to remember this ratio. So to
sum up, we talked about the standards devotion matrix.
We delved into how to move along the axis of the
matrix and get into the justice and love category
with inquiry and feedback. We talked about being
mindful about cultural differences and we introduce the concept
of positive reinforcement and constructive advice.
Now on to the homework.
So first off, my task for you is to find yourself
on the standards devotion matrix. What is the default for you?
Find yourself in all categories with whom you are,
in which quadrants. The second task is
to reveal your devotion. So ask questions.
The more you ask, the more you're going to build up on
that devotion quality. And the third task
is to practice giving constructive advice.
And you can come up to a friend and tell them,
you know what, I'm going to practice this. I'm going to practice giving
you very specific, short,
sincere, non judgmental,
constructive advice. I might not be great at it at first,
but I need to practice to be better. So please help
me practice with that. I'm going to
showcase you my sources.
It's a book called Unleashed by Frances
Rye and Anne Morris of the Leadership Consortium.
It is a book of memorable deeds and saying by
Valeris Maximus and the Culture mob by Erin
Mayer. If you want to get some additional reading
on feedback, Marcus Buckingham has a great book called
Feedback Fallacy that I encourage you to check out.
Thank you so much for tuning in to my talk, and I hope
you enjoy the rest of the talks in Con 42
DevOps 2024 conference. Take care.