You.
Hi. Welcome to my talk today. My presentation will be
a little less technical, but I hope you learn a lot from it.
I will focus today on building a better web, the role
of front end code and resource optimization.
And why am I trying to raise this subject? The answer is
simple, reducing carbon emissions.
So let's start with this question. Do website contribute
to global warming? Today?
The Internet and digital systems are developing very
rapidly. Digital ecology is trying to make
the development of the Internet more sustainable and less
aggressive towards the environment. So it's not
about taking a step back, but making the Internet
a better place in practice. Everything we do online
and everything we do offline with our devices generates
some amount of carbon footprint.
So how does the Internet emit co2?
Let's go through the journey of the data package on the Internet.
This adventure of this data starts in some
kind of data storage servers, data centers or
the cloud. Everything that comes to us from the Internet
and everything we send to the Internet must be stored
somewhere. No arrays. As you know, most data is stored
in the cloud. And what's the cloud?
The name suggests it's something above our heads, white and
light, and we just upload files there and
then we can magically access them from any device and
any place in the world. Unfortunately,
the trough is brutal, and clouds are not just shadows in the sky,
but they are actually huge, massive data centers that needed
to be powered all the time. The cloud is storing
more and more data, even if users don't
necessarily want it. So any data must
be transported from the cloud to your device. And that's
done by the communication infrastructure that also
needs to be continuously powered up. We'll take a closer
look at this stage in the next section.
The final step is the end devices.
Our smartphones, laptops and tablets needed to
be powered too, not to mention
the resources that are needed to produce them.
This is also in terms of digital ecology. A study done
by Canadian University says that the energy
used to charge smartphones has overtaken the energy used to charge
pcs and laptops in 2020.
The production and charging of smartphones alone is
responsible for about 1% of all global emissions.
It's important to extend the use time of smartphones so they
can produce fewer of them. But does
all of this have a real impact? Should we be
so concerned? The answer is yes.
The digital world has a significant impact on the climate
change. As much as 4% of all greenhouses
gases code from the ECT world the growth
of the Internet is not holding back. And on the contrary,
by 2025,
100 zetabytes of data will be stored in the
cloud and generating 200 billion
tons of co2 per year.
So what can we do about this to live more sustainable
digital life? Let's see some examples.
First thing, emails. Guess how
many of them are sent every day. In the next year
it will be 345,000,000,000,000
emails each day. Sending just one generates
on average like 4 grams of co2 and
storing one email for a year. On average
it's 19 grams of co2.
And it's worth adding to this information.
That average Internet user arrives at
approximately 10,000 emails in their inbox.
So if you don't necessarily need to send emails,
it's worth using the other tools such as slack or
internal communication tools, or archaic text messages.
They are much lighter.
Spam statistics shows that almost
50% of emails in 2020 were spam.
Using an antispam has a positive impact on the environment.
It's also worth paying attention to the size of
the emails. If you want to add an attachment, it's better to compress the
files or send a link to download the file
by using retransfer or Google Drive,
anything. It's also worth thinking about
unnecessary extras such as footer, photo, company log,
et cetera. This all increase the size
of the email. Next thing, browsing ecological
ecosia, Lilo or ethical duckduckduckgo are
great browsers and definitely can replace the
most popular ones. You can be
a nontypical programmer and close your tabs.
Most open sites maintain an open
connection to the server and also generates a carbon footprint.
If you know the address of a page by
heart, type it directly into a browser brow
bar. This saves the energy of the search engine.
You also can make use of bookmarks and keywords.
And last thing, but also important,
try to delete your social media data from time to time.
Okay, devices. So replacing a laptop
every six years instead of standard four can
save 190
emissions per person.
You also can save some co2 by deleting
mobile apps you don't use or disabling mobile notifications.
And also you can try to disconnect from the Internet
whenever your hectic lives allows you to do so.
Finally, we come to the clue of the presentation. The websites.
First fact. Did you know that every day 250,000
of web pages are published? And every
page, every view of this page generates on average
1.8 grams of co2, what sums
up to 216
annually. That's the same thing as driving
900 km by a gasoline car.
And that's only just for one website.
And question for you, do you or your
company have a website? The better question who
doesn't? Would you like to know how much co2
is emitted of this website? Emitted by your
website? I will show you how to check this.
The first website I would like to recommend you is
the original website carbon calculator.
You only need to enter the URL of the website
and if it's okay with your website
you can get a free batch that can be added into
your project. And let's see if
we have some other examples. Yes we do.
The next one is green pixie. It works
the same as original website calculator and
the last one is echocurrider. It also works the
same. And our little tradition
on these talks and presentations
I always check how much carbon footprint
is generated by website that
describes the conference I'm talking on.
So how much carbon footprint is generated
by conf. Fourty two website?
Unfortunately it's deer than 94%
of web pages that's ever tested in
original website carbon calculator.
And every view of this page generates almost 4 grams
of co2. It's not great honestly. But the
great thing is that this web page
appears to be ranging on sustainable energy. In this
website you can also see how
many Co 2 grams
equivalent is produced
by a year, or how many bubbles, or how
many trees you need to plant to get rid
of this co2. Okay, from this
point, let's go further. This is
Tom Greenwood, the author of
Sustainable web design book which
describes techniques that make a website more sustainable.
I will tell you about some of them in a moment.
Before that, let's make a moment to talk about
how co2 is called by
a methodology presented in the Sustainable Web Design
foundation. It's based on the data transport
which is in the middle stage of the data transfer on the
Internet. The other stages are very difficult to
estimate so we only focus on this part.
According to research conducted by SWD,
75% of people return to the site
first visit means that all data must be downloaded
and returning visit means that only
2% of data is cached. So energy
emissions means how much co2 is produced
per 1.
It's vary for each country and the value is
averaged by SWD. Okay,
we can move to the part. When I talk about really
specific practices on creating the websites more
sustainable. First thing is language.
Once the website was written from the scratch or
developed using platforms like WordPress or
Wix as then we don't have total
control over the website and they are worse to maintain
perfectly. If you are coding your
website. From the scratch on the graph
you can see that the best
language is JS. A little worse might be typescript
which is transpiration of js and the
other languages like Python Perl are
not very recommended to create green websites
and from this point now I will assume
that we are talking about sites written in JS.
If you write in JS, it's already good,
but it's important to follow popular standards as use well known
frameworks such as react or angular or vue.
This way there is a greater chance that
our code will be reusable and the time spent debugging
will be shorter. The heavy libraries
most of the loadash functions or jquery
can be replaced with Vangila JS code for
HTTP clients used for queries built in fetch
can meet our requirements perfectly
and can save up to 0.2
grams of co2.
First and foremost the number of queries rethinking
whether the data all the data is needed optimizing
of the data retrieved from the API server
side or frontend caching instead of
asking each time for some data, we can cache to
the data locally and do
you know what image format do you use the most?
The best two are SFG and web.
S 5G is a vector format. Web is invented by
Google in 2010 and comparing
web to PNG saves almost twelve times more
data in our website.
Honestly, if you really
don't need to have videos on your page, just please
don't give them. And if you really
need to, please use web. It's a twin format
of web saving up to 50% of space.
Next links will be font formats.
The best one is supported by all browsers,
the system ones. The next are local
fonts that are hosted on our server,
not hosted online. And if you
want to use local fonts, please use
Wolf tool format. It's much better than ttf
and can save up to 70%
of space colors in OLED
screens. Up to 50% of energy saving is
when you have dark theme
and it's definitely worth having
the last thing hosting pew
defines the hosting efficiency indicator and
how much energy is used. And it's
better to use hosts that are running
on renewable energy and have some
green behavior policy like planting
trees or green employee.
You can find all of them on the Green
web Foundation and some examples are Sarava
from Finland s four hosting from Lithuania,
strata from Germany or crystal hosting from the UK.
The next thing is user data collection or caching.
Most sites collect user data to target advertisements.
This account for a significant portion of the data transfer
and it's not only the co2 thing, but it's also
unethical. And there was an experiment.
The USA Today website make
a copy of themselves to meet the european
GDPR policy and with this experiment they
make 91% lighter and faster website
without user data collection. So I think that's
a change. Okay, so why are we
do this? The first thing is of course carbon footprint
mitigation, the second electrical energy savings
and the third is shorter loading time.
But did you know that 55% of
users can be lost if a website loads longer than
in 3 seconds?
So the last thing is better SEO.
So our website is higher in positioning
of the search engines. So the
last thing we can do about this
is use some linter. If you're a JS developer,
you probably use eclint. And good news, there is
an eclint equivalent that tells you what you can do to make
your website greener. It's open source and
me and my team are working on to develop the store.
Okay, this is our features.
The blue ones are
already ready to use in
your projects and the purple
one are not developed yet, but we are working on them.
And does it really work or
not? The whole sustainable
thing? And our analysis shows that after implementing
the techniques from the SWD, you can
reduce page size up to 88%.
And this is without any visible
impact from the user. And our tool eclint
can definitely help with this.
So in summary, eclint prompts something
similar to lighthouse but acts like
eclint. Instead of fixing already existing pages,
eclint suggests what can be changed already
while writing the code. We are
aware that our tool is only
a drop in the ocean of needs, but ultimately
we want just one click is enough to make our website eclint.
This will be easier if you help us to develop
the tool and share the project with your friends. If you think that
what are we doing makes sense, please leave us a star on GitHub.
These are all references I used to make
this presentation and this is my profile.
Thank you for joining my talk. Feel free to
contact me on LinkedIn. You can use this QR code to
see my file. I will be happy to answer all your
questions. Again, thank you for your attention and
have a nice conference.