Hello and welcome. My name is Kevin Petro Givinch and
I will have pleasure to talk about Azure DevOps private
agents at scale. So how easy you can build
your private agent pools using my approach.
So go with me through the presentation and
at the end of it you will obtain all the information which
is needed to configure this private
agents pool in your projects. Okay,
before going to the presentation I would like to say
a few words about manager manager senior Azure architect
team, focusing mainly on the cloud migrations
and greenfield projects.
I really love to make automation of the solution,
so it includes both code deployment
and infrastructure creation. With my favorite
tool terraform. I really like to also
share knowledge. I do that through LinkedIn,
my blog Azure way, and of course events
like this.
So just firstly I would
like to show you two types of the
Azure DevOps agents which are available so
safe hosted and Microsoft hosted agents.
So briefly we see the difference between
them so you can easily define which
agent is better for your workload.
Okay, so the first thing which
I would like to compare is the maintenance. So it's
self hosted agents like the name suggest
you need to maintain this agent by yourself.
So you need to take care about the update,
the networking, the connectivity,
the tools which are installed, the updates
of the system and so on. On the other hand,
in Microsoft hosted you just use it,
you do not care at all. So this
is for sure easier path.
Okay. The second thing, the integration.
In my opinion, this is the crucial moment when you
decide which agent you should use. So imagine
that you have a project which is
network isolated so it
can be behind firewall, you can use
private endpoints, you can use another
isolation methods, then you need
to use safe hosted agent because then you can
integrate it with your network.
So on the other hand, Microsoft hosted cannot
be integrated with the virtual network.
Of course there is also Microsoft hosted
have some limits on the cpu memory and
so on. So if you even do not
have isolated
workload, but you need more
resources to build your project,
then you need to go with the self hosted.
Okay, what about pricing and scaling?
So in the self hosted mode you have a
really nice feature that if you add
user with the MSDN license to
your organization, you obtain one
license for self hosted agent
which includes private projects.
If you want more license then you
need to pay $15 per month. Of course
this $15 per month include owning the license to
running next self hosted agent.
So the entire infrastructure on which
you run this agent, you need
to pay for that. Okay, so on
the other hand, Microsoft hosted you pay
$40 per month and you do not
care about nothing. So the infrastructure
and license is included on that price.
What is really nice thing, you obtain
one Microsoft hosted agent for free
in Azure DevOps, but it has limit
of the execution.
Of course this agent for
which you pay do not have such a limit.
Okay, so if we are talking about private
agents on the DevOps, of course you
have many ways to achieve it. So this
is not one solution which
is perfect, but you can use many
ways to achieve the goal. So now I would
like you to present some of the options
which we can use to create private
agents. So the first will be maybe
not popular one, but I really like it
for certain scenarios. So this is Azure container instances
which I like on that. This is extremely
easy to set up, so you can set up
it with only one command for the
Azure ClI. So the setup is
really easy, but there is some disadvantage
that you cannot build docker images on
it. Of course you can do some
workaround. For example you can use Azure container
registry private pool in
which you can build your docker images and integrate
with your virtual network. But as
I said, this is only workaround.
Of course there is another disadvantage that
this agent is
one instance which is constantly running.
So imagine the situation that you have many pipelines
and maybe you face such a situation in
your projects. So when you build one pipeline
and then second pipeline it sometimes fail,
but in the other configuration it
succeeded. So it means that your pipelines
are somehow dependent on each other, but in
not a state way. So the order in
which run is really important because
there must be certain order that these
bill are failing. So it
can be cases because that agent
is not clear. So it has some
dependent, maybe settings
or some environment variables, maybe tools
from the other build which was run on this agent.
So yeah, we need to be careful on that and
I will show you how we can avoid it.
Okay, so the next thing will be of course Azure
Kubernetes services, so you can create your
private agent pool on the aks, which is a really
great service. I think we can agree on that.
And what's more, if you will use Keda
for it, then you can make even driven
scale of these private agents running
on the Kubernetes services. So you can adjust
your agents, for example to the
qui build. So if you're on your qui
will be for example 8910
waiting bills, then you can scale accordingly
with Keda. But of course this Azure Kubernetes services
is difficult to set up. This is not one line comment.
So this is more difficult to set
up than container instances,
but of course it's much more powerful
than container services. So of
course with the aks you can build docker
images but it requires additional configuration.
And what is great thing
you benefit from all aks features. Yeah so
self healing, scarring and so on.
So this is a really great approach. But in my opinion this
is really nice when you have a big project and
long running project. So if your project run long
time, so this is about two years
or more, then you can think about setting
up Kubernetes services.
Okay. And the last but not least option is
Azure V two R machine's case approach. So what I
like in that scenario that this is pretty easy to
set up. Of course this is more complicated than Azure container
instances but less complicated than Kubernetes
services. So it can scale up,
scale down, can build docker
images and is really cost efficient
because you always scale
to your needs and this is pretty similar to Keda.
So if you have some builds waiting then you scale
accordingly with the visual machine
skset, but this does not require any
additional configuration.
And with this last approach I would like to follow in that
presentation. So I will show you how to create
virtual machines cases setup with of course
step to step. And for what's
more I will share source code for you
in which you can run your setup
in your project. Okay.
But of course every setup has
some challenges and visual
machine skset agent pool is not different one.
So what are the challenges here?
So the first challenge will be to build a universal
agent image because if you
run such an approach then you need to cover
different teams and application needs. So you
will have some team which use net, some which use
Java, some which use node or some data
teams or even some architects
team which creates architecture, for example in azure
or AWS or even on the
other clouds. So you need to have universal
image, you can call it gold image,
but building such an image which is
a universal one is a challenge. I think we can agree
on that. So you need to install a
lot of tools and these tools will be in
many versions. So you need to be careful
on that because you cannot update
these tools with your own choice
because you can break some other build.
So you will end up with
many versions of your golden image and
you need to be sure that you update your
scale agents pool in a smooth way that you
are sure that some
teams are not using the version, for example five
and they can switch to the version six. So you need to
create a new agent pool, tell the team,
yeah, you need to switch to the new pool because new
version we deployed and check your old
pipelines, your old builds. So if they can move
to new version you can decommission previous one.
But still you need to version the image
and I will show you what tools you need to use
to achieve that goal. Okay,
so how this image build process
can be made. So the first important
thing, and I think this is a really great information
that you do not need to create this golden image because
it's already created. So on the GitHub you can find
the repo where the definition of
this image is already done. And what's
more, using those sources.
I think you use it many ways but you do not realize.
So these sources are used to build GitHub
runners and Microsoft hosted agents.
So you can build these universal agents
for your own private pool. I think this
is really great information. To build that
image you use Packer tool.
And why to use Packer?
Because you can just run it.
You can go install the tools and create the image.
Yeah, but with Packer you have a lot of tools,
you can make the test of
the setup and this is done through the CI CD pipeline.
I think this is a really great approach that you can automatically
build your golden image and
Packer do that job for you. So in the background packer
create virtual machine. On that virtual
machine it execute the scripts,
then make some best and then create
image from this virtual machine in which you can use it.
And in that process you will upload
the image created from Packer into Azure
image gallery. In that Azure image gallery
you can have many versions of
the image. So you create container.
For example my golden build agent
and on the my golden build agent you create
versions and using that versions you
can create virtual machines cases it
of course you can have many versions of one image,
which solves our problem with
versioning and different tools. I think
this is a really great approach and now I would like
you to show how to implement it
through the demo.
Firstly I would like you to present
the GitHub repository. Its name is
images and what we can find
in this repository is the source code used
to create VM images for GitHub hosted runners
used for GitHub actions, and also
Microsoft hosted agents used for Azure pipelines.
So in that repo, as you just see
is a source code which is used to
build choose hosted hanas. In my
case I will be using ubuntu 20 four.
So now let's see what are
the tools installed into this image.
To see that we need to go to the images next to
explore Ubuntu. And now go
to the readme file. Okay so
in the readme file we have all information what is
deployed into this image. So we have OS
version of course system d image version and
so on. This also specified language
and runtime which I installed package management
tools. So you have a pretty
long list of the tools.
And of course we have also some Cli tools
like Aws, Cli, azure, Cli, GitHub,
Cli, Google cloud,
openshift and so on.
Okay so now I would like you to show
how this image definition look like.
So to find the image definition we of course need
to go to ubuntu and now explore
templates. In the templates we need to
open packer definition file.
Okay and in the packer definition file we find firstly
required plugins. This is the same structure as
for terraform. And now nextly variables.
These are pretty long list of the variables and
then the build image
step with usage of the azure iam.
Okay so this is how it looks like,
but in the setup I would like you to show the
installation of the tools. So you see that
this is execution of the prepared
scripts. And for example there is also a
skip build install terraform.
So now go to that script and see
how it pools. So we need to go to the
scripts next build and then install terraform.
Okay so go ubuntu scripts
build and
ethernet. Okay so the installation
is pretty easy as you can see we first need to download
the binaries and then unzip
it to the user bin director.
And then is our invoke test tools terraform.
So let's see how this test looks like.
So again we need to go to images
ubuntu scripts
next best.
And then tools test pds one.
Now we find terraform.
Okay so we have a terraform test,
we have a terraform version and
should gcatune zero exit code.
So it's simple word. This will just return the
version of the terraform. Okay nice.
So now I would like you to show how
looks like the terraform
skip to create the packet
image and the virtual machine skip.
So firstly we start with our providers
for telephone. So we define two.
So this would be hashicop azure rm
and also hashicop random. I like
this library for the random because I
can generate random numbers, random passwords
and so on. So really nice thing.
Nextly I configure backend for
the terraform in the azure in that case of course
I use azure storage if you do not
know how to configure the backend for the terraform,
you can go to my blog and see article
which goes you through all the steps how
to configure backend and of course how to confuse
provider in the terraform for
Azure. So how to create client id,
client secret and how to set up subscription
id and of course tenant as you configure
your telephone providers then we can look
into the exit terraform script. So first
things you need to notice is the image path. So this is
path to the Ubuntu definition
in Packer. And as you can see I have the
directory running images main
and this is just simple copy of
the repo which I just show you in the seconds.
Okay, so what we need to create to
build your image and to create virtual
machine sky set. So firstly we need
a gallery. So we create shared
image gallery here.
This is just our service for storing
the images and the image version.
Next we
need to create shared image. This is just a container
for your image versions. So this is not
exact image but this is
like a resource group for the images.
So my name will be Ubuntu 2204
agent pools.
Next I need to use a new heso
because I would like to add packer in it.
I run packet image with my image
path. As you remember this is path
to the Ubuntu four packer image
definition. Next I run next
no resource bound by but now this is a
packet runner. It means to best a
packer image. Of course I
need to somehow authorize in Azure.
So I need to again set the client
id, client secret subscription
and of course tenant. What you can notice
in these parameters is a temp resource group name.
So this is a resource group which will
be used by Parker to create virtual machine
and install all these tools there. And from this
machine create image and
this image will be placed in the managed image
resource group name. Of course with
the name specified in the managed image name
parameter. Okay, after our skip
is done I need to wait for it on the depends
on. So see I must
wait for the packaging to
be finished before I can obtain azure
image. I use that data
because this is not adhesives which I create
but I just made import to
the terraform. And you remember
that this image was created by a packet just in the
packet runner step. Okay,
so while I have the exact image
I can create image version and put it in
the image gallery.
Of course I use some name in my case
will be free. And of
course you need to make a reference to the managed image
id where in my case will be the
id of the image created by Packer.
Okay so the last step will be to create
the skyset I use virtual
machine skyset module defined in the terraform
and in here I just need few
parameters, resource group and location skew
and image gallery image id.
Okay so now see how
this module look like. I create a random password.
I need it for a setup. By honesty you don't need to log
into these virtual machines because they are controlled
by Azure DevOps. So next
create just simple virtual network and
subnet. Of course there is nothing special
subnet needed. I think you
need to adjust to your needs in your project.
Next I create virtual machine skyset with the
of course name admin user password
for the instances I put one because this will be
scaled by Azure DevOps so I don't need
more. And what is really important, you need to set over provisioning
to false and upgrade mode to manual as these parameters
are needed to use this virtual machine
sketch as an agent pool. Next I
play source image id. Of course this will be
id from the guy image.
Okay next standard parameters,
nothing fancy here. Okay so
now see how this pipeline because
I use Azure DevOps to build this
terraform of course. So I
do not want to run my local machine,
I would rather use some
pipeline to do that. One important thing on the pipeline is that
timeout in minutes. You need to set a really high because
this build cases about 2 hours which I will
show you just now. Okay so
we have pipeline create plan
and apply. And you see that this took about 2
hours. Of course it can vary.
Okay so next go to terraform
apply. Of course this is some standard setup.
So I install terraform, I made some in it.
I made terraform validate and then terraform apply.
But what I would like to show here are tests.
So go and find it.
Yeah, so you see that we have discovered five tests.
Discovery was pretty fast. Now these
are filter selected four tests to run.
As you see the filter is power nodules
and there is a running of the
best. And you see that test passed
four fight zero skipped zero, not on
one. And if you find that any
of the best will be fired, of course the build of the
image will be fired also. So you are sure
that all pools are working.
In another case you will just do not build this image.
Okay, so now take a
look for Azure side there
is an agent pool automation code
resource group and what we can find it.
Yeah, so we have compute gallery, we have image,
we have virtual machines cases, we have some virtual
network. We have image definition and image
version. So now take a look how this all connects with
each other. So firstly go to the image
gallery. In the image gallery
you will find definition. So this is our Ubuntu
2004 agent pool. So you see that this
is only image definition which I can
rely when I try to create virtual
machines case it. So go to this definition.
Okay, so you see that I have some versions
and using that image definition I
can create virtual machine or I can create virtual
machine skyset. If you go to the version
you also have create VM, a create
virtual machines case set. But then when
you use it you will use the exact version
of the image. So in my case will be free.
What is really nice is the update replication.
So you see that we have a target region, replica count
and stripe skew and replication status.
So when you firstly run out form,
the replication status won't be completed,
but will be in progress and you will see a percentage
how much of this application was completed.
Of course this replication status must be to completed.
Two this step on the telephone will be
finished. So as you
can see you can put this image in many regions
and also use many versions. So if
you would like to build another Ubuntu 2205
ZFO agent pool, you will just put another version
to that image definition. And then next you
can use it with the virtual machine
skill set creation. Okay, so now
we can go to find how we can see
how we can create a private agent
pools. So we need to go to the organization settings.
Next go to agent pools and
in the next you need to go and click add pull as
a pools type we'll choose virtual
machine skset project
for service connection. In my case will be azure way Azure
subscription. So our connection will
be enterprise subscription.
Next I created a special virtual
machine skate set for this demo.
We specify the name,
okay, and now we have few options to choose. First is
an automaticality down virtual machine after
use what it means. It means that when
your build finished then your machine will
be destroyed and new machine will
be created to use for the next build. This is
a really nice feature because you are sure that your
agents is clean. I do not have
any dependencies from other build,
so for sure we want to turn on
this feature. Next, the maximum number
of each of our machines is Skyset.
I think the description is pretty obvious, but you cannot set more
than you have parallel jobs.
So in Macari this is a nine,
okay, so numbers of agents to keep on standby.
So this will be the number of the petrol
machines which are waiting for the bills.
So if you want to save money, just put a zero here.
But you must agree with that, that for the first
build you need to wait a little bit.
This will be about two, three minutes. Just to
this agents will be connected to the delts.
The last parameter is delay in minutes before
deleting excess idle agents.
So it means that this is a time,
how much time this agents will keep
on standby. If there is no action in
that 30 minutes, this will be ticked down.
So if you have really big
number of the bills waiting, then this
number won't be used because these agents
will be occupied and you will never
touch this delay. But if
for example your team stopped working at this
day and because this is an end of work
for now, then probably all agents will be
teamed down with this delay.
Okay, so of course how to provision this agent pull in our
project. It depends on your needs. Okay,
so if you don't want to have
this pool be available on all projects, just turn
it off.
Okay, so when you click create,
then this pools will be ready in about 15
minutes. So you must be patient here.
15 minutes is beacons small time.
So go to the, now we go to the agent pools.
Again, there is an example,
this is example pools as
you can see on the agents. This is
built on the example virtual machines kset.
And this is also made on the
same image which I just showed you.
So I would like to go and
present you that
using this pool I can build the
docker image. I will just make a run pipeline here
and show you.
Yeah, so you see that I have a really simple pipeline
built and push state and there is
a docker build, easy one, nothing fancy here.
Okay, so I just
run this pipeline, it should be finished in
about three minutes, maybe two.
So we'll back to it in a second.
And as you can see, one more thing,
it uses the example bitchuma machine,
skset agent and of
course the machine, the name is
the same. Okay, so we back
in a minute to see how it
goes. Okay,
so the summary of the process, it looks like
that. So first we need to create shared image
gallery just to have
possibility to later on use image to create virtual
machines case it. And next we create shared
image. Remember that this is just a container for the image versions.
Then we unpack an image build. To build our
image as an output we
need to create image version.
So after we create the image version, we can create
virtual machines cases. And the
last step will be configure Azure DevOps agent
pool okay so maybe
we see how our build is going,
we need a few moments more. Okay so
what if of course I had different issues
when I tried to build this golden image. So the
first was we stopped hearing from
agent, from the hosted agent
okay so I tried to use Microsoft hosted agent and
after one and a half hour I got
that this hosted agent was disconnected.
If you will put this error into
the Google you will see a lot of
issues with the hosted Microsoft agents and
of course nothing was resolved.
So in order to build that image I used another
private agent. I set it up on the virtual
machine, the Linux one of course the Ubuntu so then
it all worked just fine.
But I have another arrow.
This was fate to fetch four fee for Biden.
So I got this arrow, why don't
unlink one of the pools? Maybe that was, you know,
some issue with that server.
I know how to say when I rerun
this process the image was built without errors.
Okay so yeah you see that the
build is already finished. It took almost two
minutes. Let's see how the agents
looks like. So you see that my agent is offline
because I have a settings that it needs
to be teared down after the build.
When I will another
pipeline then I will go to fetch agent.
Okay so what about the costs?
So in my project I run it
for one month, I set it up maximum number of
agents to 15 and the build was
$150. So it
means that I paid $10 pay
per agent. Of course this $10 is only the
cost of the infrastructure. So this is
cost of virtual machines cases. I think this is a pretty
good price as the hosted
agents, the Microsoft hosted agent it cost about
$40 per month. So I use
the same image as the Microsoft hosted pay $10.
So I think this is a pretty good and of
course this cost may vary because
you can set up another number
of the Eden agents, you can have more bills.
So it all depends on the project but you
see the overall cost. Okay so
if you would like to obtain the source code
and description for the terraform which I just show
you and of course the pipelines,
you can go to my blog. This is Azureway cloud,
you can scan this QR code and see the description
and all the needed URLs.
So the GitHub, GitHub runners
and the GitHub repository of my Azure
way blog.
Okay if you would like to
stay in touch with me you can just follow me
on my LinkedIn and if you have any questions of
problems with my examples you can
contact me on the private message. For sure.
I will help you with that.
Okay. So thank you for your attention. I hope
you enjoyed the session and
I hope that you will use this approach in your projects.
And the setup will be really smooth using my
tutorial and source code. Bye.
Have a nice day.