It. Hi, this is Gordon Rudd coming to you from Conference 42s
Golang conference. I'm going
to talk to you today about information security and
specifically how to be a chief information security officer.
This is me. Please feel free to connect with me
on any social media platform. Give me a call anytime.
We're always here to go. So without further ado,
we've got a lot to go through today. I'm going to make sure that we
get through everything. And again, if we have any questions, connect with me
on social media. I'll be happy to answer any questions you may have.
We are going to talk about every CISO's 1st 90
days and how to achieve lasting success as a CISO.
Our agenda for the day is really quite simple. You want
to be a CISO? Yeah, everybody wants to be a
CISO. Not everybody, but a lot of folks do.
And 30, 60, 90 day plans. You're a CISO
now. What should you be doing with your day? What should you
be doing for your organization? How should you be conducting yourself
and what does a world class CISO look like and creating your roadmap
for success. And we want to make sure during
this time that we're getting your head in the game and that we're
giving you some clues on where to go to next. Because after
all, for a lot of people, being a chief information security officer is a dream
job. And we want to make sure that when you get that dream job,
you understand what you're getting into. You are not going to be a
rock star. This is a rock star. This is
a CISO. Cisos spend a good deal of time being underwater.
That's just the way it works. We are normally
a little bit behind the curve. We're trying to anticipate everything that's going to
happen. But as you might guess, anticipating what's going to happen
can sometimes lead you a little astray. What I'm going
to do today is give you a for sure
methodology for making sure that you succeed
as a chief information security officer, or chief information officer,
or chief technology officer for that matter. I'm going to really begin
to outline the measure, assess plan or the map
strategy, so that you can measure what you've got in place
when you get there. When you get to the new job, you can
assess the gap, figure out what's needed, and then you can simply
plan the work and work the plan. It's what we all want to do.
And it doesn't better how you came to be the CISO, whether you started the
help desk and went through network administration. Perhaps you were a
SoC analyst, maybe even a forensic analyst, and then a CISO.
It doesn't matter how we come to it. If you're going to have a
great career, if you're going to succeed as
a CISO, you've got to make sure that you're monitoring these
nine things all the time, the tone from the top. You've got
to watch the board and the senior management team and make sure
that you understand their priorities and
what they perceive to be a complete information
security program. You also want to look at your GRC, your governance,
risk and compliance, and you want to make sure you stay with the cisos.
The kiss principle. Excuse me? You want to make sure you keep
it simple, not necessarily for the stupid, but for the sake of simplicity.
You want to make sure that you have employee ownership. The employees have to
own the information security program, because information security
is a team sport. And you're going to find that you can't do it without
everybody. So let's make them owners, let's get them involved,
and we're going to solve problems. And it's not just
buying new tech. A lot of times we find that organizations
will want to buy a new piece of software, some new
service, when they already have something on the ground that'll do it and
probably meet every specification they've got.
So we're also going to talk a little about finding your company's rhythm,
about due diligence, collaboration, and automating
everything as much as possible. Automation is your
friend. One of the first things I really want you to do if you're thinking
about being a CISO, is take a moment and decide what kind of CISo
are you? Are you a technical or a managerial CISO?
That's a hands on versus an executive. We've got a
lot of different acronyms, three letter acronyms, four letter acronyms,
or tlas and flas that we're throwing around today.
Technically oriented CISO, that's the one that
would be the hands on CISO. It's usually a one man band, maybe two
or three people. A policy oriented CISO, also known
as a business information security officer,
that's somebody that doesn't touch the technology, that just kind of stays
in the sea level and makes sure that everything's itoperations
correctly from the strategic and tactical
levels, not necessarily boots on the ground. Or are you
strategically oriented CISO, or also a
strategic information security officer? Are you looking forward? Are you
looking at new things and trying to figure out how to dial them? Into your
organization. The first thing I want to make sure we're all doing is
getting our head in the game. And to do that, you're going to have to
measure asses and plan or map yourself. You're going to have to
do an agonizing self appraisal and find out where your strengths are and where your
weaknesses are. You're going to have to know, what are you?
Are you the information security CISO that everybody
talks about that can fix anything, or are you the strategy CISO?
Are you the executive CISO? You're going to have to figure out who you are.
I always suggest that to do that, you start with a diagram very
much like this, and you go through the who you are, where you're going,
how you're going to get there, what actions you're going to take, and how
to evaluate and review everything that's going on.
Those are stages that
will do you well. They will serve you well if
you use smart goals and objectives, specific, measurable,
attainable, realistic and time bound. The evaluate and review
that we see over here, this evaluate and review
that is absolutely part of the process.
Put times on the different activities that you feel
you have to have to make yourself a better executive.
And when you come to that time, mark,
reevaluate. You've got lots of things to think about as a
CISO today or as any technology executive. You've got a lot of decisions
to make. I strongly suggest that you find either
a coach or an accountability partner. Either one will do.
You don't necessarily have to have a coach, but you need an accountability partner,
somebody that you can talk to and you can
work through the process of saying, I've got these things to
do, these are my timelines. And somebody just holds you accountable.
And I've always found that using your boss as that
accountability partner doesn't often work out the way you'd
think, because a lot of times you want to give some
reasoning why you're late. Many times the boss doesn't
have an ear for that sort of thing. I want you to remember that
you are running a marathon. As a chief information security officer,
however, that marathon is going to be running sprints. You're going to go hard,
stop and rest. Go hard, stop and rest. At least we hope you
get that stop and rest cycle in there. So I want to make sure you're
ready for this because it's going to be sprint, rest,
sprint rest until you get the whole 26.2 miles.
Now, to get the job as CISo, you probably
had the whole, okay, we're promoted.
We're replacing somebody.
Candidate selection process. At any rate, as you went through all
these things, you did the resume, you did the COVID letter, you did the interview,
you did all your research at the interview. You should have
had in your possession a 30,
60, 90 day plan that you used as a
tool to tee up what you think
you should be doing during your first 90 days on the job. That you
can also use to find out what your supervisor, what your boss
thinks you should be doing every day on the job. That's the beauty of that
plan. It's a communication tool for you. And then you're going to take
your plan that probably looked like a word document and
you're going to break it down like this. You will notice that
before you got there, before day one,
you had a 30, 60, 90 day plan. You understood your manager's
expectations. You had a copy of the chart. You'd done your research on
the industry, the company, the department. And now you're going to start measuring things.
The strategic and tactical, the budget, the GRC policy
and procedure analysis, enterprise risk assessments, that sort of thing.
Assets that are being managed, assets that are unmanaged,
vulnerability assessments, personnel skill access controls,
interviews. Those are just a few of the things that you're going to do.
You want to understand the change management process from jump.
Ask what the change management process is
and how information security fits into it. The other
thing you want to make sure you're doing is to assess the
enterprise's cybersecurity, their architecture and baseline their current training plan.
Software development teams, DevOps teams can be
the same thing. Maybe not. Some folks
just do development. Some folks do DevOps. We're seeing DevOps
take over. But there's still a significant number of organizations out there
today that have the software development teams that are all developing
different pieces for the systems that are found throughout the
organization. How the organization is meeting,
all its, you know, it should be NYDFs,
not NTDFs,
CCPA, GDPR,
all those. How are you doing that? And you want
to look at your backup management plan. That backup management,
especially if you're looking at a ransomware situation, can save
you. It will save you or kill you, depending on whether you're doing it right
or if you're just not paying attention to it. And then you're going to plan
all these things. Corporate information protection plan,
that's yours to create. You need to have one. You need to have it blessed
by the board. So from wherever you are to the board,
you've got to work your way through those layers of management,
filtering that plan, making changes and additions to it until
you get consensus on it. And you're going to have to build you,
you're going to have to figure out where you are and where you
need to be. So you're going to plan for yourself, you're going to plan for
your executive growth. You want to make sure that you're testing
every bit of business continuity management that the organization
has. Business continuity management, again, it's going
to make you or break you in any kind of an incident. So prep,
measure, assess, plan, mapping everything out. And again,
this is very generic. Yours is going to be different depending on
your industry, depending on your organization, and depending on your
skill set. Remember, we're all going to start out the same place.
We're all going to start out with data at the center. That app
is going to be, there's going to be an app wrapped around the data,
that's pulling the data in and reading and writing the data, storing the data.
There's going to be a host that the app sets on. The host is going
to sit on a network. The network is going to have a perimeter, it's going
to have physical security. We're going to have policies and procedures
for data governance, and we're going to have a security education, training and
awareness program. Those are all things we have to have.
Very interesting. When you start looking at it, you must
have those pieces to that puzzle. And the way we put them together for
chief information security officer is to create overlapping
layers of security to create this model so
that you've got your perimeter security. You step inside and you've
got another layer of layer of security.
Some of the items that you might find, like a
firewall and VPN on the outside, might have counterparts
in that middle circle. So if you're looking outside
at your perimeter and then looking a step inside,
this would be inside the firewall, that would be forward
facing what you're looking at the wild, wild west
and you're going to look at your encryption inside. What have you got
inside? Remember, cybersecurity is very complex
today. It's not just the agile development cycles or the DevOps
teams that are creating code, packaging it and putting it through
change management and an automated process. We've got mobile, we've got websites.
Websites today are normally going to be the
busiest branch or physical location that you have.
Normally your website will do ten times more business every
day than all your physical sites put together. As just kind of
a rule of thumb that we're seeing. So that complexity means that
you're really going to have to stay on top of things. You're going to have
to make sure that you're pitching in every chance you get
to keep the wheels turning. And to do that,
there's a skill set that if you don't have, you need to develop. If you
do have, you need to hone it. The security program, creation,
management and operations, creating the program,
managing the program and operating the program are three different stages.
You need to be familiar with those stages. You need to understand them. The information
security core concepts. If you're a CISSP, look at
the domains that go with that certification. We used to
have ten, now we've got eight. But they're still very valid domains.
So those are the core concepts. Encryption,
all that sort of thing that's found in those domains
is pertinent to your job. You should know those domains, you should be familiar
with them. You also need to have the ability to plan,
need to have a rudimentary understanding of finance, risk management and
vendor management or third party risk management.
Depending on the size of your organization, your governance, risk and compliance
is going to be key. And those five p's, program,
processes, procedures, projects and people.
You need to know your programs, your processes, your procedures,
your projects and your people. And it's at this point
that I would suggest to you that a project that's gone on for more than
that's allotted time, let's say just for the sake of argument, it was supposed to
be a year long project. You're going into year three. That's not
a project anymore. That's a process. Just call it a process.
Declare the project done, take the win and go home.
And whether or not you're in information technology
or information security management, controls and auditing,
that ties into that GRC. How do you control it?
How do you audit and what techniques acumen do
you need? If you're hands on CISO, you're going
to need to understand the technology. And then we're going
to take a look at the organization itself as part of that mapping
process. We're going to assess the organizational maturity and the operational readiness.
And the way we're going to do that is just use a basic CMMI
model so that we're starting down here in the
initial stages where all organizations start,
they're all pretty much, this is actually level one
down here. They're all pretty much competent people
using heroic efforts to keep things going, keep all
the wheels spinning round and round every day. And when you move up
from that. When you move up to the managed but isolated projects,
you start to see basic project management.
You start to see different tactics being used,
but they're used inconsistently. And as you move up,
you're looking at defined processes, multiple project capabilities.
So all of a sudden at level three here, you're going to be seeing a
project portfolio, and projects across the
entire organization are all going to be grouped together in one portfolio
and managed as such. You get up to level four. It's all counted.
Everything's counted, quantitatively managed,
quantitatively operated. Every one of those things
is absolutely where you want it to be, but it's counted.
And that's really kind of the bottom
line, because the five is going to be part of the defense industrial complex or
really big organization, federal government kind of thing.
All that sizing is
to say that we don't want to throw anything away. We want to be able
to purchase the equipment we need today and figure out a way
for it to scale, because scalability gives the organization economic
flexibility. So as we come up through our network with
our itoperations, systems, applications, the whole thing,
123456 serves as
we come up the seven layers. The one thing I want
you to understand is that every time you build in scalability, you're building in
economic flexibility, and that's important to your organization.
Okay. You've got to maintain the confidentiality,
integrity and availability triad while you're doing it. But you
also need to make sure that it's scalable. You don't want to do forklift
upgrades. You want to minimize the number of forklift upgrades you're
doing. And you do that by simply remembering that one size doesn't
fit all. It does not fit all. You're going to have different solutions
as the organization grows more employees than
organization has. The differences
in not only the infrastructure, but the information
security that's involved in securing that infrastructure will
change. But I want to make sure that the four points
of alignment, and you notice there's actually five things on that slide,
but we call them the four points of alignment because you see functionality twice.
You want to stop and say, what functionality do I have on the ground
right now? The pieces, parts, the systems that I have in place
today? What's their functionality? What's their capability? Then you want
to look at aligning the economics. Does it make dollars and cents?
And then you want to look at the talent. Do we have the talent to
drive the equipment we have, or is the talent not trained up
enough? So the talent your people are telling you that the equipment
doesn't function the way they need it to function. Not your optimum
situation to be in, but you can train your way out of that.
And then you want to decide, are we going to use our existing
equipment or are we going to use new equipment? Whose equipment are we going to
use and what's it going to look like? And we want to make sure
that you're leaving breadcrumbs, that you're creating a roadmap for
yourself. You're using everything you've got,
just using all the skills that you've been taught
and making sure that you're collecting all the appropriate artifacts. You want to make sure
that you're collecting threat hunting artifacts, that you're doing.
Log aggregation, every computer on the planet allows you to log everything that
happens on it. That can get a little messy because any computer on
the planet can exhaust any amount of disk space by
simply sitting there and operating and recording everything to log
files. Log aggregation, log management,
very critical. Firewall clustering, AI user
behavior analytics are critical for you. Vulnerability management.
If you look at the threat hunting, threat hunting, vulnerability management,
and patch management all go
together. So there's a little triad there, a little trilogy.
You want to make sure you're aware of your security research, your incident response,
your forensics, your training and cross training.
Those types of things are all artifact
driven. You want to record where you are and where you're going. You want
to make sure you know how you got where you are, and you want to
make sure you're looking at your network and endpoint defenses.
Are we monitoring multiple layers of security? Well, I hope
so. We should be by now. We want to look at our
firewalls, our dlp spam filtering, antivirus threat emulation,
HTTPs inspection, bot protection, application control,
and ur filtering. It's at this point that I would say, if you're not familiar
with the OWAS model, you should be. If we go back here and we
look at the log aggregation, we just say, okay, great,
we're going to aggregate these logs. Why do we want to do that? We don't
have enough disk space for everything. So if you think about
a stream flowing into a creek flowing into a river,
that flows into a lake, that eventually flows into a bigger river and flows
into the ocean, through that entire scenario,
you're looking at water on moss moving.
You're not looking at the drops of water in it. But as an information security
professional, especially if I'm into forensics, I'm looking
for the data points. Now, Python has been
the biggest thing in the world for security forensics,
and for analyzing log files,
taking care of everything. That is log
aggregation. That has been a python
kind of thing for the longest time. My friends that are really
into forensics and
investigative services are telling me,
they started telling me this last year, actually, that they're moving to go because they
find go to be easier to use,
quicker to learn, and you can do the same thing with
less lines of code. Now, I'm not a professional go programmer.
I could best be described as kind of an amateur. As a programmer,
I can do a little python, I can do a little go.
And from what I've seen of go, I believe that it
has the strength and the flexibility of a.
A python, that kind of thing. But I think it's also a
little easier to use for me, it's easier for me to understand.
So I'm looking at go as becoming
part of an information security professional's arsenal,
a tool that they're going to have in their toolbox. And we know that all
those things aren't enough because nothing's foolproof, okay?
Users make mistakes, vendors make mistakes. You and
I have both are all, I guess I should say,
gotten overwhelmed. And we've clicked on something that we
didn't look at closely, and we all know that what we don't see can kill
us. We can start a brute force attack accidentally.
The detecting and evading that the bad actors
do, privilege, escalation, lateral movement,
all those things we need to see. Protocol poisoning, something we
needed to watch. How do we gain insight? The AI insight
machine learning cluster, algorithms, you may have
to add staff. I like to automate where possible, because when
you automate it, the automation doesn't normally take the day off.
It doesn't have to have a vacation, doesn't have to have a
child's recital or a sick
spouse. Those are all things that happen in life.
If you're doing anything with a human, the humans that
you've got are going to have the same problems. All humans have nothing
wrong with that. Just acknowledge it and say, hey, people are just
not going to be showing up every day for work like you'd like.
And that's okay. There are people that AI inside
will give you the view you need. So if you look at the behavioral analytics
and you learn what your network traffic looks like, which to
bake it in is going to take six to nine months. And if
the salesperson says it's shorter than that, you want
to look at them. Kind of funny, because I'm seeing more AI installs
simply because we're getting a lot more sophisticated at installing
them and tuning them up out of the crate. A lot of more AI
installs are taking nine to twelve months to actually normalize.
And by that I mean to ferret out all the false positives and false
negatives and to actually be useful
for exposing intruders and seeing those individual drops of
water that are flowing around inside. So we always want to use
that. We want to make sure that we're letting it scan the networks and detect
new devices and that we're doing it in a controlled fashion.
When you first get your first AI tool, you're going to turn
on and see what's on the whole network. Well, that's the wrong answer because that'll
probably cause enough network traffic that for all intents and purposes
your average user is going to think that the network is down.
Not a good idea, let's not do that. What are your benefits?
Where are you going to keep your vulnerable systems on your radar? You're going to
watch these vulnerability notifications that are going to pop up out of these systems.
You're going to be able to assign remediation tasks. You're going to be able to
track that remediation and make vulnerability management
workable. It's got to be workable. And you decrease your
attack surface. So as we're rocking along
doing these things, we want to make sure that we're constantly assessing,
we're constantly evaluating, and that's supposedly a
representation of the old stoplight method, green, yellow and red.
Because your success as a CISO
hinges on your team's ability to monitor
the central nervous system of your organization and
make sure that they understand everything they're seeing and can report it
accurately to the senior management team and the board. So while
we're talking about that, what you do for a living as
a go programmer, as a python, programs anything in
it, unless you're talking to another IT professional,
the chances of folks really understanding what
you're doing and who you are are kind of slim
to none. So I want to encourage you to over communicate what
you feel like is over communicating. I'm not saying tell the
senior management team and the board how the watch was made. I'm saying
don't be afraid to communicate because if you don't communicate
they're going to speculate. And that is not a place you want to
be in. One of those first things that you want to do is make
sure you're taking a look at this little red box here. You want to make
sure that you're looking at your strategic planning and
your project requests and how those are coming in and how
you're doing them, because you're going to have
an IT executive board, I don't know if you call it the president's
Cabinet Technology Operations service committee,
whatever you call it, you're going to have an IT strategic advisory
committee. You're going to have committees of the
board, like the audit committee that may meet quarterly.
And you're going to have all these issues that you see here.
Every one of these issues you're going to have. When it gets down to governance,
I want to make sure that for whatever reason you can
rationalize in your head, you put strategic planning
and the project request and project prioritization
ahead of all these other things. Because if you can do that,
you can succeed as a CISO today. But you've got to be able to
understand the projects, the priority they have,
and how those priorities are going to change over time.
So to do that, you're going to have to communicate. If you're looking at
board reporting, you've got to realize that the board is 100%
responsible for the organization. In the story, the board governs
the organization, not the senior management team, but the board.
Members of the senior management team may have a seat on the board.
That happens. Some will, some won't. You're also going to make sure
that you look at your regulatory guidance. If you're in the finance industry, you're going
to make sure that your ffic regulatory requirements are met.
If you're in healthcare, you're going to look at the high trust model
and you're going to make sure that you're ticking and checking off everything on
the high trust model. You always want that tone from the
top, from the board and senior management team.
And you're going to find every industry
that has a regulatory body behind it is going to want the board to
be involved and they're going to want you to be able to prove the board's
involved. So how are we going to do that?
Well, boards today, even a small, medium size or small
to medium sized organization, may have as many as
700 to 1000 pages that they're supposed to read every
month for a board meeting. Well, now, every board that I've
ever been on, the week before the board meeting, they'll give you a board packet.
Basically they give you an iPad today and you log into a
website and the board packet is all online. You've got
800 pages online. You've got a week to read it and oh, by the way,
you've still got a day job. It's going to be tough. So you want to
make sure that you set up a frequency of reporting
so you're not inundating the board of the senior management
team. The board needs to have at least an annual report, should probably
have quarterly reports and an annual summary, at least your governance,
risk and compliance, your compliance committee, risk management committee,
technology services committee, that sort of thing. You want
to report to them every month, every time they meet. Committees of the board,
like the audit committee, may meet quarterly. You want to report to them quarterly.
And you want to make sure that you dial in
the board, the senior management and your key stakeholders when you're designing
this reporting framework so that they are up to speed on the frequency
and the content of the report so they know what to expect, that's good for
you. Surprising them, not good for you. Letting them know
what you're going to do and how to do it before you do it gives
them an opportunity to put their thumbprint around if they so choose.
Always a good idea to give senior management the board an opportunity to
dial you into what their expectations are.
Cybersecurity board reports should include a total inventory
of everything you're managing, your status when it comes
to threats, vulnerability and patch management. How that's working?
Is it working? Is something broken? The organization's risk
assessments now cybersecurity,
it does risk assessments. You should do a risk assessment
on every new piece of equipment you get, every new projects, every new
service. All these have risk assessments. And every year
you should be risk assessing everything you've got. So you're going to have
ongoing monitoring activities for everything that's going on,
and you're going to assess the risks that are in that and then any
material, upcoming contract renewals, terminations, any problems
also need to be reported up. And I always recommend that the
board report contain at least one
PowerPoint slide for each of these. Your asset security, these are your
columns, I'm sorry, these are your pillars or your
domains of information security. I guess domains is the thing I'm
looking for here. It's your domains. So make sure you give them
a little information on each one of these and make sure
that the other component you recommend, I'm sorry,
make sure that the other component I recommend is included.
And that is a word document that puts more detail into
each one of those sections. It also gives any important industry information,
any new regulatory guidance, updates on staff changes,
overall inventory of actively managed third parties, and any
cybersecurity program. Changes, particularly focusing on the
changes to high risk and critical areas of operation. You can
make sure that you're doing the right thing by finding the right framework.
Find a framework, use it. There are many to choose from.
CISO, NIST, ISO, probably where you
want to start. If you're in the US,
you're probably going to be NIST. The rest of the world, you're probably, especially in
the european theater, you're going to be ISO. Find a
framework and use it. Make sure you're assessing risks.
Risk comes in, there's really three parts to risk. There's the inherent risk
and there's the mitigating activities that are going to reduce the inherent risk,
and there's the residual risk and those risks.
You need to have an understanding of the people, processes and technology that
are going on within your organization, especially within it.
And information security. You need to be aware of. You also
need to be aware of the people, processes and technology in
every line of business. Because every line of business is
an attack surface. You need to know how the people are working, what processes
they're using, what technology they have in place, what are they doing all
day and how does it relate to securing the organization and maintaining that confidentiality,
integrity and availability triad?
You're also going to have to manage your team's talent
level and your project management capabilities.
Got to have an assessment on that. Standardization, how standard
are you? Do you have a standard desktop? Do you have a standard smart
device? I'll just say smart device. I keep wanting to
be vendor specific. If you've got a smartphone
or a smart tablet, what are your standards for setting those up?
What are your standards for setting up a workstation, a laptop?
What are your standards? How did you standardize server configuration?
And what are your quantitative management
capabilities? The quantitative management capability that you have, the ability
to measure everything you're doing and assess what you're doing based on
numbers, based on calculations, based on figures,
based on quantitative analytics is
really the Golden Circle because once you get down to that, then you
can say, we're running a little shy in this area, we need to flange
it up or, wow, we have certainly seen
an escalation in the number of bad actors moving past our firewall.
Now, to do all this, you want to make sure that you understand
the skills that you have on your team. This is a
very simple skills determination. I think it makes the point
you just take the person that you've got,
whoever the person is, the current role they're in,
the skills. Now, one person may have more than one
role, and one role may have more than one skills. So you
may have these things fanning out on you as you
go down. Then what's your current capability
and what's your ideal capability for that particular person,
for that particular job, and what's your developmental action
going to be? How are you going to bring them up to speed today?
I'm going to just go out on a limb and say this. You need to
stop looking for the unicorn employee. The unicorn employee
does not exist. It's not there. If you
find the unicorn employee, they're going to want too much money.
And then as soon as somebody comes along and offers them 20% to 25%
more than you're paying them, they're gone. Don't look for that
unicorn employee. If one drops in your lab, take them.
No doubt about it. Stop looking for the unicorn.
Start building your team. Build your own unicorns and do it
using a model like this. You can refine it, you can make it
do anything you need it to do for your organization,
but get a training plan in place to bring your team up to where they
need to be, and you may have to include it in it. The technology
groups oftentimes have to move in tandem, and you needed
to make sure that your people and the IT people have certifications.
Well, there are a few certifications out there. I didn't
list all the certifications from sans because there are
just tons of them.
CCNA, CCIE, all good certifications.
The CISSP is usually the cert.
By last figure, I saw 68%, almost 69%
of all chief information security officers hold a CISO.
So not a bad place to be. Now, remember, when we start
talking about certifications, your certifications, your team's
certifications, I want you to understand that
they're going to have to go take tests. You're going to have to take a
test. And it kind of behooves us to stop at this
point and take a look at what is
learning. Now, for those of you that have children,
especially ones that you might read a bedtime story to, the thing
you're going to notice at some point is they're going to want you to read
the same story over and over and over
and over until you're frankly sick of
the story. And then you're going to start,
the child's asleep and you're sleepy, and you're going to start going through,
and you're going to be. And you're skip a word and
your child's going to say it. Didn't say that it
says this. And even though the child can't
read, the child has the book.
Every time you reread the same book to your child,
you're building the child's iq. They're learning.
They're building mental capacity. When they
get a little older and they start playing video games, they're doing the same thing.
They're learning, they're building mental capacity in video games,
especially games that have problems to solve,
whether it's something that's civilization
building or army building. Even first
person shooter games all have the ability
to help the individuals that are playing them learn,
increase their iq, and get some serious
problem solving skills. So remember,
your employees are going to start out right where you are.
They're going to start out in that comfort zone where they feel safe. The next
zone away from comfort is fear.
You cannot learn when you're afraid, fear releases
a chemical in your body that shuts down your frontal cortex.
And I promise you, once the front part of your brain,
the frontal lobe, ceases to function normally,
and it's in that kind of fight, flight, or freeze state, you're not
learning anything. The learning zone actually
is the next zone over after fear. And the growth
zone actually happens after the learning
zone, where you know the material enough that you
can actually apply it, you can see how it works.
The best example I can give you of that is long,
long time ago for the certified novell administrator
exam. I'd been a novel administrator for
four or five years before I ever took the exam. And they had know,
hey, if you do this, we'll give you a free exam ticket. So our organization
punched the first ticket. We got a free exam. I went and took the exam,
passed it, and never really studied for it.
But then I had worked with Novell long enough
that I was not in the fear zone or
in the comfort zone or even the learning zone. You could ask me
how to do anything after working with it for five years, and I could tell
you. So I was, at that point, in a growth zone,
looking to get better. Not in the comfort zone, not in the
fear zone, and not in the learning zone.
Remember, match your
frameworks to your industry and
to your organization, and make sure that
as you're pulling up certifications and saying, it'd be great if
we had one of those, make sure that that certification fits
with the framework. Certification must fit with framework.
There are Togaf certifications, Zachmans, ISOs,
itils. Koso's got a cert,
NIST, CFS. I'm sure there's a
cert out there somewhere for it. I don't know off the top of my head
where it is, but I'll bet somebody's providing it, and you
should have a clock in your head constantly
running. I like to
justify the technology that I have on the ground that I'm currently
using every 18 months. And 18 months isn't
something that it isn't
arbitrary, is what I'm trying to say. 18 months isn't arbitrary. Moore's law
says that every 32 months, the power of the technology
that we're using doubles. So if you've got technology that's
been on the ground for 32 months or more, it's probably time
to upgrade it, because the power that
you can get in that same equipment today
is going to be at least double what it was 36 months ago.
Well, that's all great. Especially Moore's law is a little
old. Now. Today, about every 18 months,
the power of the technology doubles.
So you want to make sure that you train yourself and your teams to
justify that technology. And by that, I mean to take a look at it and
say, is there anything better out there? If you're looking at firewalls and you're
looking at the big players, the junipers, the CISos, the checkpoints,
the palo altos, you're looking at those. If you've got one,
let's say, for the sake of argument, you're a CISO. Every 18 months,
your team needed to come back and say, yeah, Cisco is still the best answer
for us, and you want to make sure that you're training every
three months. I like my technology teams to train for five days
every three months. That doesn't necessarily mean they have to go away.
They may sit at their desk or stay home or do something
that's self paced learning. But every three months,
they need to train for five days, and we need to train more than one
person to do every particular thing. The old
saying, two is one and one is none, is very
real. Make sure that you've got more than one person trained to
do everything. You need at least two firewall drivers, at least two
network security administrators, at least two forensic experts.
Now, if you have, let's say, two forensic experts,
you know that both of them aren't going to have the exact same skills.
One of them is going to be a little ahead of the other one,
and that's okay. Figure out a way to challenge them so that they
keep one up and the other one, and keep learning and keep raising the bar
for each other. Look at your framework adjustments. Frameworks get adjusted.
Gosh, about every month anymore there's a release
that says CISO or NIST is considering changing some framework
somewhere, which means that down the line that framework
is going to get adjusted. You need to track those adjustments and say,
okay, what's NISt thinking? What's CISO
thinking? Where might this go? How should
our organization react to it? And the generally available releases,
you're going to have every twelve to 18 months, a generally available
release of every piece of software you've got.
Okay, so we want
to make sure that every twelve to 18 months,
no matter what, we're looking at our GA releases.
Sometimes those are PRN. If you're in healthcare, you know that that means as
needed, we're going to look at framework adjustments and generally
available release adjustments no matter what, every twelve to 18
months. And certainly as needed, the vulnerability
assessments, you need to be doing those daily. And by that I mean
you're going to be scanning your networks. You're not going to scan the whole network
all at once. I think anybody that's been a CISO got
really happy and turned on their
vulnerability scanner, got 9 million items for every
thousand employees they had, and sit around
scratching their head going, wow, that's amazing. And then they realized
that the call log to the help center went nuts during that
time frame and they're going to be wondering why they go nuts. Well,
the bandwidth utilization to do those scans is usually a little more extreme than just
daily operations. So what you're looking at is a situation
where you can scan a network and decrease the bandwidth to the point that
the network appears to be down to the end user.
Not a good place to be. So scan small network
segments daily. Scan something every day, but make it a different segment.
Unless something gets wonky on one of your
scans and you want to redo it, scan the next segment. Keep moving,
keep those scans going and that clock is going to keep on ticking. You're going
to be doing risk assessments at least annually or
as needed. If you have a new product service or a new piece of gear,
you're going to do code reviews, DevOps and software
development or team sports. Code reviews are
a real deal. Isolated programmers
creating magic. Doesn't happen very often. Again,
those people are unicorns. Normally you're going to
want to have more than one person reviewing the code that comes out
to see if it's efficient, to make sure there's nothing missed, to make sure that
all the security parameters you can are dialed into that code.
Your patches every week. You want to make sure you don't have any
patches for anything or as needed.
That is one of those things. If we look at Spectra and meltdown,
Spectra and Meltdown come out, I'm read up on them. We made a
decision on what to do and I'm sitting around the day of the board meeting
that I'm not scheduled to be at, thinking I might want to
be ready to go to this particular board meeting. And time goes by and I
think, well, I'm going to be missing this one. Oh,
no. Still got to go to the board and say, hey,
the spectrum meltdown thing, that's a problem. What are we going to
do? And then I had to explain that, yes, it is a vulnerability.
Yes, we do have it. No, at this point in time,
nobody's weaponized that vulnerability. Yes, there is a
patch out. At that point in time, Microsoft had a patch,
but our tests have found that if we patch the servers
we have in production today, it won't
kill them, but they'll run so slow that the end user will think that they're
down. So that's not something we can do. We're going
to have to trust our perimeter security, trust our behavior
analytics, and make sure that we're watching our log aggregation
and the AI inside is tuned up and telling us what's going
on because we really don't want to patch Spectre
and meltdown right now. And I think everybody went through the same kind of
thing and they're all the people that I know in information security going,
well, you're going to have to wait for a new generation of processors before
we can do anything with it. That sort of
thing happens from time to time. And you're going to find things like the
solar winds utilization of a software
repository didn't go exactly like they thought it would.
Those kind of things are going to happen. There's just no way around it.
What you want to make sure you do is have your business continuity
management in place so that you have a place to back up, back off and
make sure that everything you're doing can be restored.
System configuration always happens pre production. You never
put a system in and produce it.
And the roadmap that you're going to have for cybersecurity for
any organization better include these nine items. Your security education,
training and awareness program. Who are your stakeholders?
Who are they? Well, senior management, the board and heads of the lines of
business and anybody else that might be a key player for
you. Watch your numbers, watch your budget numbers, your number of employees,
your burn rate. Burn rate is a term that you're going to hear
venture capitalists use. Burn rate simply means, what does it
cost to keep the doors open every day? So, for your information security
program, you should be able to tell your senior management team,
your board of directors, anybody that asks, this is our burn rate. It cisos us
this much every day or this much every month to keep information security
going. You should know that number. You should also be
able to show what the organization is getting for that number
and know your four p's or your five p's, depending on how you look at
them. Your policies, your procedures, your processes,
your projects, all those four things make up a program.
So programs, policies, procedures, processes, and projects,
you got to know them. What's your security architecture? Are you too tall?
If you're too tall. Tools. Hierarchical. You're not going to be able to shut down
segments efficiently without downing entire work
groups that you don't intend to down. You want your network to be
as flat and as horizontal as possible. So if you do have something
that happens to one network segment, oh, let's say ransomware
happens, if that happens, then you can close that segment down.
You can isolate it, you can do your forensics on it, you can
maintain your chain of custody on it, and you can handle the problem without
it affecting the rest of your network, the rest of your plant.
Make sure that your assets have been identified. Business continuity
planning, disaster recovery planning. You got to have it. You got to
understand it. You got to understand your recovery time objective, your recovery
point objective, and your maximum allowable downtime. The business
impact analysis is the tool that you should,
if you're not involved in it, you should get involved in, because the BIA,
the business impact analysis, will rank every process in the entire
organization for every line of business, and then
it'll tell the it folks, this is the most important
process. That gives them the ability to say, that process runs on that
system. So that's the most important system we've got. We need
to make sure that either doesn't go down or can come back up within our
recovery point objectives. Recovery time objectives, and certainly
within the maximum allowable downtime.
Training. Training train. I think we made
the point on training. If we haven't, give me a call. We'll talk about
it. Five areas where successful cisos excel.
Well, cisos are usually smart, but they're also emotionally smart.
They also have their emotions in check, so their IQ and their EIQ are
in line. They have the ability to communicate. They have the ability
to talk to the board of directors, the senior management team, align a business or
an audience, such as yourselves, and they
have technical kung fu instead of krav maga.
If you know anything about martial arts, you understand that kung fu
is a very elegant art form. Krav maga
is extraordinarily brutal. You really want to
strive for technical kung fu versus Krav maga?
Now, we've all thrown stuff together to get it running in the middle of the
night, and at 09:00 in the morning, you're going,
darn, we were up all night, and we've got this combo together, and we still
got 72 things we need to do to make it stable.
We've all been there, but as much as possible, work your way out of that
and get back to the elegance that, you know, your technology should have.
High performance team building. Every successful C
level, anybody, doesn't matter if it's a chief financial officer,
chief operating officer, chief information officer, chief technology officer,
chief information officer, or chief information security officer
has the ability to put high performance teams together.
If they don't, I'd suggest that the board needs to find somebody else.
The third party risk management. Got to do
it. You got to understand how to handle third party risk
today, because your vendors, vendors,
vendor could be the Achilles heel in your organization.
If you're not doing third party risk management, you're not doing it correctly. You're never
going to find that out again. What you don't see, what you
don't know, can kill you. And remember, you're always going
to be measuring, assessing and planning. You're always
going to be going through this loop. Measure it,
assess it. It's a gap assessment. And then what's the plan to close
the gap? Very simple stuff. Measure,
assess, plan, map.
The information security department, the people in it, and the organization it
serves. Sounds simple. It'll take you a little time,
but it's very insightful. It's a very insightful task or
set of tasks. Very insightful project. Let's call it what it is. It's project,
and we want to make sure that we're developing organizational
specific tools to accurately determine the capabilities
and operational readiness of the department.
My big tell on operational readiness, when we work
with clients or somebody comes to me and says, I think
I'm good to go, you want to take a walk through with me? The first
question I ask them is, well, show me your sock. Your security operations
center. They may say, well, we don't have a sock. We've got a
nox job. Isn't exactly the same
as a sock, network operating centers and security operating systems
do have overlap, not the same. A good sock should
have the ability to manipulate network segments and perform
some exhaustive forensics from the SoC. I would submit
that a network operating center doesn't have a
need to do that. Sometimes I get a
little blowback on that. But for the most part, the sea level
people that I work with really understand that you want to make sure that
you've got a security itoperations better because it's going to be doing
a set of tasks with a set of tools that are different from
what the technology folks, the it folks are doing.
And you want to make sure that you're creating the people, processes and technology roadmaps
for your entire information security department.
You're going to measure the department, the people, the organization it
serves, and you're going to assess same department,
people organization over and over again.
We're going to do this and then you're going to plan same thing for
this department, for the people, and for the organization that
you're going to create that information security plan for your entire organization.
You're looking at that team, you're looking at your information technology team.
You're looking at your third parties. You're assessing them.
You're making sure that they understand that you're going
to plan the work and work the plan that you've got a strategic plan and
you've got some tactical plans. You need to share those.
That's where your competition or speculation comes in. What is your strategy?
What are your tactics? That should not be something that's
a secret. If it's a secret with a closely held group, well,
it's not a plan. Plans are something you can lay out on the table and
show everybody, this is where we're going, this is how we're doing it.
This is what it looks like. Please feel free to come on down,
do whatever you want, and you're going to measure your progress against your plan.
Plans have to have a timeline on them. And as Elon Musk
said, if you allow a project to take a month, it'll take a month.
If you allow it to take a week, it'll take a week. Same project.
He's right. You've got to measure your progress, put a timeline on it that's
realistic and measure the progress against it.
Demonstrate your program's effectiveness,
demonstrate the process effectiveness that you have within
your program and demonstrate the level of security that you have
to your senior management team, the heads of the lines of business and your board
of directors. And make sure that you constantly,
constantly, constantly are measuring, assessing, and planning your industry,
your organization's lifecycle position within the industry.
You're always looking at the industry expanding or contracting.
When you're looking at those things, see if there are ways that you can
actually help your company disrupt the industry.
You're always looking for that disruption potential. Make sure that you have critical
infrastructure designations in your
mind. The Homeland Security Department has 17 or 18
critical infrastructure designations. If you're one of those,
there's a lot of help out there for you. If you're in the finance industry,
defense, industrial complex, healthcare, communications, that sort
of thing, they being the Department of Homeland Security and
the whole federal government, have a lot of resources. And make
sure that you don't have too much culture shock for you or any new
people you bring on. If you're looking at that operational readiness,
we want to make sure that we absolutely, positively, as we
talked about, looked at that BIA, RPO, RTO and
maximum allowable downtime. And in the
business impact analysis, everybody can't be number one. You've got to
define that criticality which comes from the tone
from the top. And you want to make sure that you also have disaster
recovery, pandemic planning and incident response in your
business continuity management plan. And you want to make sure that
you understand disaster recovery only recovers three
things. We recover people, facilities, and systems. We recover
them in that order. And the reason we do it is because if we don't
have people, we don't need facilities. If we don't have people or facilities,
we certainly don't need systems. So we recover the people, put them
in facilities or send them home. Home is a facility,
and we make sure they've got the systems they need. And we're going to assess
risk. We're going to look for the context that a risk
has. We're going to identify it, analyze it, and then we're going to look at
handling it. We're going to accept it, mitigate it, transfer it, avoid it or exploit
it. And risk analysis is really simple. You should have a risk appetite
statement. If you don't, the thing I would encourage you to do is simply ask
your chief financial officer what's a material loss.
Now, I've done that before, and when I'd asked the first time,
the CFO would say 25,000,
I'd ask him five years later and he's 300,000. So the risk appetite
of the organization moves. The risk appetite of the organization
in different areas also moves. But you're always always going
to be looking at the threat times, the vulnerability times, the consequences,
gives you your inherent risk. Your inherent risk minus
your risk mitigation is going to give you a residual risk and you're going to
be doing things that look like this. That's the same inherent
risk you just calculated it. It moves to the next equation
and you're going to put simple things together like this.
The earthquakes in Oklahoma is something that we lived through prior
to the early OS. We may have had one or
two earthquakes every year or two,
maybe in 2009, we had almost
1000 earthquakes in Oklahoma. Virtually every
square mile of Oklahoma had an earthquake in it.
So while the probability pre 2009
was close to one, it wasn't zero, but it was close to one.
The probability during 2009 was close to 100%.
So those risks are going to change and you're going to be doing risk assessments
that are going to look like this. And of course this
is online for you to go back and look at later and you're going to
expand them that look like this. And these
are the risk assessments that you need to be doing. And you need to be
aware of change management and how
change management differs from the Internet of things all the way through the
SDLC. DevOps has a change management
style that's different. Agile has a change management style
that's different. You need to understand those and adapt to them.
Now, how do you adapt since
we really have no logical alternative? Well,
you look at your hard skills and your soft skills, you look at your comfort
zone, and then you always surround yourself with smarter people. They're going
to help you figure out alternatives, logical alternatives,
alternatives that will work in your environment. And that's really what you want.
You want to make sure that you can do exactly
what you're planning. You want to be able to measure your skills with a skill
matrix, your EIQ, you can use a Myers Briggs,
you can use a disk assessment, you can use true colors, any of
those. Don't just do it for you, do it for your entire team.
It will help you put together a better team. Look at your risk
appetite, look at your obsolescence. What is
your end of life looking like for every piece of equipment you've got?
Your team's composition, what are their hard skills, what are their soft skills?
Where do they need help? Where do they need to be trained up?
Be willing to invest in your team, get them
certifications, get them more than one. There's always same
certification slide, always a way to do it, always a way to make
it happen, even if it's lunch and learns. And remember, not everybody can
get all the way over to the growth zone. A lot of people are stuck
in comfort. They hit that fear zone when we start talking about certs.
To get them over it, you've got to get them through the learning zone,
and that's repetition, repetition, repetition,
repetition. And let's have a few final thoughts here, since we're
running a little long. I always like to make sure that the wire
is done right up front, that your network infrastructure is perfect.
And for my money, you cannot have too much memory spinning disks.
Why, they're a little archaic anymore.
It costs a little more to get some SSD, but I'm going to submit
that it's kind of the way to go. I've had a lot of
good luck with it over the last five years. Some of the early fits and
starts seem to have worked out, so I don't really have a problem with it.
Asset management, you got to know what's on the wire. When the wire's working,
you got to know what's on it. Make sure you know what's on your wire.
Personnel people can be your best asset,
so take care of them. And the CISO
has released its best practices to save you from being
disrupted by ransomware. Filtering network traffic to
prohibit ingress and egress communications with known malicious ip
addresses. Very important strong spam filters.
Phishing. A set of programs. Security education, training and awareness.
Extremely important. Implementing robust network
segmentation between information technology and the operational
technology networks is critical. Regularly testing manual
controls. If it's manual, you got to test it at least every week and
ensuring that backups are implemented and regularly tested. Backups should
be tested every day. You don't have a good backup unless you've tested it isolated
from your network connections. Oh my gosh,
let's get our backups off of our network connections.
You got to do that or you end up backing up the
cryptography that's encrypting your network with ransomware.
So when you go to restore, you're just restoring a bad situation.
Don't want to do that. And again, please don't hesitate
to connect with me on social media. Send me feedback
on what you thought about the program. And please
have a good day. Make sure that you're doing
everything you can to stay secure. If you want to be a chief
information security officer, that you keep a career
map in your mind and go ahead and write it out, plan it
out, map it out for you so you can be
a world class CISO. That's all I have for you today.
Thank you for your time and attention. I look forward to
hearing from you in the near future.