Hi all and welcome to this presentation regarding managing
secrets with confidence. A comprehensive guide to using Hashicorp vault in
Kubernetes clusters let me introduce myself. I'm Alain Lompo.
I'm a senior software developer. I'm a DevOps and I'm security consultant in
the public sector. I've been working with software development technologies
for 20 years now. I've been doing also training and consulting.
Let's see our agenda. First we'll be talking about handling
sensitive resources in Kubernetes. Then I will introduce briefly
Hashicorp vault and after that we'll deep dive into its architecture
before seeing how we can integrate vault with Kubernetes.
And then we'll see some real world scenarios. After that I will do some demos
and we'll wrap it up. First, let's talk about handling
sensitive resources. When it comes to handling sensitive resources in
Kubernetes clusters, there are a few questions we need to ask ourselves.
First, what are we to store and then what
tools are available to do that? How are the assets stored
and how do the application access the stored assets?
In terms of types of sensitive resources, we can talk about credentials
such as password API keys,
certificates such as TLS and GPG keys,
or also application configurations such as runtime arguments.
Of course, depending on our application, there may be many
more various data that
are considered sensitive in our particular context.
Regarding storing sensitive information, we should ask
ourselves what are the available secret management storage solutions?
How is sensitive asset intended to be used, what application framework
is being used and what are the options for injecting external
configurations? When it comes to kubernetes, the natural default
is to think of using Kubernetes secrets resource since it's
included in every Kubernetes distribution,
but it provide only some form of protection since
the values are not encrypted, but instead they are simply base 64
encoded, which means that anybody that can access them can also decode
them. To create a Kubernetes secret resource in
a Kubernetes cluster I can use a manifest like the following and
use a tool like Kubectl to create it into
my cluster. Now let's introduce Hashicorp Vault.
Hashicorp Vault is one of the solutions out there for managing
sensitive information. It's one
of my favorite for various reasons. First, Hashicorp Vault
is a very popular open source platform that helps
us manage secret it helps us store these secrets, centralize its
access control, as well as ensure compliance with various other
security standards. In terms of its
high level features, I can say that it simplifies secret
management. It helps protect sensitive data. We can integrate it with various
cloud and infrastructure platforms. It provides also a unified
and secure solution for secret management. Now let's see.
Hashicorp Vault architecture this
present slide shows the main component of
Hashicorp vault, and we'll first talk about the encryption
layer called the barrier. When Hashicorp vault start,
it tries to write to the storage backend, but since the
storage backend is outside the barrier, it is considered untrusted.
Therefore, the data must
first be encrypted before being written to the storage backend,
so that even if the storage backend is compromised,
the hacker may not be able to use
these compromised data, since they will remain encrypted until
vault itself decrypt them at the start.
Vault find itself in a sealed set and it must be unsealed before any operation
can be performed on it. Unsealing vault is done by
providing the unsealed keys.
At initialization, Vault generates an encryption key. It's used to protect
all vault data,
and the encryption key itself is protected by a root key that is
stored alongside all the other vault data. But it's encrypted
itself by another mechanism called the unsealed key.
This unsealed key is handled using Xiaomi's secret sharing algorithm,
in which the unsealed key is splitted in a certain number of
shards, among which there's a required amount of this shard
that are needed in order to reconstruct the unsealed key
and use it to decrypt the root key. Once that
is done and vaults retrieve the encryption key, it secrets the
data in the storage backend. It enters then in an
unsilled state, and once it's in the unsealed state,
it can load the configured audit device authentication method
and secret engines. Let's see then how to
secure the audit device. The authentication method, and the secret engines.
They are all sensitive components.
They are stored in vaults, and that means they are protected by ACL,
and any change to them will be tracked by audit logs,
and only users with permission can modify them.
Now, let's talk about the role of the core component
of hashicorp vaults. Among others,
it process the traffic between
the API and the other component of the system,
but it's also enforced access control list, and it ensures
audit logging is done. In terms of authentication mechanism,
vaults is very flexible and present
various authentication mechanisms such as using
login and password, using GitHub, using app role,
using LDAP, et cetera. Vault use policies in
order to grant access to protected sensitive
information, and these policies
actually are simply named access control list rules.
For example, we have the root policy, that's a built in policy, and it
permit access to all resources. We can create any number of policies,
and it allows us a fine grained control over the
various paths that we are trying to protect. Vault operates also in
an allowed access mode, which means that any access to
a specific path will be denied unless there's an
explicit policy granting the required access.
Client tokens are the default and preferred mechanism for
authentication used by Vault, and once a request
has been authenticated, client token
will be generated and it will be associated with
it. Also a list of policies, as well as the user identity,
through which the user can then in his
subsequent request, access the
sensitive information he would like to retrieve.
Therefore, the client token is used for making future requests
in an approach similar to the authentication
cookies used in web application.
But client token may also have an associate lease,
which means that they may need to be renewed
periodically to avoid invalidation. Talking a bit
about the request authorization flow,
the authentication request will be made by providing the client token,
and the client token will be used to verify that client.
That way, it can be ensured that the request is authorized and
the associate policies will be used to
authorize the client request. Now let's talk about the
secret engine. The secret engine is a very flexible component
of hashicorp vault. It's used to store and to
encrypt sensitive data.
In terms of its function. It receives a set of data, it will process
them, and it will return a certain result.
It can cover various tasks,
but at its core it will be used to return the secrets.
And once it returns a secret, the core will register it
with the expiration manager. It may attach a lease id
to it, and the client will use this lease id to renew or revoke
their secrets. If the client ever allowed that lease
to expire, the expiration manager will automatically
revoke that secret. Let's see now.
The audit broker and the audit devices.
We talk about them in relationship with the core because the
core will log the request and response to the audit broker, and thus
they will be distributed to the various configured audit devices.
In terms of other vaults activities outside
of the request flow that we have seen, the core performs
specific background activities such as list management,
but it also handles specific partial failure case by using
writehead logging with a rollback manager. But this is something
completely transparent to the user. It's done within the core. Now let's
talk about various aspects of integrating vault
with Kubernetes and first, why is it important to
consider that first, because containers are ephemeral,
they are not the best place to store and manage their own secrets.
Vault provide the possibility to centralize the secret
management. It offers access control
and auditing and it offers also integration with other tools.
And there are various approaches to integrating vault, each one with their
own benefits and limitation. Globally speaking,
when I consider using vaults to secure sensitive
information, I'm considering
a use case where a
given application can provide access to sensitive information to
its users. But first, this sensitive information should
be stored by the security team or other privileged user
in Hashicorp vaults and then when the user make a
request to the sensitive information, his credentials,
his claims might be verified, the application will
access Hashicorp vault and request to receive the secrets presenting
the claims of the credentials of this user. Once they are verified,
the application will be granted the access and the user can
access the sensitive information he was looking for.
In terms of integration of Hashicorp vault with Kubernetes Hashicorp
Vault can also function as a KMS key management server
through the help of an adapter that presents itself as a Hashicorp vaults
KMS plugin for Kubernetes. Other than that,
one of the common ways to using Hashicorp vault
to inject secret into pod is through the
Hashicorp vault agent injector that
will be used to mutate an existing
Kubernetes pod and inject into it
a sidecar container that will be responsible
for handling access to the secrets from Hashicorp
fault. This is very interesting because this allows for
example a legacy application to be able
to have its secret management
handled by Hashicorp vault even without being aware of Hashicorp vault
itself. Now let's talk a bit about Kubernetes authentication
backend. They are used to enable pod and service to authenticate
with vault and so to be able to
obtain secret dynamically after their authorization
have been verified and in this case a
token will be returned upon success.
This following slide presents a bit what type of command
I could use as security manager
to enable authentication Kubernetes authentication
with Hashicorp vaults as well as to configure
its endpoint. Among the benefit of using Kubernetes
authentication backend,
there will be no more need for manual token distribution among
ports as well as manual token management.
I could access a tight control of access based
on ports, identity and permission and I have a seamless integration
with Kubernetes. It is also possible to confidence
automatic token renewal and I can manage
my secrets in a secure and scalable fashion in a Kubernetes
environment. Now let's talk about using custom resource
definition, which is one of the important aspect.
Also related to integrating Hashicorp vault with Kubernetes.
Custom resource definition are a way to specify additional
resources into the Kubernetes API so
that I can use these additional resources
along with classic resource used in standard Kubernetes API.
Not only can I create new custom resources, but I can
also modify them and in this case through the
operator it will detect the change event and
will adjust the current state. Otherwise in case
of conflicts it will launch
a reconciliation process. This is an example of
custom resource definition that may look a bit
more complicated, but based on simple things like
managing my server and archiving
these actions, the benefits of using custom resource definition
is simply that they are native Kubernetes integration.
They are configured declaratively, they offer
scalability as well as extensibility. All right,
now let's see a bit of world scenarios that we could
use with Hashicorp vaults. We actually
have a lot of possible scenarios. I just
selected a few that are relevant to what
I'm doing currently. One of them will be storing
application secrets. Another could be integrating
with Kubernetes service accounts so as to grant
this service account dynamic
configured access to sensitive resources.
Another scenario would be centralizing secret
management through a centralized secret store
that could be used with various teams without
any interference and without any risk of secrets
leaking. Another option will be to implement role based
access control for Kubernetes secrets. Other than that,
I can provide secrets to legacy app using Hashicorp vault and
vault agent injector approach with sidecar containers.
Or I could use Hashicorp vaults to manage SSI key
for Kubernetes clusters as well as integrating with
other security and compliance tools. Now let's see
a simple demo of injecting secrets into a
pod with hashicorp vault. So because
the steps of my demos are
a bit extensive, I have simply created
slide of the demos instead of doing everything manually.
So the first step of this demo will be to enable
a secret engine on my Hashicorp vault server. I could do it with
the following command vault secrets
enable and I give a pass. Everything is a pass with hashicorp vaults.
In this case my pass is internal and the
secret engine is Kvv
two. And in case of success I have a message
that looks like the following. Next I would create a secrets
at a specific path and here I can see that I'm using
vault kv put and I give the path to my
secret and since it's a key value secret engine
I can then give the various keys and the values.
In this case the first key is username, the value db
read only username. The second key is password and the value is
db secret password once I have created the secret
I can verify that the secret has been effectively created
using vault kv get and I give the
pod and it will give me various information
but at the end I will see the
state of my keys and values and I could
verify that both the username and the password has
been effectively created to confidence
kubernetes authentication I have similar commands
vault enable kubernetes to enable using Kubernetes
authentication and then I could use vault write
give it part to the configuration where I could configure
the Kubernetes host. Once I've done that I
need to create a policy that
will grant certain number of capabilities.
In this case I just need read capabilities to be able to read the
secret at the specified part so it will
look like what we see in this slide.
Vault policy write then I specify
the name of the policy that I want to
write inside I have which pad should
be the target of this policy and which capabilities I'm
giving. In this case only the read capability.
After I've done that I will create a Kubernetes authentication role
and I define the role using odd Kubernetes
role internal app pad and
what's important in the role is as we can see what
I have highlighted here to which service account
it is bound. The service account is called internal
app and to which namespace we'll be using the
default namespace and then which policies
are associated with this role. The internal policy
that we created. Internal app policy that we created before.
Now what I need to do is to create the corresponding service account defined
here as internal app. So I could
use Kubectl to create that service
account and once this is done I could
test it on a simple application like what we see right here,
my demo app. And what we could notice with this demo app
is I'm using a service account name the
service account given before internal app.
So I can see now that I have created the demo app,
its container is running alongside the
other vault containers, the vault server here
with name vault zero and the agent injector.
Now let's inject secrets into the
pod. To do that I will patch my
previous deployment using this
new manifest. And all we can see here
is that by in dispatching I'm simply adding
a bunch of annotations that are all prefixed with hashicorp.com
and then I have various properties associated with this
prefix agent injects through which role I'm
using internal app and then I give the part to
the secret. I use Kubectl
patch to patch my previous deployment with this
new manifest and then I can verify that the
secret can now be accessed. All right,
last but not least,
Hashicorp vault can also be used in the context
of CI CD pipelines.
And as you can see here, it's used in combination with various other tools
such as GiT,
as well as sealed secrets and Argo CD
that are used generally in
the GitHub's approach or in CI CD pipelines.
In this case, all we are trying
to do is use
seal secrets tool to encrypt the
secrets before storing them in my repositories.
And once these changes are done to the repositories,
Argo CD will be able to detect the change and trigger the pipelines.
And we can see that one step here is doing is it applies
and decrypt the secrets. And then the secrets will be stored
in vault and then they will be consumed over half the tp and
they will be injected with CSI driver into the port
so that at the end the port can receive
the secrets in an automated fashion to
wrap it up. I would say Hashicorp vaults is really a very interesting
secret management platform
for handling sensitive secret for kubernetes,
not only for Kubernetes but as well as for other platform.
It integrates very well with various
platforms, it integrates very well with kubernetes.
It allows us to
perform secret management for various scenarios, not only what we have seen in
this presentation, but many more use cases such as database
credentials or certificate management and many more.
So I will simply say I really enjoy using this
platform and I will encourage you to try it and
then thank you very much.