Everyone, welcome to my session. First I want to
thank comfort. Amazing this conference. Now let's
talk about the carbon emission of your cloud infrastructure.
I'm Olivier Biale. I'm usually software engineer at elastic
in the reducing team, but I'm taking a break to work on
Carbonifer. Carbonifer is a platform for managing,
measuring and reducing the Carbonifer emissions of your cloud.
Here is a sentence I hear quite often. I have all my infrastructure in
the cloud, so I do not emit co2. Yes, we all know that
whatever you put in the cloud disappear. It's just magic. It doesn't have physical
existence. But still we know that it's running on
servers and data centers and those are powered by electricity.
But electricity is clean, right? No, not really.
So let's talk about electricity. First let's look at some
numbers. We considered that data centers are responsible
of 20% to 25% of the electricity used by the digital
sector, which is one 3% of the total electricity used
worldwide. And if we look at some projection,
we considered that by 2030 the
digital sector is going to be responsible of 20% of the
worldwide electricity demand and amongst that
the data centers are going to be responsible.
Third, if we talk in term of greenhouse
gas emissions, we consider that the cloud is emitting more
than 300 megatons of co2 yearly, which is around the
same carbon footprint as countries like France
or UK. We have recently overthrown
the civil aviation. Basically the cloud is emitting more co2
than flights and these numbers can
be around 8% by 2038%.
That's huge and that's concerning as human being, but it's
also concerning as company. Why? Because there is
some regulation and lows that care coming.
Looking at the carbon footprint of a company is
also a great way for attracting SG funds.
Those funds are investing money in companies that are
showing some sustainability and obviously as
a company you want to attract them. It's also a great tool for
recruitment and staff retention. You care more keen to join a company if
it's showing some ethics and
sustainability. And there are some studies that are showing that it's
also great for customer retention for the same reason.
And that could also lead to some cost reductions.
So in order to know what the company is responsible
of very three scopes. The first scope is
your direct emission. So basically if you are burning fuel or if
you have diesel generator for
example, in scope two is your indirect emission
related to purchase of energy. So basically that's your electricity
bill. Scop. Three is basically everything else. Other indirect emission,
value chain emission. So it's basically your
business travel purchase of servers, and even the
purchase of cloud services or your subscription to
a cloud provider. So basically, if you
are running your infrastructure on a private cloud, that means
the electricity used by this private cloud is going to be accounted in
your scope two, but the purchase of those
servers is going to be accounted in the scope three. If you are running only
on public cloud, that means everything is going to be
accounted as the scope three. So what should
we put in the scope three? For example,
Mozilla had a very wide definition of the scope
three in their sustainability report in 2019.
They counted the use of their product
and they discovered that 98% of their
carbon footprint is coming from the usage of their
product. Basically people using firefox.
And there is even some people that are thinking
of counting as the scope three. Even things
like Spotify, for example. If you
need to have music streaming while you are working, while you are coding,
should we account that as the scope three of your company?
Because you need it. So you have emitted co2 for your work at
your company. So where should we stop? So basically, companies are
responsible of defining the parameter of their scope three.
In term of regulations, there are some directive and
laws coming in the next years. For example, in Europe,
you have the CSRD. CSRD stands for corporate sustainability
reporting directive. It's going to be enforced in 2024
for large companies and in two years for listed SMEs, it's going
to be for scope one and two and even scope three. The SFDR
is for financial companies, so they will need to
account as their scope three, the carbon
footprint of the company. They are financing. They are financing.
And in us you have the SEC climate
disclosure rule which is encompassing scope one and two,
and even scope three as optional. And it's going to be enforced
pretty soon. So here are some terms
you probably have heard. If we are talking about co2
offsetting, that mean we are doing some compensation
or removal. Removal is basically direct air capture,
removing co2 from the atmosphere.
Compensation is giving money to some project which
is helping offsetting co2,
basically planting trees. If we are talking about elimination,
that obviously mean we are not emitting co2. We are eliminating
the source of co2. So if a company is talking
about being carbon neutral, that means they are not necessarily
looking at their emissions but just focusing on offsetting.
So they are emitting the same and they are
just compensating or neutralize all
their emission by again planting trees.
If we are talking about net being net zero, that means
we are focusing on elimination. We are reducing
the co2 that we are emitting and we are
offsetting the rest. If a company is talking
about 100% being renewable, that means they
are using only renewable electricity.
But is it powered by or matched by powered by. That means
you are sure that the electricity coming in the data centers
are coming from renewable energy source if it's match
by that means. For example, if they are producing twice their
need with solar panel, but during
the night they still need to buy electricity on the market. So in that case
it's match buy, it's a little bit less interesting.
So now how we can measure your cloud infrastructure
and the carbon footprint of your cloud infrastructure. So how it's working.
Electricity is produced different ways. For example, coal or
gas plants, nuclear plants for example.
Side note, in this presentation,
nuclear is considered as clean energy because it doesn't emit
any co2. It could be also produced by renewable energy,
solar panel, windmills and hydroelectricity.
So all of this
generator of electricity is mixed in what we call an energy
mix. And this electricity is translating over
your regional grids. And when it entered the data center, a little
bit of this electricity is taken for powering
the administrative building, the air conditioning, the heating,
et cetera, et cetera. But the large majority of the electricity is for
the servers. So if you have a cloud infrastructure on
a public cloud provider, that mean you will have VMS,
containers, applications running on those
servers and you can take a ratio of the
electricity powering this data center
for your own component for your needs.
So in order to calculate that, the Green software foundation
came up with this Sci formula. SCi stands for
software carbon intensity. So the idea with
that is to calculate how many gram of co, 2 /hour
your software is going to emit.
So let's look at the end of the formula.
What is the m here? It's called embodied emissions.
So, embodied emissions is emission generating during
the manufacture, the delivery and the disposal of
your hardware. So for example, if you bought a server and
this server required 4000
be manufactured, that means virtually every year you
will emit 1000 kilogram of co2.
So you can do the math for knowing the ratio
per month, per hour per process, et cetera, et cetera.
The usage emissions are the emissions during the
use of your software. So for example,
if you are running AWS, m four large
machine with two cpu and 8gb of ram during
50%, with 50% use by your
process, there is some ways to calculate that it's going to
use ten watts during an hour. So there's different ways
to calculate that. The easiest way is to use some probes,
but if you are running on the public cloud, you don't have access to the
hardware. So in that case there is some different ways to calculate that. So let's
assume it's ten watt during an hour. We multiply
that by the power usage effectiveness. The power usage effectiveness,
the pue is how many kilowatt hour I
need to inject in the data center in order to have 1.
So in AWS Ireland, we consider the PuE is one
two, which means we need one two kilowatt hour in order to
have 1 usable by the servers.
We multiply that by the carbon intensity of the grid.
For example, in Ireland we consider that the kilowatt hour generated
300 grams of co2 during
an hour. So that means that the energy mix the different ways
to generate electricity. In Ireland, the average during
a year is going to emit 300 grams of co 2.
So if you multiply all of that, we have the greenhouse house
emission in grams of co2 equivalent per
hour. So we are talking in gram of co2 equivalent because not
only co2 are emitted when we care generating electricity,
that could also be methane ch four. The methane
is 84 times more potent as greenhouse gas as
the co2. So in order to ease calculation, we care talking
of gram of co2 equivalent.
So if we circle back to the sci formula,
if we multiply e by I, which is the
emissions of the use, we have three eight gram of co 2,
then we take the ratio of the embodied emission, basically the manufacturer
of this hardware. And in this calculation is when the
two gram of co 2
is now five gram of co 2 /hour so
where should we find this data? All those average
carbon intensity of regional grid care, really well known.
It's pretty easy to find. And you even have this
application name electricitymaps.com.
With this application you can browse a map where you can
click on some countries and have live carbon intensity of
the regional grids. In this example, in March 22 in
France it was emitting 157 grams
of co 2, while in US
in New York region, it was emitting 100
grams of co2 more than France.
PUE is also pretty easily
available data. So for example, we have
all major cloud provider pv per data centers
there are data that are less available. For example,
the CPU memory and the storage,
the energy consumed by this hardware. For example,
if you are running on the public cloud, it's really difficult for you to have
access on the name of the CPU,
the brand of the GPU, the type of memory, et cetera,
et cetera. And you need to have that in order to calculate what
the power needed by those, and you need to have their
power profile, et cetera, et cetera. So in order
to ease that, we are using estimation and coefficient.
So with estimation it's sometimes sufficient to have
rough number and to have some relative
calculations. But you need to be careful. For example,
if you are using gravitron instance on AWS with ARM CPU,
ARM CPU are really efficient in term of energy. It can be lower
than 1, while legacy
cpus could climb up to eight. So you need to be careful
with those estimations. The embodied emission of the
hardware, again, the emissions generated
during the manufacture of this hardware, to know that, you need to know what
is the brand of hardware, where it has been produced and
when. And this data is pretty impossible to get if
you look at your AWS or GCP console.
But fortunately we have some data sets around and some
benchmarks and the energy
mix is pretty difficult to predict. Obviously,
to know what was the electricity mix in the past
and to have the carbon intensity of
some regions in the past is pretty easy to have. But in
the future, in one, two, three weeks, one month, it's pretty impossible to
guess. In order to ease that,
fortunately, we have some tools. So major cloud providers
like AWS, JCP or Microsoft Azure have
released a carbon footprint tool, dashboard or calculator.
With that, with one click, you can have the carbon footprint of your
infrastructure per month and per account.
If you want to dive in a little bit more, you have tools like
cloud carbon footprint. It's an open source tool and basically
reads the bill of your cloud provider and get how many instances,
what type of instances, during for how long, what kind of serverless
services you use, like lambda or
anything else. And it gives you those
co2 emissions per day. And you can even do some nice
comparison, for example, knowing how
many flights from New York to London. It is similar.
And yeah, you have a lot of nice things in this dashboard.
If you want to be more accurate, you can use tools like Scaffondra.
So basically Scaffonder is monitoring cpu power,
so it's using some probes to get what the actual
electricity is used by your cpu. So obviously you will not
be able to use that on the cloud. But if you have access to your
physical machines, that's pretty interesting. It's not directly
telling you the Carbonifer emissions, but you have
the most complicated part, which is knowing the
electricity used by your software.
You have some interesting APIs like climatic. Climatic is a commercial API
not only for the cloud also for different sectors like freight or agriculture
or anything, you name it. And among that they have cloud computing.
So basically you can query this API asking them hey,
I have an instance running on AWS for
this time and it's going to give you what is the
Carbonifer emissions of that. You can
also use tools made by Boa Vista.
So those are free open source tool and you have the Boa
vista API. Same thing you can query. I have a
machine running on AWS M four large during 1 hour
and it kind of give you what is the co2 emitted during
the use of this instance
and it will give you the manufacturing emission, the embodied
emission for the entire lifespan.
And finally my little tool
named Carbonifer. So basically Carbonifer is able to
read terraform projects. So if you don't know terraform, terraform is an infrastructure
as code tool. So as a code you will describe what is
the infrastructure we want to have deployed, for example on JCP.
So in this example you have an e two standard, two instance.
You want to deploy it in Europe west nine and
if you run terraform plan and terraform
apply, sorry, it will deploy it on GCP in
the region you pick and that's what terraform is.
So Carbonifer is pretty similar, but instead of deploying
it will read your terraform project and try to estimate
the carbon emissions.
Basically it's reading your terraform
infrastructure as code files and
try to make some estimations. Obviously those estimations will
not be accurate, it's just rough estimation. But it's
already a good way to make some comparison and take some decisions
there. Care some tools in this awesome list powered by the
Green Software foundation strongly encourage you to check those
out. So now we know how to measure your cloud
infrastructure, how we can reduce it. Obviously if you are
running a poorly designed, not optimized code on your infrastructure,
the only way you will get the performance
you want is by increasing the size of the machine.
So obviously you need to optimize your code and use some
eco design. Good practice for your software once you have
done that, very good practice is to choose
the right instance type and the right generation
of cpu. For example, you can use
gravitron instance on AWS and choose exactly the size
you want. You not necessarily need to overcome it.
And obviously a nice way to lower
your carbon emission is to move to hyperscaler. So all
major hyperscalers, public cloud like
AWS, GCP and Microsoft Azure are
claiming to be net zero or even carbon negative by 2030.
They are making a lot of improvement on their pue,
on the lifespan of their hardware and buying
more and more renewable energy.
One thing which could be also interesting is looking at
alternative cloud providers. For example,
Denver in France is deploying
some floating data centers. So basically they're going to
be naturally cooled down by the stream. So those are
really interesting to check. So basically if you have all
your servers on premises, you tend to have numerous
underused servers just in case you will have a search
of traffic. If you are in the cloud, you can adjust it to the bare
minimum and have fewer highly used server which leads to
using less resources and then emitting
less co2. So basically you
would like to use some finops good
practices in order to be greenups basically. So FinOps
is a way for better controlling
the cost of your infrastructure. For example, if you are bringing
some automation to shut down instances
during the night or adjusting the number of instance to your
traffic, which is called auto scaling group, in that
case you will pay only what you need and not more.
And in that case you're using less resource and again you are emitting
less co2. Be careful with the reserved instance.
With the reserve instance you're going to save a lot of money, but it's going
to be still the same amount of instance.
So in that case you will still emit a
lot of co2.
Obviously you need to pick the region which is having
the best carbon intensity. So in this
example, it's on Google
platform website. You have the different regions
in Europe, and as you can see, that could be as
low as Paris with 70 grams of
co 2, up to more than
700 in Europe Central two.
So you need to pick the region very carefully.
And then if you want to be more fancy, you can move to
carbon aware. So Carbonifer aware is the ability of
a software or an infrastructure to know its own
emissions and to adjust itself according
to its own emissions. So the first things you can
do is temporary shifting. So basically temperate shifting
is scheduling asynchronous tasks when
the electricity is going to be less carbon
intensive. For example, video processing, AI training,
machine learning, et cetera. So if you want to train your AI
model, you don't necessarily need to
do it right now. You can wait for the electricity to be
less carbon intensive. That's exactly
what they are doing at Google for their
own need. So basically they care, waiting for the right
time frame to launch some synchronous tasks.
And doing that, they lowered a lot their carbon footprint.
Another thing you can do is demand shaping. So basically demand
shaping is doing more when electricity is emitting
less, for example, lowering the quality of the video when the
electricity is very carbon intensive and go back to high definition
when the electricity is less carbon intensive.
Another good example is a CI server, adding more
or less worker to the CI server depending on the
carbonifer intensity of electricity. So basically, if it's
a peak of co2, during a peak of co2,
your developer are going to wait a little bit more for having their
pr built and it's going to go back to normal when
the electricity is going to be greener.
Another good way is special shifting. So basically special
shifting is moving your infrastructure alongside with the carbon
emissions of local grid. Or if you have
two different data centers, picking the one with
the greenest energy mix. So for example,
in odd carbon 23 conference raised
some people that are shown, sorry that they are doing that with
two different data centers in two different regions.
So they have a load balancer directing the request from the
user to the data center, which is the closest to the user,
and then they change it to take into account also the carbonifer intensity
of those region where those data centers are.
And by doing so, they managed to reduce their carbon footprint
by 21%, which is already great without
any compromise on the latency and with an acceptable
latency, which means that the user will barely notice it, they managed to
reduce their carbon footprint by 51%.
So this is super interesting.
So as a conclusion, if you want to be the
less carbon intensive and to have
a greener cloud infrastructure,
the first thing you need to do is collecting metrics. You cannot
reduce what you cannot measure. So first measure it.
Then once you have your metrics of your cpu, ram, et cetera,
you can estimate the power used by those. And then
you can even estimate the carbon emissions in term of gram of co
2 /hour once you have that, you can use some tools,
some dashboards, some analytics to make
some thinking and correlation and come up with
actions reductions, resizing and scheduling
according to the intensity of the grid.
And then if you can go cardboard aware.
That's all for me. Thank you very much for listening. If you
want to know more, you can send me messages, but you
can also check the Green Software foundation website. They care very good material
on this topic. You can listen to their podcast and I strongly
encourage you to also check boavista.org to
have a lot of good documentation and
tools for helping you on that journey. Thank you very much.