Hello everyone, my name is Dmitrii Ivashchenko and I'm a software engineer
at Mygames and this talk. We'll look at these
differences between WebGL and soon to
be released Web GPU and learn how to prepare your projects
for this transition. Let's begin by exploring the timeline
of WebGL and WebGPU, as well as the current state of
the WebGPU. WebGL, similar to other technologies,
has a history that dates back to the past. These desktop
version of OpenGL debuted way back in 1990.
These in 2011, WebgL 10
was released as the first stable version of WebGL.
It was based on OpenGlas 20,
which was introduced in 2007.
This release allowed web developers to incorporate
videographics into web browsers without requiring
any extra plugins. In 2017,
a new version of WebGL was introduced called
WebGL 20. This version was released
six years after the initial version and was based on Openjlas
30, which was released in 2012.
WebGL 20 came with several improvements and new features,
making it even more capable of producing powerful treaty graphics on
the web. Lately, there has been a growing
interest in new graphics API that
offer developers more control and flexibility,
and three notable APIs. Here are Vulcan,
direct, these to twelve, and Metal.
Together, these three APIs create a foundation
for Web GPU. Vulcan, developed by the Kronos
Group, is a cross platform API that provides developers with
lower level access to the graphics resource hardware.
This allows for high performance applications
with better control over graphics hardware direct these
D twelve, created by Microsoft, is exclusively for Windows
and Xbox and offers developers deeper control over graphics
resources. Metal, an exclusive API for
Apple devices, was designed by Apple with maximum performance in
mind on their hardware. WebGPU has been
making significant progress lately. It's expanded to platforms
like Mac, Windows and Chrome OS and available in
Chrome 130 and H 130 versions.
Linux and Android support is expected to be added
soon. There are several engines that either
support or are experimenting with WebGPU.
Babylon JS fully supports WebGPU,
while these JS currently has experimental support.
Blake Canvas is still in development, but its future looks promising.
Unity made an announcement of early and experimental
web GPU support in Alpha version 2023.2 and
cost creator 3.6.2 officially supports
web GPU and finally construct is
currently only supported in Chrome version 130
or later on Windows, macOS and Chrome OS machines.
Taking this into consideration, it seems like wise
move to start transitioning towards web GPU or at least preparing
projects for a future transition. Let's take a closer
look at some of the code pieces of the API.
This won't be comprehensive, but WebGL touch on all
the most important bits. The GPU adapter is
a pivotal component. Adapters represent the
gpus. The device can be axed.
This can be even software based like Swift shader,
and typically it returns one adapter at a time.
However, you can specify an adapter based on certain criteria,
like power performance, low power,
and it provides a snapshot of the GPU specifications
such as vendor Nvidia architecture, tuning,
and furthermore it outlines the features and limits
of the capable to the GPU device.
The GPU device plays a central role.
It serves as a main interface for the API.
This company is responsible for creating resources
such as textures, buffers and pipelines.
It comes equipped with GPU queue
to carry out comments, and functionally it's
quite akin to WebGL rendering contexts.
Webgl extensions are roughly equivalent to those in WebGPU.
However, they are not universally supported across all
systems. Each adapter provides a list of available
extensions to activate them. They must
be specified when requesting the device. There are
numerical constraints on GPU capabilities.
Baseline exists that every web
GPU implementation must meet. The adapter
indicates the actual limits of the system. By default,
only these limits are active unless specified during
the device request. WebGPU enables rendering to
the canvas after creation. It needs configuration
to link with device. Multiple canvases
can share the same device, and they can be reconfigured
as necessary. It supplies a
texture for rendering and there
are several resource types in web GPU.
First, we have the GPU buffer. It defines
the size and its usage. It can
be used from uniforms, vertices, indices and general
data. Next is the GPU
texture. It designates dimensions as
along with size maps, samples, formats and usage.
Then there is a GPU texture view.
It is a subset of a texture used for sampling or
as rendering targets. You can specify
its use as a cube map, array, texture, and more.
The GPU sampler is also important. It dictates these
textures, filtering and wrapping behavior.
It's crucial to note that all these resources
maintain a fixed shape post creation.
However, their content can be modified.
The device comes with a default GPU queue.
Currently, it's the only queue available for use.
However, future API versions might offer more options.
This queue is essential for submitting comments to
the GPU. Additionally, it features
useful helper functions. These assist
in writing to buffers and textures, and these are
the simplest method to update the content of these resources.
It's highly recommended to make use of them. To record
GPU comments, start by creating GPU comment encoder from
your device. This allows you to transfer data between buffers and
textures. You can then initiate render or
compute passes. Once you're done,
it generates the CPU comment buffer.
Remember, comment buffer remains inactive until they are
queued, and once a comment buffer
is submitted, it can be reused.
Passes play a significant role in GPU operations. A render
pass can utilize GPU render pipelines.
It binds to vertex or index buffers,
issues, draw calls, and write to one or
multiple textures. On the other hand, a compute
pass taps into GPU compute pipelines.
It's responsible for issuing dispatch calls.
It's essential to note that when a pass is active, you can't
record other comment types. However,
both render and compute passes have capability
to set bind groups. Initially, a render pass
requires you to provide details about its
attachments. This includes these output designation
and methods to load and save these. Here,
the clearing of data types take place. It's also where
you establish multi sample results, ensuring accuracy at
the past. Conclusion now let's explore the main high level
differences when beginning to work with GraphQL APIs,
the first step is to initialize the main object for interaction.
This process has some differences between WebGL and WebGPu,
which can cause some issues in both systems. In WebGL,
this object is called context and represent these interface
for drawing on an HTML five canvas element.
Obtaining this context is quite easy, but it's
important to note that it's tied to a specific canvas.
This means that if you need to render on multiple
canvases, you will need multiple contexts.
WebGPU introduces a new concept called device.
The device represents a gpu abstraction that you will
interact with. The initialization process is
a bit more complex than in webgl, but it provides more
flexibility. One advantage of this model is that one
device can render on multiple canvases, or even none.
This provides additional flexibility, allowing for one device to control
rendering on multiple windows or contexts.
Buffer management in both APIs looks the same.
However, in WebGPu, once a buffer is created, its size
and destination are fixed. It's also worth noting
that don't bind the desired buffer.
Instead, it simply passed as an argument.
This approach can be found throughout the whole API for
shaders. The big change is that WebGL
uses GLSL and WebGPU uses a new shader
language called WGSL. It's designed to
cross compile nicely to the various Buchanan's preferred shader
variants. Note that in WGSL,
the fragment and vertex shaders can be part of the same shader
as long as they have different function names.
This can be very convenient. WebGL and WebGPU
are two distinct methods for managing and organizing the
graphic pipeline. In WebGL, the primary emphasis
is on the shader program, which is combined vertex and
fragment shaders to determine how vertices are
transformed and how each pixel is colored. To create a
program in WebGL, you need to follow simple steps.
Just write and compile a shader code for source
code for shaders. Attach these compiled shaders to the
program and these link them. Activate the program before rendering
and transmit data to activated program. That's all?
Yeah. This process provides flexible control over
graphics, but can be complicated and prone to errors,
particularly for large and complex projects. When developing
graphics for the web, it's essential to have a streamlined and efficient process,
and in web GPU it's achieved through the use of a pipeline.
The pipeline replaces these need for separate programs
and includes not only shaders, but also
other critical information that's established as state
in WebGL. Creating a pipeline in WebGPU
may seem more complicated initially, but it offers
greater flexibility and modularity. The process
involves three key steps. First, you must define
the shader by writing compiling the shader source code just
as you would in WebGL. Second, you create these
pipeline by combining the shader and other rendering parameters into
adhesive unit. Finally, you must activate the pipeline before rendering.
Compared to WebGL, WebGpu encapsulates
more aspects of rendering into a single object. This approach
creates a more predictable and error resistant
process. Instead of managing shaders and rendering
states separately, everything is combined into one pipeline
object. By following these steps, developer can
create optimized and efficient graphics for the web with ease.
Finally, we get to drawing again.
WebGPU looks more complex, but that's
actually in this case,
we are more explicit about setting up render
target, whereas WebGl there is a
default one, but during the actual rendering,
web GPU avoids setting up the
vertex attribute layout because that's part of the pipeline.
Let's now compare uniforms in WebGL and
WebGPU uniforms, variables offer constant data
that can be accessed by all shader instances.
With basic WebGL, we can set uniform variables
directly via API calls. However, this approach
is straightforward, but necessities multiple API calls
for each uniform variable. With these
advent of WebGL, two developers are now able to group
uniform variables into buffers, a highly efficient alternative
to using separate uniform shaders, and by
consolidating different uniforms into a larger structure. Using uniform buffers,
all uniform data can be transmitted to the GPU advance,
leading to reduced API calls and superior performance.
In these case of webGl, two subsets
of a large uniform buffers can be bound through a special
API call known as bind buffer range.
Similarly, in web GPU, dynamic uniform buffers offsets
are utilized for the same purpose. Eleven is the
passing of a list of offsets when invoking the setbind group
API. This level of flexibility and optimization has
made uniform buffers a valuable tool for developers looking to optimize
their WebGL and WebGPU projects. A better
method is available through Webgpu. Instead of supporting individual
uniform variables, work is exclusively done through
uniform buffers. Loading data in one
large block is preferred by modern gpus instead of
many small ones. Rather than recreating
and rebiding small buffers each time, creating one
large buffer is using different part width for
different row calls can significantly increase performance,
while WebGL is more imperative resetting global state with each
call and striving to be as simple as possible.
WebGPU aims to be more object oriented and focused
on resource reuse, which leads to efficiency.
Although transitioning from WebgL to WebGpu
may seem difficult due to differences in methods,
starting with transition to Webgl two as an immediate
step can simplifies our work. Transitioning from WebGL
to WebGPU involves modifying both API and shaders.
The WGSL specification facilitates a seamless
and intuitive transition while ensuring optimal efficiency and performance
for contemporary gpus. I have an example shader for
texture that uses GLSL and WGSL.
GLSL serves as a connection between web
gpu and these native APIs.
Although WGSL appears to be more worthy
than GLSL, the format is still recognizable.
The following tables display a comparison between the basic and metrics
data types found in GLSL and WGSL.
Moving from GLSL to WGSL indicates a
preference for these more stringent typing and clear specification
of data sizes, resulting in better code
legibility and lower chains to make
mistakes. The meta declaring structures has
been altered with these addition of explicit
syntax for declaring fields in WGSL structures.
This highlights the need for improved clarity
and simplification of data structures and shaders.
By altering the syntax of function in WGSL, it promotes a unified
approach to declarations and return values,
which results in more consistent and predictable code.
If you are working with WGSL, you'll notice that some of
the built in GLSL functions have different names
or have been replaced. This is actually helpful because
it simplifies the function names and make them more intuitive.
This will make it easier for developers who are familiar
with these graphic APIs to transition to WGSL
if you are planning to convert your WebGL projects
to WebGPu, there are a lot of tools available that
can automate the process of converting GLSL to WGSL,
and one such tool is Naga. It's a rust
library that can be used to convert GLSL to WGSL,
and best of all, it can be even used
right from your browser with the help of webassembly.
Now, let's talk about some differences in conventions
between WebGL and WebGPu. Specifically, we will
go over the disparities in textures, viewport and clip spaces.
When you migrate, you may come across an unexpected issue
where u images are flipped. This is a common
problem for those who have moved. Implications from OpenGL
to direct OpenGL and WebGL images
are usually loaded so that the first pixel is on
the bottom left corner. However, many developers load images
starting from the top left corner, which results in flipped
images. Directory D and metal systems, on the other hand,
use the upper left corner as a start point for textures.
The developers of WebGPU have decided to follow this
practice since it's appear to be more straightforward approach for most
developers. If your WebGL code selects
pixels from the frame buffer, it's important to keep in mind that
WebGpU uses a different coordinate system to adjust.
For this, you may need to apply a straightforward y
equal one minus y operation to correct these coordinates.
If a developer encounters a problem where objects are
disappearing or being clipped too soon,
it may be due to differences in the depth domain.
WebGL and Webgpu have different
definitions of the depth range of the clip space,
while WebGl uses a range from minus one to one, WebgpU uses
a range from zero to one, which is similar to other graphics APIs
like direct to D, Metal and Vulcan.
This definition was made based on advantages of
using the range from zero to one that were discovered while working with
our graphics APIs. The projection matrix
is primarily responsible for transforming a position of your
model into a clip space. One useful way
to make adjustments to a code is to ensure that the projection
matrix generates outputs ranging from zero to one. This can be
achieved by implementing certain functions available in libraries like GL matrix,
such as the perspective co function.
Other metrics operations also offer
comparable functions that you can utilize in the event
you're working with an existing matrix projection
and that can be modified. Yeah, there is still a
solution. You can transform the projection matrix
to fit the zero to one range by applying another
matrix that modifies these range before
the projection matrix. This pre multiplication technique
can be an effective way to adjust the range of your projection matrix to fit
your needs. Now let's discuss some tips
and tricks of working in this web GPU.
First of all, of course, minimize the number of
pipelines you use. The more pipelines you use, the more
states which you have and the less performance it result.
It may be not trivial depending on where your
assets come from. Creating a pipeline and
then immediately using it it works but
don't do it. Yeah, just create functions,
return immediately and it start work on
a different thread when you use it. The queue execution
needs to wait for pending pipeline creation to finish.
This causes a significant junk. Make sure you
leave some time between create and first use,
or even better, use the Create pipeline async variants.
The promise resolves when the pipeline is ready to
use without any styling. Render bundles
are prerecorded partial reusable render
passes. They can contain most rendering
comments, except for things like setting the viewport.
They can be replayed as part of
an actual render passes later on. Render bundles
can be executed alongside regular render passes comments.
The render pass state is reset to defaults
before and after every bundle execution, primarily for reducing
JavaScript overheat or drop in. So GPU performance is
the same either way. So transitioning to
web GPU is more than just switching graphic APIs.
It is a step towards the future of web graphics,
combining successful features and practices from various graphics
APIs. These migrations requires
thorough understanding of technical and philosophical changes,
but the benefits are really significant. So thank you for your
attention and I hope you enjoy the conference. See you.