Hey everyone, I hope you've been having a great time at the conference so
far. My name is Arsh Sharma and my session is going to be
about making DevOps friendlier for developers.
So before I start this talk, I want to catch you up all on what
the story has been till now. Like before microservices, cloud and all
the fancy stuff related to DevOps started coming into picture where we were.
So earlier, people who built applications,
sorry, people who wrote application code like developers, were different
from people who packaged up the application, which were application builders.
But Docker popularized the use of containers and
that sort of led us to ask the question that hey, now, the developer
can itself, they can themselves package the application in a container.
So these two kind of people got merged and
basically application building got shifted left. Shifted left means
became a responsibility of the developers. Now this led to teams
which could iterate much more faster because now, because every time you know
that there's a dependency on someone and task has to go from one team to
the other, there is a delay. But when you sort of merge those kind of
teams, you sort of skip that delay. And this is how we started
shipping code more faster. And agile culture came to be the norm
in the industry. But this was still separated
from the ops people whose primary responsibility still
was like managing clusters and doing deployments and all the
infrastructure side of things. So developers still sort of
were not self sufficient in a sense because they had to rely on
ops people. But then came DevOps.
So DevOps, the idea was to make developers more independent.
The idea was that the dependency for developers
on other people should reduce so that we are able to ship features
and bug fixes much more faster. So the whole goal was that the
Ops team now sets up processes which developers can rely
on to be self sufficient. And this is where
things started to get tricky because we sort of agreed
upon two processes which were CI pipelines, CI CD pipelines
and staging environments. But these processes didn't exactly
solve what they set. But to let's see how things
changed for developers, like with these processes. The problem with both these
processes was that development still took place in can environment,
which was nothing like production. So in production you have all these clusters and kubernetes
running, but when you're developing, you're still developing locally in
your editor and bringing up services locally,
or even if you went the extra step and ran containers,
everything was not exactly like it would be in production.
So let's say whenever there's a but in the production environment,
and now you have to replicate that bug locally. Developers would call upon ops
people and try to spin up local kubernetes, clusters and do all of
that. But even then it's tough because you can use minikube or kind or
something like that, but you can never get the exact same thing you were
getting in production locally. So CI CD pipelines and
staging environments have their use. They help you ship code
better and faster. But still the use does not come into
picture when the developer is writing code, that is, they are far from developer
like. A developer would have to commit and push these changes for
CI pipelines to come into picture. And same for staging environments,
you would have to wait for accesses and a build to complete, and then these
things come into picture. But when you're writing code, it's just you and your local
environment which is problematic and which leads to
the feedback loop. The outer feedback loop got simplified because of CI CD pipelines
and staging environments. But the inner feedback loop, which is like when you writing
code and seeing your changes, that became longer because now you saw your changes locally
on your laptop as you coded them out, but you still weren't sure if how
they would look in production, because for that you would have to commit and build
them and all that sort of thing. Similarly for Ops people.
Also, things did not get that easy, right? Because now,
like we said, if there was a bug in production and that had to be
replicated locally, Ops people would have to configure environments for each developer
so that they can now replicate that bug. And these environments weren't replicable.
Sure, you could use something like terraform to have a standard thing spin up,
but that's just for your infrastructure, right? Not for your application.
So developers weren't that happy. Ops people weren't
that happy. How do we fix this is the inevitable question to
that. I think the best solution I have found is cloud dev environments.
And what these dev environments do we'll soon see in a demo. But the
whole idea is that if everything is happening in the cloud like
production is there, staging environments are there, CI CD pipelines are there.
So why shouldn't your dev environments live there too? Because we as an
industry have always agreed on the fact that development should happen in an exactly production
like environment. And if that's the case, then why
haven't we been moving close towards it? Developers should not
have to rely on Ops and infrastructure people every
time they need such an environment. And this is why we
came up with a solution which was Okteto Cli, which is a completely open
source project and this is the problem it aims to solve.
The way this problem is solved is that the operations team configures an Okteto
manifest, which is just like a one time process. And this Okteto manifest
contains all the instructions required to spin up a dev environment.
Now that includes how to deploy your application, something which
Ops people would have to spend like synchronous
calls with developers to do that. Now all of that is in a one configuration
file and it's easily replicable and reproducible. So what
happens is these dev environment gets deployed in a Kubernetes cluster. So your
application, all these microservices are deployed to a cluster and then a two way file
synchronization service is set up. So what this means is that the
code you write gets synced with the code running in the cluster.
So this way you are able to seems all your changes as soon as you
make them and you get live feedback. And that feedback is in a productivity like
environment. So you know that whenever you
build it or push it, nothing will fall apart, right? And even if,
let's say there are some bugs, you catch them early on, or if there are
already existing bugs, then you're able to replicate them because this environment is
exactly like the environment which is there in production.
So that was the idea. To make it super clear, I'm going
to show you a demo of how this works and I'm going to be
using this simple application which is a movies application,
which is a movies rental application. The source code for this is at forward
slash movies. I have it already cloned and
I have Okteto Cli installed. And with octo Cli
all you have to do is set a context which is basically the Kubernetes cluster
you want to use and deploy to. I'm using Okteto cloud, but you
can use any cluster like it works with AWS, Google Cloud,
any vanilla Kubernetes cluster. And once you do that, all you have to
do is run Okteto up. It's one single command.
And this common uses this configuration file
which I was talking to you about, which the Ops people said it's one time
configuration. It tells how to build all the microservices. So let's
say these front end microservice, the context for building that is in the front end
folder and there it uses all the existing docker files there are,
and then how you deploy all the stuff you need using helm. And then
there's a dev section which tells how the development for these microservices
should happen like what folders should be synced and all port forwarding
stuff is here. So let's wait for the
deployment to complete.
Once the deployment is complete, Okta will prompt you to choose which one of
your microservices you want to develop. Let's just keep it simple in this
video and make a change on the front end. So I'll choose front end.
But these beauty of this approach is that all of these microservices are now deployed
to the cloud and are working together. So let's say if you personally
wanted to bring up this application, you as a developer would have to bring each
of these services up individually. Whereas with things approach all of
them are up and deployed in one single command.
So once you select which service you want to develop, what happens
is there is a container replacement step.
The container running in the cluster gets replaced by a dev container. And what's
special about things Dev container is that whatever code we write on our local machine
gets synced with the code running in the dev container. So that way any
change we make here will be reflected live in that environment which is
running in the cluster. So that's how you are able to develop in a production
like environment. And to see this, like you see we have access
to the terminal in that dev container and we also have access
to endpoints where we can visit our application. So this
is the endpoint where the front end lives. But like I said, this is running
in the cluster, running in the cloud cluster. But everything is sort of like
how you would be developing locally because it is still at the end of the
day like development which is happening on your machine,
right. So to do that you would have to first run
yarn to install all the dependencies. So let's just go back
to our ide and run yarn like you would locally.
So all of this is like locally but all of this is happening in the
cloud. And then you run yarn start. And what that basically does
is start the server where the application is. And if
we hit refresh now, we see that our application is up
and running. Now like I said, this is just the application running and
whatever code you write will get synced. So let's also test that out.
And I have things code already written, I'll just uncomment it which is
basically a discount coupon. And if we go back
here we see that this thing appears,
which is the code we just wrote. If we comment it again,
go back, hit refresh, it's gone.
So I hope you can now see the beauty of this approach
how whatever code we write gets synced, and how the inner
dev cycle has now reduced and its dependencies
on things like CI pipelines and waiting for builds to complete or waiting for
ops people to set up environments has reduced significantly. And developers
now are much more independent and much more confident when
writing code, because you know that if that code works here, it will work in
production, it will work in your CI pipelines and your staging environments. So that's the
whole idea, that's the whole goal, that we simplify DevOps by giving
developers all the tools to be self sufficient and the ops people only
have to be responsible for setting up and maintaining these tools. Going back
to the slides, just a recap of all the benefits of this approach is like
developers can now get to the code writing phase by skipping all the
configuration. Like you saw, we only needed to run octeto up. We did
not need to bring up front end by writing yarn start and then bring up
the back end and then configure the database and all that sort of microservices stuff.
All of that was skipped. All you had to do was run one single command
of Tetoap and the environment was exactly like production. The feedback
is instantaneous. So as soon as you hit save you get to see your results.
Whereas with a CI pipeline you would have to wait a few minutes for all
the building and deployment to happen.
So the goal is that shipping for the cloud,
then you have to develop in these cloud as well, because that is
how you're going to make less mistakes and ship applications which are
much more smoother and much more cloud native in nature. Thanks.
This was it. Thanks for watching. If you have any questions,
feel free to reach out to me on Twitter at these razorinkyakidad and
I hope you have a fun conference ahead.