Thank you for being here today to talk about a complex topic,
which is kubernetes. My goal is to provide clarity
about the principles and the concepts of
kubernetes and compare them to the virtualization world that
you might be familiar with. So hopefully by the end of this
presentation you have a better grasp of kubernetes
and you'll be able to start using it as well. So let's
begin. My name is Julia and I'm a global technologist at
VIM. And as the name indicates, we started
providing services backups mainly for virtual machines.
But nowadays we've expanded and we provide backup for
most environments like cloud SAS, including kubernetes
as well. But we're not here to talk about that today.
We're here to explain and clarify kubernetes
in an easier way for virtualization
admins. So we traced the evolution of infrastructure
through four significant stages. Initially,
applications ran directly on dedicated physical servers,
limiting resource utilization and scalability. But with
the advent of virtualization, we introduced vms,
enabling multiple virtual instances on a single physical
server. Each VM included a complete guest
operating system alongside the application, reducing hardware
costs and simplifying management. Then with cloud
computing, we elevated virtualization by
offering vms as a service, so facilitating
on demand provisioning and scalability, and removing
the burden of physical infrastructure management.
So this was really amazing. But then with the latest
evolution containers we optimized resource usage
by sharing the host OS. Kernel containers
encapsulate only essential components necessary
for running applications, enhancing efficiency and
portability across diverse environments. Virtual machines
and containers differ in several ways, but the primary
difference is that containers provide a way to virtualize
an OS so that multiple workloads can
run on a single OS instance, whereas with
vms the hardware is being virtualized to run
multiple OS instances. As organizations
seek for future ready infrastructure solutions, the integration
of kubernetes and virtualization in hybrid environments
will emerge as a compelling strategy. That's why it's so
important to understand kubernetes, so we can all start
using kubernetes as well. Similar to how shipping
containers encapsulate goods, software containers similar
to how shipping containers encapsulate goods,
software containers encapsulate applications and all their dependencies,
making them highly portable and consistent across different
environments. This portability enables developers
to build applications once and deploy them anywhere.
Also, just as shipping containers enhance security by
sealing goods from external elements,
software containers enhance security by isolating
applications from the underlying infrastructure,
ensuring that they run consistently and securely regardless
of the hosting environment, containers at their core
share the host operating system's kernel with other containers.
The shared OS components are red only,
resulting in remarkable lightweight properties. This means
you can deploy multiple containers on a single server
or virtual machine, eliminating the need to dedicate an
entire server to a single application. This not
only optimize resource utilization, but also reduces
the overhead of maintaining multiple operating systems.
Scaling up becomes effortless, requiring no
additional server space. Containerization also addresses
various other challenges in software development and deployment.
It provides a robust solution for mass deployment,
as showncased in the deployment layer at the top of this image
and here we focus on how to efficiently deploy and
manage numerous containers beneath. On the
bottom lies the nodes layer,
encompassing the hardware and the runtime environment necessary
to execute these tasks. The nodes play a
crucial role in supporting containerized applications
and ensuring they are seamless operation and we'll talk
about both the deployment layer and the nodes layer in
a little bit. Kubernetes represents nothing short
of a revolution in infrastructure management.
It has fundamentally reshaped the way we orchestrate,
deploy, and scale applications in today's dynamic
it landscape.
Now let's explore the architecture of Kubernetes and
compare its key components to familiar concepts in
virtualization. At the heart of Kubernetes is the
Kube API server, which acts as the central control
point. Think of it as similar to the vcentering
virtualization. It exposes the Kubernetes API,
allowing users to interact with the cluster, the ETCD.
It's a database that behind the scene is
basically a distributed key value store. So let me go back here
and it serves as the Kubernetes memory storing configurations,
states and other essential information, and also
in virtualization. The vcenter also relies
on a database to store configuration data, so we
can compare both to the vcenter.
Then the Kubernetes, like we said,
is API driven, offering both a command
line interface and a programmatic API for
interaction. This is like how we interact
with Vcenter through tools like vsphere client and
ESX cloud. Also in Kubernetes,
pods are fundamental units that host our containers.
They are like the equivalent of vms in the virtualization
world, providing a layer of abstraction for running application.
Then, just as virtualization platforms use hypervisor
or container runtimes to manage resources,
Kubernetes here employs a container runtime
like Docker or containerd to oversee
the execution of containers. And finally, the control
plane that we'll explain more in
a few slides further encompasses components
like Kube, API, server, etcd,
etc. To regulate the cluster's behavior.
Similar to how virtualization has a control plane
responsible for orchestrating the vms.
Kubernetes, like we said, is the go to container orchestrator
for provisioning, managing, and scaling applications.
Beyond containers, kubernetes also take care of additional
resources like volumes, networks, and secrets.
This ensures that your apps have what they need to
connect to databases, interact with firewall
backends and safeguard keys.
Kubernetes also operates on a declarative model,
so you specify the desire state and
Kubernetes takes care of the rest. If you need like
five instances, for instance, you don't need to manually
start them, you just tell kubernetes and it ensures your
desired state is maintained. Even if something goes
wrong, kubernetes will repair that and maintain
that desired state. A Kubernetes cluster is
essentially a collection of nodes where each
node can be either a physical machine or a virtual machine.
The cluster thrives on the synergy between a
master and worker nodes, where the master node
orchestrate and directs and the worker nodes execute
and perform. This collaboration forms the bedrock
of modern containerized applications deployment
now talking a little bit more about the worker nodes
at the foundation, a node comprises the physical hardware
serving as the infrastructure backbone. Then installed
on top of the hardware is the operating system, acting as
the base software layer for resource management and application
execution, similar to a hypervisor or a host OS
in virtualization. Then to execute containers,
a container runtime like docker, container Id,
crio or others is installed.
This software is responsible for launching and managing the containers.
The Kubelet service acts as an agency on
every node within the cluster. It takes commands
from the master controller, and you can also think of Kubelet
as a nodes coordinator, which ensures that containers
run as directed. And finally,
the worker node also has a cube proxy,
which is another critical components residing on each node.
It plays a pivotal role in proxying connections
to the pods from another components known as services.
This is like how a load balancer or network proxy
directs traffic to various virtual machines in
virtualization setups. Now the
master node let's talk about the master node, which is also
called a control plane. Again, this control
plane is responsible for orchestrating and managing the
cluster's operation. Within the control plane,
the controller manages services. When you submit
tasks or requests to Kubernetes, the controller reads
them via the API and orchestrates their execution
across the worker nodes. Then there is also another
components called the scheduler, similar to configuring
resource allocation in virtualization, like specifying
resources for a new vm in VSphere,
the scheduler that determines where to run containerized
services, which are represented as pods within the cluster,
it selects a suitable worker node for deploying pods,
optimizing resource allocation. Now, in Kubernetes,
pods serve as the lowest form of deployment.
They are configured using YAML,
following a declarative approach where you specify resources,
container details, and more. Like creating a
vm with power CLI, you define the
pod's name, container location, prepackaged services,
and any necessary arguments.
Additionally, you can introduce a persistent devalue
claim known as PVC to request
storage for a non ethermoral date.
Kubernetes, being an orchestration layer,
manages the storage requirements specified in the PVC,
creating what is known as a persistent volume,
or pv. This is reminiscent of
managing data stores or NFS exports in virtualization,
with pvcs resembling the VM's data disk.
Now, while pods are the fundamental building blocks,
deployments are like the orchestration conductors that
simplify the management of these pods. Think of
deployments in Kubernetes as orchestration conductors
for the pods. They serve as blueprints
defining your application's desired state,
including replica counts, container images,
storage secrets, and config maps.
Config maps they store configuration data as key
value pairs, allowing containers to customize
behavior without altering the image. For instance,
environments, variable, and settings can be stored in config
maps, simplifying multiple environment setups.
Secrets, on the other hand, securely hold sensitive
information like password or keys.
They enable your application to access vital security related
data without exposing it in container image
or configurations. So Kubernetes continuously
monitors and enforces this desired state,
providing seamless updates. So whether you're changing
container images or configuration in config maps
or managing secrets, kubernetes handles the rollout
while maintaining high availability deployments.
They simplify the application management,
including config maps and secrets, streamlining configuration
changes, and scaling to meet evolving requirements.
They are really a powerful tool for orchestrating
containerized applications in a Kubernetes cluster.
Now let's talk
about stateful sets. The biggest myth in the
Kubernetes world, and even in
the virtualization operations infrastructure
world, is that Kubernetes is only for stateless applications.
Stateful sets empower Kubernetes to orchestrate
stateful workloads and data services with efficiency
and reliability. In a typical Kubernetes setup,
attaching storage to a pod guarantees data
persistency even if the pod is restarted.
However, there is a caveat. The pod's identity
remains ephemeral. So after a restart,
it might reappear with a different hostname or identifier,
a characteristic that doesn't align with the requirements of stateful
applications. But stateful sets ensure
that each pod maintains a steadfast and predictable
identity, irrespective of whether it's terminated
or rescheduled. So let's say, for instance,
envision a scenario where a stateful set oversees
three database nodes. If one of these nodes undergoes
termination, it doesn't reappear as an entirely
new entity. Instead, it will retain its
identity and seamlessly reconnect to the same underlying
storage construct, and will preserve the vital role
within the cluster. So this feature,
stateful sets, proves indispensable for stateful applications
that require both high availability and data consistency.
Now another important
components with Kubernetes is
services. They play a crucial role in managing communication
and ensuring the availability of containerized applications.
Imagine another scenario where you have multiple
instances of a service running for high availability.
You need an efficient way to communicate with them.
And now think of services as a traffic coordinator
within your cluster. When external traffic
comes in, you can create an ingress layer which
acts like a load balancer, directing requests to
the appropriate destination. Each destination is
represented by a pod, and these pods, they can be
independent and dynamically managed, spun up,
spun down, or updated as needed. So like,
let's say, let's consider a WordPress application.
In a traditional setup, everything might run on a
single virtual machine, making it challenging to scale individual
components. But with containerization and kubernetes,
you can have individual pods for each service,
such as authentication, content and more.
This modular approach allows you to scale each service
independently. So if your WordPress site experiences
a surge in traffic, you can add another service layer, acting as
a load balancer to distribute the load efficiently.
Kubernetes services, they simplify the management of
communication and scalability in your containerized application.
Now finally, network policies in Kubernetes are
application centric rules that determine how pods
can communicate with different network entities.
Essentially, they control the flow of traffic at
the IP address or port level, operating at OSI
layers three and four. So by default,
in the absence of specific policies in a namespace,
all inbound and outbound traffic is permitted for
pods within that name within that namespace.
These policies are a
vital tool for fine tuning and securing network communication
within your Kubernetes environment, allowing to define precisely
how your pods interact within the network. Now,
just to finish this, let's recap
about how Kubernetes reflects
in the virtualization world.
Kubernetes excels in managing modern cloud
native workloads, offering dynamic scaling and efficient
resource virtualization, while virtualization still
remains a robust choice for legacy applications.
But understanding the right tool for your workload is crucial
because as all organizations seek
future ready infrastructure solutions, there will
be an integration between Kubernetes and virtualization in hybrid
environments and it will be a very powerful strategy.
So this approach bridges the gap between traditional
workloads and cloud native applications.
Additionally, I just want to mention that solutions
like Kasten by Vim simplified the migration process
from virtualization to kubernetes, ensuring a
seamless transition and providing data management capabilities
for crucial for modern workloads. So if
you have more questions and if you're interested about that,
feel free to check out Castin
IO or reach out to me on social media.
I would be glad to answer any questions that you have
on this presentation or on Kubernetes or even
on virtualization. I hope this presentation was helpful
and thank you for watching it. Bye.