Next 20 minutes, I'm going to speak about
platformless, a new concept and how
platformless is affecting enterprise software engineering.
I would like to start this story with greek
myth that in the ancient days we used to
think that Atlas is holding
the world. So everybody thought about this
before they realized the truth.
Similarly, inside an enterprise,
Atlas is the platform. Because any
IT expenditure or any IT related
work that we do as a developer,
architect, project manager,
CIO, all these activities are related
to providing some kind of digital experience
to our end users. We need a platform,
and if you talk to most of the technical teams inside
enterprises, they are building platforms.
Platform is a necessity. But there's a problem.
The problem is application development teams are focusing
on building a platform rather than delivering
applications. So I am in bunch of CTO clubs
in the Bay Area, and whenever we get together,
most of the CTOs and CIOs, even architects
are discussing about the teams are mainly focusing on
Kubernetes, how you can run a service mesh,
how you can have resiliency on microservices,
things like that. Related to, and unfortunately
with that trend, these development
teams are not focusing on application development.
As a result, business is not benefiting what
the technical team should deliver to the business.
So that's where there should be a change
happen in the industry. And we think
it as a focus shift from
platforms, CTO, application development.
So how you can do that,
to do that, the platform should be there, but it
should disappear from the focus.
So that's where this concept or analogy
like dark matter and dark energy will come and
play a role, because even dark matter
is not visible, but it is supporting
to have the universe, these galaxies
and all the different components that we
can find in the space. I'm not going
to talk about this too much. We are going to
tell more about this concept during a conference
that we are running that's called WSO two con
and it's posting on May 7, CTO 9th
in Florida. So if you are interested to get
to know more about how dark matter and platformless
connected, please come to the conference and we
will tell you this story. So, moving back
to the platforms, let's dig in deep into what
exactly that two layers I highlighted earlier on
digital experiences and then platform looks
like. So if you look at the platform,
there are two main layers.
One is a business platform and the second one
we call it as an internal developer platform. So recently
this term internal developer portal also came
to the picture that some of
the analyst firms are referring the internal developer platform
as an internal developer portal. So there
are bunch of different stakeholders inside
the enterprise responsible for
these different layers. If you look at the digital experiences
layer, the product owners are responsible to
deliver that. And if you look at the business platform that I
have highlighted here, the chief architect
and application architects are responsible to deliver that.
And then the internal developer platform has become
the main focus of this new role called
platform engineering. And platform engineering teams are
mainly focusing on delivering that internal
developer platform. So the platform is
consist with these two things, business platform and internal
developer platform. So why
the focus should shift from the building platforms into
application development? It's basically the
business advantage or the competitive advantages an
enterprise can get coming from the digital experiences
and the business platform that they are building, not from
the internal developer platform. Because internal developer platform
is a technical platform and those capabilities are common for
any enterprise. So there won't be a big business
advantage the organization will get by
mainly focusing on that,
kind of elaborate more on the
internal developer platform. We can even divide it into
two sections, an enterprise software engineering platform
and an infrastructure level platform.
Those two are connecting and creating this internal
developer platform mainly. Today,
most of the platform teams are mainly focusing
on the delivery platform, not the enterprise
software engineering platform. So that's an issue
because the delivery should contain
the enterprise software engineering capabilities
as well. Otherwise application developers will be
not that productive in the platform. And if the application developers
are not productive on the platform,
we might go back to these shadow it type of approaches and
application developers will build applications outside
the platform. So this internal
developer platform is facilitating the enterprise software engineering.
As I highlighted in this diagram, it is addressing the development
time as well as it is addressing the runtime.
And then to have more collaboration
you need a marketplace. So that way you design
APIs, services and then it will be available
for discovery and consumption for the application developers.
And application developers can use these concepts like domain
driven design to group these workloads and at the runtime
the same concept should appear as well. So I
introduced a concept called Cell based architecture.
So that's where the runtime is contained
with the cells, that cell A, cell B as
I have highlighted, and the components inside the cell connected
with a mesh. And then you can
secure this environment by bringing various
security principles, authorization,
authentication, entitlement,
so on and so forth. And that way you can build a zero trust environment
and there should be a synergy in between the development time and runtime.
If you are interested about the Sylvester architecture you can read
more. So if you Google from my
name and Sylves architecture, you will get
the paper and you can go through that in detail.
So then going back to this platformless
concept, it contains four fundamental things.
API first, cloud native middleware, developer experience and
then obviously the platform engineering.
So the API
first approach is basically in everywhere
in the organization. You should be able to expose APIs,
secure them, and then you should have internal
access as well as external access to
these APIs. And it has to be facilitated
by the platform that the technical team shouldn't be worried too
much about creating these APIs.
The platform should enable the developers
to create APIs and then publish it in the marketplace
and let the consumers to consume the APIs.
And it can happen at various levels, data APIs,
domain APIs and then at the edge you will get
the experience of edge APIs as well.
Then cloud native middleware is really important.
Middleware is a bit of outdated term, but still middleware
is important, but it has to mainly
model into cloud native architecture.
So I wrote an article some time back by describing middleware
as disappearing into code and infrastructure.
It's already happening. But having
this middleware either in the code or infrastructure is
pretty important. That's where the platform should provide these
middleware capabilities. As example, the security components
that we discussed and various other runtimes like service measures,
message brokers and way to
secure the APIs through API gateways.
All these type of supportive things that you
need to build an application should come in the cloud native middle
and then the developers are the craftments of digital experiences.
So developer experience is really important. So having a
rich developer experience in the platform is key.
So it has CTO be self service and pipeline
tune. That means like when developer starts doing
this application development, it should automatically connect to
the organization approved pipeline
and then they should be able to collaborate these different
type of workloads and consume
them. And sharing should be there and high agility
should be there for the developers. And developers should be able to
use their favorite tools and connect to the platform.
As an example, if developers are preferred to use vs
code as an IDE, they should be able to use
that and if they are willing to use command prompt
to do CLI to do a lot of development,
the platform should support a CLI and platform itself should
have some set of system APIs that the
developers can use it to extend some of these capabilities.
Then the platform engineering is the foundation and the result
should be platformless. So it should provide all these capabilities
and provide that application development environment
for the developers at the development time and
then CI CD during the development
phase two production and then how you can monitor
and manage this development runtime and have
a proper application lifecycle. So you create,
you run and you manage and you deprecate these
runtimes based on the
application needs. And you should be able to find the
dependencies and all the related
observability as well as debugging capabilities as well.
So platform engineering is not only about DevOps,
it's about site reliability engineering
as well as the platform engineering should have a
fair understanding about the application development
because they have to provide this rich developer experience
by understanding the developer
needs. So that's where a platform team will really important
consist with platform engineers as well as people
who got some knowledge about application development.
So to have another analogy about
platformless, earlier days when it comes
to an enterprise, to have emails
like we used to set up these email servers
and then we used to set up chat servers,
all these work related systems
we used to run. But today any enterprise
that will leverage capabilities provided by
Google Workspace or Microsoft 365 or similar solutions
instead of running these servers. So it's basically not
about focusing on running these servers,
mainly focusing on the consumption and the experience that
you get. So basically it's about the collaboration,
not about how you run this workload.
So similarly, on the platform
less environment, just focus on the application
development and you will just add developers
to the platform for them to focusing on business problems
and deliver applications for the enterprise.
So how you can achieve it, there can be two
parts. First part is you build it. So that's where you
have CTO, have a dedicated platform engineering team,
treat the platform as a product and look
at the technology advancements happening and keep
an eye on the future technology changes,
understand the developer needs and build that. You can start
it from scratch, or you can use a framework and build your
platform on top of that. So main thing is
it has to be a dedicated team and it has to treat as a
product and you have to keep on maintaining
it. Just building it and handovering it to the
application developers will not work. The platform engineering
team should mainly focus on that and build it.
WSO it's bigger investment because
it takes time, specific skill set as well
as you have to maintain this, as I explained earlier,
and then as a technology provider, we are helping people
who's building that. That's where we provide API
management integration and identity and access management
products. If somebody is building a platform, they can use all
this cloud native middleware runtimes and build
the platform. So the other part is you
buy off the shelf internal developer
platform when you're choosing an internal developer platform, you have to
take a look at whether it's providing a platformless experience
and the four key features that I explained.
API efforts, cloud native, middleware,
developer experience and platform engineering should
deliver from this platform. There are many choices
in the market, so you can go through them and then
see whether it is meeting your requirements as well as
whether it's addressing platformless capabilities.
So as a technology provider, we have a
solution built that we call it as choreo. Choreo stands
for choreography and how you can choreograph
different type of workloads at the development time,
at the runtime, and not only that at
the people level or the development teams level, how you can
collaborate with each other. So if you are interested
then you can go to wsru.com slash courier
and take a look how this internal developer
platform looks like and whether it is fit into your
requirements. It's a SaaS experience WSo you can just
sign up and try it out. So in summary,
the digital experiences are the key when it comes to an
enterprise. So you have to focus on delivering these
digital experiences. That's where you can create a
differentiator in the market and then the
digital experiences should be modern and it
has to leverage cloud native concepts because we
are in a cloud native era. So how you can use those
different type of cloud native skills and
how you can use this platform is very important.
So platform less is the concept that you can mainly
focus on the application development and then have less
focus on the technical platforms that you are building.
And I think with the requirements
coming from the business, expectations coming
from the end users or the consumers, it's really
important to look at this concept and it's time
to go platformless. So we wrote
a paper about this concept. It's called the platformless
manifesto and it is available under this URL
and it is released using
creative comments by phototo.
So feel free to send a PR with some
improvements or any suggestions that you think. It's currently
under zero eight version and we are in the process of
bringing it to 10 with your feedback as well.
So read the paper and if you have any suggestions, please send
this information. So that's about it.
And if you like to have productive conversations and a
detailed conversation about these concepts, these are my contact
details. I blog in my personal blog blog architectoarchitect.com
and you can read all my readings from much rank
URL I have provided and you can email me on
my email address and you can connect with me in LinkedIn
as well as x platform. These are my contact
details, and if you have any question, you can post it in
the channel. And I am happy to answer
those questions as well. So till
we meet in another conference, thank you very much.
Hope this is useful for.