What if you could work with some of the world's most innovative companies,
all from the comfort of a remote workplace? Andela has matched
thousands of technologists across the globe to their next career adventure.
We're empowering new talent worldwide, from Sao
Paulo to Egypt and Lagos to Warsaw.
Now the future of work is yours to create.
Anytime, anywhere. The world is at your fingertips.
This is Andela.
So welcome to today's talk in Peernet. My name is Akilan Selvacoumar and
I'm a software engineer at Peernet and I work towards the Peernet core repository.
And today I'm excited to talk about Peernet and the core protocol
we've been working on, or the new standard and implementation of our peer
to peer network, which we built purely using Golang.
So just to recap or just a good way to start
or a high overview of Purenet is Purenet is a peer to peer protocol
designed for file sharing.
But what we have done is we have actually used the best techniques available out
there for sharing files between two peers, learning about
peers in the network. We have implemented our technique, or the
best techniques used for escaping that.
And because we'll talk about the
whole protocol is purely in pure go. So the advantage
of this is we can run completely cross platform. So if you run
on an Android phone, you can basically run pure. Net natively
on an Android phone and various other architectures like Risk V and so
forth. This is the reason why we've written purely in go.
And also another benefit is it's easy to extend your application
on top of Peernet because it's a single binary.
We have a good set of APIs, and if you're a go developer, you can
actually call function calls from the packages to
make sure it's something customized to a certain function you're writing in your
go application. But in a higher overview, Peernet is a
simple peer to pay protocol for sharing files, and we're building a browser on
top of it, which helps
in file sharing to regular users. But for now it's
only a Windows machine. But today's talk is just about the Purenet
standard and the implementation we've done so far with our open source protocol,
which is available on GitHub. So just
to start, these are the design considerations of pure. Net. So the first
packet must establish a connection we're talking about here about we do handshaking,
which does this. We want
to secure against eavesdropping. We want to ensure that there's no sniffing or
spoofing. The third point is we want to secure against message forgery.
So we want to ensure that the message is coming from an actual peer.
For example, peer B gets a message from peer a,
it is from peer a and not from some other node
called peer c acting as peer a.
We want to secure against tampering can extension,
and by extension a bitflip. Basically when we
transfer packets maybe over a larger network or two nodes
between completely different countries,
there's a chance that the packet could get corrupted due to some
reason, and we want to ensure that we can identify this. Either we
can identify this and correct it, or just retransmit, or ask
for a new packet which is not corrupted. The fifth point is
we want the packets to be as small as possible. So if nodes are far
away it increases deliverability and lesser packet loss. And the
last point is we want TCP like acknowledgments because Purenet is built purely
using UDP. We want UDP to act like TCP.
So we basically want a reliable version of UDP and we use something called UDT,
which we'll talk about later. So this
is Purenet architecture at a high overview.
So what you see on your right side right here is a browser command line
and the Peernet core which is the implementation of the standard
slash protocol which is in Purego as you mentioned.
So basically the entire
core, or the entire core library comes built in with the command
line project itself. So it's part of the command
line package when you build the binary and the browser interacts
with the command line using a set of rest API calls.
If you could replace this browser with your own application as well on top of
it and do a set of rest API calls with Peernet running locally
on your phone and you have a peer to peer network overlay.
But this is just Peernet at a very high overview. We're going
to talk about in the next slides. We're going to talk about few of the
important modules independently. And just to recap, we do
UDP connection with other peers in the network as well.
So let's talk about blockchain, our fancy link list.
Or I like to think of blockchain as a fancy link list. So the blockchain
does two things. The first thing we use it to store file
metadata. The next thing we use it to store user profile information.
So what happens is when we have a blockchain,
we share it across other peers in the network, and then
once the other peers get the blockchain, they know about a file
metadata. So when searching they can just look up our blockchain and see if we
have the following file. If we have it, get that information
from, get that information from up here or download
the file. And something interesting is
our blockchain is actually kind of mutable. So that
means the blockchain does not always grow in size. So if
we delete a file, that entry also gets deleted from the blockchain.
So how does this work? Doesn't it define? So how does this
work? So basically what happens is if we delete a file rather than removing that
entry from the block, what we do is we remove the entry and at the
same time we change the version number of the blockchain with
a new version number and then we propagate that new version number.
So within the minute all the nodes in the peer
to peer network should have the new blockchain version number
or with the new blockchain itself. So what happens
in the end is Peernet is kind of like a Merkle forest if
we want to think of it with a ton of blockchains, which can be
like a Merkel tree. But basically every peer in Peernet
has their own blockchain and they share it with each other's peers. So all the
peers will have a bunch of blockchains of other peers in the network.
This will help using during search specifically.
So let's talk about the packet structure
of Peernet. So in Peernet we have something called
announce, which is a pseudo generated random number.
And basically this helps against preventing replay attacks
and so forth. The next one we have is something called a protocol
version. By default it's zero for in our case because
peer nets in the initial stages, but eventually we'll have one version
one version two. And this is just to ensure that two nodes
can communicate with each other. This is just to ensure two nodes of the same
version communicate with each other. Or if
we have something like backwards compatibility, we can just address it by ensuring
all nodes that within the packet itself that both nodes are
of the same version. This is obviously a future using, but not right now.
The next one is command. We'll talk about this in the next step. The next
one is sequence. We're talking about packet sequences over here, pretty self
explanatory. The next one is the size of
the payload data, basically the size of payload
you're sending. And the payload over here could be anything.
It could be a part file, it could be maybe a get block message,
something related to the announcement, depending on what the user is sending through the
packet. And the last one is the
randomly generated packets. Now this is kind of important because
this is to ensure that a router cannot just say this is a peer net
packet based on the size of a packets.
And basically this protects against fingerprinting.
So yeah, this is one way
we use to skip the firewall. So part of our
packet itself, the last one is in
pure net, most of the pack. For example, if you do get block or most
of the commands, they are encrypted using salsa 20. But if you do a file
transfer, for now it's actually unencrypted and it's rather in
plain text. So the reason for this is because
of efficiency reasons, there has been like high cpu usage when
we encrypt and send for each and every single, when we do
a file transfer, because in file transfers we send a bunch of packets,
because of course it's a file, we're transferring a huge file to the network.
So we generate multiple smaller packets and transmit them through.
And of course signing and sending actually slows down,
increases cpu performance. So this is an open
problem. We're still looking into it. We want to find an efficient way to
anchor packets and send them over for file transfers.
Next one is peer discovery, something simple. So one way is
we use something called bootstrapping. So initially when you start Peernet,
you would connect to a set of root peers. These root peers are basically Peernet
servers, basically running Peernet itself.
And basically it's a single point or it could be multiple root
peers where all peers connect to these root peers. To learn about
more nodes in the network. This helps immediately learn
have a larger peer list, and this means we can find more files
in the network increases, dispersing more peers, increasing our
discovery to other peers.
This looks like a centralized approach, but this is the only time.
Maybe it's centralized, but you could have your own set
of root peers or your own set of bootstrap nodes,
and this could be even some computer in your house. So when you're running a
private network, you want to ensure you learn about nodes in your private network through
your bootstrap node or just through your root node
so you can have your own list
of it. But for now we've
provided punit nodes to ensure you can learn them quickly.
The next one is exchanging pls,
basically exchanging, this is just part of the bootstrap
process, or exchanging pls is I communicate to node b,
I share my pls to node b, node B shares his or her
pls to node to node a, which is me. And then I learn
about new nodes from, let's say node a and node b knows
about new nodes from me and so forth helps
about learning about new peers in the network. The next step is if we want
to quickly discover nodes in our local network, we use
two things. One is an IPV four broadcast, and the other
one is something called an IPV six multicast. So with an IPV
four broadcast, we send, let's say an announcement message
to a single IP address to actually a broadcast
IP address in the network, and then that's sent to other nodes.
Basically that broadcast IP sends the announcement messages to all nodes
in the network. And whichever node is running Peernet in
your local network will respond back to the broadcast address itself or
respond to our node actually, and then
we would know about that new node or new nodes in our network.
And IPV six multicast is sending a datagram
to a specific group of nodes in the network.
These are just two techniques we use to learn about more nodes in
our network. So we
use two techniques, escape NAT. One is something, one is called UPnP
and UDP holepunching. So UPnP just stands for universal plug and
play. This means this is actually only certain routers
support UPnP. This depends on your router model and
whether it's enabled or not. And what UPnP does is something really simple.
You tell your router, open the following external port for me and
map it to my computer, which is running Peernet.
And this will ensure that nodes outside your network can
communicate through you by escaping NAT.
And of course this is only if your router is enabled. And many people also
disable it, sometimes for security reasons. So let's
say you don't have UPNP. Another way you can do or PNN automatically
will do it for you is using UDP hole punching where you'd use another
server or actually use another node, which is any node in the network which is
escape NAT to communicate. So this helps if two nodes
are behind nats to communicate with each other. We use the rendezvous server,
which is our middle server, and for example client a.
Basically what we do here is
both nodes, both of us connect to the middle server to know about each other.
And basically it's useful
if both nodes are behind the firewall. So for example, what will happen is client
a will connect to this. Let's say this node behind Nat
and this node behind Nat would communicate to client b stating
that the messages come from client a and then client b based
on that information about client a from the rendezvous server or their middle server
would directly do a peer to peer connection with client a.
It's a widely based concept,
escape Nat. You can see it commonly used a lot with WebRTC as well.
And we have it within ourselves because
our protocol is UDP, it works perfectly. We can easily implement holepunching
and we already have it implemented, tested and it works really well for
nodes behind nets.
The next step is, the next one we want to talk about is something interesting
we've been working on. It's something really simple and we intend to improve a lot
more on this later. And this is called a decentralized search.
So decentralized search is really simple
implementation. So in a peer to peer protocol we
don't like searching using hashes or maybe a file name or
basically some IP address with the file name.
We just want to search for a keyword and then we want all the results
of nodes in the network with that keyword.
So what we do is, I'm sorry about that. So what we do is the
nodes with these key. So basically when we search. So let's actually step
back a bit. So when we upload a file to the network,
what we do is we generate something called indexes.
So basically what happens is
we take a file name and if there are spaces in the file,
we consider them as separate words and each of these words are
indexes. For example, we can have a file saying go first,
talk 2022 mp4 and each of them with a dash or
space or an underscore. We remove those underscores and each
of those words are an index. And all this index is mapped to the hash
of the file. And basically if we search using this
hash of the files, we can get the file metadata.
And using this metadata we
can either download the file or even get more information about the file from the
peer to peer network. And that's how we do indexing.
And that's why we do indexing. And when we search, we also
do the same thing. When you search, let's say, for something specific,
we make sure that all of them are lowercase. We remove
spaces, we remove quotations, and then based on your search,
we search against our index table. We get the multiple
hashes of the files and then let's
say we query them, let's say from our
blockchains we have, and then we get the metadata and we display it.
And then that's as simple as that. When you search a file, how you get
the results of your files in the network.
Actually we'll do a live demo which will make so much more sense of what
I'm talking about right now. So we have,
we'll just jump quickly. So this is something also
super interesting. And this is a warehouse. This is where we actually
store our files in Purenet, kind of like
our file system where we store files. And let's talk about how
a warehouse works. So as we know, just to
recap, a blockchain only stores metadata, whereas a
warehouse actually stores the files, as I mentioned.
So what are the features of warehouse? What we have is
automatic deblication. So to ensure that it's
kind of like when we create our little Merkel tree for every file,
we do not have redundant data.
We address files based on hash. This is important content based addressing.
So you search a file rather than the files name, you search based on the
content or based on the hash. We can do three simple actions from
our warehouse. We can read a file, write a file, or remove a file.
The next part is something interesting. We can read parts or chunks,
or we can seek parts of the file. So for example, if a peer
is downloading a file from, let's say node b or peer
b, basically peer B can also
seek a certain part of the file and transmit it over to
node to peer a, which is
important. And we can store, and the next
part is we can store file as large as what our disk supports,
which is trivial and obviously should be the case.
This is something, and this is, I would say the
last part about the technical bits of Peernet. So this is
something we've been working on for a long time. It took us a long time
to integrate. So we can elaborate about this.
And this is something we are very happy to announce that we have full
support and we've fully written in Golang about this. And this is the
UDP protocol. UDT protocol is
basically making UDP more reliable,
making UDP act like TCP,
but except most of the transport layer or most of the implementation
like congestion control, is on the application layer.
So the benefit of this is that,
for example, when we know two nodes are close by to each other, we can
actually have a larger packet size because we know there's going to be lesser
packet loss and this would increase. Essential. We're utilizing most of
the bandwidth. We can modify ascending
window size, we can modify a lot of things which normally
can only be done at a kernel level. And because
we have all these major things at an application
level, like sending acknowledgments, receiving,
sending a NAC packet not acknowledged packet, having our bucket
of peers, having a packet of packets not
sent, setting the size of the packet,
maybe even defining how the packet looks like. Like how we mentioned
in a previous slide, having all this at an application layer ensures
that it's cross platform. We can really optimize it
to utilize most amount of bandwidth available and
the stack. And yeah, just having these two benefits makes
a big deal for us and over the future is going to improve the
protocol dramatically with whatever we have plans with.
And Unity has won multiple bandwidth competitions
and making this work in Purego was not
easy. I think we're the only project that
actually fully utilizes UDT in pure go.
So we're glad about this and
we want to improve UDP because we fully have a lot of things to improve
on. But this is majorly
the backbone behind how we do file transfers between
from the most lowest level but having it completely
implemented in Golang at an application layer.
So this means that you as a contributor, it's going to be really simple to
modify it customly for your use case if you want to get to
the finer details. And you wouldn't have to change anything on
your operating system or kernel itself.
So let's jump to a lifetime of Peernet. Finally we're here.
I'm just going to quickly open my terminal right here. So let
me get a clear command. So what you see here is
the command line repository. I will, sorry, 1 minute.
Quickly, right here. Quickly put it right here. So this is the command
line repository as you can see here. All you have to
do is clone this repository. I will show you the link soon and all you
do is go build and
that's it. It takes a few seconds, obviously I've built it so it's all in
my cache, but normally it just takes a few seconds
to build. And once you're done building you can just run
that binary and you have right here. Let me
just position this in a way so that you can see what I'm talking about.
Okay cool. 1 second. Okay here so
we have a set of commands which we have improved. I'm just going to show
a few commands right now. We just wanted to show that this works. So if
I do status, sorry.
I can see a set of nodes in my network right here.
These are basically public IP addresses of all nodes in a network.
So we identify each node by their public IP address.
We can get more information. If you want to find more information about each node
we can do something called pure, pure bliss which
is right here. We can see all the adapters
available in these specific nodes,
which could be, which is substantially useful for us.
But for now,
this question mark right here, we have these other commands.
We're not going to talk about this. Today's talk, you can play around and easily
figure out what they do, since they're pretty well documented
for what they do. But just
explain, I'll explain a few important commands. For example, if you
want to test out and see how your file transfers, you can use something
called probe file transfer. So what this does is
you can have a file added to your warehouse in node a, and node b
also has that file added to the warehouse and you can just do probe file
transfer. You put that node id of node b, for example,
of who you want to test against, and you put your file hash and this
will basically do a file transfer and show you the speeds you're getting
and ensure that the file is fully transferred by comparing the
hashes towards the end. And this is a
great way to debug and ensure that the changes you're doing are working,
how efficiently they're working, and so forth.
So just wanted to mention about the command. You can also of
course try out the other commands which are super interesting.
As you can see, we're going to add commands
soon in the upcoming releases where you can actually just add a
files, remove a file and do the basic stuff. But for now you would have
to use the browser to do that. Or you could read the rest API docs
which help you add remove files. But we will soon add them to the command
line which is using certain functions which will make it easier
for us to integrate directly to the command line without having any complicated code.
So just bear with us. We will get the basic functionality like
add remove files soon so that you can directly talk with your
friends peer from any creating system just using a few command line
instructions. The next thing I
wanted to talk about was actually the peony browser itself
which is right over here. You can see this is
proprietary, but this browser uses the punt protocol itself.
So you can see right here, if you go to the explore tab, you can
see a set of videos recently
uploaded to Peernet itself. If we go to the home
tab right here, for example, I can type Ukraine if I'm
spelling it correctly, and just give it some time.
We have a set of just this is to prove that our peer net
search or search works in our peer to peer protocol as per how we
explained it in the slides. You can go here. If you hover over
your peer, you can find out from which country it's been uploaded from.
If you click play,
you can play the video as well. Currently this is a bit slow, but this
works fine. This is actually an older release, but if you do check our Twitter
pages for the new releases with the new video players and
something interesting over here is that when you
play a video, the video is played on memory and
not on disk. So yeah, it's only temporarily.
So it's great. First, eventually it's going to be great for streaming
videos as well and actually already is, but we haven't released that version,
so stay tuned to get that version from us.
So I'm going to quickly jump back to the slides
right here. I'm going to go here view
that was just a very quick demo of Peernet to understand what we've been working
on and feel free to try it out yourself. We love to see
the ideas you like us to implement next.
So these are a few ideas on how you could extend Peernet. This is just
our few ideas we found interesting, but of course you
can implement it using your own ways. One way is
to ensure that you build a distributed game engine in such a way that when
you're playing a game or you are loading a map, you could basically
load a map from the peer nearest to you by just searching based
on the hash. IPFS has a few examples. It could be interesting to
also extend it with Peernet because in Peernet over time
we are going to be way more efficient in terms of discovering peers,
transferring content between peers using
our implementation compared to other peer to peer networks. But this
is underbuilding and we're very soon to accomplish this.
So one is building a decentralized game engine.
It'll be very interesting to see how if you could have a decentralized game engine
on top of Peernet, another one we really want to improve our NLP searches.
Sorry, we really want to improve our searching. It'll be interesting
if we could actually someway embed NLP to the Peernet protocol
as an external open source project. And potentially we could
also add it'll be interesting. We're also keen to find out
how we could introduce files ranking when doing decentralized searches from,
if possible, the core protocol itself to
improve results. But these are a few ideas we think are
interesting, but it's your creativity. We just want you to play
around, try Peernet and use it for your use
cases. So how
do you contribute to Peernet? It's super simple. You can join our Discord channel or
forums on our website. I'll show them the next slide. The links to
discuss about Peernet you can do is you can also create a pr at
our GitHub repository.
If you want to contribute to changes to the Peernet protocol based on modifications
you did on your fork or your project, so forth,
it would be recommended that you create a pr and we discuss through the
changes you want so that we don't have to reject the pr
you create. So yeah, feel free to discuss on
our Discord channel or just create an issue on GitHub and we'll get right back
to you. The last way to contribute to Peernet is if
you have a large proposal, say it's going to take you more than
four months or even six months to complete. The best thing is to email us
at info@peernet.org so that we could potentially
personally talk with you and try to ensure that your idea,
which you want to merge with Peernet, is towards
all our interests and we are on track
and we are all on the same page when discussing about it.
So these are a few things. So just to summarize,
pure net is a completely decentralized network with no intermediaries.
We have a full working browser and a command line implemented.
We can escape nats and firewalls to a certain extent.
Our entire implementation is
a single binary file and you need zero configuration to
get it started and running, which is super cool.
We control most of our transfers at an application layer,
which means we can optimize
our transfer algorithms to take advantage of bandwidth available.
Our implementation can run cross platform and we don't have to really contribute
to the kernel so everything can be done directly to Peernet.
We can ensure also that we can also control packet sizes and
have various controls, which is very useful when we do something
like file transfers and so forth.
These are our links to the Peernet project.
Feel free to look at them. I'll just quickly go through them
with you right now. So here we
have the Peernet GitHub page, we have the peony
core repository right away and you
can see the Punet core. If we go back to Punet itself, we have
the Peernet CMD also. And yeah,
this is the best way to get started. Just clone the repository, build it and
get started. And if you want to find more information about Peernet, you can also
go to peernet.org and
you can actually download the browser from here and get started
right away with Peernet itself.
And of course the last point is join
our Discord channel. We'd love to discuss your
ideas to use Peernet or your
feedback or how you would like to use Peernet in the future.
For your development. So thank you for tolerating
me. Or thank you for listening to this talk today. And I hope to see
you next time. Or we hope to meet you soon in our Discord channel.
Thank you,