Hi everyone, thank you for coming for my talk today. We're going to
talk about TDD, test driven development in legacy
code. I'm Gil, I'm the
one on the left, not the one reading the book. And I'll
be with you for the next few minutes talking about TDD.
So first of all, I'm Gil, I'm coming to you from Israel.
I'm a consultant and trainer and do all kinds of workshop
and teach people,
developers, testers, automation people,
agile people, whatever, to write better software.
And this is what I do. I'm also
the author of two books, everyday unit testing, everyday spring testing.
This is the Java thing and we mostly
in Python today, although there's going to be one couple of slides that
talk about Java. You can get me@testingil.com or everydayunitetesting.com,
which is the book site, and I'll leave on Twitter so you
can actually meet me there if you have any questions afterwards
and so on. Test driven development
TDD, it's a methodology of writing
software,
although it has test in it. Basically we have three
steps. Red, green refactor, we call them. Red is when we
write the test and the test fails for any
reason. Second one is green when we write
just the code to make it work.
And then we refactor because once we
have tests and everything's passing, until now, we can
actually move stuff around and refactor it. How does it look?
Like I said, it's going to be but of Java here, before we jump into
the code. So we have a test.
You see that the squiggly lines under the calculator class,
because I haven't created it yet. So the id
will shout what are you doing? What are you doing with that?
And that's okay because the test can fail because it doesn't compile.
Then we add the code. You can see that, no more squiggly lines.
I have the calculator there and I've added the method and I have two parameters,
Inj and this works on it. I can
make it a bit more readable and I can transform inj
to something a bit more readable, which is first number and second number.
And this is the refactoring bit. And I can do this over
and over and over and over and over again and it sounds.
Could it be that easy? It could be.
It usually is. Unless we're talking about legacy code.
Because we have legacy code.
It's not like the calculator examples, right?
It works very well in new stuff, but examples
are usually too simplistic when you look it up and you
probably look at it and say, well, yes, but it probably
won't work on my code. We have a
lot of dependencies in our code, and that means
we usually focus on the code that we're writing, mock everything else
if needed, or so it depends on what we're doing.
If we have a lot of dependencies, we might need to mock a
lot. Tests become crappy and coupled to the
code, not what TDD aims
us to do. So we say, well, we need to change the code,
but we haven't written tests for the code. So thats means
that the code resists and we don't want to break stuff
whenever we are in the process. And we've heard about
a new development process, TDD included,
you want to introduce it because you've heard that it's good,
but you don't want to break anything that you've done until now because
you put a lot of effort into that. So we
don't want to change the code, but we probably could do that
fairly simple or fairly easy if we had tests to tell
us while you're breaking stuff. But we don't.
But it is a good thing to do. And this is what,
the main thing I want you to remember from this talk, it's not
like the techniques,
it's how this
affects your time and somebody else's time. Because everything we
talk about in software processes, like good software processes,
whether it's TDD or automation test automation
or design reviews or code reviews, it really doesn't matter.
Whatever we do and other people do as well,
is really making sure that we
consistently deliver code and we don't waste
time on other stuff.
And everything that we do when we
are afraid to move code around because we might
break anything that extends the time to
delivery. When we read logs
and kind of read code, when we're trying to bugs features
and understand what it does because it's not readable. That's about time.
If the code was more readable, if we had tests around, it would
be easier to change it, fix it quicker and
get it to something that's working to deliver
it. Also, new features,
we love working on new features. But again,
if this requires us not just to write new code,
but code inside other code that works,
it's going to take time. So every process
that we're talking about, clean code,
unit testing, integration tests, we're going to
talk. But today on TDD, code reviews,
design reviews, every process that is basically
other people are doing it or you're doing it to make code better,
don't think about it on making code better, think about
how to make a better
use of your time. Because if things are working,
you'll waste less time on the debugging stuff, on the reading logs,
on staring at code,
trying to understand what it does. You'll be quicker
to move over these hurdles and get to something that
we like getting working code
out there very quickly. So TDD
included in that, it's about respecting your time.
Now, I'm going to
take the principles of TDD and I'm going to look
at them got in the whole cycle thing,
but also in principles. So the things I want to do
though is I'm going to start with legacy code, is that I
don't want to break anything. Now with TDD, it's about
writing a test and then you
haven't written the code in because how can you?
That's TDD.
But before you do that, what about the code that you already
have? So how do you know that
you haven't broken anything that worked?
Now, if you're looking at a UI or something, you probably know,
but if you're looking at the code of a component and you're going
to add stuff to it, how do you know that the code, the remaining code
in that component still works?
Think about that. Try to answer that.
Then we're going to talk about how to add tests. I'm not going to teach
you uni tests in this session.
I'm assuming that it's easy to pick
up. I mostly in
my courses, but very little on tools,
more about how you use them. But then we're going to add
tests according to what we want to do and
then we're going to add code.
Right? And after we tdd the code, we're going
to do some refactor. Refactoring, for the
benefit of our session is changing the
way the code looks without changing its functionality.
It could be ruining it for the worst, but we don't
do that here. That's basically refactor. It could be like renaming
it could be like adding blank white space or blank lines
to make code readable. That's refactoring too. And it could be
something a lot more complex. Like I'm going
to show you something thats can be done manually.
Sometimes it can be done by the ide.
The complex ones are usually you need an
ide for that. And that's basically it.
Once you get the ideas of what you're doing, you can do these steps
and if TDD, regular, proper TDD is like
every ten or 15 minutes, you'll have something working, something new working
because you're working in small steps. You may not have this kind
of cycle, but you'll have a cycle and this cycle works and you'll
be able to trim it to focus on the small things.
And once you get small things working, that is the most
important thing. Small things working all
the time, you'll see that you get quicker to deliver.
And this is where my personal advice comes
in. TDD is the best way, the best,
and I've experienced a few to deliver
working code consistently in a consistent manner.
You can sure fire without test something thats
works fairly well once,
but if you're building something for a few weeks,
even a few weeks, not mentioning months, TD is the
best way to go because every time you pass a
test, you'll be able to show something. Well, I know at this point all
what I've written is working.
I'm going to show you two examples of how you can use TDD.
The first one is a bug fix and
the second one is adding a feature. And as you
probably know,
this is most of our lives. The application that
I'm going to show you is something that I've taken from my workshops.
It's a messy calculator, so we're going to
start with something that works. I know that I showed you examples of calculator before.
It's not going to be something like that. Our calculator is going
to be, it has two functions, two APIs.
One is pressing the keys.
It's not going to be a UI as messy as that, but it could be.
And you pass a string in.
And the other thing that we have
is a got display, kind of shows what's on the screen to
show it. And that's basically it. It's not complete and
it does all kinds of things in a very messy way.
So now I'm going to jump into the code, which is python code,
and see what's up. So let's
end the show. And we're in Pycharm.
Okay, so we're in the beginning and
the first thing I'm going to show you is what we have and
then I'm going to do the bugs fix.
So like I said, this is our calculator class
has a press method. You see this thing
here? It's called arrow code. Like if
else, if something like that, which is
something that you've probably seen, you've seen in the wild and
you know that it's something that's very hard to
add something to or fix something in it, because you don't know
what the effect would be on the other branches. So this
is something that we have. This is Python,
so it actually fits in one string in one screen.
We also have the get display method,
so self display. It features zero if
it's empty. And you
can see that it works with plus and Div,
but it doesn't work in minus and multiplying.
It's not complete. You have sort of calculation
here. And we have something that's weird here.
And the thing is, this is a good examples of something thats
somebody tells you, yeah, you go fix a bug and you're
not sure how to deal with that because
you haven't tested it yet. So this is where we start. I'm starting
with a very uni
testy generated code
coming from when
I create a unit test just does this. Absolutely, it fails
and that's it. I have code and I have a very
not useful tests. So what am I going
to do first? Talk about a bug fix. I'm going to do something
before that.
That something is called characterization test.
A characterization test is not a unit test or integration test. It's not a type
of test, but it's something that tells you how
the system is working. Now you usually do this by
operating the system and see what comes out.
And we have also all kinds of expectations of how it should work.
So I'm going to show you something that I've written, so calculators
stay the same for the beginning. And I wrote this
test that creates a calculator class. And I
feel that at the beginning, my expectation, it should
show zero. And when I press three,
it should show three. And this tests works.
It works according to my expectations. So I
take this and I multiply that, because I know that one test
will not be enough here. So I've written
and kind of refactor it in this way. So I'm creating calculator
once and I've accumulated all the things
that are working under the test successes.
So I'll share the code in a minute. But sulfate
star should show zero, pressing c should show zero,
pressing three should show three. You know this from the beginning. And then
we have three, plus should return three. Because this is an old calculator.
When you press an operation, the display doesn't change.
But when you write a number, operation number, it shows
only the last number. And I've added this,
all these things are working, which is cool.
But then I found out some things are not working,
so pressing plus at the beginning I expect it to
show zero, but it doesn't. And if I press zero three,
it doesn't show three because this is my expectation
of all calculators and it doesn't do
it. How do I know? I try it. I write these things and
you can see the code at the bottom. I also
have something that I thought was weird to work
and I was expecting something else,
but it fails. So I kind of created all kinds of
cases through it system. And now
I know what works and what doesn't because I know that what
works still needs to work at the end. How does it
look? Basically it's like wrapper methods using fluent
interface things. So I collect the result
at the start, pressing calls,
first reset and then press
for every character in a string. So I can actually
write this as a shorthand.
So it press three plus one plus four.
And finally it should show does the assert. So now
I have characterization test. I know this still
needs to work at the end and I can
add more here, but I decided to stop.
Okay, so now I know how the system behaves.
What are we going to do? So, going to fix a bug? The bug that
we're going to fix is, I think
one of the first one. I think it's this one, but I'll show you in
a minute.
So all the test successes, I move them into
test characterization. Haven't touched them.
Basically that's it. Just remove the features, because I want to see everything that's
failing in front of my eyes
rather than just obscured by all the other stuff.
So this is the bug fix I'm doing. So what I did here is,
first of all, let's define it. If I'm pressing plus,
oh, that's the first one. If I'm pressing plus and then zero,
I have a failure. I run it at this
point you'll see that I have a failure invalid
literal for int base ten. I'll show you what's the
problem in a minute. I've copied here all the
pressing and thats should show here, because I want something
that works first, I refactor the code later.
This is the separation between writing code for
functionality and changing the code for quality is
a whole separate thing. So that's the first thing.
I have a failing test.
Now let's look at what's causing it.
You'll see thats in this
line.
I'm trying to cast something that at the beginning is empty and I'm trying to
cast it to an int and that's the problem.
Cool. How do I fix that? Well,
now I have a test failing.
What's the most easiest way or
simplest way to pass the test? So apart from the if
that was here, I added another condition. If the
display is not empty, then do this. Then no
casting occurs. So now my test is passing.
Excellent. Excellent. Not completely. Why?
Because you can see that this pattern returns.
So my solution only works here.
So I probably need to duplicate it
in the things of oil. But I'm not just going to copy it. No,
because we're doing it in a better fixed way. Which means
we write three tests, one for each,
one for the plus, one for the div, one for the equals,
and then we can do
this thing. Now you're probably asking
why is he not using and or something like that? Because this
is the functionally working part.
Now that I've done this, I can refactor.
And the refactoring I did is if you look at
the pattern here is that if we
go in, these two are tied.
So once I have thats test working,
I actually created the method called parse key number and
probably need a better name and
basically put the check here. And if it's here
just return zero because this is what we want to display.
Otherwise we do the casting. And I put this
thing here because there's no point in duplicating the
code. It's not a major refactoring. I could do
a bit more than that, but I wanted to show you that a lot of
the times a bit of refactoring
is okay as well. Don't need to do a major refactoring
but we'll get to that in a minute. So are we done
here? Almost. Remember I copied things
from the main test mix, from the characterization tests,
the setup at start
pressing and should know I copied that into the bug fix as well
because I wanted things to work. But do I need
this application? No, I can refactor that application
out. So I'm going to refactor the test as well.
So I've created base class which has all called
base calculator tests. Has the pressing sheet no.
And the setup and then both the
characterization tests are inherit these things
and become a lot more shorter. And I've
also renamed the bugs fix thing for test calculator
at start. So before that, if you look at the bug
fixes descriptions or names I call them when pressing operation
at start should show zero and pressing div at start should show zero
and pressing equal at start should show zero. I can also reflect
the dome's name. So I put them at a class called tests
calculator at start and then I don't need at
start for everyone. This is also a refactoring in
strings, which is very cool. Makes things
a lot more easier to read.
We've done a bug fix. Well that's very cool.
Now let's talk about adding a feature.
Now the functionality. We're going to start at
the same point we are. But before we do, I want to show you what
we are going to add.
So we currently have a behavior that if
you press a number and then the operation.
Forgive the semicolon copy thing.
If you press can operation a number, thats the operation. You see the number
only. And we have that for plus and div. But we don't have minus yet.
And I want this got just to add minus as an a
key operation. I want to make sure thats the behavior of
pressing an operation after a number still
stays the same. So this is the case that we're trying to do.
But this time I'm going to take a bit another
approach. And this is refactoring the code based on what
we have right now. All the tests, the characterization test and the bug fixed test
that we have right now and try to see if we make it better.
So the risk of adding this new functionality becomes
less. So I'm going to take you through a
couple of refactoring patterns that make things simpler.
So we are here. So we have the test before we have the calculator
as before with a power ski number.
That's basically it. First thing I'm
going to do is look here. So remember I told you about the arrow
code. So error code is like you have. If it looks
like an arrow and you don't know what's working and thats is
going to be broken. We don't want it. How do you make an arrow less
of an arrow? And one of the techniques is called adding a guardrail.
So you see that if I have if do something else and
this is the last else in the function,
I can replace it with what we call a guard term.
So it looks like this.
If the key do something and return because
everything else is the else. I can just
move everything out of the else, shift it
to the left. And we already got something of less and
of can arrow. And you can do a got of the things with guard terms
like that. You usually do it
with validation and stuff like that. I showed you an example.
Next thing I'm going to refactor is, well, you look
at this, the if, this else,
this else and so on, it kind of screams that you
have like what we call a switch case or a match case. And I'm going
to use the match case from python 310
to replace these ifs with
a match case. Now this has to be manual.
No tool will do this. Very smartly for you. Very smartly
means guarantee that it works.
So you have to be a bit careful.
But you have some of the tests thats you already collected.
And if you're not really
satisfied with thats tests that you have, add more characterization tests
so you can feel covered. So how
does this look in 310?
So have a match key and cases in
all other languages, you don't need to go through
a dictionary of things. So 310 came
out in September. Think very good.
And the default is here we've
done the guard term, we've done the match case. What else
we see at least here a
repetition, it's can application. The only difference is the operation type.
So we can extract that into a method.
So let's see how
it looks like. I called it a handle op key and
I pass in the enum of the thing,
the operation that I'm doing, it's here basically
the same code extraction method. Extraction. And look at the code
that I have right now. First of all,
less of an arrow. A lot things
are separated by functionality. And now I
come to the point where, you know, what if I now TDD minus,
it will just work. Am I adding the minus? No, I'm adding
a test first. So that's the refactor bit. Let me close that up.
I'll close everything here so it
won't confuse us. I'm going to TDD a test.
This one, this is the tests I'm adding.
And this obviously fails on the color and calculator.
So I'm adding the code,
I added the minus to the enum and
TDD. Thats. And because all the behavior
regarding operation is already there and extracted
and you just need to call the right parameter and that makes
the test simply work. It's like magic
really. We worked hard at this magic, but it
just works. And do we refactor after that?
Yes. What kind of refactoring? Well, if you look at
the code of the calculator,
first of all, you see, well, this is already refactored.
This is not refactored yet. There's an opportunity to do that
and I'm going to do that. But before that, look at the
code that we have. So by extracting this code to
a method, we have something that's a higher level
of code than this one because this is like the implementation details
it was before that as well. So our
code, our press method,
really what it does, it talks in two different languages. And we
don't want that. We want the same language,
level of language at that thing. So extracting
this and extracting this will create
a higher level of, and the same level of
reading readability in this thing.
So I'm going to extract those into functions and
that's what's left. So I called handle equals, and the
rest is what handle number does.
And basically just extracting the code, nothing else.
And look how a simple it
looks right now and readable, you know,
where to look for things, where to add stuff and so
on. And it reads the same language,
the user language, rather than the implementation language, because you
don't see all the other variables
like staring you in the face. So things
to remember when you're doing refactoring. That's basically all the
code I wanted to show you today. So I want to
summarize what we did and the
principles behind them, because that's the more important stuff.
So first of all,
this is the most important stuff. You're introducing something new.
You don't want to break whatever else worked until now. You know that
from code, what I'm talking at the process level. So whatever you're trying
to do, including TDD, you're trying to minimize the risks.
And in order to do that, I've introduced you to characterization
tests. You lock in the behavior that works.
Now, sometimes it's not that easy to write them,
but sometimes it is. Sometimes it's not easy to
figure out what's expected. But that's okay.
Run it, you'll see what's happening. Then you add an assert to that.
So the more you feel you need
more tests, add more tests, that's okay.
Second thing is like you focus on
what you want to do,
where you want it. So we talked about adding a functionality.
In all the bug fix, we defined what we want.
We answered that question and only that questions. At the beginning,
we saw an opportunity to fix two more bugs.
We went back, added tests and added the code.
Then don't jump ahead, don't storm the code.
Final thing, the refactoring.
I refactored the code. I've refactored the tests. I came
back, I looked at it in terms of not do
I understand what it does? Because your programmers,
I'm a programmer eventually will
understand what it does. But does it take me
a lot to understand what it does or does it take me a short time
and do I know where to look for stuff and do I know where
to add stuff? So this is the thing that's
really important. And so refactoring really gets
to the point where next time I'm going to be here,
it's going to be less time than I probably would.
And that's basically it. That's how we are using TDD for legacy code.
Write a test, fix a bug, do it over and over and over
and over and over again. That's all I wanted to show you
today. So final words,
if you have questions, will be on the Discord channel
and you can get back to me@gilatestingguild.com.
On Twitter. I have an Instagram
channel. When you have all these memes going there, the bookstanggill.com.
I want to thank you for having me here today and
thank you and see you somewhere else.