Hi, thank you for joining me to talk about adoption and deprecation and
how to get everyone to use the internal developer platform.
I'm Omar Kahani. I'm a staff engineer in the infogroup at
SNC, where I lead platform teams. Building the internal
developer platform before we dive in a bit about the infra
group. We are three teams, but we're not doing any companywide
ops, DevOps or on call for everything.
We're building a paved path for other teams to lower cognitive
load and make their day to day happier and simpler.
As a result, if you want our solutions to be effective,
we need the teams to adopt it. It can be as simple as
a minor version of a helm chart, that provision postgres, or as
complicated as changing the git brand strategy.
Today, I want to show a framework with a set of practices that
can make migration and adoption successfully, fast and without
frustration. The framework is based on the technology
adoption lifecycle, first presented in 1957
and then republished and generalized in tools and
studies such as crossing the chess on the
lifecycle describe how technology is adapted in the general population
from zero to 100.
The model splits the market into buckets,
each with a different consumer behavior.
Using the same process, we can segment the RND and
have an adoption strategy for each group using
the model. We can also provide a systematical
way to show progress in the migration project.
Breaking down the model, we will now discuss each segment and the
tools and practices to apply to it. Also in
each segment, we will identify the relevant teams cases
on the criterias of the segments.
That mapping might change over time as teams change their
behavior. So do that exercise each time
before you start a migration project.
The first group is innovators, a small group of people
who get excited about new technology because it's novel.
People in this group are willing to pay the tax of using a product
that is not polished, has bugs, and lack any
necessary documentation for onboarding. As long
as they will be the first to use it, they will use it.
That willingness is a gift for us as we build
new solutions because we need design partners to build
with us that product.
So usually we will collaborate with ones or two teams
to test our assumptions and to test the product
that we build as we build it. Using design partners,
we will be able to build a more specific solution,
one that will work later on. For innovators,
we will look for teams that have application without risk
or low risk. We don't want application that will
impact customers if there is downtime or problems.
We also need teams that have time and are willing to
free time in their sprint for pairing with us and
make the effort to use our tool so we
know who they are, we know what to do with them. We are ready to
move to the next group. The second group is the early adapters.
This group still get excited about new technology, but they also need
to get a real value. Although they are willing to have some bugs
and figure out some things, they still need it to solve a real
problem for them. It's an excellent group to test
the product as is a moment before GA.
It's also a great group to validate and write the onboarding
guides that will help us support the majority.
Inside R D we will look for teams that have trust and
are willing to try things before they come GA. We also
need teams with time because the onboarding is not trivial
and there might be bugs that will require pairing time with us.
There's a lot more to talk about early adoptions, but I
want to talk about the next group first. The next group is
the majority, and as the name suggests, it's most of the organization.
In the model. It's about 68% of the population.
The majority cares about their day to day work and the
problems they have, and technology is only a way to
solve those problems. Therefore, approaching the majority
is completely different from the first two groups, not without a
reason. Crossing the Chessam put a gap between the early adopters
and the majority. From my experience, there are
two main reasons for failure with this group.
One is a product that doesn't solve a problem, but hopefully
doing user research, working with design patterns and
doing pocs, that's not the case.
The second reason is that the migration is too difficult.
Every product, technology, tool and practice that we use
should provide us a value, but the value get
lower by the effort it takes us to actually use that new tool.
At the left corner we can see great products, but the
effort to use them is so high that we wouldn't get any
value from them. On the right side, we can
see that the migration is so simple we can capture
all the value of the product. Good product and
low migration effort should be our goal.
There are two practices that we use at Snyk to make that
migration effort lower. The first is using
self serve tools. In one case, we upgraded
our internal deployment tools to have more options, but that
required every application team to change their deployment
configuration. That's a very high migration effort and we wanted
to lower that, so we automatically opened PR
for them, reducing the migration effort to a simple PR review
and a simple click on the merge button in GitHub
documentation can also lower that migration effort.
Use the early adapters to make sure the guides and the
docs are simple and clear for people without
prior knowledge. We also usually task
one of our teams members to follow the guide word
by word. He is not allowed to do anything that is not
strictly written in the guide so we can see where he gets
struggled and how we can improve our documentation.
The last group is the laggers. In the classic
model they hate change.
In the classic model this group hate change.
They hate it so much they never do it
unless they are forced inside the RND. Some teams
must be the last to adopt, but it doesn't mean they hate change.
There might be other reason for that.
It might be that they have a production critical application,
they can't suffer downtime and they don't want to take
any unnecessary risk. So they prefer to wait and
see the problems that other teams will have. They might have a legacy system,
one that no one is familiar with. So in
one of my previous companies we had those kind of legacy system
which was super difficult to make any change. And anytime
we wanted to change anything we had to group a lot of people
inside a room and understand the legacy system and how it's deployed in order
to make that change. Or they might need more time.
So think about that team that is currently on the hook to
deliver a very significant milestone to your company.
They don't have time to mess with their deployment process,
with the way that they provision cloud resources.
They need things to work and without any change.
So what can you do to make those team adopt your product?
What is the best thing we can provide them? We can
provide them knowledge just in time specific knowledge
for their application about the migration effort.
In other words, we can pair with them in that pairing session.
We will be able to provide the necessary knowledge to make the migration effort
as low as possible. While they can provide the specific
application context. Together we can make that change easy
and affordable. So to recap, we talked about
four segments, the innovators, our design
partners, the early adapters that will do pocs and
test our documentation, the majority,
both the early and the late, that will use our self serve tools
and guidance to make that migration.
And we talked about the laggers where we need empathy
and pairing time with them to complete that migration project.
We also talked about the majority and how they are a key group
to our success. So now I want to talk about
more tools and practices. Aiming to the majority,
we will talk about two practices, trust and sticks.
Trust is part of every buying decision we make.
A while ago we bought a home coffee machine because we thought
the coffee at home will be better than a coffee in the coffee shop.
The first way to build trust is by celebrating our early adopters success
and even using them to demo and explain the problem and
the solution in their own words. So at Snyk
there is A-R-D sprint demo which is an excellent platform
for those kind of celebration. Find the best place to celebrate
those in your company and in fact make it a
rule. A PoC must end with as many
people hearing about it. Speaking about early adoptions,
let's go back and add another criteria. Early adoptions
must represent as many use cases and groups as possible.
Trust is established by people close to you with
a similar use case, but trust is also established by
people. You value their opinion. In every group, organization and
community there are always individuals that can
reach out and influence people's decision because people trust
and value their opinion. In SNCC, those are group
level staff engineers which can influence the group practices.
In one of our first migration projects, we intended
to replace the continuous delivery system. This was a
fundamental change to an historical process inside SNCC.
Not only that, but everyone inside the group was
less than a year in the company and wasn't in the position
to build trust with the whole organization.
We had to use other people for that. So after
identifying them, we engaged with them in a series of meetings where
we presented our assumptions and shared the blueprints of the final
process. It was even before design patterns,
very early in the process, after sharing our
thinking process and our results, we asked
them, where do you see problems now? It didn't
meant that we implemented everything that came up right away,
but it helped us to prioritize and help us segment R
and D. For example, we knew some teams can be
early adopters because they have some special use cases that is not
yet covered. Besides that, they had become ambassador for
the majority. We saw that in slack threads where
someone was suddenly saying that the infragroup is working to solving that
specific problem and please engage with them.
And when it came to the actual adoption, they were able to
explain it and build trust. With all the r D
so far we were friendly. We tried to do a natural adoptions,
but sometimes sticks must be pulled.
Sticks can be as simple as a support deadline.
In four or six weeks we will stop support the old version,
but support deadline need to be realistic. If the organization
is working in two weeks prints you probably need to put
four or six or even 80 weeks in advance to give teams
the times to add it to the next prints.
The other stick that can be used is getting high level manager support
so they will instruct teams to create time for the migration.
Use high level manager support. You don't want to force
every change across the organization. You want to be
able to create natural adoption and have lightweight sticks
like the support deadline. Sticks are not excuse
for not doing anything else. Trust, good product,
self serve migration all must be used before sticks
and in fact if you do them it will be even easier to use those
sticks and get high level manager support and people will
be less frustrated when you introduce any forcing mechanism.
So to summarize, we talked about the technology adoptions
cycle and how to segment our R D organization the
different approaches for each segment. We talked about migration
difficulty and how it affects the majority. We talked about
trust and how to establish it. And finally we talked about sticks and
forcing change. For anything else please reach
out on Twitter. Thank you.