My name is Ricardo Castro, and today we're going to talk about CI CD and
build deploy automation. Let me start by thanking the organization for
accepting my talk, and let's get on with it. So what do we have
on the menu for today? So we're going to briefly talk about CI
CD. What is CI? What is CD? We're going to
talk about regular development workflow and what
are some of the alternatives that we can find to actually employ CI
CD within our organizations. Before I leave you, I will
say, what's the problem with all of this and why
I'm talking about this topic? And I will leave you guys
with some reading material. If I was in
front of you, I would ask the following question, who here is practicing CICD?
And a lot of people will probably say, I am practicing CICD,
but let's think a little bit about it and let's see if we are really
doing CI CD or if we are only having
build and deploy automation. Let's start from the beginning. What is CI?
So according to Grady Brochure, CI is the practice
of merging all the developers working copies to a shared
mainline. Also, we can go into the Reddit definition and saying that
a successful CI means that new code changes to an app are regularly
built, tested and merged to a shared repository. It is
a solution to the problem of having too many branches of an app
in development at once that might conflict with another. And of course,
my favorite one is from Dave Farley. So CI, it's the idea that
we can do a better job if we maintain a clear picture of how changes
work alongside everyone else as they progress. So why
do we need CI? So we need CI to reduce risks.
So when we introduce changes, we want those changes to be less
risky as possible, when to decrease the number of bugs. So if we introduce
less changes, we, in theory, have less bugs. Also,
we want to minimize the integration issues. So if
we have smaller changes, it means that those changes won't have as many
integration issues as they could have with
bigger changes. And of course, it's a precursor to CD CD meaning
continuous delivery. So what is CD?
CD can stand for continuous deployment or continuous delivery,
and it's a software engineering approach in which software functionalities are
delivered frequently. Again, I'll resort to Dave Farley and
his definition of continuous delivery. So continuous delivery is the
ability to get changes of all types that could include features,
configuration changes, bug fixes or experiments into production or
into the hands of our users. And that intends
to be done safely and in a quick and sustainable way.
So why do we need CD? So we want low risk
releases. So by deploying frequently and putting frequently
changes in front of our users, we have lower risk releases.
We want fastest time to market, so we want to release features
and want to release changes as fast as possible. By releasing smaller
releases and more frequently we would
achieve higher quality because we are continuously delivering and iterating.
And of course we also incur in lower costs, better products
and overall happier teams. So bundling
this all together, what is CI CD again? Dave Farley
how we build better software faster. But we can also resort
to other definitions, for example from red app. So CI CD is a methodology
to frequently deliver apps to customers by introducing automation
into the stages of app development. Or we can go to the
knowledge of all the Internet, which is Wikipedia. So in software engineering,
CI CD is the combined practices of continuous integration and more
often continuous delivery, and less often continuous deployment.
Some people distinguish between continuous delivery, a continuous deployment.
So let's go from the start. So continuous integration,
frequently merging several small changes into a
main branch. So continuous delivery, it's when teams produce
software in short cycles with high speed and frequency, so that
reliable software can be released at any time and with
a simple and repeatable deployment process when deciding to deploy.
And continuous deployment is when software functionality is rolled
out completely automatically. In practice, some people
use continuous delivery and continuous deployment interchangeably.
But the idea here, if you were to separate between continuous delivery and
continuous deployment, it means that continuous integration, you build your
software, you test it, and you merge that into some form of main branch.
With continuous delivery, you get into a point that
the software is ready to be put in front of users. And continuous deployment
is the process where you actually put software in front of
your users. In practice, what does that mean? CI CD.
So CI CD, there's not a strict rule, but as
a rule of thumb, we should do CI CD at least once per day.
This means that we should integrate code at least daily from all
developers on a team, and it should be put in front of users at least
daily. So Dave Farley says that
CI, for example, should run under 5 minutes. So your CI
process should run whatever it is, should run under 5 minutes.
Charity major says that your whole process for CI CD should run under
15 minutes. And according to the door report, elite performers
perform Cit under 1 hour. So those are the teams that are
really performing, and they have their whole process from
having some form of code to be merged, tested and deployed,
and that should be done in under an hour. So to
refute what CI CD is we would
need to contradict the Dori board, which is the best approach and
the best way that we have at the moment. What is your development workflow?
And if we were face to face, I would ask and get some feedback
from all of you. But let's go into a typical workflow
that exists in many organizations. So feature branches.
So most companies have some form of main branch
or master branch from which they do feature branches.
So what is a feature branch? In theory, a feature branch is
a branch where you develop an entire feature for your product. So my question
would be, what would be the process? By using feature branches, you are
probably doing pull requests, right? So you have
a master branch, you create a feature branch to develop some kind of feature,
when you're ready for that to be tested, that you
open a pull request that someone will review,
and then eventually it will be merged on a main branch.
So pull requests are usually tied with code reviews.
So code reviews are used to ensure,
in theory, are used to ensure that code, that your code
is actually doing what it is supposed to do and adhering to
some rules that are pre established. So what
is the number one reason for code reviews? Usually the
code reviews are done. So to ensure that
code don't like tests and
that it follows all the best practices.
The problem with this is that prs are slow. So you do
a branch, you submit a pull request, you do a code review and it eventually
gets merged. So let's just go through an example scenario.
So you make a change, you submit a pr to be approved.
It takes some time for someone to pick up that pull request and do
the review. Let's say 10 minutes, 1 hour could be a week. Let's say,
for example, 10 minutes. So someone stopped working.
So you will be at least 10 minutes waiting for someone to review that
pr. Then it needs to be reviewed. If everything is okay, you'll get a
thumbs up. If not, you'll have to go back and forth with the reviewer
to have your changes up to the standard theyre supposed to be.
And then you'll have to be waiting while this iteration is going.
This means that CI, so if we want to follow theyre CI practices,
we need to do this multiple times a day. So let's imagine a team
of four, five, six, whatever number of engineers,
everyone, to follow this CI CD mindset.
Everyone would have to do this multiple times a day. So people will
keep getting interrupted to do, for example, course reviews on prs.
How often do you really want to be interrupted daily?
And how many reviews
can you actually do per day. And for CIT to work again,
you need to do at least one review per change per day.
So what we can do is to bad changes, which means no
CI CD, it's also async, and there's no two way communication.
So what are some alternatives to this? So an alternative
is to use trunk based development. This means that you
can submit directly to a master or trunk or a main branch,
or you can create short lived branches and that can be merged
directly, directly to a main branch.
So the data from the state of DevOps report is clear.
Trunk based development predicts higher throughput and better stability,
and even higher job satisfaction and lower rates of burnout. And this comes
from the DevOps Handbook. You could be asking yourself, yeah, but with PRS,
we have code reviews. We can also do that with trunk based development.
You can do, for example, pair programming, right? So the idea of pair programming
is that, for example, two engineers are working on the same piece of code,
and they are reviewing while one is writing and the
other is reviewing and they are discussing the changes.
But pair programming usually has some kind of criticism.
Dismissify some of that criticism. So the first criticism is
inefficiency. So it means that two devs working on the same code is
wasteful resource. In practice, that's false.
And we have evidence that can be found in the case for collaborative
programming by John Nosek.
Another criticism, it's that it is uncomfortable. So most
people who try find out in reality that it's
not the case, but this one is down to personal preference. The other
criticism is lack of focus and
intrusion, which is also false. Pairs are usually able
to sustain a better focus than an individual alone,
and then we can see evidence of that on a comparison
of solo and pair programming in terms of flow experience,
coding quality, and coding achievement. In the Journal of Education and Computing
Research. The other criticism that the
pair programming has is the fact now that we work
a lot remotely, that we will have to, people have to be working
remotely on pair programming, and the problem might
be, for example, different time zones. So we can try and find a
middle ground here. So I stole the fluid pull request
name from my colleague Marcelo, but this idea
is something that I've been doing for some years now, and it's the idea
that we have some kind of a middle ground between a full pull request and
a trunk based pull request. This means that you'll have policy
specifications so you can specify which changes,
which changes are low risk and can be automation
merged, and who are the best people to review these
changes. And all of those are policies that are pre established before
you start developing. So you need to trust developers to
merge before code reviews are done. And you need to keep track
of those pull requests that should be reviewed after much.
So the idea here is
that you have code reviews is that
you have some sort of policy which can tell you,
for example, if this change needs to be reviewed by someone or
can be automatically merged. For example, you can have, for example, changes to
some sort of documentation automatically merged. But some
changes, you can flag them as critical, for example, and someone needs
to be assigned for review. And that can also be a policy
that is specified and a specific person
can be assigned to that review. So we've been talking a lot about CI CD,
and if you've noticed, I haven't spoken so far of
any tool, any pipeline, nothing. So I haven't talked about the
well established build service
like Jenkins or Azure DevOps or other
types of tools, because CI
CD is not about a tool, it's about a practice.
So stealing from Simon Sinek,
the golden circle so the why of
CICD is for us to build better software.
So how can we do that? By having faster feedback.
And what can we do to achieve faster feedback is to have build servers,
pipelines, et cetera. But the idea here is that
just because we have build and deploy automation, it doesn't mean that we are doing
CI CD. So we need tools and automation to do this
at scale, of course. So speed reduced efforts,
but theyre are helped by these tools, pipelines and build servers,
but theyre are not required. So why do people usually stop
here? Because usually some automation in and on itself is
already very valuable. So you get the speed of just having
stuff automated. Another reason is because people are fearful
and they lack some trust on other people.
So this means that we actually have to enforce some
kind of rules. And of course it also needs some investment. You have to build
the tools from the ground up to support all
of this. But in essence, what CI CD tries
to achieve is this, shorter development cycles. We want to
increase security, we want compliance and development process in our whole process,
and we want higher quality code. So before I leave you,
I'll leave you guys with some reading material. So of course,
two of the bibles in continuous integration and continuous delivery are
the continuous delivery and continuous integration book.
Regarding the Dora report, you have the very good
accelerate book which describes the whole scientific process that
is behind the generation of the Dora report.
And like I said before, the term of fluid pull requests I told
from my colleague Marcelo, but I'll leave you here with a link for his
blog post from his company and a talk that he
gave at the DevOps portal and DevOps tools portal meetup
about fluid pull requests, and I highly advise for you guys
to see that talk and have a better sense of what fluid pull requests
could be. So in summary, so we talked about what is
CI and what is CD. So CI is the idea that we
merge changes from all the engineers into some sort of
branch, at least daily. And CD is the process
that we get those changes in front of our users and iterate quickly. The usually
development workflow in most companies uses feature branches.
So we have some sort of main branch, we perform some
form of feature branch, we develop our entire feature. We submit
a pull request which is reviewed and then eventually gets merged and
deployed. The problem with this is that feature branches are usually long lived,
which means that it's very hard to do deployment
CI CD. So do that daily with
feature branches. So what can we do? We can use, for example,
trunk based development, which is the idea that we create short lived branches and
continuously merge them and deploy them to production.
To ensure that we have code reviews, we can use pair
programming to actually continuously review the
code while we develop. Or we can use some middle ground between full
pull requests and pair programming by using the concept
of fluid pull requests. So what's the problem with all of this?
The problem with all of this is that usually people employ some kind of
tool or some kind of pipeline and assume they're using CI CD. But as we
see in practice, we haven't talked about any tool
or any pipelines in specific, and we only talk about the philosophy build
in between CI CD. So CI CD is a lot more powerful
than just having build and deploy automation. And before
I point you guys to some reading material that
would be useful to expand on these topics. And that's all from
my part. I hope you guys enjoy enjoyed this talk.
I hope you enjoy the conference. Don't hesitate in contacting me
through social. Thank you very much for attending my talk and
have a great conference.