Welcome to this Javascript session.
Canvas pixel manipulation beauty comes slowly.
This Conf 42 talk is basically
a coding session, which I call pseudo
live coding session because, well, it's pre recorded
and it will deal with the Javascript canvas API
and in the second part with the
usage of web workers to ease user interactions
when there's a lot of computations to
do. So these are learnings I
had on a personal project called Mosaics,
which transforms a
map into a color
map with kind of mosaic delimited by
roads. I'm Victor.
I'm a lead developer at Theodo company
based in Paris. Well, as for the Paris
office. So where exactly in Paris
is Theodo based? So you
can have a look at this beautiful map on maposeic.com.
Maybe you can recognize Paris map if
I zoom a little bit. Well,
Theodo is kind of here,
so it takes a few seconds to compute it.
We'll discuss it later, but after a few seconds
we have a beautiful mosaic.
Towns are beautiful, but such is the countryside,
such as this town in Borgoin.
This is actually the place where I had the id
during the containment to draw automatically
maps delimited by roads. So I
was doing it by hand and that's how I
looked at the canvas. So our
goal today is to build this
mosaic from scratch.
In order to do so, I have a small project
running on localhost, a small react app
that displays a map on the left and on
the right. We are going to progressively
build our mosaic.
So let's have a look at the code. I have a
react app with typescript,
and here is a component called canvas demo that renders
on the left the mapbox container,
and on the right the mosaic container that we're going
to fill. So what exactly is Mapbox?
Mapbox is a great library that
allows you to build a maps. Just calling
Mapbox map a new object that
is initialized with the container.
I pass the reference of the container a
style. So here the style is a satellite maps,
a zoom level between zero and 22,
I think, and a center to initialize
the map with. So here I put
a random longitude latitude so that we are
able to travel a little bit.
And when the map is rendered, I call this
unrender function that console log renders
and stop the loading the
loading indicator.
So if I refresh,
you can see that there are a couple of, couple of renders.
Okay, so our first steps
for pixels manipulation, we are going to first paint a rectangle,
then access the rectangle pixels. We're going
to paint the pixels randomly we're going to
set the size to look like the map box size,
copy its pixels, apply a transformation,
and then we'll apply the area detection
algorithm to paint the mosaics. So let's
first add this rectangle.
So I initialize a constant with
the canvas element that I get by id.
So this is a reference to this id,
a canvas HTML element.
Then I need to access its context. Okay,
so there are a couple of different contexts available
and I'm using the 2d context.
And then the mosaic context is possibly
null. So if it is null,
let's just return. Okay.
Then I say, okay, I want you to fill with the
style color magenta and fill a rectangle
at the initial position. So top
left corner with the canvas
dimensions. So how does it look?
Well, we have a beautiful, very beautiful magenta
rectangle with the canvas
default size actually. So 300
by 150 pixels. Okay,
so that's a good first step. Then we're going
to look at the pixels because
this is an image. So we
should be able to see what this is composed of.
So the mosaidata is actually
the context on the context. I call this method
guest image data with the top left
corner and the size of the data I want.
Okay, so if we
console log it,
what do we get? Okay,
image data. So you see there is three properties
and we're console logging the data directly.
Okay, so we have an array of numbers,
actually eight clamped numbers.
So clamped means that they're between zero and 255.
And actually each pixel
is composed of four numbers, the RGB
and a values. So that's what I put here.
So our pixels are indexed
from top left to bottom right. The first
pixel is this one. And each pixel is
composed of four numbers. Okay, so magenta
is a mix between blue and red.
Okay, so having that, let's paint
the pixels. So we're going to paint them
randomly.
So this size is not defined canvas
width and height canvas.
And let's iterate over the data of
the data. And at
each pixel index I,
we assign random pixel
value, a random number
between zero and 255. And then
once we have this, we need to apply to
the context, the new image data with
the put image data method.
Okay, so now you can see that
we have kind of mosaic,
actually a lot of pixels with random columns.
And each time the map box renders,
map renders, we have a new computation.
So maybe I could just display the console here.
Okay,
now we want to set the same size as
for the mapbox shape.
So we need here to access
the mapbox canvas. Okay,
so the same way we're going to use
a mapbox context, which this time will not be the 2d context,
but instead the Webgl context because mapbox
uses webgl API and we'll
set our mosaics canvas width and height with the
drawing buffer width and height of the mapbox context.
Okay, so we'll
need to do this before.
And the map is actually the object we just
constructed here.
So we need to pass a maps to our function map
gl dot map object.
Okay, so the same way this context may
not be it presence.
Okay,
so what do we got here? We got actually a huge
canvas that is twice the desired size.
This is because on
retina screens mapbox renders twice
as much as pixels per directions.
So actually I need to fix the CSS size
to access the CSS size here.
So if I put a width of let's say 644,
it's not going to make it.
Okay, now we're good. So we need to do it in
the code. So that's
why I use this.
So I use the style property of our HTML
elements and I set it to a string
necessarily with the size divided by two.
So you see that the width of the canvas must not
be confended with
the style width property.
Okay, so it started looking nice.
What do we have to do now? So we are going to copy mapbox
pixels. So in order to copy mapbox pixels
we need to get Mapbox pixels. So actually
we're going to use the Webgl
API before
or after this? Yeah, actually I don't
need to console like this.
Okay, so I construct a new
int number array of the correct
size. So width times height times four
because each pixel has four coordinates.
And to write the pixels in this array
I need to call the read pixels method on the mapbox
context with initial positions,
the size and some other constants and also
the reference to my constant. Okay, so now
I have the mapbox pixels so I'm able to
copy them.
Okay, nice. So it's
not actually done yet in Shemando
Taranel because you see Shemanda Taranell
here is written on the opposite side.
This is because the mapbox, the Webgl convention
started in the bottom left.
So we need to apply some transformation
to our pixels. So here I wrote some
utils to be able to do that.
So it considers that we have an x and y axis
and each index position can allow
us to find the x and y point
position. So basically
when we start to find a
transformation from one canvas to the other,
I have the I position in the index
position in the mosaic reference,
I convert it into an x and y point.
Then this point in the mapbox canvas
is just the same, but with a transformation
on the y axis. And then with this
calculus I get the
map box index, pixel index.
So I just need to call this
little functional
it.
Okay, then I get the mapbox pixel index.
So now we recreate,
so that we could completely paint
access the pixels of a
map. So we are going to apply our
detection algorithm.
So let's describe a bit this detection algorithm.
So the source is basically binary color image
and the target is going to be a
colorful image.
So I have to detect three areas here in this
image. So how do we do? We iterate over
all pixels of the image and we make
sure we delimit the contour of
the image. So this is a zoom.
Well, not actually a zoom, but yeah, with very big pixels
our source. And we'll iterate from
top left to bottom right with this eye
index. And we are going
to detect first this black area.
So the source color is black and we want a target
color of Xiong.
And we call this routine paint area which push
the index in a stack, in a two visit stack.
And while this stack is not empty,
it pops an element and
paints this element.
Then it
looks at the neighbors of this element.
So there is one at east, south,
southwest and north, and the west
and north pixel are not considered here.
And if the neighbor color is
of the same color,
which is black, it pushes it
in the two visit stack. So it will push here the south
pixels. And once the
stack is empty, Webgl have this
first area painted.
Then it takes the next pixel,
well that we haven't visited. So each time we
visit a pixel, we also mark it as visited and
it paints the white area the same way.
Then these two pixels have already been
visited. So the next pixel will be this one and
the target color this time will be burgundy,
which is Bordeaux. And here we go.
So I just need to call
this transformer.
Instead of doing this,
I have a class canvas data transformer,
which is actually the implementation of the previously described
algorithm, which has,
well, is contrasted with a source pixel array,
a target pixel array, a size, and it
generalizes a visited pixel
sex. The paint target data is
the main method and it will do what I previously
described. Okay, for each area
that we have not visited, it calls the pen current
area method, which initialize
this tag, et cetera.
Okay,
let's look for example at the method adjacent points.
This is the method that gives the
neighbor of a point.
So for each point, each point has four neighbors,
southeast, west and north.
Okay, so having this, we'll call
the transformer method,
paint target data.
And now what we have from our
transformer, we can get the
target pixel array.
So actually put image data,
receives an image data. So actually it's the image
data that we need to pass here and
we need to set. Actually we cannot set
it like this. We cannot assign data to a value because it's
a read only property. So we use the set method.
Okay,
let's look at it.
It's working even with this
shape, which is quite nice.
So we have a threshold, although it doesn't
work very well with full colored
images because we just have a threshold to detect white
areas. So that's why I'm using now another
style for our Mapbox mile maps,
which is a road style that I customized.
So that's what is really nice with Mapbox is that
there is an application tile
studio or something. Yeah.
Where you can customize your map styles.
And this is the one I created
to be able to render the
map. So actually we're facing here,
I'm facing some user interaction
problems because all the computation is
taken by
my algorithm and it blocks the UI.
So with difficulties here,
I want to drag, but I can't get
it. So even if I want to see the Kamarg,
I'm going to have a lot of troubles to do this.
So that leads me to the second part of this talk,
which is how to ease user
interaction with a web worker.
So we want to run the process of the
algorithm in a web worker. So why do we want
this?
Web workers are a simple means for web content to run
scripts in background threads. That's perfect. The worker
thread can perform tasks without interfering with the user interface.
Okay, so basically, how does it work?
Basically we initialize a worker with a file
and we send on
the worker side, we have an on message function
that listens to messages, do the jobs,
and then pass the result to the main thread.
Okay, so the problem is
for us is that we cannot use this for me,
actually, I cannot use this directly because webpack
is going to build the application and the URL is
not going to be available anymore. So that's why
I need to use a worker loader.
So worker loader is a webpack module that
I already installed in my node modules.
Okay.
So I just need to import the
worker with this syntax. And actually this syntax is to
make webpack understand to load the file with the worker
loader. So what
I also had to do is to eject my create react
app to be able to
override webpack configuration.
So that's what I did and this is what my config
looks like. So I'm using customize.
Correct. But it's basically the same syntax as the
one we just saw. Okay,
so I'll import.
Okay, we also have in this documentation
a typescript hint that indicates
you to declare a new module so that web
worker is understood by typescript.
Okay, so this
is where my custom typing is.
I have here a paintworker that
initialize. Well, there's a constant that
we call the on message method on.
And when we receive a message, I will console log the
message.
So new
worker. And the URL is it.
So our worker is paint
worker. Okay. And const
worker, new worker.
That's what we're supposed to do.
Yeah, you'll need this because
there's a rule added by create react
app that
doesn't want you to use this syntax because they
don't want to be bound to webpacks actually.
So that's why to ignore next line.
Okay, is there any
log? No, because we haven't passed any message to
our walker. So before we do all this transformation,
we'll pass a message.
Work on this please.
And Webgl listen to the
response.
The worker received the message, which is a message
event with the data. Work on this piece
and in the other side we
receive the response.
Got it? Okay, so now we're going to be
able to put this in
our walker so
it's not the maps box pixels, so work
on our data. We're going to initialize
it with the data we want.
Okay. And this is actually an object with
the type I created and.
Yeah, sorry,
worker payload. Yeah, worker payload
is an object with what I need here.
And we're going to use it in
our class, in our constructor,
so there is no event anymore.
Okay. And then when I call the transformer paint
target data, I will pass the
data that was just painted.
Okay. And here I need,
instead of doing this,
I'm going to call the worker with the payload
and target pixel array will be
the mosaic data, the data.
The source pixel array will be the walker,
the mapbox pixels and
the size of the canvas.
And we'll post this
payload and on the
reception so it's the same data which
is a worker response type UIT
array I
can console receives.
And then we'll set the Masai data to this
new data we just received and
then put image data, the new image data and
set is loading inside the on message function.
Okay,
reorder to type our
magenta pixel and
you see that the UI is not
blocked anymore. However, there is
a lot of render that are triggered.
The worker previously is doing jobs
that are outdated. So to prevent this I
can terminate the worker job each time I'm
about to do a new render.
So this aborts the
worker and it's also killed it. So I need to recreate it.
That's why I want it to be a variable.
Okay, and now you see that the worker is not
doing any unnecessary renders.
This is the only message response I
received. Okay, so now
we are done with our beautiful mosaic.
As for a conclusion, as you can see,
my solution is quite slow,
so the algorithm is quite long
to compute. So for example, for the 5 million pixels
I have on my full
screen, it takes up to 5
seconds, so it's very long indeed.
So how could I improve this? So first I asked myself,
why does mapbox map render
so quickly? So first they apply only
on layers, so they have a background, for example.
Then they apply a layer of road, then a layer
of forest, so they don't need to fill the whole image
pixel by pixel.
And then they use the Webgl API which allows you to
draw shapes very efficiently thanks
to vertex arrays.
So maybe I could inspire
with this with a new algorithm. Algorithm that would
follow the road with the GPS
coordinates and find the intersections
to delimit the area's vertexes
and then apply a layer with these
vertexes. Another,
another option. I asked
myself why a software like Photoshops is
so fast to detect areas. And one
hypothesis is that it uses all the
capabilities of the operating system.
So I would like to try to
run my process with binary instructions which
can be compiled with webassembly
and maybe it could improve.
Well, it would be interesting to see the gain with this,
so if you have any suggestion, don't hesitate
to contact me. So I put my email
address here. Thank, thanks a lot for your attention
and I hope you'll do
some great drawing with the canvas API.