Hello there. Good morning, good afternoon, good evening. Whenever you
may be watching this, I'm excited to speak to you today on
my talk called nuclear rust fission powered code for the modern
world. I am John Darrington.
I work for the Idaho National Laboratory. Here in Idaho,
we have a laboratory.
The land we own is roughly the size of Rhode island.
We were behind the first city in America powered
with nuclear power. That was Arco, Idaho,
and we have been working for a long time with
nuclear energy and nuclear fuel, seeing what behaves,
what misbehaves, and working in that realm for
a very long time. And I'm excited to talk to you today about our
experience with the rust programming language and some
of the reasons why we chose rust and we went that direction.
So just a little bit about myself. My name is John Darrington
again. I'm the lead architect for the digital engineering department at
the Idaho Idaho National Laboratory,
work primarily with data management and work in
the digital twin and digital transformation spaces. I've also
been working primarily on a data management warehouse,
or data lake, more of data Lake at
this point, called deep links, and other various tools in that ecosystem.
I've been a software developer for over ten years, been working
in that realm, as well as just working with data management overall.
So let's get started with the fun stuff. This is the
preliminaries we have to get this out of the way. But let's start talking
about the fun, or in this case,
not so fun. If you were watching the news
back in 2011, you would maybe
recognize this image, and the scale of it might be a little hard to see.
You can see there's a truck off here to the
left here, a big crane truck.
This is one of the outbuildings of the. Or not the outbuildings.
One of the buildings of the Fukushima power plant.
And in 2011, a 15 meters high tsunami
disabled the power supply on three of the Dai Chi reactors.
All three of them largely melted in the first three days, and it took
until December to reach an official shutdown condition.
Now, why do I start with a
nuclear accident, so to speak,
for talking about rust and talking about our experience
with rust? Well, I think it's a little bit easy. So no
industry is immune from accidents, but all industries learn from them.
There have been three major accidents in the nuclear world
that we kind of refer back to three Mile Island,
Fukushima, and, of course, Chernobyl.
In every industry, there are accidents, and hopefully we learn from
those accidents. And programming, to be honest, is more
than an industry. It affects all these other industries.
In and of itself, and hopefully we learn from them. And I think that's kind
of where we get with rust. But let me
talk a little bit about where our department and where inl
kind of finds itself in the nuclear industry. So this is
the state of software industry in the nuclear world.
We are very risk averse for obvious reasons. I mean, it makes sense.
We're dealing with nuclear power, nuclear energy, things that could
go very spectacularly awry, as we've seen with Chernobyl,
and affect millions of people and cause untold
damage. So we are very risk averse
in this industry. We want to make sure that what we're doing is safe.
We want to make sure that it obviously comes in with
budget, but mainly it has to do a lot
with safety and making sure that we're doing the right things. Because of
that change is slow. We're so adverse to risk
that we worry about changing things too
rapidly and moving too far forward.
And so that kind of change is slow. It has to go through committees.
It has to go through the nuclear regulatory committee for
even running simple reactors.
It takes a while to get things moving. And in the same vein,
again, committees, everything's done by committee. It feels like we
have committees for software and cyber control. And it's
not bad things. That's what I hope to get through. It's not necessarily that
they're bad, but everyone in the committee has their
own goals, has their own experiences, and that can cause things
to be extremely slow. Again, risk averse change is slow. We find ourselves
in that industry, in just the software that we're dealing
with. And there's a very set way of doing things.
We've done this for years. It's been safe. We're not going to change it.
We're using this same exact microcontroller.
Weve used it for 20 years. Nothing's happened.
It must be safe. We're going to continue to use it. And it's hard to
push up against that because you're trying to introduced either new
technologies, new paradigms, and if something's worked
for 20 years, that doesn't necessarily mean it's better. It just means it's
worked for 20 years. And who knows that there might be a catastrophic failure
in the future. But again, it's a set way of doing things. And we
have to push up against that. Ancient protocols.
We are dealing with ancient network protocols,
ancient communication protocols between microcontrollers
and facilities. And so we have to
find technologies and
things that work in these ancient setups.
So again, this is where we find ourselves in the industry.
So this is the original slide that I put together in 2022
about why we felt the need to introduce a new programming
language, especially in the department.
At inL, for one, we have our
deep links data warehouse. We were using a high
level programming language and we needed lower level
programming language than we typically use. We were looking at embedding
it or using either webassembly or putting it
closer edge compute. We weve using a lot of node js,
and that's really not good for long term use by a department,
mainly because it has some performance issues. Again, it's cpu bound,
a single threaded great async for I o operations.
But if you're doing complex computations, no chances is definitely
not the right tool. And so again, that leads to a lack of
well adopted scientific computing, at least at the lab. And runtime requirements.
We have a lot of python, and while in use, again it
has a runtime, so it's not available for all deployment
pathways, especially on microcontrollers, or on
things that have either need to be very lightweight like DAs
data acquisition systems, or things that can't have
Python's bloated runtime on top of it. And yes there's Python, and yes there's whole
bunches of directions we can go there, but those are complex. And trying to
get data scientists to use that can be really difficult.
Performance is a concern for issues not covered by internal c libraries.
I think we've all seen that meme with
the really high performance speed car and says Python. And then it
zooms the picture out and it's Python on top of
this tow truck. That's C and C Plus plus. And that's
kind of what we're talking about. And then again, Python is extremely permissive and allows
the easy introduced of bugs. And if anyone's worked with either university code
or code coming in from data scientists, they're not software engineers.
Well, even software engineers make mistakes, but these
people just want to make sure something works and so they'll get it working.
And regardless of whether it's going to have bugs or not,
and the language doesn't care, it's not going to try to make them do that.
We had to make a conscious decision that's a constant in any
industry. You have to make decisions before they're made for you.
We looked at C Plus plus, but the tooling is difficult to learn and
can cause issues. And then we were looking for safety and
lower weve languages are necessary for operational control.
Why are we looking at operational control? Well, that's a good
question. And the answer is, because we are trying to
build digital twin. And a digital twin
is basically a digital representation of a physical
asset that eventually, and you kind
of can't see the level seven here. It's a little cut off by my face,
but the level seven is artificial intelligence and automated
design optimization. And so weve trying to build this digital
representation of a physical asset that would eventually control
the physical asset or have some kind of a feedback loop back
into the physical asset. And so if we're trying to build digital twins
of nuclear reactors, well, then we need to
deal with safe and performant languages,
because we are dealing with, again, nuclear reactors
and trying to build these digital twins. And again, you can go
through a little bit and look at these different levels of digital twins as you
go through. Don't worry too much about that.
Just understand, again, it's a digital asset or a digital representation
of a physical asset that will eventually,
it can predict things about the physical asset. It can interact
with the physical asset. It has feedback loops with the physical
asset. And so it can have a lot of those combinations and changes.
Roughly 70%. And this is why
safety matters. And I took this from otka.com.
70% of all cves at Microsoft are memory safety issues.
Two thirds of Linux kernel security vulnerabilities
come from memory safety issues.
Android has a bunch of vulnerabilities that are safety
issues. An analysis of that, my favorite one is
this last one of zero days that were discovered being exploited in the wild,
found that more than 80% of the exploited vulnerabilities
were because of memory safety issues. And so
if our stick was
dangerous security issues and vulnerabilities
in control software or just bad
run states or, sorry, bad states in the piece
of software, then our carrot was memory safety
was, hey, we can potentially get
rid of an entire class of bugs if
we can find some way to ensure memory
safety for our software programs and for what we're trying
to build. And so this led us to one
obvious conclusion. And I mean, you're listening to the rust conference,
so obviously I think you're coming to the same conclusion that we came into.
We put together a few different languages and kind of pitted them against
each other. And the one that came out to be a clear winner for
our use case was Rust. Now, again,
this is the original slide from 2022, so not all this might be
correct. I wanted to maintain my original look at Rust
for the department and the area and the Idaho national lab so
that you could get a glimpse into exactly what
we were looking at and what we thought about it before we even started using
it. And without having spent tons of time researching it,
I talked about the idea that it was sponsored by Mozilla because we
were concerned about long term usage and support.
Again, statically typed and compiled language. This part
was really important to us. Can target a lot of different chipsets and different oss.
You can even in some cases run it without an operating
system as long as you have a memory allocator. So it made sense,
the no garbage collector and the compiler enforcing that memory
safety. Again, the carrot and the stick, and our carrot was memory
safety. I could
have made an entire few other slides on this
if I wanted to and talk about memory safety.
I really appreciated the lean standard library large package ecosystem with
a centralized package manager. That's one of the reasons we didn't want to go with
C. Why there are package managers for C.
There is nothing as standardized it feels like to me,
and I might be wrong. Again, this is the original
slide, but this one just jumps out at you.
Concurrency model built in now, we did talk a little bit
about its complex and much steeper learning curve, and we'll talk a little bit
about our experience with it. But with
complexity comes powerful
features. The reason it's so complex is because it does have powerful features,
generics, abstractions, pattern matching, trait system,
macros. So, I mean, there's a lot of power behind it,
and I wanted to make sure that we understood that, yes, it's complex, yes,
it has a steeper learning curve, but it has a lot of powerful features.
We talked a lot about the community. We care
a lot about our developers here at INL. So we want to make sure that
they feel like it's an easy setup and an easy way to get
working. And probably the most important piece on
here for me at the time was the interop with other languages,
and I say excellent. And again, this is the original slide from 2022.
Now that we have actually introduced Rust
with Python C sharp node,
I can tell you it's not bad. It could be better,
it could be worse. But in a lot of cases, there are powerful
libraries out there already to make these interops a lot easier
to deal with. I've successfully written various Python
modules and node modules and even a C sharp
package in rust under the hood.
And so it is possible it does work.
And we've done a lot of work in Rust since we
started this in 2022 1st kind
of our bread and butter of the department is the deep links
open source data lake. We have time series and tabular data
support in there. Originally it was almost pure node js,
and you can already see a problem with dealing with data lakes with an ETL
pipeline and doing node js. They wanted to unify the
languages at the lab in use at this place,
and node was kind of picked because they had to do a front end and
they wanted to make sure that it was a full stack developer. So we started
to use a lot of node JS, and originally it was just pure node js.
We introduced Rust three months after that initial slide
and initial discussions.
And what we introduced was a postgres fast loader
module for tabular and time series data to more
quickly load that into a timescaledb
backed postgres cluster. And it was
patterned after TimescaledB's own concurrent
postgres loader. We were able to write this in
Rust and have it implemented as a native node module.
So we were able to use it in the same code base without having to
stand up a separate service or proxying it
or figuring out anything like that. It just natively works out
of the box. Right now we are
in a massive refactor of deep links where Rust is going to drive our new
tabular and time series data support, and we are integrating with a
technology called Delta Lake. If you haven't heard of Delta Lake,
I highly recommend you look it up. It basically allows
acid transactions on hard storage for time series
and tabular data like Parquet files. Just acid transactions
and parquet files on hard storage. It's fantastic. And we're using
Rust to drive that. We are working on backing
our open source graph technology
with Redis graph in order to make that fast. And we have
a loader that will load snapshots of the graph at any
point in time into redis. And weve written that in
rust again, and we are looking at integrating a
large language model, particularly llama rs if you can look it up.
And it's the rewrite of llama C
in rust, and we are looking at integrating it again
into Deeplinks'core code base. And all
of this is possible because of Rust.
We've done several other things. One is
a program called Serval. It was a websocket multiplayer game server used
to fuel or not fuel, used to
back our multiplayer
game sessions for our digital twin. So we use uni
a lot in house to represent these models in a 3d
space and let users interact with them using Microsoft
HoloLens using other tools. And so we wanted to
let users interact with other users. And so we've created this
websocket multiplayer game server to make that a reality
again. Drives the AR VR multiplayer integrations
as well as the multiplayer integration for our deep links viewer.
For
personally was creating a deep links loader which is both a Python and a c
sharp module for caching time series and tabular data
from Deeplinks locally. Letting data scientists
work with deep links in Python in a more easy fashion.
Letting us pull it down into a duckdb database to
let them query with SQL to their heart's content without having to
slam the data lake with requests
over and over and again. Leverages DuckDB and right now we use
it in a lot of our machine learning and our artificial intelligence pipelines
here at ino. And again, none of this would be possible
without Rust. This year we
finally hit the big time in dealing with Rust. We finally had the
opportunity to do what we wanted to do since we started discussing
Rust and why we wanted to use Rust.
This is the AGN 201 nuclear reactor.
It is rated for producing five watts of electricity. It is
hosted at the Idaho State University in Pocatello,
Idaho. And we, Idaho,
Idaho, Idaho National Laboratory, were asked to create
a digital twin of this nuclear reactor.
Now, if you remember back to the levels of the digital twin, we have
things like real time analytics integrations and then eventually
a feedback loop into this reactor.
Now, while we did not complete the full feedback loop because
of nuclear regulatory committee
regulations and rules, we were able to basically get
all the way up to that point and demonstrate that we could in fact,
potentially control the reactors with this safe program.
And so we built a system with deep
links at its core and a lot of rust. So we have
down in this operations portion here, we have to get the live
asset data from the nuclear reactor. We wrote a program called Jester.
It is a rust file watcher and
data acquisition tool for pulling in data from data
acquisition systems, reading it in and sending it off to the Deeplinks
data link. And again, that was written in rust. We had
a very tiny machine with tiny
specifications to work with. This is not a very powerful machine.
And so Rust allowed us to make something that was performant and that could
fit in the resource constraints that we had and then be able to
send that over the network to the Deeplinks data lake.
That data lake drove machine learning and
artificial intelligence. We passed that data out into
basically Jupyter notebooks, and these Jupyter notebooks are
using that deep links loader that I talked about for pulling in time series
data from deep links in a better manner than just
constantly hitting the database. And then we built a
program around paper mill and around others to
control the execution of Jupyter
notebooks and the code that our data scientists put together to
run anomaly detection, to run all sorts of different
algorithms on this data, to see all sorts of different things about this reactor.
And again, this is all facilitated by the use of
rust. And then that data gets shoved back into deep links,
and it goes out into this
area here, where we have a live model and human interaction. We have
an AR and VR headset that is, again,
using the same deep links loader technology,
but as a C sharp module written in
Rust to drive our AR VR,
and we have that running on a HoloLens headset.
So, again, Rust was able to target this and work on HoloLens.
It was fantastic. It made everything easy. I didn't
have to write, or we didn't have to write the code
five times in five different languages to make it work. We were able
to maintain a much smaller workforce
to accomplish this main goal. Our bet
paid off. So we launched the AGN 201 digital twin
in less than six months of development time.
Now, granted, we had a lot of the work done with the data lake,
but again, we still had to write the data acquisition system,
we had to write the machine learning portion, we had to write the loader,
and we were able to do that in six months. Now, this does
not include the rust ramp up time, and I know that is
a concern of a lot of developers, but I have seen that,
in all honesty, people pick up rust fairly quickly when
they are motivated and they have a problem to solve.
You can't expect your developers, and you can't expect those that work for you to
pick up rust in a weekend, or expect
them to pick it up when you don't have, or when you haven't handed them
problems to solve and things to work on.
We maintain speed and accuracy of the data by using native modules in Rust.
So the speed of getting that data off the
data acquisition system into machine learning and then back to the end
user was extremely important. And then the accuracy of
that data that we had no drops, or that we were able to maintain those
drops and buffer and send, and we were able to accomplish all of that
with Rust. And then this one is my
favorite. I believe that we demonstrated the ability for rust
to eventually become part of nuclear control instruments and paradigms.
We now have a working digital twin that is functional accurate,
safe, and hopefully we can demonstrate that.
Hey, we have new technology that we should
utilize in dealing with nuclear reactors.
Lessons learned. The big one is,
again, find what drives management and those that make the big decisions
and use those to drive your adoption of rust.
Drive your innovation. Have a game plan,
but leave wiggle room for all the people that you have
working for you working in rust to experiment and try
their own things, and again, give them a problem to solve.
Let them prototype early and quickly and often,
and you'll be amazed about
what you can develop and what you can create with Rust.
My experience in dealing with rust in the nuclear world
has been nothing but positive.
There are hitches. There are little ugly spots.
We talk about the asynchronous implementation in Rust that
could use some work. We talk about libraries that
are rough to use. We talk about the trace system, which can be
difficult to understand sometimes, and proc
macros. But we have so many good tools
now. We have so many good resources that
it doesn't, again, give them problems to solve.
And you'll see your individual developers and those
working in Rust just continue to excel and continue to
use this language in a powerful way.
Thank you so much for the opportunity to talk to you today. I really hope
that you enjoyed this presentation. I really hope it's
encouraged you to pick up Rust, see what it can do for you, because I
promise you, in whether it's 510,
15 years from now, Rust will be involved in
nuclear energy and it will be making the world a
safer place.