Hello, my name is JJ Asghar, and as you can see
up over there, you can
find me at jgasgar on Twitter or more or less anywhere else.
And awesome@ibm.com. Yes, I really do have that email address,
which is always fun. So you've come here today
to learn about some githubs. I'm just kind of
stepping myself into this world and the things that I finally learned
Andor embraced. Frankly speaking, I'm shocked
it took me this long to get here. I'm very excited about this
talk, and we're going to go over some basic things to make sure we're all
talking about the same stuff, and then we're actually going to play with some Gitops
and two very simple use cases that
as you build off of it, youve be amazed on what you can actually
get done. And it just seems like a natural progression
for all our cloud native lifestyles.
So let me go ahead and flip my screen.
There we go. Youve should be able to see IBM there.
Yes, as I said earlier, I do work for IBM.
And here we go. Taking a step back and leveraging
Gitops to wrangle your clusters and projects. And again,
JJ, developer advocate. So please,
if you have any questions or thoughts, never hesitate to reach out directly
to me. My life is to be a personable nerd to
help you out here. All right,
so let's talk about the introduction.
Basically, if you're at this talk, you've probably made
your adventure into cloud native. You probably have a kubernetes or a couple
of kubernetes clusters or maybe even some openshift clusters,
and you have this ability
to deploy stuff. You understand what pods are,
you understand what the advantage of
cloud native is, and you're doing well.
But this git ops thing keeps popping up in a lot of different conversations,
and you probably want to learn and or leverage it,
and that's why you're here. I'm here because I'm
slow but surely taking over more and more stories inside of
IBM around Gitops. It's becoming more and more a
de facto way to do work with our cloud
native space, and it really is just a natural progression.
And I'm really hoping this talk kind of brings that to you.
The natural thing you need to start talking to after about understanding this, you need
to start talking about CI and CD. If you've never seen these two terms
before, I'm shocked.
It's kind of can industry standard now, but CI
stands for continuous integration and CD
stands for continuous delivery.
CI is pretty much industry standard now across the board.
If youve writing some software somewhere, you probably have some level
of a CI pipeline that constantly either builds it or
runs your unit tests or runs. Youve integration tests
or things like mean by
default things like GitHub actions and
Travis and Circle CI. They're very
low overhead to get running, and it gives you a peace of mind
that your code is doing what you need to do. As I said,
it's pretty much the standard. Now,
CD, on the other hand, which is continuous delivery.
As much as people want to say it's CI and CD in one breath,
CD isn't industry standard. Continuous delivery
is a rather robust,
mature process that you know, you can trust
your code to continually get deployed. There's philosophies
out there that the main branch should always be deployable.
There's also a lot of different philosophies, like the production branch should
always be deployable, things like that. And that type of
gating on there actually kind of goes in the face of
CD, where your application should just be
deployable. I guess arguably the production branch or main branch
you target and then it's always deployable, and then you can always
make sure it works. But the point being is that when
CI finishes, CD happens.
So if everything's green, it just goes out there. So as soon as you merge
it to whatever deploy branch you have, which should be main,
in my personal opinion. When you hit that big green button,
the tests kick off one last time to verify everything hasn't changed.
Nothing, no regressions. And then the theory was
is to deploy it. And that's where we kind of come into
this conversation around Githubs. Gitops is basically
the other half of CI. It is the
CD portion of it. So let's bring this over here.
So what is Gitops? Simply said, it's a way to leverage
the typical git workflow in configuration of one or many kubernetes.
Clusters can also be openshift. In the applications inside
of them. It leverages something called a pull
mechanism instead of a push, which is very important to talk about.
We'll talk about more in a minute. You can
deploy something from like GitHub actions or Jenkins, or even
Openshift webhooks. The biggest pain
point that GitHub takes away is that now you have
a true history of your deployment and how things happen.
There are real problems with not leveraging
Gitops completely. This is more or less a whole or nothing process.
You can't kind of just do a Gitops workflow right.
It doesn't work that way. When you decide to
go down the Gitops path, you are making a change to your
deployment process and your deployment mechanisms that will be
complete whole hog. One reason why we like it on the openshift
side so much is because we do pick the best of breed of things from
the red hat standpoint. And the Gitops workflow
actually fits really well in that space, which is really
nice. So why
should you care, right? As long as our app is up and running,
why should I bother with all this overhead?
Well, if you have one clusters, okay, maybe this
isn't worth it, right? But as soon as you start building multiple
clusters, you start building a dev cluster, building a QA cluster,
or for that matter,
you have a process where you need features out quickly.
The idea of doing manual deployments is tough.
Obviously youve moved to the cloud native space and now you have multiple kubernetes
or Openshift clusters. It could
even be spread around various clouds. Right. Like you're not all on IBM
cloud, which you should be. I'm just saying.
Kidding. I work for IBM. Of course I'm going to say that.
But it's got unruly. You have clusters,
you have your dev environment Andor Azure your production,
and IBM Cloud Andor for
some reason you have a bunch of s three buckets. I dont know. It's unruly.
It's frustrating. And I'm here to tell you not
to worry. One of the beauties of Gitops is the
ability to maintain all these clusters. Because what is a Kubernetes cluster
but a bunch of yaml and leveraging Gitops to edit
that Yaml Andor whatnot allows for
some way to wrangle around clusters.
IBM here to tell you and give you these tools to help
make this happen, to help make this happen
so you can focus on building for the business instead of
fighting your infrastructure. You've already spent so much time Andor effort learning
how to get your application inside of kubernetes.
Now you got to fight maintaining the infrastructure
all over again. And Gitops kind of takes some of that pain away
and in turn gives you that CD that we were talking about earlier
that you desperately should be moving towards.
Leveraging Gitops and the principles around is a mashup of traditional
infrastructure management andor software development
practices that your developers have been using for almost decades now.
And it gives you an audible, accountable, and enforceable way to
interface with all of your Kubernetes fleets, which is
really important.
So from what I've been learning
about Gitops and all that. I genuinely believe this is going to become the de
facto way that we are going to maintain
more than one cluster. Okay. Arguably youve can
maintain one, as I said earlier, you can maintain one cluster with this if you
really want, but for me, this really
feels like what we are going to be doing moving forward.
So let's talk about a typical git workflow,
right? Like I mentioned about leveraging into main earlier,
this is a very simple example, right? And of
course you're going to have a lot of different arguments around all the different stuff,
but let's just stay with this very simple, very simple
workflow that I'm about to show as a de facto way to
use git. Okay? I mean, if you want to talk about git
flow and other weird ways of doing it, sure, fine.
You can absolutely implement those inside of the space, but I'm
looking for just showing people how to get started so
they can mold it to their normal workflow.
So this is it, right? You've got your main
branch, where that's all your code, and then you have a feature
branch or a bugfish branch that branches off,
does the fixes, and then you merge it back into main. That's it,
right? It's nothing too crazy. You work in isolation, which is
really nice. Your feature branch and youve bugfish branch are off
on bits own branch, as you can see from here.
And that's important to know. So that means that main is always deployable,
right? Like again, CD continuous deployment.
So this simple branch, right, it's a simple branching mechanism, is all
you need to do to start with to leverage Gitops in your normal workflow.
So there's multiple different ways of making
this happen. And the first one we need to talk about is pull versus push.
So I mentioned earlier that Gitops is a pull based mechanism
instead of a push based mechanism. So when you run
your CI pipeline and you push out your
code to your main branch, and now it does all
the tests and whatnot,
traditionally you would push your deployment out to the new clusters
to push it out to your
new servers or whatever, right? Well, Gitops comes
and flips the narrative. What they do now is pull.
So constantly there's a little agent that sits on side
of your cluster pulling against
wherever youve Git repo is looking for changes.
You can obviously change how quickly and how slow you want to do it,
and that's fine. But the idea is
that you pull into your cluster any changes,
which means your application needs to be aware
of that it could be updated at any time, which can be a little
bit level of, could be a little bit of
an engineering problem. I mean, that's the reason why you should run things through QA
and test and all. But the idea is that it pulls constantly,
which actually opens up some really interesting conversations because
that means now if you have can air gapped environment, you can
have this agent running on an air gapped cluster somewhere
that pulls off of a cache that's been security scanned, for instance,
which is really neat. So instead of you just pushing your code and it pushes
out to that environment, now you can cache the
things and verify that it's the stuff you expect it to be. This also gives
the ability to pull in a,
you don't have to push everything off at the same time. You pull things at
a rate that you feel comfortable with, which allows for better,
like, you know, uptime and whatnot in the long term,
because youve know, if you pull Andor something breaks,
youve can have the intelligence in there to make sure it doesn't change it.
But if you push on top of it, pushing on top of it, unless youve
made some really interesting engineering choices, you could
take your application down. So it's important to recognize these things.
So let's talk about the three major players
in the space, and one's Argo CD, the other one's Jenkins
X. And frankly speaking, the granddaddy
of them all is something called Flux CD. Argo is the
first one, Jenkins X, and obviously flux.
So flux CD is CLI
based and is very lightweight and does
exactly what you want it to do. It is unbelievably
powerful. And IBM very, very impressed with the work it
does. You have Jenkins X, which is kind of the next
generation of the Jenkins ecosystem,
and it's very impressive, but it's
very prescriptive, or at least the last time I played with it,
it was expecting some very specific things.
And if you're already in the Jenkins ecosystem,
Jenkins actually is a natural progression and more power
to you. The one that kind of grabbed me and really made
me understand the beauty of Gitops is Argo.
And in the rest of this talk, I'm going to be actually focusing this conversation
around Argo CD because it really did just
kind of make things make sense to me, and that's important to say.
So let's go ahead and install one,
and I'm going to go ahead and bring this small.
No, that's not what I wanted.
Let's see here. We're going to make this small,
this over here, and then bring this over here,
and then probably make this a little bit bigger so youve all
can see.
And then if I do cubectl
get ns.
So as we see here, I'm on an openshift cluster and
this should work. There we go. As you can
see, and I built an upset cluster about 17 days ago.
Got a bunch of projects in here, but if you look here, kget pods,
I'm in the default namespace and there's nothing in there, which is exactly
what we wanted.
Where is my notes? So the first thing first is
I need to.
What the.
So there are some really nice straightforward ways to install
Argo CD. And right here is
I've actually created a nice little markdown file. But the first thing we're going to
do here is we're going to create a namespace,
Argo CD namespace, and then I'm just going to pull it directly down from
the stable branch and kubectl apply it. So there we go.
So you see, we creates the namespace and we threw in some custom resources,
which is nice. And that's actually all
you need to do. Argo CD is just two commands,
which is always fun. So if I do kgetpods
and Argocd,
as you see, we're creating our containers. I did not pre bake
this, I wanted to show this live, which is important. But that's actually
it, that's actually all the installation, which is
pretty nice. So let's see
here,
bring this back over here. And as that is
going. So let's talk about some infrastructure management.
So the first thing I wanted to talk about obviously has the way
to deal with a bunch of fleets. So as I've been seeing with different customers
out there, as much as I
tried to tell people have one, big clusters use
namespaces and projects to split stuff up.
Frankly speaking, people didn't adopt it right. They started spinning
up multiple clusters for dev, QA and
prod or whatever. So that's actually where Argo CD comes
into play really nicely. You can leverage Argo CD
to maintain some level of consistency through all
of your different Openshift clusters, or Kubernetes clusters.
I'm going to be showing Openshift because it's just a little bit easier with the
GUI, but all these things work on kubernetes just fine
too. So this right here,
if you can read it,
is basically creating something called a menu link inside
of our console on our Openshift cluster.
I'm going to show here in just a second,
plugging it in and making it happen. But the idea is, let's say
for instance, you wanted to change, I don't know,
a logo everywhere. Or for that matter,
you wanted to add a link to Google, to every single openshift cluster. If you
bring, take a look here, just so I'm completely transparent,
here's an openshift cluster here. And you
see here, there's this nice little drop down up here. There's this
manager managed cluster right here. The idea is to add a link to Google,
right? It's not great, it's not a great example, but the idea is
now I can shotgun this across every single cluster.
You have an internal website that you all need to add for like privacy,
I don't know, whatever you imagine it. So now every single
cluster that's running Argo CD and I add this little
configuration to will now get that link, which is pretty nice.
So if I come back over here and see that
Argo CD is up, there we go, we're running,
everything's great. So the interesting part about it
with Argo CD is that you
don't have to expose it to the Internet, right? It can just sit
on the cluster by itself. So one of those times
you might want to actually do it is you
go ahead and create a port forward here. If I bring this back over and
then I go to 127
80, 80, there we go. It's like,
hey, youve not secure, blah, blah blah. And as
youve can see here, here's Argo CD, right, like I did port forward
to it. It's sitting there. IBM not exposed to the real Internet.
It's nice and secure, which is always good. But before I go any farther,
IBM going to need that password. So I'm going to go ahead and
grab this and
there it is. Don't worry. You do not worry
about stealing this from me because I will be blowing up this cluster after the
fact. But if I go to admin here and then pop
that password in, and there we go, we got argo CD
sitting in here running, and by default it has cluster admin rights,
so it can create namespaces, andor do things and whatnot, which is always nice.
So I have this Gitops tutorial repository,
which is important to show this is what
we're actually going to be linking up against. I actually have my installation instructions
in here too, so you're more than welcome to play with this in the future
if you like. If you go into the OS thing here,
and then if I go into
tenants. And then here's my link to google. Here is
my customization file which is if you need that, know what that is. But here
is the actual yaml which is kind of
nice. I don't know if you can read that but hopefully youve can.
So if I go ahead and bring this up over here,
I can go ahead and just create a new app here. Now you can do
this through multiple different ways. I'm just going to do it through the GUI because
it's nice and easy. So I'm going to do link to
google and then my
sync policies, I want to have it do automatic so it's constantly building against
it. And then the source repository is
this whole thing here. If IBM going to go ahead and go ahead and here
copy this and then you can actually change
it to whatever revision you want which is nice.
And did I erase that? All that oops link to
google. I want this to be automatic.
It can actually self heal which is nice too. That's important to recognize.
So if something goes funky you can always try to do it. And then
grab that there and then the path and
then I'm going to go directly to here which is
OS tennis main copy. Put that
in there and then
the cluster URL, you can actually have argo
CD control a bunch of remote clusters if you wanted to, which is
neat too. But we're just going to do this for the local one
and we're going to go ahead and do this in the
default namespace and then that
should be it. So let's go ahead and create default.
And there we go. We go ahead and create it. And if I've got
my notes correct, this should
make it happen.
The path needs to be absolutely create.
How about that one?
Maybe. Let's see.
This did go faster in my previous testing, so I'm so
sorry this is taking so long.
One more time.
So then I believe by default this checks every five
minutes, but we'll see. And there we go. So now it looks and
then it sees this and it's in cluster. And then what we're going to do
is go ahead and hit that sync button. Synchronize.
There we go. As you can see immediately it said it's
out of sync. So it's figuring that out. It synced it.
And then if I've got this right,
we should be able to see okay,
that's synced. So then if I come back over to our cluster
here and I refresh this page.
There we go. We got our link to google. Youve see that? Pretty neat.
Cool. So if I wanted to change this all of a sudden.
Hang on. The idea is I could be able to change this
to whatever I need it to be. So if I go back over here
to this link copy,
throw it in here, and then go
back into os, and then tenants link to google
and change this to bing, for instance, because I'm
crazy or whatever, I commit that
again, I should have created another branch, do all that stuff, but you get the
point. And now if I go ahead and say,
sync this one, and then I synchronize again
and it'll say it's out of sync here in a second.
Last sync.
There we go. So it's out of sync. It recognized. Hey, it's out of sync.
Now, this does self heal. So if I had a bunch of clusters, I wouldn't
have to synchronize every single one of them. But the idea is that, right?
And now we should see this
change here in a second refresh
maybe. There we go. So now
if I come back over to my openshift cluster refresh,
and if I click on this one and link to google,
there I am. At mean,
point taken. It's not super crazy, but the idea
is that now I have my configuration inside of
my GitHub repository, which could be any git repository,
and be able to change that now if I have enough time, which I don't
think I do, unfortunately,
I wanted to show off the ability
to do a simple application here, which in that same repository I
can easily add. And this little simple python app,
as you can see, is so much more advanced. But it's all in there too,
where you can play around and sync
it all in, and then you can just make a small change to the flask
app or the deployment or whatever,
and then it
actually federates throughout the whole thing. That moment that you see everything
go from out of sync and then back to sync all of a sudden makes
Argo CD makes so much more sense. It really truly does.
So I'm coming right up to 30 minutes,
or actually 26 minutes. So let's just talk about a conclusion real
fast. I genuinely believe this to be
the next generation of how we're going to maintain our
Openshift or Kubernetes clusters. Fleets and
fleets of clusters out there need
consistency. If I learned anything from the configuration management space,
which was when you spin up a bunch of EC, two instances or vms
or whatever, you need to make sure that they all have the same version
of OpensSL or whatever on top of it well, in the
Kubernetes space and Openshift space, you're going to
have a bunch of devs touching a bunch of different clusters,
and they're going to want the same interface and know that the same stuff is
there on each one. And Gitops
is just going to do that for us as administrators
has people who maintain the infrastructure for
your cloud native users. It's just a natural progression.
People do say that Gitops is DevOps two or
3.0 or whatever you want to call it.
I think that's a little bits unfair.
I think Gitops is a natural progression, but not really
another version.
It's got some strengths to it, and I believe it's going to be the next
one. But DevOps is still encompassing so much more than
just maintaining infrastructures.
So thank you for your time. Hopefully you did learn something new,
and please don't hesitate to reach out. My job is
to be a nerd that you can find, as I said at the beginning,
and hopefully this tickled your fancy
and play around on that Gitops tutorial.
There's a few things in there. I am updating it pretty regularly
with new stuff or whatever,
and I do want to say Christian Hernandez from Red
Hat has some amazing tutorials on how to use
Argo CD. Actually, the Gitops tutorial I
have there is from his tutorial, which is
a lot more in depth than what I did. But if
this spurred something, I strongly suggest going
through his thanks y'all and to I
hope to see youve everyone in the real world soon.