Jamaica make up real
time feedback into the behavior of your distributed systems and observing
changes exceptions. Errors in real time allows
you to not only experiment with confidence, but respond
instantly to get things working again.
You good
morning, good afternoon, or good evening based on where you are.
My name is Alemi. I'm a senior developer advocate at Postman.
I'm french, but I actually live in London and I'm here today
to talk about winning friends. It might not be something
that you are looking for, but we kind of see how you
can do that with API first within your company.
This is not a title to hide marketing stuff. I do work at Postman and
I'm going to chat about it on this slide and then just a little bit
at the start. But it's going to be like a high view of what is
API first, but quick talk there.
Postman is an API collaboration platform used by 17 million people,
and the good thing is me working there
means that I get to talk with a lot of people that are using APIs
in different setups, in different sizes,
teams, et cetera, et cetera. So that talk is mostly going to be me sharing
what I've learned from all of these people that I've talked to.
Going back to the talk, the name of the talk is
how, how, how, how to win friends and influence first.
So the same way we have a lot of users, we do have a lot
of people using APIs in general. So we'll go all the way from
when you start off thinking about your API, all the way to implementing
it, et cetera. And the aim of that talk is to show the benefits of
different ways to do it. To do that, I'll go through these five
points. First, what does API first mean? I think
it's very important to define. So we're all talking about the same thing,
the benefits of API first, practical tools and workflows.
And that's where I'm just going to jump back to Postman, but also other tools,
some industry examples and some key points. You might
be wondering what this has to do with chaos engineering.
Hopefully this is going to be cleared out very soon when we keep going through
the talk. But basically we also
want to reduce the number of issues that
can come up later on in your production app using API
first. And you see that in some follow up slides.
So let's start with what does API
first mean to you? Well, it can mean different
things and usually if we were in the live setup, I would be yelling at
you and be like, oh, you, what does it mean? But I'm here
in front of my computer talking to my camera. So the
good thing is we actually have a survey that we do with Postman
and we run it every year. If you're familiar with the state
of cows engineering that Kremlin does, we kind of do the same for the state
of the API and we do it. I think we have
like 28,000 people from the API industry that answer
that survey. So it's a good enough representation.
And that's what we asked them. We asked them, what do you think API
first is? 11% of them were not
sure, and that's actually 2% down from the previous year. So that
is 2021. The previous year was 2020. So more
and more people are aware of it. But even then, in the 89%
left, there's still some different
ways to see what is API
first. So there's defining and designing APIs and schemas before
beginning development, developing APIs before developing the applications
that are going to integrate with it, or very much like going
all the way to the start and defining the business requirements
before even going into defining and designing your API.
I think to define what is API first,
we can go the complete opposite, and the complete opposite of
API first, you would think it's API last,
but we actually call that code first.
It's a workflow that may well be very familiar with you.
Start with the core functionality, so that could be your back end,
you're a booking service,
how do you handle that? And then on top of that, once you have your
booking service that's working, put an API,
slap an API on top, and then you'll have a
web app that's going to come in and plug itself to it.
Start coding the API,
use your core functionality or booking application, et cetera.
But then someone else comes in.
Maybe you want an admin app to handle your bookings, or there's
a mobile app that comes in and you need to change
your core functionality, you need to upgrade your API, add new endpoints,
et cetera. Or maybe you have a completely
different type of service that is going to plug in,
maybe a third party booking, et cetera. And you need an
entirely new API. And as
you can see, there's many use cases here and it's just going to
keep on changing and you'll have to evolve all of the
parts of your app, all of your layers, whether it's the core
functionality, the API, et cetera,
to manage that. So some
companies have transitioned from that to API first,
and one of them is Etsy. What happened with
Etsy is that they had only a website
and then they realized they wanted to create mobile apps on top,
but they had to rebuild everything. So that's Stephanie Schumer
from Etsy. And what she said is all of the code that was built for
the website then had to be rebuilt in our API to be used by our
iOS and Android apps. So basically recreate different APIs
for each of these platforms. And one of
the, I saw that tweet a while back now,
but one of the way that I think really represents that when you have
them disconnected with the code first approach, when you have your
back end, your front end, and then you need to connect them together,
this is what happens. Two parts
that are individually, they are perfect, right?
They work fine. I can walk on that pavement from one
side to the other, but then when I want to switch from one to
the other, there's a disconnect. That's kind of the,
if you go with cut Apifirst, what might happen?
So now let's have a look at the workflow for API first.
In the API, first case, you start with your API.
Surprise, the interface. So you think about who's going to
use it, your products, your customers, typically your
application engineers, they will be the first one to consume it.
So again, like from your web app, admin app, mobile API, et cetera.
But that paves the way for more platforms and services
to connect to it. And because you start with
the API, whenever you start thinking about implementing a new functionality on
top, well, you'll add
it to the API first, and then both parties,
whether it's whoever consumes or ever produces
the backend, they'll evolve at the same time.
So give back cut ApIfirst, you code,
and that's a lower level type of implementation
of codefirst that we're looking at now. You start with the code, you commit your
code to a source repository, people are going to start
integrated with it, then you deploy it. It doesn't have
deploying to production, it can be deploying to a stage environment, et cetera.
And then people can eventually test it, debug it, document it,
and there's a few problems with that.
And this is how you do not make friends. And this is the problems we've
kind of identified with the code. ApIfirst approach bottlenecks,
delay contributors and consumers. And the bottleneck is very
much because you have this one entity at the start, the code, if you
don't add anything to it, all of the other functionalities
are blocked and it's a funnel rather than a lifecycle.
Yeah, I'm not quite sure what's the right word here, but it's jacko.
There's a lot of rework that happens late in the development cycle.
You might be building stuff that no one wants,
you're writing code and then eventually it goes all the way to deploying
it and it was got what people wanted, so maybe
it's not going to be used. The end product might not be well
documented, and the API is constrained by what
you have in the backend. And if someone
wants like a new endpoint, you'll have to rework your backend, et cetera.
In the API first case, you start with your API
and we will see that later. But from just defining your API
using an API definition and different types of specification,
you can already generate a lot of stuff. So you can generate documentation,
you can generate mocks for your front end developers
to start heating and kind of see how they could build the front end.
And you can generate tests as well. You may as well be
able to generate server side code.
There's a few tools that allow you to do that out there. That said,
my background is in software engineering. I do like to write my own code sometimes,
and I do like to know what I'm writing. So some people might
not be confident giving the
tasks to some code generation thing,
but it's there. But once you have that,
you generate code or you write your code,
and now you have your id, you have the environment where
your code lives and you can start
integrating with, and then you have your
tests that run between whatever you design at first and whatever is in
production. And that's a one to one, because you've first thought
about how your API was going to be used by consumers and therefore you
know what you want to build in the backend. So you might already
see a few key differences, and by then
maybe you're already API first,
probably have tons of friends already, because how do you make friends?
By doing earlier validation. So because you start
from the beginning of defining what your API is going to do, you get
feedback much earlier in the development cycle and your team can adapt
to new inputs. If we go all the way to the
cost of it, you can know how much resources you're going
to have to put against it, et cetera. You're decoupling dependencies.
And the point here being there's not that bottleneck anymore
because you have your API defined
somewhere and you can generate all these other items from it, and then your teams
can actually work in parallel developers testers writer
just basing their work on the definition. They can do
their own thing. Obviously this creates
faster growth. The lifecycle is much
faster from when you need a
new endpoint, for example, to deploying
it. Freedom from constraints.
If you focus on the API instead of the code, kind of freeze the
design that's already baked in there. There's a few companies that are
known for the API first approach, but before jumping into that,
I'm going to make the connection with chaos engineering.
You might know, know they do
some chaos engineering stuff and I'm pretty sure they'll be part of that conference.
But from a shorty story of chaos engineering
on their website, this is what they say. Chaos engineering is preventive
medicine. So chaos engineering is a disciplined approach to
identifying failures before they become outages. And this would probably
more apply to when you're in production. But the principle of API
first is the same because you're kind of starting
to already think about how it's going to be implemented, who is going to be
using it, et cetera.
What's the saying in English? Better safe than sorry. That's very much like what's
behind API first. And looking at companies that do that,
there's a few very well known ones. Twitter is very famous at the moment for
handling everything using apifirst. So their new
spaces, API using that, et cetera. Another one that is also
pretty well known in the chaos engineering realm is
Netflix.
Actually. I forgot the name of
the tool that they created, but the main chaos engineering one,
but basically what they've done as well and what allowed them to have that much
flexibility, like in production, et cetera, was moving to API
first. And this is from 2013, which is nine
years from now. I mean, nine years before now, which is
a long time ago. But what they said, or what Ben Christensen said,
a single team should not become a bottleneck, nor need to have expertise on
every client application to create optimized endpoints. Rapid innovations
through fast decoupled development cycles across a wide variety of device types,
and distributed ownership and expertise across teams should be enabled.
And you probably see a lot of similarities between that and
the benefits of apifirst. So you have the rapid innovation cycles,
you have the wide variety of diva slides that are supported,
and then you have the different teams working together.
So yeah, that's what
happens when you go API first. But let's go back at the
different ways we define it. We actually
surveyed something else in that survey. We looked how people
that are actually thinking of themselves as being API first were defining
it. So what came out of that
is that most people were defining API first or
most of the people that were calling themselves as full on API first
because you can be at different stages of that. They were defining
it as defining and designing API and schemas before development.
And that's the definition we're going to go with now.
So let's kind of dig deeper and now look at the different tools and workflows
that can help you achieve API first within your company.
Again, I've said it before, I work at Postman. I'm going to
talk a bit about Postman here. There's other tools out there.
There's actually website called OpenAPi tools
which lists it's meant to be or we
want it to be an exhaustive list. And I say we don't support it.
We're not the ones maintaining it. But it's out there. If you're interested, there's tons
of tools there that you can go and check out.
But main question, you have
a monolith somewhere and you're wondering how do you transform a
clouded API development workflow? There's three things that I'm
going to talk about here, API specifications, and I've mentioned it a bit
before, mock savers and consumer driven contract testing.
The last one is probably going to be one of the most relevant here because
it involves testing things against production.
But let's start with API specifications.
API specifications have can
API specification is the specification you're going to use to define your API.
Once you have defined your API, you have an API definition. So there's different ways,
there's different description format, there's open API B, two,
e, three, there's Raml, graphql, async API. If you're
doing async stuff, there's ton of them out there. So then you
have the document. So that's
the API definition. So that's the description of your specific API.
So if you go back to Twitter, for example, a description of the
Twitter spaces API, and then you have the documentation. So again,
how does an API consumer come in and use your API? Well, you give them
an API reference and it's kind of a guide of how do
you use that API, what you can do with it, what you would
get back from it, et cetera.
Again, if you go through that, that already saves you a lot of time later
on because from the API definition you can generate tons of elements,
tests, documentation,
mock server, et cetera, et cetera. So we kind
of surveyed people as well to see what type of
API specification they were using. And this is a bit of
a heavy one. So on the left you can see the type of
definition of specification. So swagger, open API,
graphql, et cetera. And then by color you have orange,
never heard of it. Yellow is aware but don't use it.
Can blue is use it and
then the dark blue is use it and love it. So JSon schema is
at the top there is the most used, is the most loved.
It is a specification for JSOn. It's not used
to describe the API, but it's still up there and you're
probably using JSon if you're doing anything with APIs.
And then you can see in order it's open API two,
also known as swagger two, open API three,
graphql and then async APIs and other type of async
or lesser used API specification.
This is self reported. So that's when we ask people, and because
it's postman surveying people, it might be BSD
a bit, but also because we are postman,
we have other type of data that we can get just from people that are
doing things in the app. This is our finding.
So it's kind of similar to what you can see in the
previous one, but you can see still a wide
use of open API two, then open API
three, and then in this small thing, in this small yellow one, this wager one,
waddle and raml, which are very minimal
usage. So this is a quick
video of what you can do with open API.
So you have your API
definition here, you can add a different version and you
have automatic validation. So the same way you would have like a
code linter or something like that that warns you of any errors.
You have the same thing for your API definition,
and you can obviously collaborate on this type of stuff. So if
you're within a team, you can tag people and you
can tell them oh, come and check, this is the right way to do it.
And that's the whole earlier validation that we talked
about before. Just as you're defining
your API, you can already ask the other teams what
they would be wanting to see.
Now let's move on to the next tool that you could use.
Mock servers. If you're not familiar with mock servers,
it's basically generating some mock endpoints
for all your API endpoints, but they're live,
anyone can call them. And basically instead
of hitting your production servers or even
a stage server, it's just going to reply with the default
response from the API. And you can define different ways based
on the parameters that are sent with the query, et cetera.
But that's a good way to have your front
end team. A good practice is to have your front end team use the mock
server, heat it, et cetera, while you develop the
backend in parallel. And then once the back end is ready,
you can just kind of swap the URL of the mock servers with the
one from production or sharing. And it should work because
both of them are defined from the same API definition.
So let's have a look how you can generate them. So we mentioned
you have your API definition, just from your API definition.
You can go ahead, say that you want
to generate it from the API definition, give it a name and
then generate it. So give it another name
and then create a mock server. So now this should give you a URL.
And as I mentioned, that's how
it works in postman. All the tools do that gives you a URL.
You can go and start creating that one. So I already had a collection.
So my documentation generated from that API definition
can go ahead, swap the URL that is hitting my local host with
the one of the mock server that I just generated, save it.
And I can hit a live endpoint.
So I can just send that request and I can see that I have
a live endpoint that's sending data back to me.
And now I can send that URL to anyone else in my team
and they'll be able to use that same endpoint,
start creating whatever items they need to create using
that.
So we use that open API spec to generate the mock
server. The testers can start writing tests against it, the writers
can dig in, documenting against it, et cetera. The last workflow
we'll talk about, and this one might
be the most relevant to the chaos engineering folks out there.
Consumer driven contract testing and I'm going to quote
here the principles of Cos engineering, which some of you
may be familiar with. But one
of the first paragraph in there is even when all of the individual services
in a distributed system are functioning properly, the interactions between
the services can cause unpredictable outcomes.
Unpredictable outcomes completed by rare but disruptive real world events
that affect production environments make this distributed system inherently chaotic.
And if this is too long, et cetera. I always
have a meme to explain things
another way. This is a bit outdated now, but basically
consumer driven contract testing is what stops your app
from breaking at the last minute because you have these tests
that are running against your client, et cetera.
Let's jump into it so you can actually understand what I'm talking about
what is consumer driven contract testing.
So the API provider, in that case,
I can be any company, I can be Netflix, it can be Spotify
or whatever, I'll give my consumers
a contract. And that contract is in our example,
the API definition, the consumer.
So any of my users or partner, they write tests against it.
So you can see on the right here, I tell them this
is what my API is, and they tell me using test, this is
how I'm about to use your API. And then the last step is
this creates the contract and we can then test against
it. So me as the provider, whenever I'm going to make
an update to that API definition, I'm going
to run tests from my consumers in my pipeline.
And when I say consumers, this API
consumer can be internal, it can be like a team within my company. It can
be an external team, it can be any external users.
But the point being, if I see that something's break,
well, I can stop the deployment and avoid anything breaking in production.
And that goes back to the preventive medicine thing
that we talked earlier on. So the way we do it at Postman,
each squad, so squad is in charge of different parts of
the app or wider services,
has a blueprint collection based on the API definition.
From that we generate mock servers to have parallel
development from different teams. And then we'll also do
CDC testing between the different squads.
So let's say we have an IM squad, which is in charge of
everything, logging in, et cetera, or permissions.
They'll have all these other squads relying on what they do, and they'll
get their contract, run it as part of their pipelines to make sure they do
not break anything. Now let's
have a look at our last point. What are the key points for becoming API
first? If I've convinced you that you should be apifirst,
if you want to give it a try, or if you're already API first,
but you just want to make sure that you tick all the boxes.
Let's have a look quickly at how we defined it.
There's different meaning. API first development and API first design.
And the way we used during that talk was
the API first design. So it's the designing and
defining my API before. When I think about creating any resources,
benefits of it, again, earlier validation,
decoupling dependencies, faster growth and freedom from constraints.
But one of the things that you may wonder is,
is apifirst for you or is API first for everyone?
Well, tons of services out there. We love
to support multiple platforms and services and devices as well.
So having this API first or
this API in the middle, defining what all the consumers are
going to do is a great way to do it.
And there's a ton more cloud usage out there as well.
And when you're using different cloud providers, what do you look at when
you're going to use the services? You're probably looking at the API.
None of these friends are slowing down.
I don't think anyone is going to tell me wrong unless everything changed between the
recording of that video and when it's being published. But I
don't think these friends are slowing down. That said,
API first, let's say you're just creating an app
for your personal usage, et cetera. It might not be worth the
trouble, but as soon as you have a few
different users, devices, et cetera,
then you probably want to
go for API first.
I'll leave you with two more quotes.
Developers are used to code first, but there
are definitely benefits to moving to that. And that's a quote from Andrew,
whose last name I do not know, who said
API first in organization means that we can think of what is possible rather than
what is not possible. When it comes to providing the best features and
functionality for our product and services to our members,
we no longer have the difficulties of customizations or integrations with systems
and applications. So that's
one. And the other one, which is a much simpler one coming from Kinlane,
the chief evangelist, the postman. It's going to be hard
if you're planning to turn to API first.
That's a big journey, but it's a good one. The benefits are
incredible at the end, but especially if you've been code for us this whole time,
it is going to be hard, but there's tons of tools out there to help
you. There's tons of companies. I'm here if you
have any questions around Apifirst in general.
But as we see every
time we do this survey, we see the usage
of Apifirst growing, we see the knowledge of Apifirst growing. So I
don't think it's going anywhere. The sooner you start,
the better place you'll be and the more friends you'll
make. With that said, if you
want to learn more about API first, we have a website called API first
world that you can go to and check it.
It's a quick novel that kind of goes through very
high level of what is API first
or what is an Apifirst world. It's very light.
Do not expect any very technical details.
It's very much a comic, which actually we can find
it here. Just going to try to show you,
literally just a comic with someone that talks to you.
But yeah, with that said, thank you for watching.
I'm available on most networks. If you find me on LinkedIn
on twitter. So twitter.com slash alemi,
LinkedIn, alemi, etc.
Find me. Ask me any questions if you have any around API first or
just API in general and have a good.