There. Today's talk is about truth about
running cloud security assessments in 2021. A practitioner story.
The topic should really have been documentation versus the reality
of cloud cloud cloud security assessments in modern
day architecture of cloud environment in
2021. That should have been the real title. But clearly you
would not be here if I said that you might think it's just a fun
talk. Maybe you may be right. But before I get into this,
let's talk about what am I going to discuss in this talk? I would
be talking about the framework that people use to run assessments and
the framework that people use to run assessments against themselves in
any given paid engagement. We also talk about assessment landscape,
the type of threats, the assessment types, automation,
do you even need it? And come of the differentiation
between running an assessment from an auditor versus having automated
tooling. And in conclusion, well, we'll conclude
with what the real truth is about everything, but the documentation
really holds up the test of ground. There is an assumption made that
you understand one or more services of the cloud service provider that
you may be dealing with. It could be any cloud service provider. You don't have
to be an expert in it, but having some understanding of some of
the foundational pieces would be helpful as we go through this talk. If you're
an auditor, even better, maybe this may be an introduction to
what modern auditing could look like. So without further ado,
let's get into this. First of all, nine to five, I am the head
of security and as a CISO, four of a growing company.
Normal day for me is about running initiatives and trying
to reduce the risk of an overall organization's security posture.
Before that, I used to run a practice of cloud
security for a consulting company, which I'm an investor in.
We used to help organizations of all sizes in
different industries, specifically enterprise, move into
cloud through digital transformation. Outside my nine to
five on the weekends, I am the host of Cloud security podcast, a weekly
video podcast which is live streamed every week, and we talk to different
cloud security experts on various topics around cloud security each week.
If you are a follower of the podcast and subscribe
or come on livestream special shout out to you and thank you for joining me
over here. Looking at the experience that I've had as an auditor, you would be
able to take that and apply some of those concepts into your
environment as applying from a perspective of if you
have an internal auditor, what kind of questions you should be asking them, or what
kind of expectations you should have from them, or what kind of information you should
be provider them so they can help you the best way possible. First thing,
suitable framework based on the organization you work for and
the kind of data you deal with. You may have a lot of frameworks from
a compliance perspective that you may have to adhere to. Those frameworks
are pretty rigid in terms of requirements
they have. Some of them even call out specifically what encryption algorithms
should be used. You could be looking at things like NIST,
ISO 27,001, GDPR, sock two type two,
PCI, HIPAA. We can keep going on, but a
lot of these would primarily depend on the kind of organization you have and the
kind of data you store in cloud. This may not be as different to
what you run on your data center environment, but it will be
different in terms of the kind of landscape you have in your
cloud environment and how shared responsibility plays an important
role in this, especially if you're in a hybrid environment where your applications
exist both in an on premise world as well as a
cloud world. You may have to think about custom frameworks where what
segmentation is appropriate for your architecture, whether you
have your non compliance driven architecture
or non compliance driven data and application
hosted in cloud, whereas the compliance driven sensitive data
being hosted on premise. There could be multiple models like that as well.
But primarily you would use a foundational piece like a NIST
CSF or ISO 27,001 as a base.
And on top of that, build for the cloud service provider you work
on now, that's generally the kind of framework as a
baseline that you would start with. Let's talk about the cloud assessment landscape.
As you can imagine, I love blogs. The reason I had this picture for expectation
versus reality is the expectation that people have about
landscape. For any cloud environment. I'm going to take the three most popular ones,
Azure, GCP and AWS. They all have
documentation on AWS. Well architected framework,
well architected framework in Google Cloud, well architected framework
in Azure. But how many people actually follow these?
Even though cloud service providers have been quite open about what you
should be doing as the right form of architecture? Answer is none of
them. People go through exercises to shape some of their
organization architecture with the well architected framework.
I think AWS and some of the other cloud service provider
have assessments that help you map to how aligned you
are to the well architected framework. But a lot of times what we
would find in an audit is it's not really well aligned,
it's not by the textbook. So that kind of makes things quite
challenging. To that point, the cloud adoption type,
what you really see in the real world as an auditor or as someone
who runs a cloud security assessment is cloud architecture,
which would have been migrated into cloud.
How do I put this in a simple way so I don't offend
anyone? There are two ways to move into cloud. One is a simple lift
and shift model where you had something on premise and you moved it exactly as
it is into cloud. That's called lift and shift, whereas there's another model
where you migrated into cloud but went through digital transformation,
you made them into microservices and started using some of the services
which were provided by a cloud provider. Now, depending on
what stage of migration you are in, like for example, if you're migrated
recently, or if you've been in the cloud for a
year or maybe for a few years, you may have a separate security
tenancy or account in your cloud service provider.
And depending on the cloud adoption type, you could have gone down
either ways. What that means is you would come across teams which have
been specifically designed that their job is to provision
the tenancy or accounts for the CSP that
the customer is using. Each business unit sometimes are given
a lot of liberty in what they can do in each of these tenancies,
but there's usually like a central team that creates it.
Sometimes it's just the individual business unit are paying for themselves.
But predominantly the adoption type is varied.
So when you walk into an organization and thinking about, okay, clearly well
architected framework is not going to be the case because the
reality is depending on what stage of migration they are in and
how they migrated, it could be a combination of any of these.
So my advice would be to what kind of adoption was this
and at what stage of migration to cloud they are currently
at, to kind of get into that physical mind from of, okay, this is
the kind of question or the subset I should be thinking of. Once you
understand the type of adoption or the stage that the
customer is in, the next obvious step that a lot of people go into is
let's talk about the different source types that I need to assess expectation
over there. If you look at the documentation, if you're in AWS, the expectation would
be, I would get a lot of cloudformation templates. You probably would
be only using one cloud service provider, maybe two maximum,
right? Why would you go more than two? If you are a mature organization,
you may even be using cloud native services, which could be
cheap combination of services provider by your cloud
service provider and maybe even deploying multiple times a day as well.
All of that would be built on a code repository because everything
would be running on code, and no one would have access to any of
the production environment either via RDP or SSH.
Unfortunately, the reality is different. The truth is, I've been in
assessments where infrastructure type is a mix of
containers, kubernetes, vms, EC two,
you go in and you're told, hey, we only have one tenancy.
And you make an assumption that okay, one tenancy. So they would have gone down
the well architected framework, they would have segmented their network properly and would
only be using one type of compute because you would only have one application per
network. Unfortunately, a lot of the conversations that I
had was where one network had multiple assets
or multiple applications hosted within that one single network, which is not
a bad pattern if you segment them properly. But you're told
that there's only one network without letting you know that there are
hundreds of services within it. So you can see where the
discrepancy comes in, because it's cloud, and one click gets your data
better. So assuming that if someone tells you we only have one tenancy,
whether it's AWS, azure or GCP, you probably are
looking at potentially hundreds of services. That's kind of
point number one, application itself, you could have a mix of monolith
or a microservices. Now generally this is easier to kind of comprehend,
because if an organization has been in existence for over ten years,
it's most likely they already have some monoliths which they've been carrying over.
So digital transformation may not have fully
been adopted. So you might see a mix of things which are
not that flexible, so they might not give you that to
assess. They would just say, hey, focus on these, do not focus on
these. So there could be those kind of scenarios as well. Now we'd mentioned source
types, and I think it's worthwhile calling out, not everyone does
automation in cloud, not everyone does infrastructure has
cloud. Sometimes it's just easier for you to click through
the console of your favorite CSP and just deploy
them. But what that also means is the other extreme where
people have gone down the infrastructure has code path. What I was getting a
lot of times as an auditor was a Yaml file, and I was told,
hey, audit the Yaml file. This is exactly what we use, and this goes
into production. So no access to the actual accounts as well
as you can imagine, that makes things very difficult. The other thing that
you would also notice from a source perspective is the type of
access you get. Some organizations, they'll give you all admin
access, because it's a small team like some of the startups that I worked with
gave me full access, and this is a trust because it's a small team
of 25 people, everyone knows everyone and understandable,
but I would probably say do not give admin access to an external auditor who's
trying to assess your cloud environment. The other one example that
I've seen is where each business unit gets its own
data center or tenancy, and you end up in a situation
where you have 20 plus accounts under one business unit because
they were told by Amazon you should have segregation of accounts.
And they've created multiple accounts because creating an account is free,
but you just put so much stuff in there. So that's another
version which we come across where they might ask you to audit just one
business unit, but then again, kind of like the infrastructure type where you
assume it's just one business unit. So Max might what, five to ten applications,
but kind of realize it's a lot more. These are examples of
not so mature cloud organizations. However, there are
some good examples as well that I had the fortune to work with some of
these mature organizations. An enterprise, they had
predefined security default for all their environments. They did
have a centralized team to deploy and provision cloud
tenancies for their entire organization. So if I was a business unit
and I wanted a AWS account, I can go to that team and get an
AWS account which already had my security defaults over there. I was
given access with a read only permission and I was
given, provided, even provided mean I was mind
blown at that point. I'm like oh my God, they want me to actually use
come of the automation that I've created to not waste their
time with me asking them questions and figuring out how to put
access keys instead I could just run come automation and do the
entire audit in half the time. So I can understand
the architecture of the application in the first half of
my audit and the remaining is basically cut in half because I'm just going
to run a tool while I'm having the interview with them. So I'm just saying
I love mature organizations. So that's some of the realities that you
find in a organization which has just,
I guess found their way to maturity. You can already see documentation is
starting to show some cracks. We definitely don't have AWS well architected
framework or Azure or even Google Cloud's well architected framework
being used. And then the assumption that everything is cloud native.
Because if you read documentation from any of your CSPM, they're basically calling
out like for example Azure would say use Azure DevOps,
don't use Jenkins or any other tool, insert another tool which is
open source, but your developers love it. They would also call out you should
use only the tools that are there in their cloud service provider,
which clearly is not a complete security suite. But sure,
we clearly cannot be following that to the t. Not just
as someone who audits AWS assessments or does AWS
assessments or even runs a team that has AWS assessments.
If you're one of those, you probably should start thinking about don't just rely on
cloud native and stop drinking the kool aid. For lack of better word,
they don't have all the answers to all your security requirements.
So you definitely have to seek an external person to
either identify what you're missing or have someone in your team
research and find out what you're actually missing. From a risk perspective,
you could be completely missing out on some of the blind spots that
are created by just drinking the cloud koolaid. Let's talk about threats.
And I love this. As I mentioned, I love dogs. So this was something hilarious
that I found out somehow people have this negative, I guess, emotion attached
to doing threats assessments. And I just do not
get it because I understand there's a compliance requirement and you're trying to have a
certification. So you can increase your sales as a startup or
as an enterprise. You can show that the customers can
trust your organization because you take security seriously and consider all
kinds of threats in cloud. So let's go through these threats and
identify what kind of brackets do these really fit in.
This is the meter attack, which is a really popular TTP
or tactic tools and techniques. That's how they say it. Or tactic techniques
and tools. However you want to say it, every threat hunter would
look at something like this in order to understand what is the kill chain
or aka how do I completely take over an
AWS, GCP or azure account or tenancy?
These are some of the kill chains that are known in the industry.
So as you can see, start from the left, how you get initial access,
how do you persist access? How do you go about
escalating your privileges, what kind of defense measures you
can take, and credential access? How can you do discovery work?
I'm going to try and focus on the initial access because
everything else is built on the assumption that you have access.
So I guess why not build threat on how someone
would get initial access, right? So let's focus on that. If you look at all
of these drive by compromise, exploit, public facing application
phishing, trusted relationship and valid accounts, they kind of fall into
three big buckets. Someone's exploiting a public facing
application of yours, or someone who's successful in getting credentials
from one of your staff members, or you're not managing
your supply chain or third party in a good way. Let's take a deeper look,
right, because we're talking about threats. I'm not just not going to give you the
high level definition. Let's go a bit more deeper. Public facing applications is usually
around application security and network security. Remember the conversation about one network
that I had just before? And application security is the application which is
hosted inside that network. Accidental s three bucket
being made public, or a Google Cloud bucket being made public. Those are
scenarios for public facing application. There's another scenario where you could have
a Kubernetes clusters API open to the Internet as well.
Someone's able to use that and escape out. Brings me to point number two,
which is phishing identity access management and secret management. Your identity
access management uses the same password as
your corporate username password. There is no single sign on, there is
no multiple factor. And to make things worse,
in a cloud environment, it's not just a regular user,
an admin user, there's a third kind of user or an identity
in a cloud environment, which is also called a server identity
or a computer identity. The concept is even when you're
not logged in, you can make a server or a service have permissions
which they can use to go and take some actions. Now it's
great from an automation perspective, you could be sleeping and all your machines
are being patched or all your scans are running while you're sleeping away.
But the other point to this also is that if someone exploits that and
is able to use that key that's been provided to that, I guess,
server, they can use it for doing exactly the opposite of what it should
be doing. So that's phishing, invalid accounts. Third party management
for this is primarily around shared responsibility. Now whether it's
shared responsibility between the third party that you give access to, you may have a
CSPM for managing security posture, you may have a data
dog for performance management or something else. Include any services
that you may think of and you give them access user either a
credential of some sort into your cloud service provider. As you've done that,
you've basically opened up another identity that has access to your environment.
So let's just say probably should look into reviewing this ongoingly
and also try to look at having come kind of a check
for how often was someone accessing or updating
new third party supply chains or new third party into
your supply chain? Let's talk about assessment types. We've spoken about the source,
we've spoken about the kind of adoption. So I'm an auditor,
or I'm about to learn auditing and I've kind of gone in. Okay, so I've
given you a realistic picture of the kind of environments you would see.
Let's talk about the kind of assessments that people do. One is
a point in time, big bracket. Point in time would be someone, an auditor
comes in, goes through a checklist with you for one of the compliance
standards that we mentioned earlier, whether that's iso 27,001 or NIST
standard or soc two, type two as well. Another type for point in time is
someone like me or another person who would have been part of my team who
uses automation. We would come in, we would ask you about architecture
review of what is the architecture of your cloud
environment, what kind of services are you using? And we may even
validate that using some kind of an automation tool. Because let's face
it, you may think you know all the services, but that may not be the
complete truth. So it's always a good idea to have
some kind of automation handy with some access keys or some
username passwords that you can have for the AWS or
Azure or Google Cloud account. So you can understand on your own,
are there services that the customer or the client should be aware of,
which they're not currently, unless they have basically chosen to hide that
information. The complete different story. Now, these are point in time,
another form of assessment that a lot of people think is an assessment,
but I think it's more awareness and visibility and
monitoring, which is the continuous assessment type, which is providers
like of your CSPM, which is cloud security posture manager or
cloud access security brokers, CASP, what these provide,
and I would not be going into too much definition of these providers.
They are excellent tools. If you are starting off in cloud for the
first time and you have no idea where to go, great tools for that.
It gives you visibility for what your cloud
looks like compared to a standard which could be CIs or
NIST or some other standard that they support right now. And CASB's
are almost, the way I would put this is it's a proxy for
what kind of services are allowed in your network. So you could choose
to say I only allow AWS as a cloud service
provider in my environment. Or Azure has the only one, or maybe a
combination of two most popular ones nothing outside that. You would control
that using cloud access security broker you scans also use that for checking
what other SaaS services are being used in your organization, but that's
more of a continuous model. So what's the reality of getting
any of these assessments done? If you're looking at a point in time or continuous
assessment, the difference would be in a point in time continuous
assessment. If you do a regular point in time assessment, you get an audit
of your architecture and get information about
what may be a potential risk that you're exposing yourself to without realizing
in your cloud environment, which the CSPM may not have
considered and worthwhile calling out the cspms of the world.
They are great tools, but they're usually focusing on the checklist
approach because there's an API that they call and they rely on
the availability of an API before they can even add that checklist in there.
There's no manual approach to it. So the risk that is shared
is a based on a checklist which is API
driven. Great for something that already has an API.
But for me personally, what I found after running CSPM
for a lot of years, it looks a context for why
is something a high risk? Why is it a high risk
if I have an s three bucket open to public when it is supposed to
be public? Or why do I have it has a risk
when my s three bucket policy on the top of AWS account,
which controls all the s three bucket policies says irrespective of the status
of the individual bucket, all my buckets are going to remain private.
So things like that are just not there. There is a context
missing between a CSPM and a CASB. It's a great tool
for you, giving you visibility, but it just lacks that
context. So it doesn't have the context of the architecture. If it makes sense
to architect a solution like that from a security context, if there
are enough defense and dev layers, it doesn't make sense from a
concept of okay, as I'm saying this, I do want to call it
out. I don't dislike CSPM. Hate is probably a strong word.
The reason I say this is because I think it's worthwhile calling
out that the report that you would get from a
point in time assessment would help you create actionable backlogs
in your security team or relevant development teams. Whereas what you get from
a CASB or CSPM may really be about how
do you link to a compliance checklist, which may be the goal of
your organizations are totally fine with that, but you probably need more than
that to understand why is this something a risk? And is this genuinely a
risk or just a false positive? So a real risk is
only real, in my opinion, is when it's assessed by people
like you and I, unless AI machine learning gets to that point where it can
make that, I guess, call. So whenever that happens, but for the moment,
we're stuck with this. So I'm going to stop bashing
CSPM. But let me just tell you about, I guess the other things that I've
noticed being has caspian CSPM after being customer of these for some
time. The checks and controls are obviously API driven and
if there is a service which is released by one of the cloud service
provider, it's not always the case that it becomes available
on the day of the release. So if there's a new service that
gets announced right now by any of the cloud service providers,
your CASB or your CSPM may take some time or may rely on
your feedback before this gets added into your so
called continuous assessment tool, which ends up in a scenario
where you have a lot of wall of red. So for example, assume I
came in or someone else who looks like me and knows like me uses
automation for reducing the audit time to half and comes
with a checklist and gives it to you. What you might realize if you use
some of that checklist and dig into one of these CSPM. A lot of them
may already be there, but they're buried in the gamut
of false positives or ignored messages or alerts
of CSPM. If this was real chalk, I would probably go
raise your hand if you have seen a wall of red on your CSPM
provider. How many have zero as the alerts
on their CSPM provider? I do not know of that many
examples where people have not had false positive because of
the lack of context, which is what I was talking about earlier. So that's the
honest truth between a point of in time assessment as well has an
automation driven assessment and a
tool which is a CSPM or a CASP. That's the difference. Talking about tools,
I wanted to call out some of the tools that I've personally used and some
of the tools that have been recommended by the community, I would definitely
ask you to check them out. Obviously this is not a complete list. This is
the one that I could fit in the slide, but if there are ones that
are popular and I've missed out on them, clearly add them in has
you go these are just for the tools of the
compute itself, but there's another version that's coming out which
is specifically for infrastructure as code, which I believe is almost like
the next generation of cloud security. Having done cloud security podcast
for almost two years with 40,000 downloads, and having endless conversations with
cloud security experts around the world, one thing I've realized, we're going through evolutions
of how cloud security is evolving. These are lists which
are applicable across the board for the moment, irrespective of
if you're using infrastructure as code or not. But now we're
at that generation where a lot of tools like checkoff from bridge
crew and other tools which are going into the space of infrastructure
as code security where the DevOps is transformed into devsecops
and the security alerts are being captured right in the beginning when it's
being committed into your source repository or your code repository.
So do check them out as well. But this is a great place to start
if you are someone who may have a combination of complex environments
with a bit of infrastructure as code, and bit of automation and bit of click
Ops. So definitely check these out and obviously ask any questions if
you have any. In conclusion, I have a few truth that I wanted to reveal.
You definitely need both continuous as well as point in time assessments.
Continuous assessments are great from a monitoring perspective, as at any given
point in time you don't want to wait for a hypothetical ashish to knock on
your door and hey, let's talk for the next two weeks and see what we
can find out when you're done. Assessment you need something ongoing so you can monitor
for configuration drifts. So you definitely need something
like a CSPM, or probably even something better than a CSPM if you can design
it on your own. Talking about designing on your own, the challenge with open source
tools, if you do go down that path, like the example that I gave you
before, open source tools are great, but they also would not cover
all the new services, which means you need to have some skill set in your
team to either add and contribute into the open
source so you have the new services available and
someone has spent the time to understand what is a security requirement
for a particular service that has been released. I would also ask if
you are engaging an auditor, definitely understand if they
have an understanding of cloud, because let's be honest,
running an assessment on premise is not the same as running assessment
on cloud, where a lot of compute can be ephemeral.
You may have instances right now, but the IP changes
because the instance went down and a new ip came up and it has been
auto scaling or dynamically scaling up and down.
So you need to have an auditor that understands that
context because you don't want to go into a compliance audit
without realizing the truth behind whether they understand the environment in order,
whether you are in this exercise going to spend probably a lot more time
than someone who just understands cloud and know what to do when
you tell them, hey, I'm using this service from this cloud service provider,
and that's why we comply with this requirement. What do you think? They should be
able to give you a reasonable answer, which makes sense to both you and them
as well. So I would say the other approach you can take,
if you don't find one of those auditors and you probably are stuck with someone
who doesn't run internal assessments, call in someone. Again,
it doesn't need to be someone who has tools, that people
have been creating the community, but at least they have an understanding of
what the cloud infrastructure should be like, and they understand what
kind of common security services from the cloud service
provider you can use to pass your assessments.
But at the same time, what are the gaps that are left behind by using
those cloud assessment tools which are provided by the cloud service provider?
Last but not the least, the one truth that I want to give away,
and that's quite bold and underlined, a successful compliance certification
doesn't really mean you're secure. It just does mean that you were able to
convince an auditor that you are ticking all the boxes. So I
would ask you to be honest yourself with an audit now you
know what the truth behind doing an assessment from an auditor perspective
or a practitioner perspective is. So I would hope you would make
the right call and find an internal assessment
by your team or by calling an external auditor, maybe even build
some tools of your own and some checklists of your own which are relevant for
your organization or your industry, and use that as a baseline
for calling yourself secure. Or I guess, as secure as possible, because no
one's 100% secure. That's what my conclusion for you would be. And one final
thought would be find your trusted advisor to get a real picture
of risk in your cloud environment. I hope you learned something from this. So if
you have any questions or feedback, feel free to reach out to me
on that website. But otherwise, I just wanted to say thank you for inviting
me for this talk, and I am looking forward to some of the questions
that come through for this. If you're someone who enjoys cloud security content,
I would definitely ask you to just check out cloud cloud security podcast.
Well, but otherwise I would see you, but in the wild. But thank you so
much for your time, and I look forward to talking to you soon.