Hello, welcome in our session. My name is Carlo
Skripak, I'm technical director in the Melodic project
and today, together with Alaran from
the Melodic project, ALA is a technical lead in
this project. We will tell you
about our platform, our project,
and probably most important, we will tell you how to
deploy application into the multicloud and how to
done it with the optimized way, fully automatic
to the different cloud provided and
using optimized resources
to save the cost and to maximize the performance
of the applications. Let's start from the very beginning.
What is Melodic? Melodic is a single
universal platform for two things. One is the
deployment, automatic deployment of the application to
the multi cloud, so to the different cloud providers.
And the second one is the optimization of the
usage of the resources. So melodic automatically optimizes
which resources are used and how
to save the cost, maximize the performance and
other elements of the application.
Melodic is fully open resources project so
it cloud be download and use. It has been created
using the horizontal 2020 melodic project and
is further developed by the
seven Bulls company. Today we
will tell you what melodic is. We will show
some use cases so how it can be used for the AI
based application. And here we have the example of
the AI investments company which is using
melodic to optimize their trainings and trainings
of their machine learning models. And also we
will show the example of the big data application
based off nongenome which is used during the
research related to the genome processing and genome
mutation identification. So I hope that you will
find this session interesting. The first question
is why we should use platform like
melodic to deploy the applications. The first
and probably the most important reasons is that melodic
is the simplest and easiest way to use the
multi cloud approach. So instead of deploying manually
application choosing or selecting manually the
right cloud CTO which we want to deploy the application,
it is automatically done by the melodic based on
the already predefined model. The second thing is that
it's probably the only one unified way to
deploy virtual machines, containers,
serverless and big data frameworks automatically
to the different cloud providers. So melodic
supports all of these components and even more.
We're currently working on the support for the GPU
and FPGA's accelerators to
allow to deploy the machine learning workloads
to the accelerated resources.
As I said, it is automatically deployed to these cloud providers
listed below. So we are integrated them and the
deployment is done fully, automatically and even more.
Melodic optimize the usage of the cloud computing
resources. So melodic fetch all of the offers
from the cloud providers with pricing, with technical
parameters and select the
best one set of the resources to deploy
the application. And even more, it automatically
monitor the application and reconfigure the
application to optimize that deployment.
It's a very unique and probably the
only one platform which supports all
of this. The first step is to model the application
and we are using the camel cloud application
modeling and execution language. It is
the cloud agnostic language, not like
a cloud formation or heat or so it's
very similar to the Tosca, but also contains
the superset of additional features. Comparing to
the Tosca, we can model application so
not only the infrastructure, but also the application components,
connections, security. We can of course model infrastructure
as well. And very important,
we can define requirements,
constraints and utility function value for our
application. Thanks to that, we are
able to transform this model into the mathematical
form like a constraint
programming model. And this constraint programming model is
based for the optimizing resources
and that's the very unique element of
the melodic platform. The second unique element
is the way of determining what
is the best deployment. Melodic collect the
metrics or the different measurements like the cpu
usage, memory usage and other technical metrics,
but also the business metrics like average response
time to the customer, average handling time for
the customer, average time for the processing given
job, and so on. And additional metric
could be very easily add especially the metric
specific for the application. Based on that
collected metrics and the current deployment, we can
define so called utility function
which defines what is this best deployments.
Usually this deployment is a trade off
between the cost, performance, availability, security and
other elements. Because if
we do not have this trade off, then if we want
to minimize the cost, then we just do not need to
deploy the application because the cost will be zero.
If we want to maximize performance without minimizing
the cost, then we can deploy application
on the biggest virtual machines, or also usually
we have this trade off between the cost and performance,
availability and so on. And melodic, based on
the defined utility function is able
to find the optimal solution for
that. And this is the very unique
feature of the melodic. It is not supported,
at least according to my knowledge, by other platforms.
How melodic works the first step is to
prepare the application, the model of the application,
and set the parameters, initial values of
the requirements and constraints. It is done once,
only once. Of course the parameters could be adjust,
but they are also adjusted by the melodic during
the optimization process. So it is usually done
once. And after that melodic calculates
initial deployments based on the predefined parameters and
deploy the application to the selected cloud providers.
After the deployment, the metrics started to be collected
and melodic is verifying if the certain
threshold are exceeded. So for example,
if the response time is too long, or the typical
processing time is too long, or any other metric
is exceeded, we called that SLO violation.
So in case of this SLO violation, the new
deployment, the new solution is calculated,
new optimization is started with the new
values of the metrics and the parameters.
Thanks to that, melodic is continuously optimizing
application to allow them and to
adjust them to the current workload. So it
doesn't need to be done manually or through the predefined
set of rules. It is done completely automatically.
Melodic is using very advanced optimization algorithms.
We are using constraint programming
optimization, we are using genetic optimization.
We are using Monte Carlo research with neural network
in the similar way as the alphago is using for
solving the optimization platform. So the results
of proactive optimization are really good.
Here we have the overall architecture of the melodic.
I maybe not go into too deeply into that,
but few key elements are that we
are using the microservice architecture. Each of
the key module is a separate microservice.
We are using enterprise service pass mule,
esp in the community edition as a control plane.
The logic and business flow is
orchestrated through the BPM. We are using Kamunda and
monitoring plane using for the sending metrics
is done presented using
the active MQ broker that's
melodic. But we are of course still working on
that. And new version is developed
within the morphemic project. And the
first key novelty of that project
will be the polymorph architecture. So application
will not only be adapt through the selecting resources,
through the selecting to which cloud providers we
should deploy and CTO which type of virtual machines we should
choose, but we can also adapt the architecture.
So we would
be able to change the architecture of
the application. We could decide that instead of using
the virtual machines or containers, we can use the serverless components
and we can use also accelerated hardware
like FPGA or GPU.
The second novelty will be the proactive adaptation.
Actually melodic is adapting to the current workload,
to the current values of the metrics. But we
want to make a step farther into the future.
So we want to adapt to the expected
workload. We want to try to forecast execution
context and to be able to make a reconfiguration
anticipating for example the increase of the workflow,
increase number of the customers.
Actually if the number of the customers is resync,
we are starting reconfiguration and it
takes some times. So there is
a short period when the application is not ready
for this increased number of the customers.
But in morphemic we want to predicted that and to
add that feature to the melodic platform.
So we will be able to predict the future
workloads and anticipated this deployment and
prepare application for that.
So the proactive adaptation will work starting
from the initial deployment. Then the metrics will be
collected as currently collected
in the melodic. But in the third point,
we will forecast the future values of the metrics
and the optimization of the resources will
be based on the forecasted values of the metrics,
and the deployment of the optimal deployment plan
will be determined based on that forecasted values.
And then the application will be
reconfigured anticipating
that workflow. Yeah.
So if you find that interesting, if you
find melodic and melodic platform
interesting, please stay in touch with us. Follow us
on LinkedIn, Twitter and Facebook,
or visit the melodic cloud website.
And now I want to briefly tell about the
use based so who is using melodic?
What are the benefits of using melodic?
And after these use cases, Allah will present
the live demo, how to use melodic,
how it looks like. And I really encourage
you to give a so
first user of the melodic is AI investments.
It is a polish company, fintech company,
which is working on advanced methods for the portfolio
optimization using AI models.
AI investments is working on the time series forecasting
and also portfolio optimizations.
AI investment platform invest in over 200
markets, different markets, and for each
market, separate forecasting model is trained
and it needs to be retrained periodically.
So the typical business goal for the AI
investments is to train predefined number of the
models in the specific time. Of course using
as minimal number of resources as possible,
just to save the cost.
The investment analyst in the AI starts to
train the models using on premises resources because
it's already present, so it can be used.
But if melodic determines that
on premises resources, it takes too long.
So for example, premises resources, it can
take 3 hours. Then additional cloud
resources are deployed and the number of the workers
is increased. After that,
new metrics value are collected and
melodic is calculating the
time to finish. If it's still too long, then additional
resources are added and
if the number of the resources is enough
to process in the given time, the processing
is finished and all of the cloud resources
are removed just to save the cost.
So that's a very typical process for
the using of melodic. I think it's quite simple,
but the results of that optimization are very
significant. So the benefits
are from the AI investments point of
view, it is the very effective way of the optimization
of the resources.
Melodic is very well fit for the scaling machine
learning training. Also we can control
the budget because we could optimize the time
having the budget constraints so not
exceed the usage of the cloud resources.
And also it increased
reliability and higher availability of the application.
Because in case of the failure of the one components,
the melodic deploys additional one.
So for the AI investments, the savings
are quite significant.
So we are able to save
175,000 of
us dollars. In the three years perspective,
it is the difference between the optimal and
the non optimal solutions. Probably the real
savings are lower but are still very significant.
We have published these results so they are
available with all of the condition and
how the measurements has been done.
You can find that on the melodic webpage
with the more detailed use case description.
Second application this is the
application big data application deployed
on the spark and it is based to process genome
data to find the mutation in
the genome in the given genome comparing to the reference
one. This application is used by the one
of the polish universities to perform research
related to the genome, especially to
the mutation in the genome. And it is a very valuable
knowledge to identify some genome
based disease and diseases and other
issues. And comparing this
mutation and the similarity
between this mutation give the researchers
from the university very valuable knowledge. And they
are also using melodic to optimize the processing
time. The use case is
very similar as for the AI investments.
So the researcher on the university is starting
processing the given workload. So usually it is the given
genome data and want to compare them
with the reference data. After starting the process,
melodic is trying to determine how long it
takes. If it takes too long, then additional resources
are added and again the metrics
are collected and melodic determines how long
it takes. It's still too long.
So the researcher wants to finish this
task in the 1 hour. But even
with the additional resources, it's still too long.
Somalodic is automatically added new
resources and the new time
to finish is below the 1 hour.
Also the costs are optimized to
have a balance between the processing time and
cost. And of course after the finishing deployment,
melodic is removing all
of the cloud resources.
That's the most typical use case application.
Of course we have more users of the melodic. All of
these stories are described on the melodic
website. So I really encourage you CTO,
take a look and go
deeply into that. And now allah will
show the live demo how the melodic works.
We will go through the whole workload. So we will
start with the camel model of the application.
Then maybe we will not deploy the melodic platform but
briefly show the melodic platform.
Then allah will show how to submit the
camel model to the melodic, how to start the deployment
application. Then everything is done fully,
automatically and at the end you can
connect CTO your application and
enjoy. So now it's time for the
live presentation. Now I would like to
present you how to automatically deploy own application
by melodic platform. I will perform deployment
of spark based application. We will monitor application
metrics and observe reconfiguration process
which is done by melodic for reasons of optimization.
My melodic platform is installed on virtual machine
on AWS and it is up and running.
I'm locked in. Melodic users are
managed by LDAP. We have three possible roles
of users common user he can perform application
deployments admin user he manages
of users accounts and also has all
privileges from common user and
technical user. He is used only internally by
melodic components and he is not important
from client's point of view. The first
step in melodic usage is the defining of
cloud settings. In provider settings menu
part, we can check and update providers
credentials and options. As we can see in
cloud definition for providers view, filling these
values is required in order to perform successful
deployment because they are based in contact
with providers. For example, by creating
virtual instances on my environment,
I have already defined these values for
Amazon web service and for
OpenStack providers. In these definitions
we provided cloud credentials and properties,
for example settings for Amazon Security group
or set of private images which we would like to
use in our deployments. When our platform
is properly configured, we can go to deployment
bookmark. Today I would like to
deploy genome application which was described
by Pavel a moment ago. Before deployment we
need to model our application with its
requirements in camel model which is human,
understandable and editable form.
After that such model is transformed to XMI
format form understandable formulaic
we upload this file here by drag and
drop. Now our model is being validated
and after that it will be saved in database.
In a minute I will be asked for field values
of AWS developers credentials.
Providing these credentials is required in order
to save results of our genome application in
AWS S freebucket.
But in view of security reasons, we shouldn't
put them directly in camel model file.
So we use placeholders in camel file and
after that we need to provide these values here.
In this case, it is not the first
upload of such model on this virtual machine.
So these variables already exist in predicted
secure store. I can verify them
update if they were changed and after that
choose save button in the last step
I need to choose which application I want to
deploy and which cloud providers I want
to use. Here is also possible to run application
in simulation mode. Simulation mode
is the case when we don't want to deploy real
virtual machines on provided platform but
only check which solution will be chosen by
melodic. We manually set values of
metrics in simulation part and
observe the result but today our aim
is to perform real deployment of
genome application so
I leave this option turned off. We would
like to deploy genome only on AWS
so we chose this cloud definition. Thanks to
that melodic has credentials for this provider.
After that we can go to the last step here where
starting deployment is available.
After starting the process, in a minute we are moved to the
deployment process view. Here we
can observe the progress of that. In the
meantime, I would like to briefly describe application
which is being deployed
by melodic. Now Genome is a big data
application which performs some calculations
and safe results in AWS as freebacket
so we need to provide developers credentials to AWS.
Genome's performance is managed by Spark.
In genome application we use Spark as platform
for big data operations which are performed
parallel on many machines and managed by
one machine named Sparkmaster.
Sparkmaster is available by default on
melodic platform. Melodic creates proper
number of spark workers as virtual machines
considered our requirements from camel model.
Thanks to measurements of application metrics, melodic makes
a decision about creating additional instances
with workers or about deleting unnecessary
ones. Spark divides all calculations
named tasks between available workers in
order to optimize application performance and
cost. Please let me come back
to our process. Phishing offers is
the first step of deployment process. We have
information about current total number of
offers from previously selected providers.
So in this case from AWS.
From these offers melodic will choose the best solution
for worker component. After choosing
this box or offer option from mani
which is available here, we are directed
to view of all currently available offers.
There are clouds with my credentials
and also with my properties for security group
and for filters for our private images.
Also we have here hardware
with information about cores,
ram and disk and available locations
where our virtual machines could
be located and the last element here images.
There are only private images
visible here but of course all public images
are available for us. Now I come
back to our process view and we can see that the
next step of process is generating constraint problem.
Constraint problem is generated based
off our requirements defined in
KaML model. In a simple process view
there are visualized all variables from constraint problem
with the domain values for genome
worker, cardinality worker course and provider
for Spark worker. Detailed data
are shown after click of this box and
here are presented list of variables with
additional information about component type,
domain and type of this domain.
Utility formula. It is used for measure
utility of each possible solutions and choose
the best one list of constants with
types and values. They are created from user requirements
and are used in melodic calculations.
Here we can see for example minimum and
maximum values for cardinality of spark worker
instances or the same type of restriction
for number of spark worker cores.
So we can see that in our deployments
we would like CTO have from one to maximum
ten workers and the last element here
list of metrics with data types and values
initial values. They describe current performance
of this application. Thanks to them, melodic can make
a decision about triggering the reconfiguration
process which means creating new
additional instances or deleting not
fully used ones. Thanks to metrics,
melodic can do the most important task which
is cost optimization. We back to process
view when constraint problem is generated,
it is time for rezoning. Melodic finds here the
best the most profitable solution for the problem defined
by us. When resulting is completed,
we can observe information about calculate solution
utility value and values for each variables.
In that case one as
worker cardinality for worker cores and provider
for spark worker from zero index. So it
is AWS. The next
step in process deployment is deploying.
Here melodic performs operations based on
calculated solution. This solution is deployed
for each application component. Velodic creates
proper instances, remains them or deletes.
If you want to have more detailed view,
it is possible to see the process view using kamunda
by choosing advanced view button from upper
left corner. From this view,
Kamunda is tool for monitoring and
for modeling processes in BPM and standard and
for management of them. I log in by the same
credentials as for my melodic platform and
in order to see detailed view in Kamunda,
I need to choose running process instances
and after that process to monitoring from
the list. And now we can see
view of chosen process with all day variables
and also detailed view of
the whole process with each steps.
This view is for more technical users.
It could be useful for example during diagnostic
of some problems. We can see
that now we are even
here. So it is the end of our process.
In order to verify this fact I go to
Merlot Qi again and yes we can see
that our application successfully started.
So the deployment process is
finished and I can check the result in
your application bookmark.
In this view there are displayed list
of created virtual machines and functions.
Genome application requires only virtual machines.
We can see that melodic creates one virtual
machine. As far this machine is
created in AWS EC two provided in Dublin.
What is more we have here button for web SSH
connection which is really useful in testing process.
When I successfully deployed spark application by melodic
I can go to Grafana.
Grafana is tool for
monitoring displaying statistics and metrics.
We can use them for monitoring performance of
applications deployed by melodic. Each application
has own metrics and own parameters to
control so we need to create predicted Grafana
dashboard for each of them. Also genome
application has own grafana settings
and we can see them here.
For now metrics from our application
are not available yet. We can see only that
we have now one instance so one
worker. In the meantime we can control
our application in Sparkmaster
UI.
Sparkmaster is built into melodic platform
so we go to the same IP address and 81
81 port in order to
check the Sparkmaster UI and
here we can observe list
of available workers after refreshing
of this view, of course we can see
that now we have one worker and
one running application and also
one driver. So now all
tasks are sent to this one worker
by our spark master and
it is situation after initial deployment decision
about creating the new ones or
deleting. Some of workers
are made by melodic based on measured metrics.
In such situation new process is
triggered and it is named reconfiguration
process. I think that now we can
go again to our grafana dashboard
and we can see that metrics are
being correctly calculated and passed
to the melodic because they are visible
also in our Grafana view.
Color of limitation of traffic lights
inform us if application will finish on time.
Now we can see the first estimation so
it can be not correct. I think
because we
have no enough data
for a good estimation so we need
to wait a minute and even now we can see
that our light is red.
Also we
can see that our time left is
not enough to finish our calculate on time
because the initial
time indicated time because
the expected time is indicated in
camel model and in this case it is equal to
60 minutes. We can observe
how many minutes left from this time period. Under this
time left value and based on current
performance it is calculate the estimated
time left on the left.
On the first chart we can monitor number
of instances. So now we have one
node so one worker and
in the bottom ones it is presented number
of remaining simulation. This value is
decreasing with performing
next task by spark.
On the right on chart named number
of cores we can see value of minimum
course needed to finish calculations on time
and current number of course under total
course value the green one is the value of required
number, of course, and the yellow one means current number
of them. Now melodic claims that
we need at least four cores and even
now six cores, seven cores,
seven cores and we have only one.
Also estimated time is higher
than time left. We can see red
light. So tree are signals
that our application needs more resources.
In such situation, melodic makes a decision
about triggering reconfiguration process.
So we can suppose that in the background reconfiguration
process should being done in
order to verify it.
I back CTo our melodic UI
and I go to process view and here
we can see current process and
it is our reconfiguration process. In reconfiguration
process, melodic doesn't fetch new offers and
uses the same constraint problem as for initial
deployment. For tree reasons, the first
step is rezoning. As result,
we can see new calculated solution which
will be deployed. Now melody claims
that two workers will be needed
and this solution is now deployed.
So in a minute we will see
our new worker.
Oh yes, even now our new worker
should be visible because the reconfiguration
process is finished. I can verify
this fact also in your application part.
And yes, now we have two virtual machines,
two workers and this is the new one from
our reconfiguration process.
Also I can check this fact
in our Sparkmaster UI. I need to
refresh this view. And now two workers
are available. We have two live workers.
So now we can see that Sparkmaster
divides tasks between these two
workers in case of
genome. In the first part of performing calculations,
additional workers are created. As far as
melodic measures that effectiveness of application is
too low. In the final part of performance of
spark jobs, melodic makes decision about
deleting unnecessary instances when
it is visible that application will
finish on time. And now we are
in our initial
part of the whole process because as
I mentioned, we have 60 minutes to
perform the whole process. So we are at the beginning
of them and now additional workers are
being created because of effectiveness
of our application.
Now I go to Grafana view and
we can see that now we have two workers,
two nodes. Next tasks are
done and we can see that now
our estimated time is close to time left.
And even now melody claims that it will
be possible to finish the whole process on time.
But now our estimated time is
bigger again. So we can suppose
that in a minute our time will
be red again. And probably
we will see the new reconfiguration process
and the whole process is being performed to
the moment where our estimated
time will be enough for us,
enough for our requirements and
thanks to that, finishing the whole process in
our expected time will be possible, right? So we successfully
observed the configuration process of spark application.
This is the end of spark application deployment
done by melodic demonstration and we
can see that the whole optimization process is
done fully automatically. Okay,
so thank you very much for your
attention and this is all from my
side. Thank you. Thank you Allah.
I hope you enjoyed that presentation. If you have any
question, please do not hesitate to ask these questions.
And also as I said, I really encourage to download melodic
and at least give a try.
Especially that melodic is fully open source release
under the Mozilla Public License 20.
So you can use that for any type of
workloads, commercial and non commercial
one. And also please follow
us on the LinkedIn, Twitter,
Facebook and please visit melodic
site www. Melodic Cloud.
If you have any questions, please do not hesitate
to contact us.
Also, I really encourage to follow our morphemic
project which is the successor of the melodic
and aim for the further development of the
melodic platform with really novel
and unique concept like polymorphic adaptation
and proactive adaptation. So stay
tuned, take a look and I think
that it could be very interesting see
what are the results will be. And once
again thank you for the invitation. We are very
happy that able to present
you this session and I hope that you would
find that useful. Thank you.