Hello. Hello people. My name is Andrea.
I'm from Brazil and I have been working with
Python for over five years and with
RPA for over two years.
I work at a company here in Brazil that provides
accounting and tax services.
My job here is to help my colleagues to
reduce their time spent on repetitive tasks.
I will divide my presentation into two parts.
The first one is a sequence of slides,
and the second one I will bring you a
real case of a task automated by a bot.
So first of all, I make
a disclaimer here for the english speakers.
I apologize for the accent sometimes,
and I will try to make myself clear
enough and make this presentation
at least understandable for you. Okay?
So imagine that
you can apply this to any system
in your company, be it an rep
like SAP system or any other
internal system in your company, or even a
web application. We will see
how to do this. So RPA
stands for robotic process. Automation is
the use of technology to handle repetitive
tasks, freeing up human workers
for more complex responsibilities.
Let's move on.
Why Python is a popular choice for RPA
Python has a simple syntax,
extensive libraries, and a huge community
support.
Some of benefits of using RPA
in a day to work are time efficiency,
error reduction, and cost savings.
For time efficiency, one of the primary advantages
of RPA is
its ability to accelerate tasks,
freeing up valuable time for
employees to focus on more strategic and value
added activities.
By automating repetitive tasks,
employees can channel their energy towards more
meaningful work. There is
reduction too,
and cost savings.
Implementing RPA can resulting in substantial
cost savings for any organizations.
How RPA automates repetitive tasks
in three main ways.
Automated workflows it
has efficient data handling and
for the result of this increase
or productivity, will you
see here some examples of RPA applications
in some industries? Okay,
financing, healthcare, retail, chimeshafue in
financing, automating, transaction processing,
report generation, and compliance tasks
is some of the
tasks that be automated by
a bot.
To illustrate the practical application of RPA
in Python, let's consider a case study
involving an invoice in processing.
Let's imagine a following scenario.
A company has receives an invoice via
email daily, okay?
So the accounts payable team
manually extracts relevant information such
as invoice number, date, and total amount
from each invoice. So with
that data, integers it into
the accounting system or an
excel worksheet or whatever.
So this is a classical
repetitive tasks, tasks that can
be automated by a bot, by an RPA
solution.
We can build an RPA solution
with Python, of course,
that checks the email inbox that
open the PDF file in
that email from that person that
sent to us the invoice here
and apply some OCR
techniques to extract data from
this PEDF and save this
information in whatever
place we want. Okay,
so this is one of
example of how an RPA
solution can help us in our daily
work here.
Some libraries for RPA development in Python,
some of them is Pyautogi,
selenium board, numpy pandas
and among others. Okay,
let's go to my computer screen to
see a real case of
a task by automated by a bot. Okay,
let's do this.
What I need to do here,
I need to search some codes from
this excel worksheet in application
desktop and bring back
the description from each code and
save it here.
I will do this manually one
or two times.
So this is my application desktop.
I click here and I need
to click here.
This is what I have to do.
So I put this code here
and search as a result this
bring me this description
and receive
and control v.
Okay I will
do this again for the second
one search.
Okay, there is another description here,
control c, control v.
So here I have five codes but
imagine if
I have 100 codes, 1000 codes,
and to do this again and again and again and again.
So this is a tasks that a bot
can help me a lot. I wrote this code in Python
that do that for me. Okay,
this code import an excel file with the codes
I need to consult, access a
desktop application, query one
code at a time, extract the description and save it
into my Excel file.
Okay, so let's see this
in action.
I will import my Excel file here.
So hands up the
bot, execute these steps for me. Okay,
here it search
the first code, get the description, save it
into my Excel file.
So search the second one,
get the description, save it in my excel,
search the third and do this
again and again and again and
again. Okay, so this is a huge benefit
because some tasks like
that can be automated by RPA
solution. That's saving my time.
That's the real benefit. Okay,
so let's see the result here.
Okay, all the description saved here.
Okay,
so let's
go back to my presentation.
Let's drag to
here in a conclusion.
An RPA solution in Python
offers so many benefits
for any company, for any organization.
By automating repetitive tasks, RPA liberates
employees from repetitive work,
allowing them to focus on strategic
initiatives that drive business
growth. Okay,
thank you. Thank you so much for this opportunity.
I hope this overview has provided
you some insights into the world of
RPA and its potential to
help our daily work.
Okay. And special thanks for
the conf, for the two organizers.
Okay, thank you. Thank you.