Are youll an SRE a
developer, a quality engineer
who wants to tackle the challenge of improving reliability in your DevOps?
You can enable your DevOps for reliability with chaos native.
Create your free account at Chaos native. Litmus Cloud
hello everyone. Welcome to this session. Deploy n applications
to n clusters using Argo City application set my name is Dewan
Ahmed. I'm a developer advocate at Red Hat.
I'm from Moncton, New Brunswick, which is in the beautiful Atlantic
region of Canada. I love everything cloud native
with a focus on DevOps and Gitops tools.
Besides work, I love to play pool and ping pong.
I'm also a freelance carrier coach, where I help students and
new grads to start a career in tech.
In terms of today's agenda, we'll start with the idea
of Githubs, especially Githubs on Kubernetes,
and then we'll cover the popular open source tool Argo
CD. The main focus of today's session
is a subproject of Argo CD called Application set.
For both Argo CD and application set, we'll have demos
and at the end we'll have some time for Q A.
On the bottom right corner of your screen youll can see a link to
a Git repository. In that repository
I have added detailed instructions on how you can
do demo on Kubernetes platform.
The demo I'll be showing will be based on OpenShift platform.
If you have a mobile device, you can also can that QR
code which will take you right to that git repository.
Luis Fasira summarized Gitops in one
slide. So Gitops in one slide
means there are three main principles. We use
Git as the single source of truth.
We use Git as the single place where we operate.
That means not on direct clusters, but we
do that on git, and the challenges is reflected on the
clusters. All the changes we're
making will also be observable and verifiable.
From the fun fact of Gitops Alexis Richardson first came
up with the term Gitops, and when he ran it by his friend,
his friend thought it's the ugliest word he has ever heard,
and now he can't unhear it trying to
come up with a term that is easy to pronounce but also difficult
to forget. Alex knew that he came up with a perfect term.
Now let's understand Gitop's BoM
or bill of material on kubernetes.
First we need Git repo, where our application manifests
files will reside. Then we need kubernetes
cluster or OpenShift cluster where we
are deploying our application. You might also need a manifest
generation tool like customize. If you have different environments
like dev, Preprod and Prod, don't use
a CI server to orchestrate straight direct updates to kubernetes as
a set of CI jobs. There's a blog post mentioned in
the resources section that covers why this is an anti pattern.
And finally, you'll need your kubernetes manifest files such
as deployments and services what
is Argo CD? ArgoCD is declarative,
GitHub's continuous delivery tool for Kubernetes.
It is part of an open source project. The project started at
Intuit, but then companies like IBM and Red Hat
and various individual contributors have contributed
to this project. From this diagram,
the concept is pretty simple. ArgoCD watches over your Git repository
and whatever change you have or whatever
configuration you have in your Git repositories,
ArgoCD implements that change declaratively
on your clusters.
Now why Argocd? The first few points
have been covered in previous slides, like why we're
using that. In Argo CD,
you use git push for managing your application,
delivering including changes to your cluster.
This is the flow your developers are familiar and comfortable
with. In terms of security, Argo CD
offers so integration based on OIDC or Auth
two, and it offers a single sign on for
various social profiles as well, including GitHub,
GitLab, LinkedIn, et cetera. In terms of automation,
ArgoCD offers multi tenancy and arbic policies.
ArgoCD also offers audit trails for application events
and API calls. In terms of rollbacks or youll
anywhere, it's a matter of youll application
configuration committed in a git repository, so you can go back to
any specific commit that's in your git repository,
either using the UI or the CLI.
If you do Argo CD app diff from your
CLI, ArgoCD performs a diff between
target and a live state of the cluster, and this can also be seen
on the UI, so you can observe the drift of your application
defined in git and the state in the target cluster.
Now considering all this, your application team will
have a higher velocity for faster application
delivery.
Now how Argo CD works Argo
CD is implemented as a Kubernetes controller which
continuously monitors running applications and compares
the current live state against the desired target state as
specified in the Git repo. So on the left hand
side you can see our developer Persona who does a
gate push or after a pr merges,
ArgoCD reacts to that change.
A deployed application, these live state deviates from
the target state is considered out of sync.
The ArgoCD API server is a GrPC and
rest server which exposes the API consumed by
the web UI, CLI and various
CI CD systems that we can see on the left hand side of our screen
on the blue square you can see there is a repositories server
which is an internal service that maintains a local cache
of the git repositories holding the application manifests.
Synchronization can be configured using resource
hooks so that what we see at the bottom of our
screen hooks are ways to run scripts before,
during and after a sync operation.
One example or use case of such hooks is
if you want to orchestrate a complex deployment that
require more sort of sophistication than the Kubernetes rolling
update strategy. You can have a script
run before, during or after the
sync operation. All right, so that's
enough theory. Let's dive into Argo CD demo
hello everyone, the first demo is on Argo
CD. This is based on OpenShift, but if
you'd like to follow a Kubernetes based demo, you can
go to this GitHub repository and follow the instructions.
This is based on vanilla Kubernetes.
Coming back to OpenShift, we are installing can
operator called Red Hat Openshift Gitops operator.
This operator out of the box gives you an argo CD
instance and also installs applicationset controller under
Openshift GitHubs namespace. To begin
with I'll connect to the argocd UI. For that
I'll need the default argocd admin password
and we can find that under workflows secrets under Openshift
GitHubs project. Openshift GitHubs cluster
is the name of that secret. I'll copy the secret
and open Arcocd UI
from here. The username is admin
and password is what I just copied.
Arcocd has a concept of projects.
Now this is not Openshift projects. This is Arco CD projects
where you can group your deployment applications.
You can also add repositories. If it's a private
repository, you can connect using your password or
token. The repository which
we are using for this demo is a public repository,
so we don't need to connect it in advance.
So let me copy the URL of the repositories and
try to create an application. You can create application from
the arco CD UI or using arco CD Cli
but I'll create the application using the OpenShift
console. So under the operator
I'm going into application create application,
let me give it a name.
Argo sample app
and then under destination
I have to give the server location since it's the
same server where arco CD is installed. It's the
default Kubernetes service. And the namespace I'll use
Openshift gitHubs. You can choose deploy in a different namespace
and you have to add a label that says managed by Openshift GitHubs.
But for now I'll use Openshift GitHubs namespace project
is the argo CD project which is default. That's the only project
that's on these Argo CD server now. So only default
project. So that's what we are using now under
source I'm adding the repository URL which I just copied
and under path customize nginx openshift so
this is the path where my manifest files are for
sync options or sync policy,
which basically says that if youll like to
automation sync the application when there is a change in git repository,
or youll like to manually sync either clicking the sync button or
using the cli I won't go with the automated
route now, so it's a manual sync option and I'll create these application.
Once I hit create on the Arcocd console,
I can see the app was created.
If I go inside I can see that my
three resources, the service deployment and these route were
created. And if you look at the automation
file you can see that there was a name prefix prod
which you can see in all three resources
as well. Now once I
sync the application, you'll see that the
applications will sync and it turns
green. It's synced sync ok, and you see the single
pod that is being created.
Now if I'd like to change these number
of replicas from one
to these,
let's see if I make a change.
So going the git ops route, making change to
the git repository and seeing the change reflect on the
cluster, I'm not going to go through the pull request route,
I'll push directly to the main.
So once I do that, if I
hit refresh, I'll hover over here, see the synced options
should turn yellow out of sync.
So it's out of sync now and I can click on app diff
to see the difference what changed.
So when I scroll down you can see on line 110.
So these number of replicas in these cluster it's one, but in
get repository expected or desired is three
and hence the application is out of sync.
All we need to do is hit sync,
synchronize and the application
will go in sync.
All right, so we can delete the application either
from here argo CD UI, or we can delete the application
from Openshift console as well. Let's delete the application.
I can create the same application, but let's use
auto sync now. So I'll say this is arco
CD sample app.
Let's say this is autosync destination,
the same cluster and namespace,
same ergo CD project under source I'm
using the same source that we used customize nginx Openshift
and then under sync policy I'll
choose automated and then hit the
prone and cell field. What prone does is if you
delete a resource from git, then argocd will
delete that on the cluster as well. And if you
check self heal, then even if you
delete a resource directly on the cluster,
Argocd will not let your app go out of sync and it will prevent
youll app from even seeing that challenges.
So let's keep those two options and create the
app again. And if we go back to application,
so the new application was created and this time, if you notice,
we didn't have to click sync because it's
auto sync, these app was automatically synced.
So let's try to delete one of the resource
to see the self field feature in action. So for
that I'll log in to the
cluster. So let me log in and
I'll switch to openshift Githubs. I'm already openshift GitHub's
project, so let me check
the service. OC get service what
are the service I'm getting?
Okay, I see the prod nginx, so let me
delete that service. OC delete service prod
nginx and then observe
what happens on Arco City UI.
So if you observe here,
you don't see the app going out of sync. And that's
because even if we try to delete that resource,
which you can see, the service was in fact deleted, but it
got recreated. Even if you refresh, you see
the service is right there. So Argo city prevented
that operation from happening.
So that's a pretty powerful
feature. With auto sync and cell field,
we created the app using OpenShift console.
You can very much delete the app from Argo CD UI.
It's using the same set of APIs so
it will be the same operation.
And that's the demo with
arcocd deploying a single application from
single git repository to these same cluster. In the
next demo we'll see arco city application set
where we deploy application to multiple clusters.
That was a demo of ArgoCD. These we deployed
one application from a single gate repository to a single cluster.
But what if you youll like to deploy Argo CD application to
multiple Kubernetes clusters all at once? Or what if
you had multiple argo CD applications in the same repository?
More like a Monorepo introducing
applications set controller for Argo CD unlike
with an argo CD application resource, which deploys resources
from a single git repository to a single destination cluster or namespace,
applicationset uses templated automation to create,
modify and manage multiple ArgoCd applications
simultaneously, which targets multiple destination
clusters and namespaces. The applicationset
controller is installed alongside ArgoCD within
the same namespace, and it automatically generates
ArgOCD applications based on the contents of
a new application set custom resource on the right hand side of the
YAML on line number two you can see the kind bing application set.
Now generators are responsible for generating parameters
which are then rendered into the templates field of the
application set resource. We'll be seeing two of
the generators in the demo today. In this example,
the list generator passes the URL and the cluster fields
into the application template as parameters, which are these rendered into
the template as three corresponding ArgoCD applications, one for
these each defined cluster targeting new
clusters is simply a matter of adding new deployments
to the application set resource, and the corresponding ArgoCD
applications will be automatically created.
The sole responsibility of the applicationset
controller is to create, update and delete
application resources within Dargo CD namespace.
The controller's only job to ensure that the application
resources remain consistent with a defined declarative
application set resource, nothing more.
Thus, the application set controller does not create,
modify or delete kubernetes resources other than
the application custom resource does not connect
to cluster. You have to already have the clusters
defined in Argo CD application
controller does not interact with namespaces other
than the one where ArgoCD is deployed.
It is Argo CD itself that is responsible
for the actual deployment of the generated child application resources
such as deployments, services, and config maps.
The application set controller can thus be thought of as
an application factory, taking an application set
resource as input and outputting one or
more Argo CD application resources that correspond
to the parameters of that set.
Here are some of the generators for application set.
You can find more details of each of the generator from application
set. Read these docs page, which are in the resources section of
the GitHub repo which I showed earlier.
All right, again, enough theory and let's dive into
application set demo.
In the second part of the demo we'll use argo
CD application set to deploy applications
to multiple clusters. Let's look at the example.
In these examples we have some
generators, but specifically we'll use list
generator and git generator directory
example let's start with list
generator. Now in the list example we
have a custom resource with
kind application set, and we're trying to deploy
this particular application, argo city application,
into two clusters, engineering dev and engineering prod.
I'll be commenting out this engineering prod
resource pretty soon now. One thing
to notice is the template part is pretty similar to an arcocity
application, and here some values are dynamically
injected. For example cluster. These values
would be coming from here and here, and URL value
is coming from the URL files.
One other thing to notice is if you don't have
a namespace, you can use this flag
create namespace equals true for the remote
clusters.
The first thing to do when you're deploying to multiple clusters
is adding the remote cluster to Argocd
server. First, I'll log into ArgoCD
server. Let me go to server
by clicking this link, which will open up
the ArgoCD server UI, and we'll use
the default admin account with the
admin password to find the admin password. If you're
using Openshift, go to workloads secrets
from Openshift GitHub's namespace and you can get the
Openshift GitHubs cluster secret and that
will get us logged in to the cluster from here.
If I see clusters, I can see there's only a cluster.
That means where ArgoCD is installed, there's no remote
cluster added. In order to add the remote
cluster, we have to add it through Argo CD Cli.
You cannot do that from argocd UI. So let
me log in to argo CD server from the
command line. I'll do argocd
login, and argo CD
is pretty picky about the URL, so I have to remove
the HTTPs part,
the username admin, and the
default admin password.
All right, so once you are logged in,
we have to log into the remote cluster.
So this is the remote cluster.
Let me see if I'm already logged into the remote cluster.
Yes, I'm already logged into the remote cluster as you can see.
So we have to add this context argo
CD cluster add
and these context. So once we do that,
a service account cluster role and cluster role binding will be
created into the remote cluster. That will let Argo CD manage
resources in the remote clusters. I already executed this step
beforehand, that's why it says it already exists.
Let's start with the list generator example.
In this yaml we have an application set custom resource
called Guestbook and we'll be deploying this application
in two different clusters. One is the cluster where Argoc is
installed and the other is a remote server. I'll uncomment
these two lines shortly, so let's
copy this yaml you
can create this application set custom resources from
these CLI, but if you're using Openshift Githubs operator,
you can create this application set from the
console. So we hit
create application set button and we paste
the custom resource here. Now one thing to notice is
because you're creating this application set
in a different namespace than Openshift Githubs guestbook
ns you'll have to create this guestbook ns
namespace beforehand with a specific flag
called managed by Openshift Gitops.
So here's that namespace youll
have to create this beforehand.
Notice this specific label field. So I have already
done that. I'll uncomment these two lines
and also update the URL field.
So let me go back to my argocd
web UI and from cluster I can see the
remote cluster and I'll update
this value which is engineering prod and
let's create this application set. So once I
create that under application I can
see these two argosd applications are being created,
one in the cluster where argosd is deployed and one
is in the remote cluster. Both apps are synced
and healthy. If I try to delete one of these applications,
you'll see that the applications will be out of sync
shortly. But applicationset controller will recreate
this application because these applications were created
using application set. In contrast, if you
created these two applications separately using Argo CD,
youll be able to individually delete this application.
So that was the list generator example demo.
I have to delete these two applications from here using application
set and now I'll be able to delete this application.
Now let's look at the git generator directory.
Example for the git generator directory
I have three different applications in the same repository,
a helm, a jSonnet, and a customized application and
similarly I have to create three namespaces beforehand because
these three applications are being deployed in three different namespace.
So this specific label allows Openshift,
Githubs or argo CD to be able to
create resources in those namespaces.
I have already created these three namespaces.
Now let's look at the example for git
generator directory.
I'll create application set from
the Yaml view and here
you can see that path base name which is all the folders
in this specific path, which are the three applications
guestbook helm, guestbook, JSON and guestbook customize.
These will be the three arcocity applications that will be created.
Let's create this application set and
we should see three applications will be created.
I did not have autosync enabled for these three applications,
so I'll have to manually sync this application.
Once I click on sync,
these three applications should be synced similarly
to the previous example. If I try to manually delete any of this
application argosage application set will create this application
again. So that
was these demo for git generator directory and
you can practice on your own on these generators
or if you want to test out matrix
generator. That example is in
this repo ergo city application set demo and if you scroll
down to the bottom of the page you can red hat.
I have an example for matrix generator
as well and this repository is based on vanilla
kubernetes. To sum up in
this talk, we learned about the concept of Gitops, more specifically
Gitops. On Kubernetes. We talked about a declarative
Gitops tool for Kubernetes Argo CD.
We deployed an application from a single repository to a single
cluster and then mentioned about the challenges of
deploying multiple application to multiple clusters.
We talked about Argo CD application set which is a subproject
of Argo CD, and how we can use various generators within
application set to deploy n number of application to
n number of clusters. Thank you for your time today
to listen to my talk and I welcome any questions you have.