Good. Everybody, welcome to Conf
42 conference. I am Ahmed Bankole and I'm
going to be talking about building awesome UI applications with
viewjs. Before I continue this talk, I'd like
to explain what this talk is about, what you aim
to get after this, and what you're going
to learn from it.
So I'm using that you might be new
or new to view JS, or you might
just be trying it out for the first time, or you have been using it
for a very long time and you still haven't
gotten the angle v so I'm going to put all that into
just one talk. So it's going to be more of a
talk session rather than a technical workshop
or a practical session.
I mean, so I would like to introduce myself, I would
like to keep it short. I am Ahmed Bankole, I'm a software engineer
from Lagos, Nigeria, and I work at ambiantic
AI where we provide remote care services for
the elderly. So we are just kind of artificial
intelligence company where we provide services
that could help elderly remotely.
That's just about me. And also don't forget to follow me on Twitter at
geeky aimed now let's get to the talk.
View JS, pronounced View Live
View is a popular JavaScript framework for building modern and interactive
web interface. It was developed by Evenew.
Basically Vue is just a framework for building modern and
interactive web interfaces just like any other framework.
But if you take a look at Vue, you'll find that
view provides us the ability not just to write
less JavaScript code, but also the ability to
write less Javascript code and do more,
including design. It also focus on designing
aspect but has a front end developers and the
new trends coming up on design, then you might need to shift from
that doing JavaScript
Dom to doing more of UI,
which is going to UI and UX which is going to be one
of the parts of your job as a frontend developer.
And as you can see, VJs provides reactive data
binding and composable view components with
an API that's easy to understand. So not only you
are writing less codes and doing more, it means
that it actually provides our reactive data
binding. So when we talk of data binding, we're actually talking about
your ability to be able to get data from a
particular element and attach it to the DOM very
easy. So what VJS does is allows
you to be able to build this data from one part of your application to
the DOM, which is the regular HTML with ease,
without having to write a bunch of JavaScript code that
are going to be doing that for you.
One of the things also provides a composable view component,
which means you can be able to interact with these components and
use them all over your application with ease without having
to stress yourself trying to configure it from one place,
one part of UI applications to the other. And finally,
it's easy and understandable, but I'll get to you.
A lot of you might be asking why view JS over react
or angular. I'm not trying to compare Vue with frameworks
like angular or react, I'm just trying to tell you
why they should choose view JS because of one it is
easy to use as a framework.
The first and foremost thing to look out for is
the ability for developers to use the framework to build
project. So if I can be able to use a framework to build project,
I'd rather learn another framework to help me achieve the same purpose.
So view JS provides that ability to be
able to use it in such a way that
is very productive for both you and the company
you work for or what you do. Also, it has great
runtime speed. I'm going to be talking about that later,
but I'll just give maybe a short overview
of it and then it is lean and small when
we're talking of lean and small, we actually reference view JS in
a file, in a single file, which is the view JS file.
So if you're downloading the zip file on GitHub,
we're actually seeing that the file is less
than 16 kb. Basically,
16 kb is for a single view Js
file which is the entire framework cooped
up in one particular file, which is 16
kb kilobytes, which means that
it's very small. It's a very small package that allows you to do
more. So you don't have to worry about large file size,
like including a framework with ten megabytes
on your project which is going to consume space. You just
have to worry about just imputing it
into your project, either through can or
using the file locally in your pc
or computer. It also has a lot of cool features.
I'm going to explain. When we mean cool features,
we actually mean components,
styling, data, building props
states, state management containers, other kind
of cool features that normal framework are supposed
to have. So these are the kind of things that define a framework and
part of the reason why you should choose View jet if you are coming
up into frontend developer in 2020
or probably in the next few years. Also,
it provides a minimal project structure when we talk about
minimal project structure. We're actually talking of the way your UI applications
structured using the view CLI. So let's
say you're not working on a small project using
the JS file. Rather you're working on an enterprise project,
a large project, a complex project that needs to
make use of the view CLI. Just like you have the react CLI,
you have the angular CLI. View also has its own CLI,
and one of the most common things that you might notice in
the View CLI is because of it has a minimal
project structure. And this minimal project structure means that you don't
have lots of directory and folders. It's actually straightforward
if you just a regular project structure should have the source
folder, and inside this source folder you are going to see the
component. When you see the component, you see the assets
and that's pretty much about it. Those are the things that contains
the part of your applications that needs to be run and the
files are saved at those view, which means it provides
its own extension so that I can be able to differentiate between HTML
and view. So you don't have to worry about writing mono
entire syntax just like you write Jxx. So instead
of writing the JxX in react, you could write in view.
And basically this view, you are just writing plain old HTML.
And then you could write some scripts which are related to view.
It's not much and then it's easy to
configure. I don't
think it's actually hard to configure just by installing
it using NPM or yarn. Or you could use local
CDNC, including your project. I don't think it's that much of a
deal to set up on view JS because it doesn't weigh
much, it doesn't cost much, it doesn't consume space,
and it's easy to use and understandable.
Now, like I said, view great View JS Runtime
performance if you take a look at this chart, you're seeing react 20%
angular 35% view 45% well,
these are part of my observation, so I
don't think it's actually what you might observe, but they are part of observation
and personal routine checking. After doing
rigorous testing performance check and researching,
I found out that View has higher runtime speed
than Israel react and
angular. When we're talking about runtime speed, we are talking about loading
time. When you start the application, how fast
can you be able to run and be able to deliver the content in
it? So this is mainly talking about the loading time of your
application when you restart UI applications, how long
does it take for it to be restarted? Or how long does
it take for your application to be up and running and you can see the
chart angular does better than react. That's because react tend
to have more dependencies than the other frameworks, which is angular
and vue. And since Vuegase has a minimal project
structure, it means the runtime speed is going to be
increased by a lot, which means
you're actually getting more runtime speed,
which is good for UI applications. So in
short, View JS has a good runtime speed and a great
optimization technique.
Now let's talk about the UI aspect of View JS.
A lot of you might know View JS, but don't know that
you can actually do a lot with Vue.
Viewjs provides a lot of UI libraries that
you could be able to integrate that won't change your project
directory at all. So let's say you're not the type that loves using
a materialized CSS, or you don't like using bootstrap,
but you just want a
design of its own without including those two
libraries or any other you could use using a
correct variety of these UI libraries I just stated
out, and these are personally and paid from various
websites and they are top rated and used
by a lot of people.
Number one, we have beautify. Beautify is one
of the most popular vue JS UI
library because it provides unpicked
materialized components and buttons
with years and other UI parts of your application.
Basically using beautify you get to create UI components
that are materialized base, just like Google
for example. So these components actually allow
you to be able to configure them in such a way
that you take control of the UI design itself.
And also it also gives good ux experience. Just like flex.
You don't have to worry about writing CSS to position your
flex or your grid. All these are automatically been
set for you using the UI library. Then we
have the view sachs. Basically, view Sachs
allows you to be able to make
uis that are already crafted.
What I mean by uis are already crafted are uis that are
designed by top designers or UI experts.
So all you just have to do is just write a couple of codes
which is going to create specifically designed UI
for you that you can be able to use.
Then we have Quasar.
Quasar is just another UI library and
can also be used as a project, a framework
of its own where you get to design and also build your project on
a particular framework, which is quasar so it's built with view,
but you can actually use it in your project as
a part of your designing. Then we have the elements UI
just like any other UI library. It provides easy to use
and simple UI components for your application.
And now we have the view material. It just
gives you a material look of your website, simple materialized
look of your website, just like materialized CSS
as you all know. And it makes you build source
components that are just like a regular materialized CSS
into your View JS project. Then we
have Vox is another UI framework that you
may all know. And it's just any other regular UI
that you could just integrate because it makes use of part
of bootstrap and some part of materialize to cook up some
handmade UI components that you can be
able to use and design to your taste. We have the buoy
file, we have the I view, you have the mint UI and
you have the bootstrap view. And this bootstrap view is
just Bootstrap. In viewjet, let's say you
are the type that loves using Bootstrap for your work.
Bootstrap tree bootstrap four. You get to use them into your Vjet project
without needing to include it from CDN. You could just install
it locally, or you could use a CD or you
could use a CDN. If you have
access to Internet connection, you could use the CDN to access
Bootstrap view. You get to actually build UI
component based on bootstrap,
whether tree version three or version four.
So this is a typical project directory in
your source folder. Like I said, it provides minimal project structure.
In your source folder we have the views, we don't have the views actually we
have the component and you have the assets.
But the mistake most people make is
actually putting your pages into the components
and that is going to be a lot of problem because of putting
your pages in your component is going to make your application
messy, which is not a good idea, especially when you are
running an enterprise application or a business application,
because you can be able to differentiate if it's a component
that you'll be using a part of UI applications, or if it's a page
that you could use as a standalone component.
So these are two major problems in
the front end as a frontend
developers when using view. So since view
doesn't provide this flexibility for you to be able to
use views, for you to
be able to create pages in your component,
you can use the views folder. You could
just create a views folder and basically this view folder
should hold your pages like your own page, your contact page,
your login page. So storing your pages in
this view rather than your components is going to make
work a lot easier for you rather than taxing.
So as a final developer, you want to make your work look less
stressful because we are going to be working on it a lot and productivity
better. So if you're not productive enough to be able to separate your components
from your pages, there's going to be a huge problem when you eventually
turn into a complex application or you turn into a business
someday. Then in your components you create
another folder called shared. The reason why I'm
talking about this is based on UI and Ux. Ui and
Ux go together, so you can't have a UI without Ux and you can't have
a UX without UI. It's just kind of a bread and better
where you need them to be able to test beta
creating a shared folder the components folder actually hold
your components, like the buttons, components,
your nav bars, your sidebars, those kind of stuff.
But grouping your components
folder to shared a shared directory
what you want your shared directory to do is all components that are
used all over your application.
Components like the navigation bar,
the footer, the sidebar,
adventure, or let's say some icons,
some recapture, some buttons, some contact,
those kind of stuff. If you are going to use them all
through your application, then it's advisable to put them in
your shared folder. By putting them in your shared folder,
you're actually making work easier because you can differentiate
between components that are located for the
dashboard. Take for example for the dashboard or located
for the client area, and then you can know the ones that are used in
your general application. So let's say two, three years
later you come to check out your application. Then you could know where you group
those components. So rather than just opening a component
and seeing a long list, you could go to your shared component
and then see what you're working on.
I guess I'm done with that. And now
let's talk about something more related to
Ux rather than UI. Lazy loading a lot
of you might have heard about lazy loading, lazy loading. And I
found out that lazy loading is one of the things that caused imposter
syndrome among frontend developers.
Well, let it not be because of I'm going
to give it to you. It's going to
make your experience with UI and Ux more
easy to understand. Lazy loading is an optimization
technique that delays the loading time of objects aligned.
For a quicker load time, you might be thinking this might not be
related to UI in any way, but it is because
if you have good UI and your UX is
poor, or let's say your website takes a whole lot
of time to load, then nobody's going to view your UI, nobody's going to care
about your UI because it isn't showing them what they
want, it's delaying the consumer or the
clients. So you can visit a website
and discover that and
discover that the website takes a longer time to load.
So the longer the time it takes to load,
the more frustrated you get about the website and you tend to close
the website or visit it another day.
And if you are the type that,
let's say you just started a business and you
fail to get the consumer
or the customer attention on your website, then you're going to be
losing a lot because your website isn't loading fast enough.
So like I say, lazy loading is an optimization
technique that delays the loading of object. Basically when you
use regular HTML to load your project or your
application, the Dom actually loads
the object. So before your page actually views,
before your page can be able to be viewed in
a formal that the users can be able to view, it has
to go through some tests, it has
to go through the dome. So what you don't do is what
the dome do is it waits until all the objects are fully
prepared and then it views the web page.
So if something caught your dome or something is caught up in the
dome, the more object that is caught up in
the dome, the less the loading time is going to
be. Which means that the more images you add in your website,
the more your website bounds will be
slower. But using lazy loading, we are going to cop this.
So let's take a look at it. So here's a practical
example of lazy loading. So we have the eagle loading, the eager loading,
and we have the lazy loading. Here you can see like
the image in the dinosaur says, downloads three
mb, downloads zero mb. And this is using the native
lazy loading technique in HTML five, which is loading equal
lazy. Doing this actually makes the iframe to be
lazy is an attribute actually, which means it's actually
object and we want to load it lazily,
which means we are preventing the website, we are preventing
the object from delaying the loading of the main website. So while
the website is loading or has been loaded,
the download or the image, the object
keeps on loading until it's done without interrupting
the flow of the website itself. I hope you are
getting this technique. So when you put these attributes,
you actually make work easier
for you as a front end developers. And also you can see
here with lazy loading without lazy loading. So when you do lazy loading
it's going to show the content. First it will show the content
that are available, then it's going to show
sidebar rotating spinning bar a progress
bar that shows that part of your website are loading.
So using this technique it
actually adds part of the website that hasn't been loaded yet
so that I can view some parts that are already below it so that
way it doesn't interrupt the UX of your website or
the UI. So the users get to see what they want to see without
having to wait until the other object is being loaded.
So now let's talk about lazy loading in route in
view js in view JS you could do
lots of techniques to lazy loading.
You could use loser. There are a lot of libraries for using that
lazy loading Javascript, but I'm going to be
giving a brief overview of how to lazy load route.
And you can see this is a regular exe syntax.
And after we imported our view and imported
our router, we are creating a function called lazy load.
And then we're including the view, like I say,
for the page. Basically what we want in the view is to
show that it's the page we want to load and the
function is going to carry a parameter name
view and this parameter is the location or
the component that we want to load in our
application. So we're telling our application to load
this page or lazy load this component.
Then after we do that we are actually putting our return and
then using the return we are importing the
location of the view like we say.
So just like we put here, as we put the lazy load
ohm. So what to attend the application is that whenever
we want to visit the Ohm route, load the component
first before loading the entire application. So I'm actually
going to lazy load, we're going to bring out the component
which is the home page. Want to bring out the home page before
loading the entire page. Because of what Vue
does is that when you load a page you are loading the entire page
which includes the home page, the contact page into one
file. And that is going to contain a lot of data
which is making our application which
is going to make our application a little bit slower. And we
might not want that, especially when you have lots of uis
or lots of objects in your application or images. So what you
want to do is rather than making your application
load all at once, you make your application load bit
by bit. So when we're lazy loading the ohm,
we're only importing the ohm component, which is the ohm
route. So when I click on go to
the ohm route, we're going to lazy load it, which means we're
going to bring out only the home route into one file, rather than
bringing out the whole of our application into one file.
As you can see, I'm guessing this is very understandable.
Well, you could try it out anytime. And if you need more information
about this, send me message on
my email at thegeekyamet@gmail.com and
you could follow me on Twitter. Well,
thank you for listening to this session. I hope you have a good day day,
and I'll see you later.
And next time.