Everyone, welcome to my talk on architecting resilient microservices.
A deep dive into building service mesh with envoy
before we talk and deep dive further into this topic, let's first
understand the agenda for today's topic. So in today's
talk I'm going to cover some of the key challenges with the
microservices architecture. What is service mesh as a pattern
and its core features? The envoy proxy. And we'll try
to deep dive into a use case and a problem and try to devise
a solution for it. We'll also see the benefits around using the
service mesh with proxy as a pattern. So let's deep
dive further. Now let's first
understand what is service mesh? So service mesh is a popular
solution for managing communication between individual microservices.
In a complex microservices application or
architecture it emerges as a very popular pattern
for managing communications between individual microservices.
It provides a dedicated infrastructure for handling service to service communication.
So let's say you have number of microservices
that are deployed as service A, B and C.
With the service mesh as a pattern, the individual
services need not have to take care of which service
I'm going to call, how do I call that service
and what are the endpoints. So all such configuration has been taken care
and managed and handled by the proxy.
So along with every microservice that you are deploying
as a service, we will also have a proxy
which is nothing but a simple YaML file or
a configuration file which will take care of all these configurations
and taking care of routing configuration filterings
in a very dynamic manner. And that's how the service mesh pattern
has been thought about. Now let's
further see what are the capabilities the service mesh
provides. So it provides
lot of features, lot of abilities without implementing
a service mesh. Otherwise any architectures will need
to implement all these capabilities from scratch
and it takes lot of effort as well as time. So let's deep dive
into what are the capabilities the service mesh provides. So the first and
the foremost is it provides distributed tracing.
So any complex architectures typically
doesn't stop only with a point to point or a single
microservice calling another microservice. However, it's a chain
of microservices that we typically call and
also number of internal as well as external integrations that
are expected to be taken care in a single workflow.
When it comes to the various internal as well as external integrations.
These systems and these components may be deployed into
various different discrete systems
and that's where the distributed tracing or the
tracing comes. An important aspect.
When there is an error, it is very difficult to identify an error
in a very discrete and a distributed system and that's
where this capability of service mesh will be very very helpful.
Another capability it provides is traffic management.
It enables sophisticated traffic management capabilities with the help
of load balancing, routing and number of retries feature.
It enhances the security by providing encryption
authentication authorization mechanism as well as it helps you
to protect the data in flight as
well as at store.
It also provides the ability
to discover the services by maintaining a
service catalog along with its configuration parameters
to be sent while calling that service as well as the service endpoints,
all ins all, it provides a very resilient architectures through the
features like circuit breaking, fault injection and
overall with these features and the capabilities, service mesh improves
the application's resilience and make it high
performant. Another important aspect is the
policy enforcement. It allows for the enforcements of
policies such that it can handle the rate
limiting access control as well as traffic shaping for you now,
while we have seen the capabilities and the features of service
mesh, now let's try to understand what is envoy?
So envoy is a high performance proxy server
that can be used to take care of these
capabilities through a configuration. So compared
to the traditional proxies which struggles to
keep pace with the dynamic nature of modern service communication,
because any changes in the configuration you will have to restart
the overall system and it will eventually cause
a downtime. This problem
gets avoided when we use envoy as a proxy.
So that's the reason envoy proxy emerges
as a groundbreaking solution to the challenges of service to service
communication in modern architectures. This was originally
developed by Lyft and now it's an integral part
of CNCF. Envoy proxy offers
a feature rich and high performance proxy
layer, both for layer four as well as layer seven, and its
key features include the dynamic service discovery,
TLS termination, load balancing, building a resilient
system and provide an extensibility through
a rich set of APIs.
Now let's understand how does it works,
and in order to understand its capabilities
and the functioning, there are four major configurations one
should understand very, very carefully.
So Ny proxy it manages. First of all, it manages
the inbound as well as the outbound traffic flow using configurations
which are made through first listeners.
So the listeners are nothing but it defines
a dedicated port at a dedicated IP address,
and its job is to continue to listen for the incoming request
or the traffic through with the help of various protocols like
HTTP, HTTPS, TCP, et cetera, as an example.
Now the next comes the routers. The outs
define how envoy outs incoming requests to
different upstream services based on the criteria such
as request path headers and other metadata.
The routes are configured in a routing table and determines
which cluster to send the traffic to. So now,
when the request comes to the cluster, cluster is nothing but
a group of upstream services that envoy can
forward traffic to. Each cluster
define a set of endpoints that belong
to the cluster. Envoy uses load balancing algorithm
to distribute the traffic across endpoints within a cluster.
Now, endpoints are nothing but the individual instances of a service
that belongs to a cluster. They represent the
destination for outbound traffic from the envoy.
Envoy dynamically updates its list of endpoints
as and when there is an update without the
need of restarting your servers.
So in short, when it comes to the inbound flow, the envoy
first receives the incoming traffic and it intercepts
it through the listener. It then processes
the traffic according to the defined routes,
performs various filtering based upon
the filter chain that has been configured,
and redirects the request to the appropriate cluster based
upon the routing rule. Finally, envoy forwards
the request to the corresponding endpoint within the cluster.
Now, in case of an outbound flow, envoy receives the
traffic from the upstream services based on the configured
cluster and the corresponding endpoint.
It uses load balancing algorithm to distribute the traffic
across the available endpoints within a cluster.
Envoy then forwards the traffic to the selected
endpoint based on the load balancing decision.
Now given we have seen the capabilities, features and
the functioning of both service mesh as well as envoy
proxy, let's deep dive into a use case and a problem statement
that we will discuss today.
So the use case, this use case,
it belongs to, it's nothing but a european government initiative
in order to accelerate the digital transformation and
digitization of their government services to achieve their
sustainable development goal. This initiative,
it actually aims to build a common framework
and technical practices for the design of reusable
and interoperable operable digital components.
The aim of building this solution ins so that we
come up with the best practices and a common reusable framework that
can be used across various government stack and
it can be leveraged across various government stack for future
use so that nobody has to reinvent
or rebuild these common components from scratch.
This has also been looked from the perspective to simplify
the cost, time and the resource requirement necessarily
required otherwise to create this digital platform.
Now, the key technical ask of this use
case is that they wanted to build a gateway for secure exchange
of data and the services among various building blocks through
open API based communication. The interfaces
need to ensure that the interoperability and the
implementation has been done as per the standards and the
best practices have been incorporated. The next
requirement is to enforce the best practices
so as to bring the standardization in, data sharing policies
and the data exchange now let's see the
view about how
is the communication between various building blocks of the government stack looks
like. So the government has multiple business units,
some of them taking care of citizen ID card, some of them are taking care
of recording the childbirth,
other units, the government initiatives taking care of
the patient records and the registry and death record and registry.
And there are various other building blocks as well. All in all,
if you could just by name, it shows that all these
various business units are interconnected and at any
point in time they would need to share lot
of information between them to maintain the consistency
in the data and the records. So that's
a requirement of this use case. Now, when it
comes to the solution, what we can propose
is we can propose the implementation,
implementing the solution using service mesh with envoy proxy.
So the proposed solution that we are suggesting is
built around the envoy proxy. And in this solution we
are actually focusing more about how to ensure
a secure communication between the two building blocks
of the government stack, as well as how to ensure
that the data exchange is seamless.
So the reason we are recommending envoy
here is because of its dynamic configuration capability, the high
performance and the extensive ecosystem of plugins that are
available with envoy, which can be easily tailored
as per the need. And most importantly,
it ins an open source thing.
So the high level architecture that has
been projected here, it illustrates a couple of
key components. The first one is the invoic proxy.
It sits in the data path, intercepting any request
between the services and the rooms which needs access control authentication,
and then applying the access control and authentication
rules. It dynamically evaluates the
access information by evaluating a set of policy rules
and provide a go or no go for the intercepted request.
So multiple envoy proxies may be deployed within a security
server for internal as well as external traffic. So this
envoy proxy will sit at the front of each government
building block, the ones we have said like the health registry,
the childbirth information, the patient record.
So in front of all these building blocks, there will
be one envoy proxy which we are calling
as a security server will sit and it will take care of all
this authentication, authorization,
secure data exchange, as well as policy informants.
Whenever there are any updates in the configurations that
have been made. Then in order to manage and control
the overall ecosystem, we will also implement the
envoy control plane.
The implementation is required in
a way that the services receive the policy challenges.
Notification from the policy admin service and
it gets propagated. It will be first received by
the control plane and then it generates the access rule
for the envoy proxy in a dynamic manner and
push this update to the relevant envoy proxies,
ensuring that the policies are enforced in a
timely manner and at runtime without any delays
plus without any restart required.
So this service will use XDS protocol for the communication
the authentication service that you see in the block is
responsible for actual authentication of upstream and downstream services
like the control plane service. This service receives notification
and updates from the policy admin service. The service also
sits in the data path as the authentication service that
will be handled as a part of the request flow from the downstream
applications and the proxies. So this is a solution
that has been built using a service mesh pattern with envoy.
Now let's see how and what are the different ways you can deploy
the envoy proxy. So this is a deployment architecture
and wherein you will see that the envoy proxy ins taking care of
the internal communication as well as the external integrations.
So there are various ways this proxy can be deployed. One,
it can act as an envoy proxy, second, it can sit as a sidecar
and third, it can also take care of external facing
communications. So let's see how.
So when it comes to the envoy proxy,
it ins typically used for interproxy communications and
it is deployed to control access from and to the classic
applications which are running on VMs, the virtual service.
And this will involve ensuring setting up routing so
that all traffic has to pass through the proxy for
secure communication and authentication taken.
An alternative way of deploying it is the sidecar approach
which you are seeing here, wherein all these applications that are deployed
in Kubernetes will have envoy
proxy deployed as a sidecar. The third approach is
the external facing envoy proxy which will intercept the
request to and fro coming from the external security server
and ensure that its authentication is
done. Now I
just wanted to highlight a couple of points, why we
have proposed this solution and what are the benefits of using this solution.
So first of all, there are multiple challenges that
we have seen without service mesh and without proxy while
we build the microservices architectures. So when we propose
a solution using service mesh with proxy,
it automatically handles lot of boilerplate
code which otherwise would take lot of time and effort to implement
them from scratch. So first advantage is it makes
your system very performant because the excess rules get encoded
into the proxy configurations which are locally stored and
enforced at the proxy as a gateway
and hence there is no elapsed time.
You are also saving on the network calls.
Second, whenever you are pushing any dynamic configuration there
ins no need to restart your system and hence it
ensuring high availability of your system. Third,
the solution works well both for cloud native as well as applications that
are hosted on VMs. The solution is very future
proof because when this proxy has
been built, it already supported some of the modern protocols like
HTTP two, GPRC and others,
and it also provides a wide set of APIs
as well as it provides a number of plugins which can be easily
tailored and customizable to your needs.
And it has got an inbuilt support
for observability using the features like logging metrics and
tracing. And that's the reason we have chosen
this solution for the problem that we have just discussed.
And with this we are at the end of our session. Thanks for watching
my session. Feel free to ping me for any
questions and the queries. Thank you so much.