You okay? Welcome to
this awesome conference. We continue with this talk in
comf 22. Thanks for invite me and
also I am very it's a big pleasure to be
here. So today we talk about
the adding security to development for allowable continuous delivery
and also tom this is me. We start
for this who is Jonathan Gillianipon.
He's a simple human that I love Linux
and also love shared knowledge around for the text
ecosystem. I try to main
more easily our lives when we try to develop and
start deployed on cloud or on local on our
internal providers that we have on our countries.
So it's my passion. I sincerely love using that.
That is my social network at JTAN 24, in GitHub,
in YouTube and also in X or Twitter.
If you can contact me and adding me on LinkedIn
I use johnnypunk. You can find me and
I want to share with you this phrase that is
from Confucius life is really simple but wins is on making it
complicated that as part of avalides.
So continue here.
This is our agenda for today. We talk about for containerized applications.
What exactly this? How do we can use
that and address this using
the software development lifecycle general challenges in
these container best apps. What is the principal
challenge here? Address the challenge using the sodium element
lifecycle little demo and a couple of
conclusions here. So we start
at this part. At this part we talk about for containerizer
application. But what exactly is a container? The container is exactly
how do we can encapsulate our process encapsulate our source
code using the Docker file. I think is the
more simple way for using that.
How to using this Docker file for split
our comments and exactly wrote
these road for our applications.
How do we can add in and use our proper
ecosystem, our proper operation systems.
So at this part we define exactly every
step that we need to cover for our packaging.
This compilation of source code that is the one
part and also we have the part of the containerization,
right? This part of containerization is
how do we move from our package and how do
we can support and start using this
docker for using that. The second part
is hey, what kind of initiatives are
around here we found exactly open container
initiative that is OCI and also this
container initiative talk from a
couple of values. These values are decomposable,
portable, decentralized, open,
minimalist but we're compatible.
But one biggest part here is that around for secure
how to isolate shellbugable and
add a cryptographic for these containerized
application and generate more stronger container
for our application how to add in the part of detail
for this container and generate layer for security
site. That is pretty awesome.
And also we have a couple of benefits using containers.
The first one is about for portability.
How to use this portability for mode pretty quick
this package for software and move from one side
to another side from what cloud environment to
our bare metal or our centralized definition
for our infrastructure. The second one is the agility that we
generate for all teams around for that. Now how do
we generate this easily way to deploy the
application. And another is the installation because we
generate this installate paras software,
generate their network around for
this containerized application. And also we
talk about the resource efficiency because when we
generate this container we reduce exactly the
consumer about the memory or cpu
and disk about for this piece of
software. And how do we can drop this in all around
for our orchard station site.
So that is a couple of images that I generated
using the Hughen phase and also the Dali
generation for images. How to
the IAA generate these images for us and how
to the IAA seems the container actually work.
So when we talk about the lifecycle
we talk about these could be focuses
about these benefits or feature that we enable
when we talk about this. So from our side we talk
about the accelerated development and deployment side that
it's very awesome. Because when we start this
containerized move internally for our companies,
we enable these capabilities for all teams,
not just for development. We enable that for the testing
team and the operation teams and also for
the DevOps, Devsecops and SRE or platform engineerings
around for this ecosystem that we have internally.
The second one are related for portability and
reproducibility. That is awesome because when
you generate these docker files or these container
applications, you move from one side your
container application and also you can move this application
for another part and deploy very quick that
it's brilliant. Enhance excalibility and
resource efficiency. That is talking previously about the
cpu, memory and disk drive around for
that simplify microservice detector.
When you start that using the
docker apps for your teams,
you enable exactly these capabilities for move very
quick. And also you support the architecture that the
principal architecture definition was made for your
teams and also the architectural department behind us.
And how you can drop this using the
containerizer war. And you support very quick these new
capabilities for all ecosystems
for the architectural designs.
Or generate this valuable for all teams around
for the containerized award. Reduce the
deployment friction because you generate this and generate more
reputable software and
generate streamline testing and quality assurance because
you drop these pieces of software and you can test pretty quick this
piece of software and generate very easily these movements internally
for this generation. So enhancement,
security and compliance that is the focus that we talk in
the next slides. Improved collaboration communication
because you reduce this communication side and
also you involve all capabilities for DevOps side.
And when you added this DevOps
culture inside of we added the security part.
We enable these cuttings for
all teams. How do these cuttings works
for all and how do we can generate and reduce
this friction from one side and another side and how do
we can talk more efficiently and generate
more quality software
for our ecosystems and deploy more easily way and
also reduce this friction from all teams
around for and also reduce cost.
Because when you reduce exactly your scope
and you generate this last reduce in a minimal
way, you generate this reduction for all around
for that, that could be when you start for that
using database practice the subfatilian lifecycle.
But you need to talk about that inside of your company
because when you define this and also
you need to move internally for the companies it's not easy
to sell something like that. Because when
the companies start to generate these
DevOps or DevOps move and DevOps culture
that it's no easy to sell them because
they open this mind and this mindset
is very difficult to sell at the beginning.
So we support here all
these capabilities for the software development lifecycle using
these phases for development, for deployment
and also for the operation. Because when we
define this from one part, that is for the
develop side, we enable these capabilities for
the development team. But what happened with the
development team also using the dockerized
application, they have the capabilities for
deploy and explore and expose internally
for their computers these source code.
But what happened when we move this for hey, we need
to deploy that for development environment
or for QI environment or for testing environment for lower
environments and also for production. That is the
next challenge here. And also when I deploy
the application I need to start the parachute. When we
start the operation for this application we need
to generate these capabilities for all ecosystems,
right? Because the it guys need to take these
features and how they can access to
these capabilities. How do we can enable
these capabilities for the Docker racer apps?
How do we can enable that using software
around that, right. So what
is the challenge here?
The general challenge here are related for image vulnerabilities,
the misconfiguration supply chains attack and also
the identification and access management.
You see here in the image the OAS
top ten that is related for Docker. And when
you start docker, you start talking about the security side.
How do you can drop this security for
the old last radios that have the docker
images that you have for the containerized
application. You need to identify exactly what
is your security posture,
how to use in this security poster for generate the
roadmaps and generate the plans for doing that,
right? You need to take a look more in deep this but we talk
this talk about for image vulnerabilities,
misconfigurations, plane chains attack and interfere and
access management. So for image vulnerabilities
we talk for one site that is related in a
principal and the fierce part for
start for this the checkup's work that
is related for how do we can generate and
reduce this blaster using the image vulnerabilities? Because this
impact of the image vulnerabilities impact sacly for how
they can access to our operation system or the
runtime site or how they can gain access
to containerized application and also how they can
get data from these containerized apps.
Also you need to reduce these attacks using
exactly the image vulnerabilities. But how do
you can reduce that? We talk more in the next
slides about that. But the image vulnerabilities are
talking about the weakness or flaws that containerated
image had at the moment when you deploy the application,
right? So you can generate
this and also you can reduce these vulnerabilities
using iscans behind us. So we talk
in one tool that we generate in the demo
site and also that is one site. The another part is
the software components that you have around for
this image that you build it for the application.
Because internally for your application you had one part
for the operation system, the second one part that is
related for the runtime around for your application. And the third one
is about for the application by default.
So you have three action items here
for protect. How do you can protect these items
when you prepare and generate this image for
your site? Right? So we need
to talk and identify exactly this
vector than the definition from Docker
site or the containerized site.
The second one is related for misconfiguration. This misconfiguration
are related for how do the
applications generate or
could be the development team generate or could be
forget remove from secrets or something
like that for the container ice work.
When you use these misconfigurations and
you identify that you need to take a look for these misconfigurations.
You need to validate exactly what kind of
misconfigurations you need to cover because
you need to exactly explore tools behind us.
But these misconfigurations are related for hey how do
we can access to these misconfigurations? Could be
generate a misconfiguration by default from one ubuntu
image or Debian emash or something like that and also expose
more than one port that I need could be for
example you expose the port 22 that is
related for SSH and also I don't know could be exposed
in a public site the SSH key for
access to this docker or containerized app and
that is the part of the misconfiguration that could be
you need to cover here. And also how do you can
exactly identify this exposure network?
How do you can identify the file
insecure definitions internally for this containerized
app? How do you can address this
using a couple of software behind off that validate
from the community. For another part you
define the unsecured container registry
and how you can drop and identify
what happened with this registry.
And also if you could be exposed the
configuration the users and password for access today
and how do they can gain access to this
repository and copy change the image and tag
from your site and generate this in an evolved
image that is related for the image vulnerabilities and
generate that in that site. This impact
generates a very big impact when
the application will be deployed because
the application or could be your system
exposed unauthorized way for
these misconfigurations could be for one site for the database or
could be for your registry or could be for
the data access. When you identify
that you take a look about hey
I have this compromised world and I
need to take a look in deep about this position
and how we
can reduce this part of the misconfiguration site.
The another one is really for supply chains attack.
For supply chains attack. Also we
need to define exactly how to these attacks will be targeted
for the sword party element lifecycle,
how they could compromise the containerized
application. In this context the attacker could take
and modify our code and generate
this on the fly and generate this
process internally for the Tokyo set app and also the
final product that you deliver for your customer.
Generate an evil package of software
and could take this data from your customers generate
and obtain and get this data from your customer that it's pretty
weird because your customer could be hey,
I get my data out of your application and just
share with you what happened here. Then they
added to you could be lsla bar
for the security sites. So you need to cover that
from the zero day for the start
when you deploy this application for your customer,
right? So the
object here when we talk about this
supply chains attack also we need to validate
exactly what happened when this compromised
application will be for our apps.
What kind of security
definition we define it internally for our companies.
How do these companies define exactly what
happened with this definition for
that when they're not the part for the supply
chains attack that is related for containerizing
and also when they access
to this application also
for our source code
they can execute malicious code for the customer
side. That is the biggest challenge
here. How do we can reduce this blast and how
we can reduce and generate a copy of a culture internally for
our teams for reduce
exactly what happened here. Another part that
is the impact for this plane
change attacks that is related for data breaches, the application
disruption, the escalation privileges
and damage our reputation. Because when
you expose or could we take data from your companies offer
our companies that it's very difficult
to try to generate
and regenerate our reputation for
our customer, right.
On the other side, on the other hand we have the identity
and access management that is related. How do they containerize it
access to another components internally and externally.
How do we can reduce this blast? How do we can
exactly define for the container image
and definitions for these access
for another components around for our software?
For one part we define for the resource access control
list. How do they can access to and
generate this granular access to another mechanisms
and permissions associate for another resources.
The attribute based access control provides
more flexible approach to access control evaluation
for attributes, user and containers. And also
if we deploy using this for
Kubernetes, for example, we can enable the airbag
that is the role based access control. How do we can reduce this
access for another set of components
around for Kubernetes? And another
part the challenge here are related for the scalability,
complexibility and visibility.
Because when we drop this part
of the piece of software containerized, we define
exactly this
little piece of software and this piece of software
will be grow and reduce
these capabilities when the software grows
for explore more for those
customers, right? So we need to address
the challenge for the next topics. That's another
images related for the AA related for one to
this challenge that we need to talk in the software
lifecycle. So for one side we
need to identify very quick the vulnerabilities and
also the misconfiguration and supply chains and IAM enforcement.
And how do we can arrest using tools
internally? Because when we talk about in depth setups
based on DevOps, we talk from one
focus that is related for pipelines. When you
define these pipelines for the company you enable exactly
the capabilities for your software to deploy more
easily. But not exactly should deploy
pretty quick without quality or
unsecured software. The definition internally
for devsecops when you generate these pilots
you enable another capabilities for the software pieces
that you deploy every day or for every URL
or every minute. And added these security
capabilities too for the software that
you deploy, right. So for
this challenge we can explore these
tools around for the CNCF too. That is
related exactly for the security site that is taken
from the CNCF that
we talked at the beginning of this talk that is related
for the software the cloud native Computing foundation and
this they focused for currently tools that
are built for community, for the community and
also ones are part for the
one vendor or another vendor or could be from one cloud
provider or something like that. But you have these
tools and you can explore depends for your needs and exactly
how to you add these tools
for your pipelines or software development lifecycle depend
on the phases that you are currently have for deployed
software. So we can move very
quick for the demo. This demo are related
for how we can explore a couple of
this software inside here. Let us move here
for the demo site.
Let me move for that and also
drop here this also close this and
we can open the readme right.
So we have this repository comes 22 23
devsecops and we have here exactly
the step by step for generate one
image here and also you can use this
using I don't know could be Docker or Borman or
another container application that currently
you have in your company and start with that,
right. So we suppose that you have here
a pipeline and you clone exactly the pet link
here and you download here. I currently download
this source and just join
this folder and move internally.
And also I need to create this docker image
using the Docker file. Create a docker
image and also we can enable this and
execute this part for applications.
But we don't need exactly run that
and we check
this the plex clinic we have two docker files.
One docker file that is related for
compile the application using maven using internally
configuration for Java that is a boom xml
and we define exactly here that move or
copy all the source code related here and
when the runtime start compile
this code and start the execution, right.
But we have exactly the node docker file multi.
When you use Docker files you can define
the multistages here and you can reduce exactly the
blazer I use using this multistage part and also
we have the first part very similar
for the previously but we have here
for another phases we have here the
production side and from build that is
this part we package
exactly this base from source code and generate the
GI air packages from sprint
clinic. And also we reduce the blast ready because in
this part just generate the GR definition
and not exactly the wall source code that we
have here. So we generate the
couple of images here and so we generate
the first part that is related for pet clinic and we
generate here the pet clinic mini
using exactly the Docker mini multi file
or generate that and also if we palliate here
docker images and filter for
pet clinic we have here these couple
of images the pet clinic at mini and Pet clinic app.
And also if we check the weight for everyone
for each one we saw here exactly
the image weight from one side another,
right? And we identify exactly the app clinic
mini is less image here for
one site. If you validate or
try to validate your docker deployments you can
start for this validation site. That is the
first scan that you need to execute
for your operation infrastructure
because this is part for your
currently definition on the docker side.
So at this part we define the continuous
trust that is our currently installation for
Docker and also we mount from our
etc for the operation system in my case
for my arch Linux inside of
the container and date mount in the read only
and also we mount the container the application
in read only. Also the run c two,
the system d two and here the Bart lib
and the sock for docker that they
need this execution for these container
needs that is related for docker bench security and
also this generate these awesome
results for your docker configuration and you
can check this one about what happened internally
for your configuration and provision in your infrastructure site and
validate exactly what happened if your docker was misconfigured
right that is the one part for the misconfiguration for your
docker and also if you generate
this unconfigured installation
for your docker you can move in my site.
I propose this for tls because I open
in my port because I use for another
pucs but I don't enable the TLS communication
just open the plain communication for my docker
site. So you can check this and also validate exactly
what happened with this one. And if you want or you
need to check exactly for your move
and depends for your postgrad also depends for
your time for your team time about for generate
and reduce these lags about for security posture.
That is the one side. The second part
here that is related for mass configuration detection and
also we generate for
the pet clinic the application. If you remember
we generate two images. One images that is related
for the PET clinic that
contains the wall source code and we validate here
this part for the validate this image and
also we validate another image
that is related for the pet clinic mini,
right? When we saw these files
that has par for here and compare
these files compare selected we
saw here a couple of differences
from one side to another. But in general there are
the same image when we build the images
and also we have the same results
here, right? Because the pet clinic and the pet clinic
mini are defined using an Ubuntu base
and also this ubuntu base are born out for this CBA
and if you want to validate what is the CBA you have here
the link for validate that and if you
check here we can show exactly
what is exactly a severity for this.
At this case it's low and also if you
drop here we can find for another medium but not
in high level, right? So that is
the once part how do you can generate these misconfigurations
for your application, right? Another part
is related for the vulnerability
detection because you have for the misconfiguration detection site but
for the vulnerability this generate one
report and also you can move for your application
and drop here for your security team and bank will be generating
a couple of alerts here. But when you use
a sneak that is very similar we
can create here one folder and move
internally for this folder we download the
sneak for Linux and added the permissions
for executable site and also I just generate
this path and adding this
folder for the current site for execute and
we execute exactly in this part
the latest images that we
generated internally or generate this report internally
for the sneak account right. When we send and
execute this command here as
previous for this ethnic authentication
and generate and communicate your terminal with the ethnic
account. And also if we move very quick here
for the website the
sneak we saw here login
here and also we saw here
our dashboard and we have internally here the two
projects, the Pet clinic app and the pet
clinic mini and we saw here exactly the target
for AoS. When we change for this that
is the same OS here and
if we drop the move
for these results we
have 40 issues from one side here
40 issues too and also we have
Sony medium and not in low at the same because the
image that we scan at this moment is the same,
we just reduce exactly the weight but the
image when we define for the docker
site let me move here we
define for our docker site for this
file and another is the same basic that is
eclipse tamarine. This eclipse tamarind we found that
is based on
unto site right? So we continue here
we can also execute declare definitions
and sincerely I test
this for my site was very unstable because I
need to generate more space on my disk so I can continue
for this POC but when we start for the supply chain
chains and the am enforcement we generate
here a lot of comments around for
that because these tools generate these
reports and when you generate these reports you can
also enable the capabilities for your team
or something like that. So you need start to how do
you can verify the image and the pronounce for this image?
At this case we generate using the Docker file scan containers
and images. We can check
strong pipeline and
also we can access here and include access control code
reviews and vulnerability scanning and we check educate
your development teams. That is the biggest
task here because don't depend exactly the tools start
to depend exactly the teams and it's very difficult
for outside. Another part
for adding this monitoring activity and
another part that I love sincerely is how do you
can monitor in engineering observability for the different
components around for the teams and you
can add it here. This part depends on
how you can deploy the application and how you can use this application.
How do you can explore
your application and generate this observability stack for this
application. And when we move for the aim
enforcement we define here the less privileged principle
and if you saw here the reference more
in the talk I dropped a couple of links
around for Docker side and also the OASP and
they mentioned how you can generate this and using the less
privileged and generate groups internally for your operation system.
What's the kind of user execute application centralized
IAM. So how you can generate
this access for the another components around for the
application continuous authorization,
audit and monitoring then again
monitoring and monitor your application that
it's one part for identify exactly in
a predictably way for when you start
for the epsicob site and automate this IAM
task for validate exactly what kind of access the
application had to another component set up for
this. So we can return here
and also return for
the slides and continue here. So our conclusions continuous
deployment reliable we had this reliable
when we enable these security tools
and also if we drop here these tools and also
add it to the SoT fatalm lifecycle and adding
that for the pipeline are pretty awesome because you
generate and reduce the
scope for these security vulnerabilities
on your teams and also you can stop
this misconfiguration, stop this im
enformentment and stop and reduce this blast
for all. Principal challenge that we have internally for
the software development alcohol and when you deploy the application generate
the commitment for our teams that is again
returned for the teams and how do they access
the security side and access to the security training
internally and start the security culture
in our teams. It's very difficult. I think
this to latest conclusion because
when you involve the teams
are pretty difficult because not all dev teams
are open to start for this journey.
When you start for security site right then you start
first for the tools but you need to
involve exactly the teams for made more easily
your work because at the end of the day is
the company valuable then you need to make more valuable using these
component bonus around that. So a brief
resume for today. We talk about for continuous the satorial lifecycle
what kind of content I rise set application
are not the SOT for DNM lifecycle. The general
challenges here address the challenge using the soda lifecycle
the Kubernetes Computer foundation about the glossary about
the tools and how to these open source tools
are enabled for us and validate what kind of
components we can check for the community and also you can join
for that this a little survey please
if you can help me. I appreciate a lot you
could take 1 minute for
fill that also
for today. Thank you for joining for this session.
I pretty happy to be here so I appreciate this
time with you and also they see in the
comf 22 team. Thanks for
invite me and also for doing this
today better so let me return here
and share with you this reference exactly
that I talked for the OAS that is related for this.
Let me move here the
top ten and you can access this and
this this you can check exactly what kind of component you
can drift for your container best applications
and that's it for today. Thank you
very much for access to this talk. Thank you.