Hi and thank you so much for joining me today. We'll be
talking a little bit about problems with Kubernetes access
today and how you can say goodbye to manual Kubernetes user access onboarding
using solutions like Opensource teleport.
So this is what a terminal looked like at
a job I has. Many, many years ago we had this file
sitting there called secrets text. What do you think will
happen if we run this command? Catsecrets text,
we get some secrets. So these were access
credentials for accessing various cloud infrastructure at my,
again, old job. And so
what happened was a lot of people on the team ended
up saving credentials like this to their local
machines, because the way of us accessing
the infrastructure that we had was just so terrible and would
take forever and was filled with pain points. The way it worked was
that the way it was supposed to be has that we
had a credentials vault that you would go every
time you needed to access a resource. You'd go into the vault, search for the
resource name, open up that file, and then
just copy and paste those certificates or those access keys or
whatever back into the terminal and then access the resource.
The problem with this was that those were so many resources
with ambiguous names. There was no naming conventions.
Old credentials weren't always deleted, so sometimes they were deprecated
and it just took forever and was just such a hassle.
So what a lot of engineers did has the
most frequent resources that we had to access. We ended up
just copying and pasting those keys locally and just saving
them in files like this. Now, obviously, this is terrible security
posture, just absolutely abysmal.
But the reason for it is, and the lesson we can learn, is that
the most secure thing also has to be the simplest thing. Otherwise engineers
are going to find workarounds. If you're sacrificing engineer
productivity for security, you're going to have problems
like this in very, very many cases.
And this is a huge problem because when employees leave
as well, they still may have access to these locally stored passwords.
From a survey done by beyond identity in 2021,
they found that one in four employees surveyed still have access
to old passwords, just like we saw in the last example.
And 41.7% of employees admitted to
having shared workplace passwords. So this is, again, just like we
saw. There was shared resources that people had all
the credentials for. And then when they leave, they might still hang on
to those credentials, still allowing them to access resources that they should
not have access to anymore,
which eventually will lead to a security breach and we found
that every security breach has two things in common,
a human error for the initial infiltration. So this could be something
like keeping a sticky note on your computer, or an attempt to pivot
and an attempt to pivot to maximize the blast radius.
So human error. So this is from a Git guardian
survey in 2021. They found over 6
million leaked secrets in GitHub,
and this is a two times increase since 2020.
And the types of secrets leaked here are not surprising.
It's a lot of cloud infrastructure access keys, like AWS
IAM tokens or Azure API keys, Google Cloud
keys, scaleway tokens. And these numbers are
only going to increase as compliance scale up their infrastructure.
And you might say, okay, well, but we're not open source.
Well, too bad, because 85% of those corporate leaks
came from developers personal repos. When they were doing development,
they would fork the company's private repo into their own public personal
ones. They would make the code changes,
they would not delete the repo, and then they'd merge it in.
The other 15% came from public corporate repos.
And this is Gitguardian's findings, and they're only finding that they're accessing
these types of mistakes.
The next step, of course, is to maximize the blast radius.
For example, say you get into a slack workspace, like a recent
high profile hack happened a couple months ago,
then from there you can get access to a server, you get into a server,
you can elevate your privileges using some kind of privilege escalation attack.
From there, do what you do, maybe get some customer data,
get some internal compliance files,
and then profit from those.
Your mileage may vary. You might end up on a beach somewhere,
or somewhere a little bit less pleasant.
And so what does that mean kind of for a cloud world today?
Well, according to the Container research report published by
Datadog in 2022, their scope was
around 1.5 billion containers and tens of thousands
of companies. So this is a pretty large survey of those companies with
all those containers. They found that Kubernetes usage is
actually rising in this container ecosystem.
So more and more people are using Kubernetes. They found that
over 50% now of these companies all are using
kubernetes to manage their container access.
All those Kubernetes clusters configured
by humans who make mistakes.
So Kubernetes configuration is a huge problem
today and a huge hurdle for many development teams.
This survey also found that 40% of these clusters
are still using lax privileges. So what this means is that
these user accounts are configured with privileges, such as
being able to list all the secrets, create workloads
or certificates themselves, or even do privilege escalation
token requests so they can actually elevate their own privileges
behind what their RBAC rules are supposed to be,
and have access to a myriad of
services that they otherwise should not be allowed to.
And this kind of is the Kubernetes iceberg
has, I like to call it. So on the very tip of the iceberg,
you have making it work, right? Making Kubernetes
work, configuring one cluster, all of your networking,
all of your microservices together, allowing users to access it,
making sure it doesn't go down. And this can be extremely
hard on its own. Kubernetes is a complex beast.
Configuring this to work with, even a couple of engineers can be very difficult.
Then under the surface, however, okay, well, now that it's
working, let's make it work securely. And then now things
start getting even more difficult. When you're dealing with RBAC rules,
you want to use identity based access, say passwordless even.
You want to make sure all of your networking rules are not only work,
but they're secure from outside attack at
the very bottom of the iceberg, way under the water, in the very depths
you have. Let's make it work now at scale,
we made it work for a team of two or three engineers. What about
40? What about 100? You don't have one cluster,
you have thousands at scale in production,
and you need it to be secure and consistently available.
This is when things become extremely tricky.
And the fact of the matter is that kubernetes is not
safe by default. You have to have airtight configurations,
otherwise bad actors are going to take advantage of your configuration.
And this is absolutely key. A good
configuration is the difference between engineers being
able to use your product securely,
or outside actors being able to highlight those vulnerabilities and
actually exploit them and get into your systems. So the types of
configuration, this is an example. Kate configuration file
for deployment. And you have to consider
ETCD security. You have to consider secret management,
safe networking policies, pod to pod communication,
application level security. What does an individual pod
look like? RBAc policies for users. Audit, logging. Make sure
all that activity is being logged and monitored. Cluster onboarding,
adding new clusters, scaling up, scaling down, ephemeral cluster control,
all of this, there's so many places where it can go wrong for a manual
configuration, and you just get more and more and more and more
of these files until they just all add up and there's going to be a
problem somewhere. So what can we do
about that? Well, luckily there are solutions available
like open source teleport, kubernetes access.
And what teleport is, is it's a secure control accessing platform.
So it helps you manage all of your infrastructure access in a single place,
including your Kubernetes access. And it operates
on kind of these four pillars of access. In order to have secure
access, you need authentication,
authorization, connectivity and audit.
And this is what teleport provides. So the
first step is authentication. So authentication,
what teleport does is rather than using any long livedemo
credentials, no SSH keys,
no passwords, no long lived certificates,
what we do instead is teleport acts as its own certificate authority
and it actually generates an identity in the form of a short
lived x 509 certificate for the user and ties
that identity to a role managed by teleport mapped
to the identity from their SSO. So say you log
in with Okta or GitHub, teleport will
actually use that identity and issue a short lived certificate
per user, per session. For kubernetes
access, the next step is authorization.
So what teleport also does is it will automatically approve or deny
these access requests to a range of resources. So you have servers,
databases, kubernetes, clusters, microservices and various
CI CD systems. So it'll always make sure that
your users are accessing only what they are allowed to based
on their RBAC problems. You also have connectivity.
So teleport also acts as its own proxy, which means that
it establishes a connection between the user and the requested resource
using a reverse proxy tunnel from the teleport server to the resource.
So all of that traffic, every command being run,
every user session, is being passed through the teleport proxy,
making it secure and fully encrypted using
TLS. The next step is audit.
This is a huge thing from a diagnostic and compliance
standpoint. You need to make sure that your clusters are
being accessed by only who's allowed to be accessing
them and monitoring their activity in case something goes wrong.
And with teleport, all of your audit logs
are mapped to a central location and can be managed
from there. No matter what region your cluster is running in or
no matter how many you have, all of those audit logs get streamed into
the same location, making them easy to manage and monitor.
So here's kind of the high level architecture of it. So this
is an example of if you're hosting your teleport
in your teleport instance, in the AWS cloud,
along with a Kubernetes cluster there as well.
So you have this teleport cube agent running
on your Kubernetes cluster. And what this will do
is it'll communicate with teleport. Your teleport cluster
will then communicate with the user. So if a user wants
to access the Kubernetes cluster, they'll log in
with their SSO, in this cases GitHub, that'll confirm their identity.
Then what teleport will say is, okay, well what is their authorization
level then? What are they allowed to access? And once they're there, what permissions
do they have? Teleport will then communicate with the Kubernetes
cluster, authenticate with the Kubernetes cluster and
grab that kubeconfig. It'll pass that Kubeconfig
to the user and the user will be able to run Kubectl commands from
their local machine just as if they were in the cloud itself. And again,
all of this traffic is being passed through the teleport proxy service.
Here's an example using machine id. So machine
id is teleport's automated way to do access control.
So rather than say like a user accessing teleport,
in this case we have this worker node and this can be in a CI
CD workflow. And rather than having a shared credential for
this worker node, what you do actually is machine
id will run in the background and actually fetch and get a credential
every 20 minutes or completely configurable from
teleport and it'll have its own identity.
So if you have a bunch of different worker nodes and have trouble keeping track
of them all, teleport is a great solution. Every worker
node and every microservice, every process will have its own
identity just the same way as a human would, allowing you to keep control
of your complete CI CD automation infrastructure
and also allow you to easily manage and scale this
logging and this access control.
So let's take a look at teleport in action.
So now I'm going to give you a little demo on how teleport works.
So over here on the right, we have hours web console and this is just
the public address of our teleport cluster. So when we log
in, we're going to authenticate using GitHub as an SSO.
We log in through GitHub and now we see all of our servers
that we have access to. So we can see all of our SSh
nodes here we have our applications and our Kubernetes
clusters and we also have our databases and
our Windows DevOps. So we're going to see how
to log into a Kubernetes cluster using teleport.
So over here on the left we have my local machine. So first
thing what we're going to do is we're going to tsh login to
our cluster using GitHub as the authorization with the user Dumas
K, that's me. And the address
of the teleport host. So this
will log us into the teleport cluster. Now we're logged
in, we have that short lived certificate and now teleport knows
who I am. All of this activity is being mapped to my identity.
So next we're going to actually see what Kubernetes resources
do we have access to. Perfect. So we have our
Kate's, those here, this is the one that we're going to log into. And TsH
is just a little command line tool that allows the user to access teleport resources
and interact with the cluster. So next we're going to do a
Tsh cube login to
our host. And because I'm already logged in
with teleport, this is all you need to do.
I have the role access which allows me to access
this Kubernetes cluster. And so now what teleport actually did
is it gave us that kubeconfig. So from here we can
run all of our Kubectl commands.
So we actually are in this cluster right now and
can create pods, can delete,
can list, can do all of our different deployments, whatever we want
to do. And if we go in here now we can
actually see in the audit log these commands
being run. We see that I logged in, we see
the certificate was issued, we see the SSO login and
we see that my request to the Kubernetes cluster,
Kate's host and if we go into details we can actually see those
commands and all of that session data that was run. We can see that
the verb get the resource pods and all of
those other session data resources.
And you can see that I had access to this because we can look in
our users. So here we have Dumez K,
that's me. The type is a GitHub because it's mapped to my GitHub account.
And we can see the roles that I currently have. This access
role is the one that actually allowed me to access this Kubernetes
cluster. So if we go into roles we can actually view
this. So here's what a teleport role looks
like. This is an RBAC role that maps to various other
RBaC roles in database access,
SSH, kubernetes, clusters or
even Windows RDP boxes. So you can see my databases,
my database users, I have access to those join sessions,
I'm allowed. So we have Kate's here, that's Kubernetes and
the different Kubernetes labels. So we can see that I'm in the internal
Kubernetes user group and I can log in using
this user group. And so this
is how we map a teleport
role to a Kubernetes RBaC role. We have that I'm access
assistant masters because this is an admin role that I am in.
And the neat thing about teleport is that you can actually revoke these user
sessions. You can see these active sessions here and
you can see the various audit logs, all my commands that I'm running here.
And that's kind of teleport in a nutshell and how it works and how
you can use it to securely access your Kubernetes
resources. You can share different Kubernetes user groups
between teleport roles securely because of this audit
logging feature and because all of these sessions are
mapped to an individual's identity, even if they are sharing
Kubernetes RBAC roles, for instance, they all map back to
a teleport RBAC role which maps back to your identity.
So every activity that you do, every command that you run
and all your session is mapped to the individual rather than the shared
user group. Great.
So what's next for teleport? Well, in teleport eleven,
which we just released, we added support for GitHub actions.
So this means that you can interact with teleport protected resources such
as SSH kubernetes and your databases
directly from GitHub actions workflows without using any
long lived credentials. So you actually don't need to store any sensitive
values in your GitHub repo.
We also added Kate support for automatic service discovery.
So this means that based on Kubernetes labels, teleport can
actually pick up and onboard clusters and pods to
the teleport management system. And this way there's
no need to manually add these clusters and pods to
teleport yourself. It's easy to scale up and down Kate's
resources using teleport. So thank
you so much for watching and I hope you learned a little bit about some
of the pitfalls of Kubernetes access management and
ways around them. So check us out
on our website@gotelport.com or come
say hi in our community slack at teleport, slack.com.
We'll also be at an in person conference somewhere near you,
I'm sure, very soon. So if you're around, come say hi. We'll be
at reinvent pretty soon in Vegas. So thank you
so much again and have great day.