Hi there. This is Arfad. Today I'll
talk about how to be a digital nomad without
losing your job. I'm going to give you a small tour,
more of my life as a digital nomad, and also bring
in the bigger philosophy of why I choose to live this
way. So before I start this talk, let me tell you a little bit
about me. I'm a production engineer at Shopify,
which is like being a DevOps engineer. So I do terraform,
kubernetes, system stuff, and a lot of other buzzwordy
stuff. Aside from my job, during the summer,
I'm a hiker, and I really, really love the mountains.
So during the wanted, I am a skier and a snowboarder,
and I'm also learning how to surf.
And aside from that, I'm an avid traveler.
So I've been to many countries, and I'm always
looking for recommendations for cooler and newer places to travel to.
Since this talk is about traveling, I want to
mention that there's two kinds of traveling.
So the first kind of traveling is the one where you have new experiences
and you experience the joy and the aha. Moment of seeing
something new and novel for the very first time in your life.
So imagine if you're looking at the pyramids of Giza
or if you're looking at the Eiffel Tower. Just the sheer
bliss of, like, oh, my God, I'm seeing something new for the first time.
That's amazing. And that takes your breath away. And that's usually
what we think of when we think of the word traveling. We think of it
as, like, seeing new things. But there's another kind of traveling.
And this kind of traveling is the ability to see the same
things you're always seeing, but with a different outlook. So imagine
if you're in a relationship with a person for many years,
and even after all these years, you learn something new about them,
and you get so surprised, like, oh, my God, I still can't
believe I'm learning something new about this person. Or imagine if
you're going to an office and you've been doing the same drive to
your office for, like, 80 years, and on
this time, on this new day, instead of taking
the same old drive, you took a different route, or maybe you played a new
song, and somehow it becomes just a bit more joyful and cheerful because
you did the same thing you do every day, but you did it with a
different frame and you had a better fun
doing it. So,
ideally, my goal in life is to inspire people to learn
to do the second kind of traveling, because if you do that, then no matter
where you are and what you're doing in life, there's always an
element of spontaneity and joy that comes with the newness of
seeing new experiences. It's the ability to inject
spontaneity and novelty in anything that you're doing.
However, in the interest of time,
this talk is about the first kind of traveling,
where you learn to have novel experiences in your life while still
trying to maintain your job, your physical health, your mental health,
and you have to do all of these things without breaking a buck.
Fortunately, we are in a place where we
are extremely blessed with our abilities as
skilled programmers, managers, DevOps engineers.
We are in a unique place in history where we can use our work
to work remotely. And remote work is something that's considered
not only acceptable, in fact, it's even encouraged
in our workforce. And it's time that we take
the full advantage of this opportunity to travel and
explore the world while still maintaining our jobs.
So I sort of gave you the main idea that, yeah, traveling is cool,
traveling is fun, it's an amazing experience, and we should all do it.
But I'm also going to highlight a bigger question of why we should be
doing it. So instead of giving you all my
lessons in kind of like a package sort of a way, how about I give
you a story? A story that I actually went through myself.
And then as I followed through my own story, I would offer
different lessons, which I learned by randomly stumbling upon and
trying out many different things in my own life.
So here it goes. So 2020,
that was a very hard year for all of us. It changed
my life for the better in some ways, and also for the
worse in other ways. I had a roller coaster of
a ride. You see, at the start of the year,
I used to live in this cute little town called Ottawa.
Ottawa is the capital of Canada. And I was
working in the beautiful offices of Shopify in
Ottawa. And I had a very fun life full of
friends and coworkers. And we would. We would
meet up every day, we would hang out, we would play games,
we would go to parties together. We would have so many get togethers,
and we would do cooking, tech conferences, everything.
We would do all kinds of things. And I honestly felt so connected
to people and had such a fun life. So I've been
a very social person, and just the joy and the camaraderie
of being around people makes me very happy
now. March 2020. The COVID
happens. When the COVID happened, it was
quite a shocker for me. I was actually in complete denial.
I was still going to my gym. I literally turned off all the
news sources that were hitting me because I lived
by myself and I wanted to maintain my mental
health. For the first few days of
work from home, I was like, this thing is going to end.
This has to end. And when this ends,
I'm going to go back to my office, to my friends. We're going to
have these fancy lunches. We're going to chill out. We're going to make fun of
this. And we all know how that turned out so well.
That's life now. Different people deal with different things differently.
But for me, this was a complete turnover. I was
a very social person. And the feeling of being around people
and vibing with people is something that's very important to me.
So to revamp everything by myself was too much
work. It was a shocker, but I had
to adapt. So as months went on,
I realized that the emotions of the shock of COVID finally
faded away. And I was slowly adapting to the new
lifestyle of remote work.
I was very methodical, very calculated. I would take
good care of my health. I would always work out. I would always be diligent
with my work. And I had a very appropriate work from
home set up to take care of the work stuff.
Things were actually going fine for a couple of months until I
woke up one day and started having serious troubles in my relationships.
You see, what happened was both my dad
and my sister got really sick. They had
Covid and they all live in India. And meanwhile,
here I was in Canada, thousands and thousands of miles
away from my family. And I couldn't help
them. I was completely incapable of doing anything
to help and support them. And that, to me,
was extremely stressful because I really want
my family to be safe and healthy.
And aside from that, the rest of my social circle
was kind of drowning out day by day.
So people were moving to different cities, people were switching jobs. So pretty
soon I felt this pain of isolation
like I'd never felt before. And I really
wanted to get past it. I actually
felt like this guy, to be honest. It's like the guy hearing,
like, a bad news over the phone. That was me. I was hearing quite a
few bad news over the phone. And to be honest,
those were not good times for me. And that's
kind of how my story starts. It starts from a rather dark
places of escapism. I was having a hard time
dealing with stuff. And it turned me into someone who
wanted a coping mechanism to deal with
stuff. And fortunately for me, there comes
this ski season. So as I've told you before, I'm a good
skier and skiing is my saving grace. So I
used to go to these ski hills called Mothamblan.
It's a beautiful ski resort in Quebec. This is
an actual photo of the ski hills that I
used to go to. It's a beautiful place. It's basically straight out
of Narnia. And I love skiing.
So at the time it was a release from all the
stresses and the isolation that I was feeling.
It was a two hour drive from my city of Ottawa to Motombla and
back. So whenever I
went skiing, I always used to stay at this hostel
and I really enjoyed my time there. I even made some friends with other
people. I was finally able to connect with other people,
share the things that kind of made me very uncomfortable about
my family's illness and those kind of things. And slowly and
gradually, the emotional stability and the connection that I
was missing that was actually gained back by
connecting with people, with other skiers, other friends.
And I think that to me was the most important thing. Not just skiing,
not just the beautiful views, not just know, living in basically Narnia.
It's actually meeting with people, having fun with them, making memories and
connecting with them. And that helped me
cope with the stress of my family stuff.
Very fortunately, over the next couple of weeks,
both my dad and my sister recovered from COVID
They are perfectly fine and they're fine now.
So that's a good thing. And I had some new friends to hang out
with. So that's a great news for me. So just
to keep the momentum, I actually started going to Mothamblan
almost every weekend and staying over.
Things are looking pretty good. And one day when I was
at the hostel, they hit me that I come here
so often. I really like living here and there's really
no obligation for me know, take the journey back
to Ottawa and go there. So at this point I'd become
good friends with the people who live there. So one day I basically went
to the owner of the hostel. His name was Matthew. So I'm talking to Matthew
and I told know if
I, if I go on booking.com
and book this hostel for an entire month, it's going
to cost me like $3,600.
That's a lot of money for me at the time and
I think that might be a little too much for me. But what
happens if I just pay you straight out of pocket?
However much you want, you can make a rental agreement you can take cash however
much you want, and then I pay you and you let me stay for a
month. And this was kind of a strange request. It's like it was two in
the face. It was kind of a surprising. So told him, hey, man, take your
time. Take your time. Think about this. You don't have to answer me
right now. So the next day, he comes back and he
says, $1,200. And that was like,
bam. It's basically like one third of
the price that I was seeing on booking.com.
So I listened to this. I'm just ecstatic. I'm happy
as a person could be. And I pack up all my
stuff. I go back to auto, I pack up all my stuff. I take
it all in, and next thing you know is I'm moving over and actually
living in a ski resort. I set up my work desk.
I set up my entire workplace and everything I negotiated
with my employer that, hey, I'll be working from here,
and I'll be sticking to these particular work hours and focus on my
work in those work hours. And aside from that, I'll be skiing in
the morning or after work and stuff like that.
And those were some pretty happy
times for me. So this brings
us to the first rule of digital nomadism. You can literally
live anywhere. Anywhere. Literally anywhere, as long as you learn
how to negotiate. So I never knew in my life that
you could work from a ski resort and
set up a workspace there. But I randomly stumbled upon it because
I was going through some dark times. And I did it for two months
before the partying and the fun got the better of me and had to stop.
But that's a story for another day. So over time,
I learned this special technique for living in places. And I
learned that I could literally start messaging random hotels,
outhouses, Airbnbs, anywhere which
has a house which has an empty space. I can just send
them, like, a fancy email telling them a little bit about me, what I do.
And I would set up a call with them once. I would be on a
call with them, I would have a nice and a friendly conversation.
I would tell them about my background, and I ask them like, hey,
can I stay here for, like, two months? And I'll pay you in cash
or whatever form that works for you. We can make a rental agreement. We can
do it online, however it works for you. And this interesting thing
is that most of the times, people actually get baffled because
it's a strange request for places which are not used to working
like a rental place. And they would give me, like, 50% to 60%
off simply because I asked. And the reason they would give me that
is because they would much rather have a nice tenant who takes
care of the place and pays them consistently, rather than
sorting through all these people every weekend,
making a filter, figuring out if this is the right person or
not. They would much rather give it to someone who could just take care of
it and pay them money. So that's how I got a lot of
discounts down the line. Now, there comes a second lesson
here. And in order to understand this lesson, I have to introduce you
with another story.
Here it goes.
When I was at my company as an intern, I knew this guy
back in the day. He was a very interesting guy. He joined as
an intern at my company at the age of 36.
He was pretty late in starting his tech career,
and I asked him about his journey, and he said that when he
was younger, he spent a couple of years learning how
to farm in Kenya. And then he came back
to Canada. He found a very large piece of
land in Surrey, in Vancouver, for the purpose
of agriculture farming, and he leased it for two years
to do some organic farming. Now, for those of you
who are unaware of the canadian housing and the property market,
Surrey is a part of Vancouver, which happens to be one of
the most expensive real estate areas in Canada and quite
possibly the world. So now, naturally, the question comes that
if he did farming in such an expensive real estate area,
how did he get the money for it? So I asked him
about it, and he said,
I basically looked for, like, an old farmed land,
which was just, like, looking like it was deserted, it was dilapidated,
it was just collecting dust. And he found the owner,
and he contacted him, and he promised him that he would lease this land
and make it the best organic farm in Vancouver. He's very skilled,
and he wants to make this great organic farm. And the
owner is always welcome to take any of the fresh produce from the farm for
free. So there was a lot of back and forth between
him and the owner of the land, and he ended up
becoming close friends with the owner of the land.
Now, the crazy part is that when he finally
signed the lease, the lease was for just one dollars,
because that was the minimum legal amount of lease that was permitted
at the time. And that's insane, right?
Imagine signing the lease of an expensive land for literally just
one dollars because you become friends with the owner of
the place where you're working at. And I think that kind
of shows you something very important that in any business, deal in any
contract. It's just a contract between two people who are willing
participants. So if there's only one
thing, if there's only one thing that you can take from this entire talk
is that never be afraid to ask for the absurd.
Whether it's like a hotel where you want to live at, whether it's an Airbnb,
whether you're buying a car from a rental dealership or whatever,
always ask the absurd. Just it's
never be afraid to ask people for something that you want, whether you want
to ask someone out on a date, whether you want to ask someone out for
some help that you need. The absolute worst that someone can
say is no. So become closer
to people, and don't do this in sort of like a manipulative way, but more
in sort of like, I got to shoot my shot. Let's see what happens.
Let's see how it goes. So I'll give you an example of why this
works in traveling. You see, the thing that happens in traveling is
that most of the places that, the fancy places that you look
out for, they actually make their money during the peak season.
So most hotels, Airbnbs, hostels,
they mainly make their money during weekends. So if you
can go ahead and ask them, like, hey, if I were to stay here for
a month, can you give me a special rate? Often they'll come up
with a rate that's 50% to 60% cheaper than online booking for the entire
period of the place. And oftentimes you can even negotiate them
further down from the rate that they first give you.
And in my history, I found places which charge like $200
a night on the weekend. But if you take them for the entire month,
they'll give you one, $200. So that's like an 80% discount from
the monthly price of individually booking something online.
And the reasoning is actually very simple. Rather than finding
every new person every other weekend, sorting through people,
filtering, doing all that shebang, and then hoping that they
don't ruin your place, they would much rather have a decent working professional
who can just take care of the place, stays there for the entire month,
and they don't have to think about it. So I've
literally had calls to the Airbnbs where I told them,
hey, I know that Airbnbs are for short term stay,
but instead of staying here for short term, how about we make this instead
of booking through Airbnbs, can we just do it like a rental
agreement for a longer term? And I could stay here,
and they would often offer me, like 40% of the monthly price.
Anything that we be terminals that we use online, like booking.com,
Airbnbs, all of those things. They're kind of middlemen. They always charge you so much.
First thing you can do is you can remove the middleman. Second thing you can
do is you can tell them, hey, I'm staying for a longer period, just give
me a better rate. And the worst thing that could happen is people say no
or not give you something you want, but at least you ask.
Truth is, there are no rules.
You can get the best deal just depending on how smart you are
with negotiation. Now, let's start off with the third rule
of digital nomadism. One of the points
of friction that I always learn in the stories of people
who are digital nomads is that they want to be like,
they would search, they would google for how to be a digital nomad in Portugal,
how to be a digital nomad in South America or something like
that. And they would look at the search results and they would find these fancy
places which are like, this is set up for remote work. This has
a fastest wifi, this has a swimming pool, this has a massage area.
This has like a spa. This has all the amenities that you could need.
And you find these places, but then you would actually look at the price and
it would be like $7,000 a month.
So it would be like you could find like a fancy paradise of
remote work. Then you look at the price, you realize this is insane,
and then it kind of nudges you in the direction of
just, why bother doing this? It's too expensive.
And the truth is that you don't need these fancy
resorts to live at. You can always find much cheaper
options. If you're willing to go retro, if you're willing to go on your own,
you can always find much cheaper options by yourself. So,
for example, imagine if you want to move to a
new city and you're looking for, say,
a new apartment where you could work from. Now, if you
find an apartment that does everything, but it just doesn't fit into
the requirement of, like, I need a good desk, I need
a good place to take calls and all those kind of things.
What you can always do is that you can pair up your membership with
a membership of a remote workplace office. So like
a co working space. And the reason that is super helpful is
because you can always have a fine place to
work from, which would be your co working space, and then you can stay at
any crappy place that works just enough for you to sleep.
So that's kind of how I did. It's like I would
find any place that's good enough for me to
stay at or to sleep at, and that doesn't have to be expensive. And then
I would pair it with a remote work membership, and that
way you can have the best of both worlds where your place of stay
doesn't have to satisfy all the constraints, but it is good enough for
you just to survive. So moving
on to the next part of my journey.
So we learned some few good lessons from the first part of
the journey. So after I was staying in Mothamla,
I had some couple of really amazing experiences and
I had a good time, I got to be honest. But I realized
it wasn't very conducive to being productive at work.
And I had to decide to move back to
a more normal lifestyle where I was living in a normal
household. And I wanted to experience the joys of the
boring life without the ski bumps and the adventure.
So I moved to Vancouver, which is another
city, which is way far off in the west coast.
I literally found like an Airbnb. I negotiated a month
of stay for lesser price than the original price. So the original
price was 1100. I negotiated up to 700.
And that's pretty low for Vancouver. And Vancouver
is a beautiful place that's very close to my herd.
And I just wanted to stay here because I wanted to explore this
beautiful city. And this is like an actual photo of
Vancouver. So for those of you don't
know, this was actually a large move. You see, Ottawa and Vancouver
are basically a country apart. They're like 3000 km away
from each other. So I had to take a long five hour flight
in order to move from Ottawa all the way back to Vancouver.
And I understand that some of my behavior here
screams of like male tecboro energy. I get it. But I can assure
you other people can do this too. And that's probably why
I'm giving this talk. Anyway. So I was flying
all the way across the country and I
had to give up literally most of the things that I owned because
I only needed the bare minimum stuff that I needed with me
and I had to give away all the best of the stuff that I didn't
need. So in the end, the end result was something like this photo.
So this is a photo of everything I owned. When I
arrived at Vancouver airport. I ended up giving
away all my possessions and everything I
didn't need. And in the end, all I was left with was
just two bags for some nice fancy clothes. My laptop,
my ski bag, which is to keep my skis and some
clothes and then my ski boots, and that's it.
I gave away my bike. I literally sold it.
I had another bag that I gave away, and I gave away a lot of
stuff that I just didn't need because I wanted to be free
and travel more. So this brings us to the fourth rule of
digital nomadism, which is minimalism
is very hard, but it's worth it. The way I arrived at this is
that I made a list. I made like a noted list
of everything that I could possibly use in my journey.
So whether it was a toothbrush, whether it was my laptop,
whether it was my slippers, anything that I use twice or twice a day,
it's very clear that I actually need it. But if it's something that I
don't need, like a candle or like a yoga
mat or something, I'll keep it on the list, but I'll make sure that I
note that I don't actually use this thing, even though I own it.
And that way I kind of came up with a list of, finally,
the things that I actually use once or twice a week, twice a week,
every day. And I just restricted myself to only having
those things, and I just gave up all of the other things away.
So you don't have to go as far as I did. You can do a
much smaller version of this in your own, in which you're
exploring something for, say, a week or two, and you're going for a short
trip. And in the short trip, you realize what you need and what
you don't need, and you just stick to the bare minimum of what you need.
So this brings us to the next rule,
and this is kind of a pivot here, which is that the part
of making lists is important, and you can use that for any other kind of
problems, too. So when I had to move to Vancouver,
I was become more and more familiar with myself, what I like and I
didn't like. And that made me realize that
every time I'm searching for apartments, every time I'm searching for rental agreements,
I can always write them down as a list problem.
And this is very particular for rental
agreements, but it applies to many other areas
of life, too. So what I would do is I would make a
list, and I would make a list of all the things I absolutely need in
a place or all the things I absolutely need to own. And then I
would keep refining and pruning that list over months and months and
years, so it becomes much easier for me to
use that list and to make it applicable. So for
example, take a look at this. This is my list for what
kind of apartment that I need. So here I
have defined all the kind of boundary conditions that I needed, an apartment that the
monthly rent could be from 900 to 1300. It has to be furnished, it has
to have a decent wifi, I have to have a flexible agreement from month
to month. So based on this list, I kind
of made like a template email message that I always used to send to Airbnbs
and to landlords. And I use these kind
of lists to help me kind of find newer things
and to make me realize that
I become very essentialist. I follow essentialism,
which is the idea that you only use the bare minimum of
exactly what you need and don't focus on the extraneous information and
the redundant stuff. So that is the
fifth rule. Write down apartment search as an optimization problem,
meaning write it down as a list and then satisfy the constraints of
the list. Now this is a 6th rule.
This is one of the major caveat that I didn't mention before,
and the reason I didn't mention is because it's actually quite hard to talk
about it, is that one thing I want to warn you people
is that no matter what you do, no matter what kind of exploration you do,
always do things in a legal manner. Don't skate around the legal logistics,
don't ruin your career because you wanted to travel, it's not worth.
So don't, don't skate around legal logistics,
taxes, all that kind of stuff. So if you're within the same country,
like if you're within Canada, it's actually very easy to move to different provinces
as long as you're not moving to Quebec. And different states have
different tax regulations, so you have to take care of those. So you have to
go online, peruse those tax regulations, but over
time you kind of make sense of them. If you're within
a single country, it's usually much easier. But if you
want to go to a foreign country, or if you want to go to another
country, like say, if you want to go to Europe and you live in,
say, South America or North America, different countries
have different regulations and you always have to know what those regulations
are. So they depend on your nationality, they depend on your passport, they depend
on kind of your work background and everything.
So the thing that you have to know is that a lot of countries are
very okay with you traveling there for a month or two or
even for 90 days. A lot of countries are okay with you traveling there,
but they're not okay with you working from there. So the
only way to figure this out is to just actually email the embassies.
Actually ask the people who are people
who work in visa agencies and stuff, and ask them like,
hey, is this legally allowed for me to work from there,
even for 30 days? And sometimes for some places in the world,
like for the United States, it can be very messy and you
might find an answer no, and there's nowhere
around it, so I wouldn't risk anything just
for a few fun trips. So always make sure whatever
you're doing, it's legal. Talk to the visa
people, talk to the state and tax regulations.
Talk to your employer about all the regulations there are and the legalities of
your working stuff. And always make sure that you don't skater around these
things because they're important. I can't tell you
exact specific thing because it depends very much because
everyone is under different circumstances, so everyone has different rules.
And that's why I can't talk more about this topic, but hopefully
you figure this out on your own. Now,
at this point in the story, I was living in Vancouver,
and I've been living there for a while and I
really enjoyed living there. So this is my third province in the
story. And as much as I enjoyed living in the paradise of
Vancouver, I couldn't resist the idea of traveling and exploring
more places. So one day,
as I'm going about my day, I searched through Google flights
and I was searching through the all areas feature. So the way
you use this feature is that in the from area you
enter the city of residence, the city where you're staying at,
and in the to area you enter the name of your country or
the continent that you want to go to, whatever it is, whatever your destination is.
So for me, the search feature kind of looked like this.
In the from area I entered Vancouver, in the to area I entered Canada.
So here's Vancouver and here's Canada.
And what it would do is that it would show me all the cheap
flights from Vancouver to other places in Canada without me
having to manually type in the name of the places over and over again.
And it kind of makes a large map of all the cheap places that
I could actually go to. So I use this feature whenever I'm feeling
a bit adventurous and I want to do a nice weekend
vacation or something. So as I was doing this,
I saw that the flights to Calgary back and forth were
just like $100. They were super cheap. So I booked
a mini weekend vacation of like a long weekend. So it
was like a four day vacation. And little did I know that
I would enjoy Calgary so much that I actually wanted to
spend more time in Calgary. So what
I did was I moved to Calgary after this experiment.
I did this mini experiment. I met some amazing people,
had some fun time, and then I made a permanent decision to
move to Calgary. But it started off with a cheap,
mini weekend vacation experiment kind of a thing.
And I think you can do this, too, is that whenever
we think of traveling and moving places, we always
think of it as this gigantic, herculean effort of like,
hey, you're going to take everything you have and just
move, and you don't have to do all of it. Truth is, you can just
take small vacations every now and then and just try out a
different place. Because the thing about trying out different things is that you don't know
what you don't know, and you don't even know that you don't know it.
So that's my argument for trying out different things,
and that's my argument for having cheap experimentation built into
your framework of living life and traveling. So, for example,
if you want to try out a new gym membership or any
other kind of fitness application or kind of a cooking application, don't get the
annual membership. Get like a monthly membership. Stay consistent with the
monthly membership. See if it fits your goal. See if it makes you actually
better in life. And then, once you're consistent with the monthly membership,
get the annual membership. The idea is that you have to maximize
the low cost experimentation in any different area of
life. And then once you have enough good
results from your cheap experimentation, you can
extrapolate those results and use it to do a major
move, or like a full time annual commitment to anything that you're
using. So cheap experimentation is, again, your best friend,
and you should try it out as much as you can.
Now, I want to offer a final note. I've given you
a lot of advice. I've given you a lot of different teeny, tiny tactics here
and there, but I wanted to offer, like, a final note, which is
kind of a warning note or a cautionary tale. And basically,
it's like, as much as I love traveling, exploring the world, I must warn
you that all the tricks are handed to you can sometimes
be quite taxing, mentally and physically,
and moving to different cities, adapting yourself to
different people, different cultures, all these things can actually be quite taxing
on your mental and physical health. The ability to
recreate everything from scratch. It's actually at a certain point, it becomes too much
work, but it's still worth it. For me, it might not
be for everyone. Life for me is like a fun challenge,
and sometimes the experience or the novelty of new experiences kind
of wears out. So I want to
show you that the way to take this talk is that it's not just
about traveling to different places. It's rather having a new outlook
on life. So you don't have to do everything that I did. You can just
take these tiny nuggets, figure out what actually works for you,
and try those things out. And when it comes
to traveling, I see traveling, in essence, as the ability to see the
world with different eyes. You can do it in a way
which I did, which is like, I literally hopped on places like a nomad
and saw different parts of the world. But you can build a new
outlook of life by doing the same thing you do every day,
just with a different outlook. So that's a choice you have to make.
And whatever you choose, it doesn't really matter as long as
you're enjoying yourself. And there's
a philosophy that's very akin to my philosophy in life, and it's called
ikigai. So ikigai is a japanese concept that
refers to something that gives a person a sense of
purpose and a meaning for life.
So it looks kind of like this. So it's kind of like the intersection of
the Venn diagram of the four areas.
So the four areas are what you love,
what you're good at, what you can be paid for, and what
the world needs. The idea is to combine all of
them to make something that's truly meaningful and beautiful
for you, and that's the kind of life you want to live.
For me, I love traveling. I think it combines all
the other aspects of life that give me meaning and joy. So I feel
that it's very much in alignment with my values,
and I encourage other people to find that
thing for themselves. It may be traveling, it may not be traveling, but whatever it
is, find that thing for yourself and try to embody it.
And with that, we arrive
at the end of our talk. It was very nice talking to
you folks, and I just wanted you to know that if you wanted
to recreate a similar journey for yourself, where you want to have remote
work and where you want to be kind of a nomad, explore other places.
One way you could do it is by joining Shopify them.
And so here's the link for Shopify. So just hop onto our careers
page and apply for the job that fits you the best. And I
wish you the very best of luck in everything. Thank you.