Hi everyone, my name is Matteo Gabrielli. I am a solution architect at
Amazon Web Services and today I want to show you
how you can empower your business use cases by getting
insights from text. So I will bring
you through the need for automating document
processing. We will have a look at the challenges and
how AWS can help mitigate these challenges
and then we will have a quick look at
a demo that is an AWS solution called document
understanding solution. So what is the current
state of documents? Well, for many industry,
documents are the primary business tool and
we can think about documents as email,
internal documentation, it could be menus,
invoices, technical documentation. And all
of this data is in different data stores across
the business, right. And is rarely
decreasing as number of documents, right. This number
is usually growing and growing year over year.
Garner research claimed that the organization worldwide
record a 25% growth in usage of paper
each year. So I don't want to focus that much
on that AWS, all the challenges that
this can bring, right? So how to extract
information at scale and how to avoid to
be prone to errors in the
processes, right? So let me recap,
what are the challenges in processing documents. So first
of all, if you are doing this manually, probably it's really time
consuming, it could be error prone and most
of the time expensive. It doesn't really scale well.
And most of the time if you are doing this,
probably we are using some rule based system
and those are not really flexible. Most of
the time, if we want to extract information and
we want to leverage machine learning,
probably we need to have a set of skills in order to
do that. And also maybe data that is labeled
many times. Also we want to incorporate in this
process the human in order to verify
and be part of this workflow. So how AWS
can help? Well, let's focus on
this use case of understanding documents.
So what is the first action that we have to do?
Well, we are given a document and we want to extract
information from there. So extract the text that is in documents.
Once we have this row text, we want to make sense
out of this data and we want to loop
to add a human in this loop to verify
that the information extracted and the
sense we are making out of this data makes
sense. So who is going to help in
implement this workflow? It will be AWS EI services.
And let's put EI services in a context.
So the context in this case is the AWS
machine learning stack. As you can see, there are
three different layers. At the bottom you can
see the machine learning frameworks and infrastructure
layer. This one is intended for expert practitioner,
right? You can find in there the more common framework,
machine learning frameworks, Tensorflow,
Pytorch, Apache, Mxnet,
the deep learning EMI and the containers gpus.
Then in the middle layer, those are
the machine learning services that make it easy for
machine learning developers and data scientists to build,
train and deploy machine learning models.
And this is happening. Leveraging Amazon Sagemaker
and its features. What we are going to concentrate
on today and is the last layer, the top one. And those
are, those are these
AI services allow all developers to use pretrained
model to add intelligence to any application
without machine learning expertise.
So what we are going to have
a closer look today at it will be comprehend
textract Kendra and comprehend
medical. Then we will also talk about Amazon
augmented EI. But let's
start with the first Amazon textract.
So Amazon texttract is a service that extracts text form and
table from document. It could be PDF or
images. What are the advantages? Well that
I have an intelligent OCR tool that is able
to extract all of this information
starting from my input and I don't have to
have any machine learning experience in order to do
that. I can just invoke text track through
an API and this means that I
can just build my workflow. So for example,
given an input, use text track, extract the information and
insert this information inside a database. And this eliminates
the manual effort of doing this and of course can
lower the document processing cost.
Comprehend is the service that will
help us in discovering insights and relationship in
text. And as you can see the input,
it could be text in general. So email chat,
social phone cases that are transcribed and
we want to apply comprehend on this
text in order to get information as what are
the entities that comprehend recognize.
So are there some name of people?
Are there some name of organization? So what
are the key phrases? Are there some personal identifiable information?
What is the sentiment of the text you are giving me? Is positive,
is neutral, is negative. I can use
comprehend to train and to do document classification,
topic recognition, detect what is the language,
syntax and also events.
Where is Amazon comprehend used? Well there are
several use cases but for
example some of that could be intelligent document processing. That is the one
we are looking at today. But there's also customer sentiment
analysis contact center call analysis because maybe
we want to recognize what is the sentiment during these cases
or maybe what is the topics they are talking
about. And also in PII detection.
We will see this later in the demo. There's another
version, let's call it like that of Amazon comprehend
and this is Amazon comprehend medical that is based
to be specialized in the medical
text. So you can for example detect entities
as medication, medical condition, test,
treatment and procedure anatomy in the text.
So body parts for example,
you can extract also the relation because there will be a relation
for example between a medication and a
dosage and entity traits. So all
of these complex way of recognizing these
entities or relationship between
inside the text is abstracted to you
through API calls. So you can just give
your input text and decide what you want to get out
from there. Amazon Kendra is
an intelligent search service powered
by machine learning. In this case,
the idea is to do some intelligent search,
right? So we want to move from this lexical
so using keywords to intelligent search
which is searching for information by meaning
this use natural language understanding and
other machine learning model to take advantage of
the rich context in unstructured
content, the one that we are providing and get much more
accurate search results. That what we can do with a
lexical search, let's say later
on we will also see how this compare
this lexical search and intelligent search in the demo that I will
show you. The last leading
actor that I want you to present
is Amazon augmented AI. That is
it allow us to easily implement human review
of machine learning prediction. How does it work? So we
want to incorporate our
reviews right inside our machine learning
workflow. So we can do that with Amazon augmented
AI. And this allow us to reduce the time
in order to build all of this. Because for
example, imagine if you have to do some reviews, sometimes you have to expose
an interface for the user to select yes,
this is correct or no, this is not correct.
So Amazon augmented UI is providing you
some pre built uis.
You can define what kind of workflows
workforce you want to dedicate in order to run these
reviews. It could be a private workflow for first.
Maybe you want to use a vendor that is trained on
how to review the data,
the prediction, or maybe you want to leverage the
public workforce.
This is for example the case as Amazon mechanical Turk,
right? And yeah, you can integrate
it with your custom machine learning model
and you can use prebuilt algorithms to increase accuracy.
So for example, how does it
work? We can think about the
client application that is sending the data and
our machine learning model making predictions.
Well, what can happen is that our machine
learning model can return a high confidence prediction.
And so we are
good probably with that because we know that it's
confident in that. But what if the confidence
is low? Maybe we want to send it to our
human review hands. In this case is where the
reviewer consolidated using Amazon
augmented AI and we store
these results, for example in a s free bucket
hands. From there we can come back to our client
application. Why not? Maybe we can use the data that at
step six we have in order to improve
our machine learning model. Right. As an example,
I wanted to bring you an integration example between texttract and
Amazon augmented AI. So using textract
but also then incorporate some human reviews and this
could happen, for example for regulatory requirements,
but also when we have to take sensitive
decision and we want to decide to
have a review. Or maybe it's because
textract is doing its best, but probably
we really want to double check because there are hard to read documents
and so maybe we have to incorporate some reviews
and well, of course the goal is
to human to review and
to provide an oversight. Let me bring you an example
of what condition can we define using
Amazon augmented AI? We can play with the confidence
score. For example, we can say if the score
is less than 90%, send it to review.
But we can also say, for example,
trigger a human review if you don't find a
field, for example, if you are not finding the name,
or if you are not finding the account number inside the
document. Or we can send just a
random sample of prediction
to Amazon augmented Di. So review for
a 10% sample of all documents.
Why not? Okay, now that we have
a better understanding of what
are the services, the EI services that will be involved
or that can be used, you can think about these EI
services and the AWS services in general as
Lego blocks that you are trying to put together in
order to create your solution. And in this case,
what I wanted to present you is the document understanding solution.
And as you can see, these four components
are going to work together and
act. So Amazon comprehend, medical Amazon
extract kendra and comprehend. So then when
we get some documents in input,
they are going to extract, understand information and
also index this data in order to
perform OCR form extraction,
intelligent search table extraction,
entity detection, medical entity detection
and reduction controls. So let's go
and see how this looks like in a demo.
This is the document understanding demo solution
that I have deployed inside my AWS
account. Later on I will tell you more about
how and where you can find this cloudformation template
just to launch and to deploy it inside your
AWS account. So as you can see,
there's three different main thing we can
do with the document understanding solution. One is the
discovery. We can work with compliance so redact
information and integrate this and do some
workflow automation. So now
we are in the list of documents. The documents
that you see here are example documents, but you can
of course bring your own documents in
there or remove or explore
inside these documents or just search by keywords.
What I wanted to show you is for example
going into a document and try to find if
there's for example some difficult elements
to extract as for example this table, right.
What I can do is just preview this document
hands, maybe select some part of it to
extract. And as you can see is detecting
the text that I'm highlighting or I can just ask
to search for a keyword like health.
And what I can also do is to convert
all of this document into row text or maybe
as we have a table in there asking to identify
the table and is correctly identifying the table,
one AWS, four rows and I can download this table
as a CSV. Another really interesting
feature. So in this case, who is
doing this job is textract, doing the row
text, extracting the row text or key value pairs or the table.
What comprehend can do is detecting entities.
So for example on this page, page five,
I can say detect organization and
AWS, you can see it's going to highlight what
are the organization as for example this or also
the American Diabetes Association.
I can also, since I see a lot of numbers,
ask him to detect quantities and is
able to detect.
Another feature that I wanted to show you is
the comprehend medical one. So as you can see, when I
go to medical entities this time, I'm able
to also identify medical conditions, test treatment
procedure, protected health information.
So let's have a look, for example, a medical condition and
as you can see, diabetes,
prediabetes, pregnant,
those are all medical condition that comprehend
medical is able to identify.
Another thing that I wanted to highlight is the possibility
of for compliance reason to redact
this information. For example, let's think if
for example we want to redact all of the medical condition,
I can just click here on reduct that
is going to remove all of these information and
then I can download my redacted
document or clear the reduction.
Now there are several use cases. One of these could be
personally identifiable information that we want to remove
easily from a document. Well, we can just redact
this information automatically.
Let's see how starting for example a search between
documents at the moment. So if I'm
here and I'm writing diabetes.
Okay, let's try now to search
through documents the information I'm looking
at. So what about if I'm searching diabetes.
As you can see there's three different tabs. The first one
is the result that I get
from a keyword search and those are provided
leveraging elasticsearch service. Then I
can get my results. The one that Kendra,
the service we were looking at before is providing me.
And of course in this case we are talking about a semantic search result
and there's also the possibility of comparing these two
results. As you can see, Kendra and
I really suggest to look in the product page in the feature section
at all the capabilities that scandra has.
For example is highlighting the frequently
asked question. So is providing me the information
that I need or maybe documents
and I can also provide a feedback to these results,
right, if they were relevant or not to me.
Okay, let's get back to the
presentation for the last information that I want to share with you.
Okay, so some
details about the document understanding solution.
So as we saw,
the document understanding solution is also really nice to
demonstrate the value of intelligent search. I really
suggest you to do some tries
also leveraging this comparison and seeing
how Kendra is and works in
order to provide the results the most relevant
resources. Well, but maybe you are wondering how
is actually all of this assembled together.
Well also on the AWS solution
page you
can find this architectural diagram and
as you can see there's several services
involved. Some of that were not mentioned today,
but I was talking about extract, comprehend,
comprehend, medical kendra. But of
course the data is also stored inside s
free. We have some lambda
doing some operation so executing some code.
We are storing the data inside dynamodb.
There is elasticsearch as well in order to provide a comparison
with Kendra and the application that we are going
to deploy when we deploy the
document understanding solution is leveraging cognito
for the authentication and cloudfront for
the distribution. So what
is also really nice about having and
starting exploring the services from AWS
solution is that for
example, the document understanding follows the well architected framework.
A lot of principles, hands, a lot of best practices altogether
and you can use it
starting from now to process hundreds
of thousands of documents. The code
is open source so you can find the solution and also tweak it
and maybe adapt it to your specific use case.
Hands is built using popular
technology CDK react in
order for the front end and CDK to define the
infrastructure. If you are wondering how
to get started on GitHub, you will find
the code for the solution. There are blogs
talking about that and also the page inside the AWS solution
you can download or directly launch
through a cloud formation one click cloud formation template
deploy inside your account and if
you need any help or you want to further explore,
feel free to reach out to AWS
these services here just a list of
compliance let's say certificate programs that these
services fulfill and just to have
an idea that these services are used
not only for proof of concept but also in productions
environment to fulfill all the business use case
you need. Thank you so much and
if you want to explore more about
machine learning on AWS, just click on your URL
bar ML AWS and thank you
so much for spending time with me. I am Matteo Gabrielli
and please if you have any questions feel free to reach out.