Many of the quantum circuits used in the niscar and beyond can be
understood visually as a collection of gates placed in a circuit, according to
some better one. Of course, the purpose of any circuit is mainly a specification
on how to perform a quantum computation. However, judging by
the managed circuits running one algorithm are often reused in more
complicated ones. The visual aspect is an important factor
for both understanding the inner working of an algorithm and
how this can be reused to build more advanced ones. As a concrete example,
we show here an implementation of the Grover search algorithm on
five qubits. What the algorithm does is that it permits searching an
unstructured data set for a particular value. 1 may observe that the circuit
is initialized in a default state, which usually is chosen to
be the state where all qubits are in the zero state. The six
ancillary qubit is initialized in one state. Next, the level of Hadamar gates
is applied. The effect of Hadamar gates is to transform the initial state
to a superposition of all possible states. You may
have heard sometime the statement that the quantum device computes all
possible results in parallel. This statement is, of course
a bit of a stretch, but it captures the rationale between this step, which is
using many other algorithms. Next, we apply a series of gates that
implement the algorithm itself. The same circuit can be
drawn in a more compact manner like this one.
We see that first we apply an oracle subsurface,
whose purpose is to mark the state we want to measure by flipping its
face, and next we apply the so called Grover diffusion operator,
which has the effect of inverting each 32 values stored in the
first five qubits around their global mean value.
Overall, these two gates have the effect of increasing the probability
of measuring the state flagged by oracle as a solution and decreasing
the probability of measuring any other state. The combination of oracle and diffusion
operator is applied several times in a row, and during
each iteration the probability of measuring the state we are searching for increases,
while the probability of measuring the other state decreases.
The results that we get when we perform the final set of measurements
on the top five qubits is not to be found with 100% certainty,
but is captured with very high probability. As another example,
we show here an implementation of quantum phase estimation, which,
like Grober, is not only a significant algorithm by itself,
but is often reused as a subcomponent in many other algorithms.
Here we also see the familiar construction of using a layer
of Hadamar gates in the preparation of the initial state for the top five
qubits. What is also important to remark here is that the
state of lower three qubits is prepared to be an eigen state of the operator
u whose eigenvalue we want to measure. As a consequence
of this, whenever we apply a control u operation on a bottom three qubit
due to a phenomenon named phase give back, the phase of u is recorded
bit by bit on the top control qubits. The case of u can be
linked to the eigenvalue of u and can be read out at the end
of the experiment by layer of measure gates shown here in red after we
applied an inverse quantum free a transform gate because the
phase was written in free a bases, while when we make
a measurement on a quantum computer we usually measure in the standard Z
base. What we have seen so far is
that the use case for designing circuits visually using an editor
is a very strong one. However, most of the existing circuit
editors are rather limited. Uranium is a platform that intends to
fill this unoccupied space. It is open source and free to
use. At its core it comprises can advanced circuit editor
which is easy to work with and powerful, and a high performance
simulator, and written eras that can run both in your browser and offline.
As a concrete example, here is how one can start using
our editor. First of all, you need to pick up gate and
drag and drop it into the editor area. Now you may
ask, do I need to do that for every gate that I want on my
circuit? The answer is not once you have added a
gate, you can easily duplicate it. You can generate an array
of identical gates of an existing one.
You can select a portion of a circuit
which you can copy, you can paste or
if you wish, you can erase.
Circuits can be reused in a sense that smaller circuits can be saved in a
project and reused that gates in a larger circuit from
the same project. For example like this one.
We also provide a very simple python API which one can
use to generate circuits programmatically. After doing that,
circuits can be imported in your existing projects.
Another very useful feature is, especially when working with compostable
circuits, is the ability to replicate a gate. This permits
you to generate an array of circuits of gates like
this, one of
the similar kinds that you have seen in quantum case estimation and are
very often used in many other algorithms of the same inspiration
for editing gate parameters, you can of course
interact with the gate pop up. So basically when you add
a gate and you can add for those gates that
accept parameters, you can add parameters from the gate
pop up, you can duplicate the gate and parameters will
be copied identically, there are a number of shortcuts between two editors
such that you can quickly switch from one gate on another or quickly
delete a gates. Measure gates behave a little bit different perhaps
I should first explain what is the role of the measure gates in our editor.
Because we display probability distribution, we do
not make sampling when you add a measure gate,
but what it happens. Well, if no measure gates are
added to the circuit, the output results for the
simulation will display results for the full Hilbert space
covered by the circuit. In this case, we have a circuit
with four qubits and the
simulation results have four states. When we add a
measure gate to the circuit, what the editor does is to
select a portion or subspace of the Hilbert space in
order to display results and ignore the
other one which is not covered by measure gates.
Whenever you add a measure gate to the circuit, it will
assign a classic bit to the measure gates and
usually the index of the classic bit is taken to be the same
with the index of the target bit. However,
for example, when you generate can array of measure gates,
this behavior might occasionally be different
because the editors tries to think to guess
which is the best configuration of measurements that you
want to apply.
In general, whenever you are uncertain about the
state of the circuit at training moment, you can
use this tooltip button which will show the parameters for
all those gates which have parameters.
And basically this is a very handy tool to
figure out what is the current state of your circuit
at any time. We support a large
collection of gates, many of which are not to be found elsewhere.
So of course we support the standard polygates xyz
gates. We support other
created closely related gates like v, which is the square root of x,
h which is square root of y and s, which is
the square root of z and
t, which is square root of f of s. We support
of course, arbitrary rotation on the blocks here around the
x, y and z axis. We support the Hadamar gates
which is used in almost every algorithm,
but we support some other gates. For example, what Hadamar
gate is is a rotation on the diagonal axis
in Zx plane. So besides this standard Hadamar
gate, there are two other Hadamar gates which are occasionally useful,
and this represent PI rotation around the diagonal axis in
the y, z and xy plane.
We support standard parametric gates ranging
from one to three parameters. We support the
sea gate which performs a
permutation on the x,
y and z axis. We support integral
root of x, y and z gates which are used,
for example, in quantum
free transform circuits for the two qubit
gates. We of course support the
swap gate and various
variants of swap like parametric swap or iswap,
and several others. We support the so called icing gates,
which are native gates to trap driven ion
devices. We support the Magic gate.
We support the Givens gate, which is used occasionally
in computational chemistry. We support the cross resonance gate,
which is a native gate in superconductic
base devices. And in
general you can add any numbers of controls to a gate.
For example, you can add controls in the Z basis
like this. Sorry,
but you can also add controls in the X
basis, or you can add controls in
the Y basis.
You can add controls either by dragging the control icon
from the top left of the UI, or you can add controls
from the gate pop up dialog where you
can add a little bit faster and larger number of controls.
We also support the aggregate gate, which is a method to
group several gates together and assign them a common
set of controls. For example,
here is an implementation of the Steen error correction code
in general, where you are unsure what a gate does.
You can use our help facility how it works. You select a gate from
the gate panel on the left and push the help button.
If you unselect the gate, you'll get to a general section
that will give you some hints on
general hints for using our editor an important detail when
we display our simulation result is the choice of ordering for qubits
when representing quantum states. Most quantum textbook use the
big indian ordering, while many commercial hardware quantum computing platform
use the little indian ordering because interpreting gates as binary
numbers makes sense. Using the letter collection,
we provide support for both.
When simulating quantum circuits, you can simulate circuits with
up to 27 qubits online. The simulator was written
in rust complex webassembly and runs very fast
in your browser, surprisingly fast. A 20 qubit circuit with
300 gigs is simulated in less than 1 second. We also
support we provide support for simulating
circuits with up to 32 qubits offline,
an important aspect to be reused. Our platform is not an isolated island
in the space of quantum computing software. We provide support for exporting
quantum circuits to Kiskit and OpencaSm format.
We also provide support for running your circuits directly on
IBMQ quantum devices. For this you need
to go to one of your projects, select a circuit you want
to run on, and then press the
ping IBMQ button.
This will take a few seconds because this will make an API call
towards IBM on the cloud. But eventually you are going
to see here a list of quantum devices which
you are allowed to use. Unfortunately, I have a basic ABM
Q account, and I have only access
to real devices, up to seven qubits.
You may be able to do more. At any rate, you also
have access to some very performance simulators.
For example, there is a tensor network simulator
which can simulate circuits with up to 100 qubits.
At this moment, you can easily create circuits in our editor with up to even
30 qubits or more. It may be a bit more tedious for the very
largest one, but it can definitely be done. And in general
it can be done fast and easily. To be fair, if you work with 30
qubits, a larger display might help, but you also provide a zoom in
zoom out function which allows you to
accommodate circuits with up to even 32 qubits
on the display of a laptop. In the future,
we want to scale our editor to hundreds of,
even perhaps thousands of qubits by
supporting circuits like this one. What you should
note here is the dots, meaning that you
could in principle will make circuits with an arbitrary
large number of qubits. Another interesting feature that we
might try to add support for is running semi classical quantum algorithms like
VQE and QA using our simulator.
In the end, I would like to invite you to try out our editor and
you have any kind of feedback, questions or feature requests, please contact
us on Discord. Thank you very much.