Hi and welcome to the OASP top ten for serverless applications.
Securing your application could be a hard task to do if you don't
know how. Luckily, we have organizations like
OASP to point out the common threats and the right
tools, open source tools you could utilize in
order to make your application much more secure.
Hi, my name is Shlomi. I'm a system architect at JIT,
an engineer, an A 200 veteran, and a cloud enthusiast.
Let's get started. So what do
you do if you suddenly realize that your application is
home alone? You need to first map the
common threats, the parameter threats,
and then understand how top utilize the
right tools in order to secure your application. So let's
take a look at a common structure of a modern application
and first let's take care of the parameter.
So let's take a look at different areas that
could be problematic. First, you have the CI CD pipeline. When everything
flows into your cloud, you have users that access
your application. It could be internal users like developers or
administrators or your clients themselves. You could
use public resources like ips and buckets.
You need to make sure they are secure. And if you are using third party
services, well of course you need to make sure you do it right.
How can you do it? You have different controls you could set in place in
order to make sure it's much more secure. You could
make sure you have least privileged access, don't give more than you need.
You could use multifactor authentication to make sure
that credentials are not stolen and then
taken advantage of. And of course you need to
make sure you don't have different cloud misconfigurations in order
to make sure you don't have attack surfaces that
could be used against you.
So you have different controls that you could use
in different areas, like the traffic secrets that you
use inside your application and cloud access top
services. When something happened, you probably want to investigate
it. You are using third party libraries,
packages and third party services. And of
course you need to make sure that if something happens,
you have a game plan in order to recover.
So let's take a look at a common
modern app and its structure.
And let's try to understand first what is
the difference between a common app, a common modern app,
and a classic app. So for instance, in these applications,
in this application, you have users, you have gateways
that lead the user inside your application.
You may have different public resources
like s three buckets in order to serve assets
and resources faster. And of course you have
your logic running inside the lambda functions.
Then you have different databases that you could utilize in order to store the
data. So what are the differences between a
common app, a common classic app, and a common serverless
app? So you have different shared responsibilities.
As we will see in a second,
serverless functions are mostly ephemeral,
which means that it has memory, it has
resources, but once it completes its execution,
everything is disappeared. Nothing is permanent, nothing is
stored mostly. Right. And you
have maybe an increased attack surface because as we
saw in the parameters slide, you have a lot of
different things that you use inside your application,
and you also have the ability to have much
more fine grained control of the application and
resources. So this is the shared responsibility
model for a classic application. If you run on AWS,
you can see that you need to take care of where the application
is located, the hardware, the global hardware,
your compute, storage, database and networking.
Everything is taken care by AWS. But from that
point on, the customer, which is you, you need to take
care of it yourself, right. You need to make sure
the data is encrypted and also the traffic and
addressed as well. You need to make sure that
the operating system, the network, the firewall are properly configured
and updated. The platform, the application users
and identity, you need to take care of them yourself.
And of course the data that you store in the databases
in a serverless application, well, the model looks
a bit different because AWS, if you run on
AWS, but it's the same probably for every cloud.
The cloud provider takes care of a lot more
things for you, right? Which makes you
responsible mostly for the logic of the application,
and that's a great difference. So let's take a look at
a security plan. Translation, what should we do? For instance, if you
have a threat that does injection,
the solution will be to validate the
input to the application and you are going to use a tool like
OSAP in order to test the different
inputs to your application, find those issues
and solve them. So who are
the Ospay foundation? What is it? So as we
can see, it's an open web application security project.
It's an open source, it's nonprofit foundation
in order to improve the security of software in
the Internet. Right. So they are
here to help us in order to make sure our application
and services are much more secure.
They have a list of the top
ten risks for basically different areas,
right? And we are going to focus on the serverless
top ten risks. We can see the list right here.
We are going to go in depth in
most of these in just a second.
But these are the ten top risks for
the OASP serverless. So let's start by mapping
them out. So this is the
same list, but mapped in categories.
So you can see that you have five different
threats in your come area. Identity and access.
You have two data and then you have log
and monitoring. Let's take a look at a few of them.
All right, so injection, what is the risk
if you don't validate your input? It cloud lead to
exploits like SQL injection.
How can you secure yourself from something like that? You could validate
the data input. You could make sure you don't have too
much privilege. If something happens, then the
resources, they cannot access other resources.
And you need to make sure you monitor and
log your resources at runtime to make sure that if
something happens, you know about it.
So you have different controls that you could use and utilize.
We'll see some of them soon. And in order to make sure that
you could achieve what we just talked about here.
All right, so you are using next one.
You're using third party or open source
code, right? We all do. We love open source.
It makes our job much easier and faster.
But the thing is that if you're using an outdated
resource, JIt could have known vulnerabilities.
But the thing is, because it's open source, it's scanned
all the time. And common threats are common. They are known.
So if you make sure that your
dependencies are updated by scanning
the different version of your dependencies
and find the common vulnerabilities, you could update
them and make sure that all known issues
are taken care of. Next, let's talk
about authentication and identity access.
The risk if, for instance, a credential
is stolen, data could be stolen as well,
right? And the flow of execution could be broken.
So in order to make sure that you are not
allowing threats through authentication, you need
to make sure you don't have unauthorized endpoints,
right. Don't have public endpoints without authentication and authorization
that could access data and make
sure that you're managing your users correctly.
Make sure you use your infra in a central
authentication method for interservices. So inside the
services as well. If something happens, you need to make sure that
the data flow is secure as well.
Make sure that all compute services and
lambdas, they require authentication in
order to make sure you prevent these things as well and
verify you don't have any unmanaged resources
like s three buckets or IP addresses to make sure
that nothing could be penetrated from
the outside world. So you could use
tools that actually scan your cloud after
deployment the real cloud to try to test and
find these issues misconfigurations.
All right, so access control. If it's broken, data leakage
from the cloud, cloud happen, and you
need to make sure you protect yourself from that. So ensure
you have list privilege for all resources, for your functions,
for your databases, and make sure that
you don't have too wide privilege. So if something happens,
the result is not top bad. You could check your
rules of the IM rules and roles with
open source tools.
All right, so sensitive data exposure.
The risk of course is data leakage.
So make sure your data is not accessible through public
endpoints. Make sure it's encrypted at rest because if
for some reason the disk is compromised, if it's
encrypted, you're probably good. And make sure the
transition of data is encrypted as well. Right? Always use SSL
so you could have controls that make sure
you don't have unencrypted data.
Scan the cloud, scan your code, find secrets and
check the transit of your data as well.
Security misconfiguration well,
you need to make sure you have the proper logging and
monitoring because information could leak and attackers
could happen. You need to make sure that if something is
not configured properly, you need to make sure that you know about it.
And you could also check that everything is configured in
your cloud properly by scanning it.
Cool. So now let's start by talking about
some of the available tools that we have we could
utilize. The first one we are going to talk about is OASP
zap. It's a web security tool.
It could can your web app and
your API in order to find misconfiguration
and vulnerabilities. It cloud find
different things like SQL injection. It works with URL and
API endpoints using open API. You could provide it
a swagger and it will test your API and
it will only work for your API endpoints. So if you
have async flows, it will not be tested with this
tool. We could test it with other tools. The next
tool we are going to talk about, it's something that will scan your code
and will check the dependencies that you
use by scanning known vulnerabilities. In libraries.
There are known databases like NVD
that you could utilize to make sure that the version of the
packages that you use are updated and don't have known
vulnerabilities. Secrets let's
talk about this tool. It's called Gitlix
and it scans for secrets in
git, right? So if by a mistake
like us, we are developers, we write code.
Sometimes we need to debug something and we put maybe a password
in order to connect to a service or a database.
Oops, maybe we forget it and it's in the code
and it goes to Jit GitHub for instance.
And once it's there, it's there forever.
So first off, you want to make sure you don't have
already secrets inside. Of course, if it's an open source project
that it's even riskier. You need to make
sure that there are no secrets in the
code. If you find them, you need to make sure you mitigate it properly,
replace the secrets, invalidate them, and make sure and try
to understand if something was compromised. And if you
want to make it even more secure, you could even use precommit
hooks in order to, in the developer's computer, utilize tools
like this in order to make sure you don't even push secrets.
Top git next we are going to talk
about Prowler. Prowler is a runtime infrastructure misconfiguration
tool. This is a very strong
tool that actually complements the OASP
zap we talked about just a second ago. Because if
OSAP scans your parameter, your web app,
and your APIs, prowling could
can your entire cloud.
JIt works with Azure and AWS,
and it could find misconfigurations in your cloud.
You could see that it has roughly 200 checks,
probably more by now, multiple output formats,
and it also supports AWS organizations.
And for instance, if you have async flows without
API gateway, Jit will scan those as well, along with a
lot of different resources it supports.
Next, we are going to talk about Airim by bridge
crew. It's a list privilege access tool.
JIT scans, IAM rules, roles,
policies to make sure you don't have more than you need.
It's easy to test that. Think about it. If you have a role with
a certain policy, it could check the logs, the cloud
rail logs, what was actually accessed, and if it doesn't
match it, cloud find issues in your
IM rules, right? All right,
so after we talked about different threats and
different tools, let's try to see how they match together.
And let's talk about the different threats
that we saw and see which tools could help
us out. All right,
so injection. What was the risk?
If you don't have input validation, it could lead to
exploits and data leakage.
So the tools that we could use here,
we have two tools, one to make sure we do have input
validation. If we don't OSAP is going to find that
out by trying to attack the API.
The other tool we could use is to make sure that if something like that
happens, we don't have too wide privilege access.
So we could scan using RIM and try
top have least privilege access control everywhere
in the system. Next,
we didn't talk about this threat, but you
could use XSe text leveraging old XML processors.
So this is something a little older, but you could do the same
thing using OSF. Find these issues and make sure you
don't use these old versions
by make sure your dependencies are updated. Same goes
for XSS. So basically you could
use OSAP, you could use OszAP in order to
find anything that is related to your API or
to your web application. It's going to use
a wide variety of tests and inputs in order
to try to break the application to
find these vulnerabilities. All right,
so if we are not using secure serialization
or deserialization, we could actually
have the same risk, the same type of risk and you
could use the same tools again, right? We cloud see that the
same set of tools give us a wide variety
of protection in different aspects.
So again, zap will find these issues and the dependency check
will make sure that if there are known issues like this,
we are going to be protected just by updating to the right version.
All right, so this is a
bit easier one to understand. We talked about this as well.
If you are using libraries and packages of
open source tools and packages,
they could have known vulnerabilities. We have databases
for these known vulnerabilities and tools that utilize
these databases in order to find be versions,
all versions that you use in your come. So by
scheduling a daily scan, a weekly can of
your dependencies, you could make sure that you are always
protected and you always use the right version,
the protected version of the packages that you use.
All right, so authentication,
especially in the serverless world when you have a lot of endpoints,
right? Everything is microservices, everything is
distributed. It could happen that you have points that are
not protected. So we have two cloud tools
that complement each other in order to find these misconfigurations.
You could scan the parameter using OWASP,
zap and you cloud use prowling in order to find
internal things, or maybe async flows
in your applications in order to find these
issues. So great tools. And by creating
scheduled scans you can find a lot of
issues in your application. All right, so if
you don't have the least
privileged access rules, roles policies for
the users or the resources that you use,
it could be problematic. And we talked about this
a few slides ago. RIm is a great tool in order
to help you do that. All right,
so that was a run through a lot of different
risks, a lot of different tools. Maybe it's
a bit too much. Let's try to summarize those
by looking at the different areas
of the application and trying to put tools where
it should be protected. So first off,
your come when you are writing code,
this is the easiest part to understand. When you secure
your code, when you write your code, you want to make sure it's secured.
You want to make sure you don't have secrets, because maybe you're a developer,
you're debugging something, you don't want to push it to jit.
You could use git leaks to make sure you don't have secrets
in the code. Secrets, environment variables, just passwords,
keys and certificates. It will find everything.
Then, because we all use open source libraries,
we want to make sure they don't have known vulnerabilities.
So we could scan dependency checks of these
packages using OAS depth check.
And of course we could use OASP zap in order to
make sure that we don't have broken endpoints.
And if we do find that, for instance, if you do not have
input validation in your code, you can
find it by using this tool. And then you could
modify your code in order to make sure that you protect
yourself from these issues.
Next, when we talk about the cloud,
we want to manage identity and access,
right? So you want to make sure that you have least privileged
access to all the resources in your application.
You could use these three tools in order to do that.
We talked about OS DESA, which is a tool that could actually
scan your parameter, also the web
application and also your API to try to find out
issues, misconfigurations and vulnerabilities.
We then talked about Prowler, which could
scan the internal of the cloud, not just a parameter,
and find different misconfiguration
issues and help you mitigate them.
And last but not least, we have rim that will check that
you have the least privilege policies that you
need in order to make sure that your application is
securely tight and secure, to make sure you
don't have too wide permissions.
Next, we are going to talk about the data, right? Because we
need to make sure our data, the customer's data is protected.
We could use OSAP in order to scan the parameter
and find out if there are data leakages from the application.
And we could use tools like prowling in order to make sure that the
data is stored securely. For instance,
if it's not encrypted at rest, we are going to find
things like that using prowler. And the last
part, we need to make sure that we know what happens
in our application. So if something does
happen, we need to know about it.
So we need to monitor and we need to log in order to find
these issues when they happen and in order
to help us first mitigate them, learn from
them, do the right research and close
them when we find them. So this is an important
part as well. And for instance, Paolo could find out if you
don't have cloud trader logs in your system in order to know
which resource. Access which resource.
All right, so let's talk a little Jit about
what we do at JIT. We try to leverage
all these tools and help you configure it
painlessly. So we took it to the next level.
We are recommending a
plan, a security plan for you based on your needs,
based on your applications, and based
on the right tools for each of these threats. And we
help you configure them and do it
for you with smooth and serverless
experience in order to make sure you have your application secured
without the hassle and need to configure everything
to understand what it does and how
to do it yourself. Right? So we
do it as code, which basically means that
you could configure it in any way you want.
You could say, I want to secure this, this and that,
and we are going to do it for you. You could automate it.
If you have different environments like dev
staging and production, you could modify
it as code, security as code for
your needs. And you could scan based on
events or schedules, and then you could get the
issues, and then we could help you actually understand what
these findings say and how to resolve
them. Right? It's not just scanning and finding
an issue, it's also what do I do when I do find
it? How do I mitigate it? How do I make my application
much more secure? All right, so now
our home alone is much more secure using the OASP
top ten for serverless, the open source tools,
and we feel much better. So thank you
very much for listening and these
are my details. You could find me right here. You can
scan the barcode and try the application out,
see if it works for you as well.
Thank you so much and have a nice day.