Hey all. Today we're going to be talking about progressive web apps and
more specifically how you can build one from the comfort of your own
home. Because. Because I guess that's the new norm, working from home,
sheltering in place whatever it is going on with you.
So my name is Michael Slotty and I am primarily a
web developer with specifically a background, mostly in
angular. But today's talk isn't an angular focus,
so don't worry about that. I'm actually going to try to cover concepts that are
framework agnostic and also include a little bit
here and there about some framework specific solutions to the concepts
and tooling that I discuss. I also happen
to be a developer program engineer focusing on web infrastructure.
So if you're interested in anything that I discuss today,
I recommend checking out the website that I work on. It's called
Web Dev, which the URL is just web
dev. Besides my love for angular,
I just love the web. I grew up on the web and I
remember what things were like in the
in our modern web environment. I love it.
It's compelling, it's exciting, and we have such incredible
tools to make amazing and compelling experiences for others.
I will also mention
that I do have a mass product. If you're not familiar with
what makes means, mass stands for means as a service.
Just making a hard pitch right there. It's memogram.com.
Check it out, hopefully you like it. Let me know what you think.
And I will finally mention that I behave made
a lot of mistakes, and I mean a lot. So I'm hoping that
maybe I can share some of the painful
things that I had to learn along the way. That way you can avoid making
the same mistakes as you build pwas yourself.
So what exactly is a PWA or
a progressive web app? And that's
not right. I would say it's not
this. What you're seeing here is definitely not what a progressive
web app application should be.
Pwas really are just web
applications that have amazing experiences. And the
reason for that is because they're fast. They're going to respond quickly,
whether that's loading or responding to a user's
interactions. They're integrated because they show up
on a user's home screen and they have access to things like sensors
and Bluetooth and can handle push notifications.
They are reliable because they're going to load instantly and
you're never going to see the dinosaur like we just saw.
And finally, they are engaging.
They feel like a natural app that deserves to be on a user's
device. With these immersive user experiences.
And if ever you doubt your ability to make a web
application like that, I'm telling you that you can. And if you
want, you can just repeat this simple mantra and that's you
spit hot fire at Chappelle jokes.
Anyway. So why pwas?
Well, users spend most of their time in native applications
rather than websites, and that's mostly because
apps end up being more predictable. They're available on a user's home screen,
so it's an easy one touch to get there. And push notifications allow
applications to reengage users back into the app. So maybe
if they haven't opened the app in a while, you can just send them a
notification and that will get them back into using your app or your web experience.
Another important thing is that space on the home
screen is really, really valuable.
Roughly 78% of the time a user spends
on their phone is within their favorite three application. So what
we're really asking for two, be an app on a user's home screen is
a commitment for time and space. And this is especially
important when an average user installs no new
apps a month while they are more likely
to visit websites.
So PWAs are essentially web
applications that provide a near native experience on mobile devices.
I ended up liking this quote, which I think came from the Google Developers website.
But building a high quality progressive web application has incredible
benefits, making it easy to delight your users,
grow engagement and increase conversions. When progressive web app app
criteria are met, Chrome will actually prompt users to add the PWA
to their own home screens. With tools like service workers,
you can send less data on the initial page load
and less data to complete transactions.
With push notifications, you're able to increase engagement,
allowing users to get updates as well as your ability
to re engage users to use your application.
And when users are typically averse to installing apps from the play
or App Store, and rather would visit a website like Facebook,
a lower barrier to entry for a website may be all you need to be
a citizen on their home screen. Native apps start
quickly, work in the background and they work offline.
They have access to all different types of sensors and there's different
versions for different platforms. Web applications
have one incredible benefit though iOS, that they have great reach
because it is one site for every platform and it can
be safe and it can handle a lot of these same features that I discussed.
But we need to introduce these into our web applications to make them feel more
native. So this is an experience
that I think really describes what a good
PWA would look like and this is the Twitter web application.
The application loads thus far. The UI looks almost identical
to that you'd find on the
Play store or App Store. It feels and looks native. I'm able
to attach pictures, it opens up the camera right away, and I'm able to
upload makes. And again, everything looks compelling.
And it's a really good example of what the PWA is
capable of. And a big thing like, one of the big
things that moved me to use the PWA Twitter application rather
than the native application is there was a period of time where I kept both
apps installed on my phone. And when I decided to go
to my installed apps, I looked at them side by side and I
saw how much space they were taking. And in both situations I
saw the number 200 and 5250. But I didn't look hard
enough at it at first. I looked at it
just maybe a few more seconds later, thinking, what's the difference?
And I realized that the Twitter native application, while installed
on my device, was taking roughly 250 megabytes
of storage versus the progressive web app location, which was
taking 250
big of a difference in size. Without any real compromises
in what the application was providing me. I moved to the web application
and I have not looked back.
So let's talk about a simple PWA that
we have. And it's a fairly simple.
It's designed to showcase popular movies. I have it running over
here, and you can see that if you clicked into a movie,
you can view some more information specific to the movie.
And a lot of things it kind of looks like what you might expect a
native Android app to look and feel like. And that's because
it follows material design guidelines for the aesthetic.
And there's a few things under the hood that I do to make the app
behave more quickly and more like a progressive web application.
And that's all fine and dandy,
but does it really qualify as PWA?
And that's a simple thing that we can check. We can test it against a
tool called Lighthouse. And so here's a video of
a lighthouse audit.
Tests are running and
nothing really there, at least not a positive score.
So in a lot of cases, this application isn't really doing
what we need. It's not getting any green check marks saying that, yes, this is
a PWA. And why is that the case?
Well, the first thing is the page isn't responding with the 200 status
code. If we're building a PWA, we might
want to use a service worker. That way this application will work even if
we're disconnected from the Internet. Secondly,
like I said, we'd want to use a service worker, but this web application as
it is now, isn't even registering a service worker that will tell
the browser what pages to load. So our service worker is really
the technology that enables our apps to use many of
the features of Pwas, one of them being
offline. But also with the service worker
we're able to actually add the web app onto a user's
home screen and handle push notifications.
Without the web app manifest file, it doesn't really meet
the requirements for installability. So browsers can actually proactively
prompt users to add their web application to the user's home
screen, which leads to higher engagement.
It's not configured for a custom splash screen, and this is one of those things
that can be set in the web app manifest file. But when you
open Twitter or Facebook on your phone, you end up seeing the Twitter or
Facebook load two go for a quick second while the app loads in.
We can do that with web applications as well. There's other things
about setting the address bar, theme, color,
ensuring that the website still works with JavaScript disabled.
And that last one is actually really important in my opinion. I remember a time
when I worked at a webshop and we were doing a lot
of great work on a client's website, but no
matter what we did, the client repeatedly told us
that the site that we were working on and hosting for them
would not work on their iPhone and legit. We had no idea why.
I will say we were all Android users, so we didn't have that
much experience with iOS. So my boss decided
to do the most reasonable thing, and that was to bias all iPod
touches. We all got iPod touches, not iPhones,
but we weren't able to replicate the issue until one day we actually met with
the client in person. We just looked at her phone to discover she
kept JavaScript disabled on her phone,
and we ended up spending a lot of time and effort trying to troubleshoot
this when we didn't necessarily do anything wrong.
The user didn't do anything wrong too. It's their decision to have JavaScript
disabled, but we could have accounted
for that and we could have provided some sort of experience if JavaScript was disabled,
might not be the full experience, it might just be a warning that hey,
JavaScript is disabled, you might not get the full experience that you expect.
But because we didn't do anything to account for that, the user didn't know what
was wrong with the site. And if you're doing this out in the wild,
they might abandon your site.
As it sounds right now, this application is not fast, it's not integrated,
it's not reliable, and it's not engaging. So one
thing I actually mentioned a little bit earlier was lighthouse. And for those of
you who don't know what Lighthouse is, it's an open source and automated tool
for improving the quality of web pages. You can run it against any
web page, whether it's public or it requires authentication,
and it has audits for things like performance, accessibility,
and whether an application is a PWA and
more. It definitely handles more than that. So you can
actually run lighthouse straight from inside of the chrome devtools.
You can run it as an extension that's available for Chrome and I believe there
iOS a version of this extension available for firefox
and it exists as a NPM module that you can
install and use in your build processes or just as
a command line tool.
So let's make this application better.
And one thing that we really want to do is we want to make sure
that this application is reliable. When something's reliable,
that means there really shouldn't be any surprises like
a chromosaur or dinosaur popping in when a user iOS visiting your
application. So when we talk about being reliable,
when the user launches the web application from the home
screen, we can use service workers to improve this
and what the service worker is going to do. It's going two enable a PWA
to load instantly, regardless of what the network state is. The service
worker is written in javascript and it's kind of like a client side proxy
and puts you in control of things like the cache and
how to respond to resource requests, whether that's post get requests,
makes, et cetera. And so by pre caching key assets and
resources, we can eliminate the dependence of the network,
ensuring that our applications are instantaneous and
reliable.
An example of how that could work is what we have here, and this
is a cache first example, which is ideal if you're building an offline first
experience. So this is how you'd handle a majority of requests. The page
would make the request that would go through the service worker. The service worker
would check the cache. If the resource doesn't exist in the cache,
it'll then go to the network, make the network request,
return it to the page, while also caching that
network request for next time. And there's other strategies
that you can use to implement with your service worker. But introducing
a service worker to your site can be super, super easy.
If you use angular, there's an angular schematic that
you can install and apply to your project with just the command Ng add.
At angular PWA, it ends up adding the
angular service worker and configuring the build to include the service worker.
And there's a lot of other things it'll do to get your application PWA
compliant, but it's a really simple,
easy to do step just from the get go for you.
Another thing is if you use create react app to create react
applications, since 2017, it has included
service worker and PWA support from out the box.
You haven't had to do any configuration or any work to have that.
And finally, also since 2017, the view
CLI has made it easy for you to enable service workers with
the view create command. What you would want to do is manually
select features, and then you would just
enable PWA support and
we can let the default settings for the rest of that stuff work.
Now, customizing configuring your service
worker is something you're going to need to do regardless of what framework you end
up using. And while the platforms can guide
you with what you should and shouldn't do, they can't know everything that you need.
So taking view, for example, you can modify aspects of the service worker by
configuring a PWA property of either your view
config file or a view field inside of the package JSOn.
But something cool with view and react is that the
tooling used to generate the service worker is built on top of a library
called workbox. So workbox
is a library that bakes in a set of best practices
and removes the boilerplate that every developer has to write. When working with service
workers, and it's available on NPM, I invite
you to go tinker with it and take a look at it. And on
web dev we actually host an article about workbox. It's written
by Jeff Posnik. He's part of the Google web
developer relations team and specifically works on workbox
itself. So you can find the article here. I definitely recommend
giving it a read if you want to get a better insight into how workbox
works. But with the service worker, our site
is now definitely reliable. It's going to work offline because we're caching
the key resources and assets in order for the site to work. And it's going
to be a bit faster because with those assets and resources
cached, it doesn't necessarily need to go to the network and wait for server
responses in order to process the
requests. So we're faster,
but we want to be even faster than that. And that's important because the average
load time of mobile sites is roughly 19 seconds on
3g connections. 53% of users will abandon the site
if it takes longer than 3 seconds to load. And once it's loaded,
users expect these sites to be fast. They don't want janky
scrolling or these slow to respond interfaces.
People on average expect the site to load within like 2
seconds, and almost half of people say that waiting on
a page to load is what they dislike the most when
browsing the web on their mobile devices.
Luckily, with their service worker that we configured in the previous section,
we've addressed a lot of these concerns. However, we can still optimize this
initial load, parse, compute and rendering of our web applications,
and that comes with this massive concern that we have.
And that's the cost of the Javascript we're actually running now.
I'm kind of stealing this slide from a friend and an amazing propagandist
for the web who works on the Chrome team adiosmani.
So keep in mind, if we want to be fast at
JavaScript, it has to be downloaded, parsed,
compiled and executed quickly. But not all
bytes weigh the same. A 200 kb JavaScript file
has a very different set of costs than a 200 kilobyte JPEG file,
and this is outside of the raw network transmission times. For both sets of bytes
they might take the same amount of time to download, but when it comes
to processing, we're dealing with very different costs.
A JPEG image may need to be decoded,
rasterized and painted onto the screen, versus a JavaScript bundle that
needs to be downloaded, parsed, compiled, executed. And there's
actually a number of other steps that an engine needs to complete.
Just be aware the costs are not equivalent, and by
remembering that the JavaScript being sent down the wire has two be
computed and rendered out for our spas for single page applications.
Pwas progressive web app this takes time,
but we can actually remove some of this burden off of a user and
these devices and onto our server with server
side rendering. Now luckily, all the major frameworks
have pretty good support for SSR,
and as a front end developer who doesn't want to write a full backend
solution, some of these solutions are really really good.
And there's non first party solutions that streamline the
daunting task of configuring your own SSR environments.
In the react world you have next js, and in
view you have nuxtjs. But again,
assuming you want to take a framework agnostic solution,
you can actually use puppeteer. Puppeteer is a node
library which provides a high level API to control chrome or
chromium over the devtools protocol.
Puppeteer runs headless by default, but can be configured to run
full non headless chrome or chromium. And you can do a lot like generate
screenshots of pages or pdfs. You can run tests in
Chrome or crawl a single page application. And most
importantly, you can use it to generate pre rendered content, I. E server
side rendering lines, workbox. You can find puppeteer
on NPM and this is actually a really simple
implementation of creating a SSR
server with puppeteer. So now
we've built a site that is both reliable and fast,
but we want our application to now be engaging and interactive.
It should feel like a natural app on the device with
an immersive user experience. And Pwas are installable.
They live on a user's home screen without the need of an app or play
store. They offer these immersive full screen experiences with
the help of a web app manifest file, and can
even reengage users with push notifications. Now the web
app manifest allows you to control how your app appears and how
it's launched. You can specify things from home screen icons,
the page to load when an app is launched, and even whether or not
to show that it's running inside of chrome.
And it's actually really easy to do. There's a great
site like Appmanifest, firebaseapp.com,
and I'll actually do this right here for you guys to
see. So here I can just type in the full name of the
application, which I will just call popular movies,
and we can put in the short name, which is the name that will end
up appearing if the full name is too long to show up
the theme color iOS kind of like that color you would see in the status
bar or whatever. And as I'm setting the colors, you can
kind of see the colors changing here, and the background color is the
color of the splash screen. So when the user first opens up the application,
the screen will turn into whatever color this is. I'll just choose
plaque black display mode.
We're going two use full screen mode orientation.
We'll lock it into portrait, though you can allow for
any orientation or lock into landscape.
And finally, I'm just going to click on icon and
I am going to choose this app icon here,
open it, generate this up.
Oh no. Well, this might have been broken
recently, but I am sure this will be up
and running again. I will probably have to pass this information on anyway,
you can generate this nice and easy.
Might be broken for the time being. Hopefully it'll be fixed by the time you
guys are seeing this. Until then, check out this URL to tinker
with the tool. It's a great resource, and once
you have downloaded the zip and gotten the files you need,
there's actually just really little work you need to do. The first thing you need
to do is you need to move the images or the resize
icons into whatever folder that you're storing
your image assets in. And then finally you're just
going to set these two lines here. The first one is manifest,
which is going to point to the manifest JSOn generated, which is going to dictate
how the app experience is going to be. And secondly, the theme color,
which is the cooler of the status bar in chrome or the Chrome bar omnibox
on mobile devices.
With that in mind, with the manifest in place, our app can now
live like a native application on a user's screen. The application
iOS fast integrated, reliable and engaging.
So here is the application with all these things in place,
we're going to run the lighthouse test and we're going to see how this goes.
So I'm going to cross my fingers by kind of know how this
is going to work out.
Well, there we
behave it. That's a lot of green. The application
is doing everything it needs to. We have that green Chuck mark
knowing that our application is a PWA. If you guys want
to check out the application, test it. Check the source code. You can find it
at PWA, O-T-A dev.
If you want to look over the slide deck, you can find it at building
PWA camel casing. It's case sensitive,
so be careful with that. And finally, if you can take anything away
from this talk, I will say no matter how much fun
or how much we all love the chromosome, or hopefully the chromosaur can go the
way of the dinosaur which iOS makes extinct.
Again, thank you. You can find me on the web, on Devto,
LinkedIn, GitHub and Twitter with just my name, Michael Slotty
and Adios.