Hey, everyone, thanks very much for having me. This is the first time
I've been invited to comfort into Python and, well,
yeah, it's great to be here. I'm going to talk to you about how you
can build animated interactive reports and dashboards
within streamlit using the technology that
we created, ipyvizzu,
integrated into the app platform,
streamlit. So first, I'm going to give you a quick overview
about Vizzu and the technology that we built. Then about
the open source package that we created for data scientists
called IPy Vizzu, and then about the bi directional
component and its use that a senior data scientist
from Streamlit called Zachary Blackwood created
for us. We are really grateful for Zachary for
investing so much into this, and we think that it's a great
step forward and that this integration has some
superb implications and a lot of potential.
Actually, this is an important moment for us because this is the first time
we talk about this integration publicly. There is still some
work to do, but it has such a huge potential that we
didn't want to wait any longer and get you
involved. And we're actually actively looking for people
who want to contribute to the success of this by using
the tool, by giving us feedback, creating examples,
or by even helping us implement new features. So if you're
that kind of person, we'd be welcome you very happily
on board. There's a repo with all the necessary links and
materials you would need to follow along and to start experimenting with
what we built. You can find it at bit Lyvizuf
42. So without further ado, let's get started.
Okay, so if you follow the link, you will end up in this
repo folder. And yeah,
friendly welcome here. And as I said, you have all the necessary lines
that you will need to follow along. And there's also the notebooks
folder, where you will find a couple of notebooks that help
you get acquainted with Ipy Vizzu.
And also there are a couple that I just prepared for you
to just play around with and have
a sense of how this tool works. Basically, I come
from a company called Vizzu, and what we created there is
an animated charting engine that building all
the different kinds of charts using the same logic.
And because of this, it can morph between the
charts that are expressed on its interface. So basically we have
a generic chart morpher,
and that's something very
unique. As you can see, this is just an animation right now within the Jupyter
notebook. So how our technology evolved.
We have the core engine that was developed
in C Plus plus. We used it already a couple of years back in
house. We built stories and interactives with it. And then in September
2021, we released our first open source product, a JavaScript charting
library for JavaScript developers. We're using WebAssembly to
compile the library so the engine in the browser,
and we just built a JavaScript API for that,
and it helped developers. And then last
year we turned our attention to data scientists and we released
ipyvizzu, which is an extension,
an opensource extension for Jupyter notebook and similar computational notebooks.
And it enabled people like, I assume yourself
to build animated charts and data stories in
notebooks using Python. And then last July,
actually on Europython, we announced ipyvizzu
Story, which is a presentation extension of
ipyvizzu that enables you to build, present and share
interactive animated presentations within Jupyter
notebook. We already have a ton of integrations. This open
source approach really helps us to make our
technology embeddable. As you can see, it's available in
many different notebooks and then other platforms such
as panel or it's already pyscript,
and then vehicles like mode and obviously streamlit that we're going
to talk to you about. There's actually a long list on our
website. So if you actually go to
ipyvizzu.com and go to the environments tab,
then you can see all these ids, notebooks,
platforms and the lines where you can use our technology.
So going down to how it works,
basically, ifi Vizzu has only one method,
the animate method, which has three
parameters. The data that you add on the chart,
the configuration of the charts, and the styling of the charts that you need to
add. And then there are the optional animation
options that determine how to animate
from one stick to the other. And basically, if you call the animate method
once with the right settings, then you will draw one chart.
If you call it again, then ipyvizzu will
automatically morph the original chart, the first chart to
the second one, and that's it.
So let's see an example that I'm going
to show you on the Titanic data set. So it's a titanic csv,
and we're using pandas to
read the csv to a data frame. And then we add the data frame
to the iPad chart. This is just a
vanilla Jupyter notebook. I just hacked the CSS a little bit so that
we are going to have the
result of the
output of a cell next to the cell itself. So we can see the code
and the output side by side. So, yeah, this is the Titanic data set.
And I'm going to building the first chart. I'm going
to say how wide and high it should be.
I add the data to it. I call the animate method,
and then I configure the chart by adding the count,
which is lines, a value that we added to the data set. That's one
for each passenger to the x axis and
then the sex of the passengers y axis.
And we also add the count to the label channel and we add a title
to the chart. So if I run this cell, I'm going to draw a
simple bar chart where I have the male and the
female passengers and the number of them represented by
the width of the bars, but it's also written on it. So x
and y are access. And label is a channel that you can attach data
series to, such as count,
sex. And next, in the next phase, I'm going
to just add the survived category to
the x axis and also to the color channel. That is
what determines whether the passengers survived
the Titanic tragedy or not. And if I do that,
then as you can see, these bars has
been split and they become stack bars,
where we can see the number of people for
each sex who died and who survived the crash.
And, yeah, I have a ton of other
options if I call the animate method over and over again.
So let's first just remove the
survived category from the x axis
and add it to the y axis.
I'm adding it to the y axis and I removed it from the x axis.
As you can see, ipvisor remembers everything from the previous phase,
so I only need to determine what to change.
And here, instead of the stack bar
chart, I ended up having a grouped bar chart. So now
I can see the numbers side by side.
And there are a couple of other configuration options. I can change
the geometry so the geometric elements used to represent data,
like circle, for example.
And then I can add the same
number that's on the label and that's on the vertical position
on the markers to the
size of the markers. So now
the circles have different size, and I can even change the coordinate system to
polar instead of euclidean. So now it's
getting into this polar coordinate system. There are a
couple of other configuration options,
like the alignment, the sorting. You can
add a title, as you saw, you can split the values.
And we actually encourage you to just
play with it. It has so much freedom.
And whatever you do, iPadiza will
take care of animating to the new state. So it's really easy
to use, or at least that's what we're working towards.
If you have any comments on why you think it or how you
think it should be easier to use our tool,
then please let us know. But that's the case.
We have access and channels and you can just add and remove
data series on those. To give you another
example, before turning our attention to
the integrated version of iPad streamlit to have
a better understanding of how this thing works. So here's
another example. It uses data about shows
much money, how much revenue different music formats generated
over the years. Let me just clear the output
of the cells and run this notebook
from the start so that clean we
are going to use presets here.
So as you saw in the previous notebook,
we just added data series to access and channels.
And now we're going to use a preset and we are going to determine
that. What we want to build is a bar chart.
We found that it's easier actually for the users to
use iPad visit. This way we have a ton of
presets that you can also find on our site.
If you go to ipivisit.com, you'll end up in our documentation site
and then within the examples, you can find a preset. As you
can see, we have plenty of those. And if you click on any
of the presets or thumbnails for that preset,
you'll end up checking out the code
of that specific preset that you clicked on.
And you can play it here, you can copy
the code and use it right away in
your notebook, and you can even copy
the whole thing and start fiddling with it.
So right now, we built this bar chart here.
There are a couple of issues, so I don't really like that all the bars
have the same color. And actually the numbers here are really huge.
So what I'm going to do is, first of all, I'm going to
use instead a group bar chart where I say that this
is data is grouped by the same category,
the format that's on
the y axis. So now each bar has a different
color because that's how group bar charts look like.
And I'm going to play and fiddle a little bit with the styling.
I'm going to add a new color palette. So I'm just listing
color codes here and I basically assign it to the different categories.
I'll change the number format, how many digits I
want, and I'm going to use
a number scale. This is a fairly new development, so I have to add it
to the x and the y axis. Now we're going to make it
easier for you later on. So what happens is
that we have a different color scheme right now and we have
the US short scale and the numbers are
shorter and easier to read. And now I'm
going to use yet another preset, the splitted column
chart, and also fill with the styling
a little bit. And here's just yet another transformation
happening automatically where I can see
how the revenue changed over time
from these music formats side by side. And also
you can add events to override
certain behaviors. So for example, I don't like that all
the years are written here next to the x axis.
And there's this short event that will
basically enable only every
fifth year or like year that's divisible by five
to be drawn the number for it. So I run the cell
and if I touch the chart then boom,
all the unnecessary years have gone.
And so there are a couple of other examples
here to go to stream graph for example.
Then to switch on the splitting feature, which is
really nice. Again, it's great for stack charts
to see them, the component side by side.
Then I'm going to just use the data
filter option, which is also really great when you have animation.
So we're going to just zoom into vinyl
and streaming as you can see.
And yeah, since all the transition is
animated, it's really like zooming in and everybody understands what's
going on, so you don't have to explain what we're looking at.
And in the next phase I'm just going to switch off the filter and the
splitting as well. So I'm going to get back to the
stream graph. This is the phase that my wife calls
when the elephants kiss. Now you know why.
And yeah, yet another preset is the
line chart, which enables us to compare
the revenue from these formats side by side. So basically
these were the only examples that I want to just show you with notebooks,
at least from ipyvizzu. And as I
said, they are here in the repo folder within the notebooks. This was
number one and number. And the
third one is an example of IPY. Visit story there's
like a longer code here. I'm not
going to go into more detail, but basically that was the first
implementation of our technology when we enabled
the use of interactive animations. And here you
basically set your views and yeah, I'm just using my buttons
on my keyboard and you cannot see it. Sorry about that. But basically you have
these buttons beneath the chart
that you can use, but you can also use a clicker or
your keyboard, just like I did initially to move
back and forth. And basically it means that you can have a lines
presentation of your findings. This is again just
a great example of zooming into certain areas and
to grouping and rearranging certain elements to
show how they changed over time while making
everyone crystal clear what's going on and not having to iterate
all over again, like what we're looking at.
So yeah, this is iPad as a story. There's an example of that in
the repo. Take a look at it if you're interested.
So that was the part of
IPiV running in notebooks and other platforms.
And now let's focus on streamlit first.
Basically, this is the
streamlit Vizzu repository is something that
we built together with Zachary. If you
go and visit it in the readme, there's like
a short description of what this is. This is the bi
directional component that Zachary built, the installation instructions.
As you can see, it's available on PiP. By the way, iPad is an
iPad story as well. And here's documentation
written also by Zachary. Great job, Zachary. Thank you
very much for that. And you can just
check out how to get started with stream with
Vizzu. There is a sample code that we're going to show you anyway.
But if you go to this repo, then you're
in good hands and
that's the best place to start. So basically, this is the
first app that I'm going to show you. Let me quickly
bring up. Yeah, so this is the app on
the right side and the code for that on the left side.
As you can see, we imported pandas and streamlit.
And then there's the streamlit visual component from
which we are going to use config data and visual chart. It's almost the
same as it is with ipyvizzu. And so we
create a Vizzu chart. We build a very
simple data frame. We add the data.
So we create the data object. We add
the data frame to the data object. We first call chart
animate data that just sets up an empty chart. And then we
add some configuration to IpI Vizzu
to tell how to display the data. And initially it's going to be that
the a series. So the XYZ is
on the x axis and then the b series, which is lines one,
two, three is on the b axis. And there's the title. Look at my
plot. So this is what we're looking at. X, y and z. And one,
two, three. Here is an interactive element
from streamlit, a checkbox called swap.
And if it's true, so if I click on the
checkbox, then notice that the configuration of
the chart changes. So now the y axis,
we're going to have the series a, and the axis is going to have
the series b. It's basically just. And the title is going to change.
So it's just swapping the configuration. And as
you can see, ivz automatically does
this and changes the configuration of
the chart. And the other thing that it does,
and that's why it's bi directional, is that if you click on
any of the markers, for example, it reads some data and
it says that the value of the click bar is two.
And here's the code for that. So basically, if the data
is not known and marker in data,
the data is what basically we read from
the chart. If it's not known, then it just writes here the value of
the click bar, and it reads the values from
the b series or array and
writes it out right beneath the chart. So it's
a very simple, great example built by
Zachary, which shows how you can manipulate the
configuration of the chart using the interactive elements from streamlit,
and also do something with the data that
comes out of the interactive chart.
So this app actually have more pages?
We have five altogether. We're going to check out all five
of these. The last one is pretty complicated, so I'm not going to go into
more details, but it's always there for you to explore.
And the second one. So this is again, the data
from about the revenue generated music format.
I used group bar chart. As you can see, I actually,
in the code, used the group bar chart
preset, which is really
easy to use. I added styling as well.
So it's basically the same thing that we used
within ifi vizzu. And the only difference is that
I have here a slider that tells you to pick a
year. And if you change the year, you can either do it
by your mouse, or again, you can change to whatever
you want, or you can move year by year
from one year to the other. For example, this is
the early 90s, where CD was really
high. But if we go backwards one by one, we can
see that actually it was around 1990.
In 1990, cassette was still raging. And then in
1991, CD became the most popular or music
format, or at least the one that generated the most revenue.
And, yeah, it's just an easy interaction.
Again, basically, the upper part of the code is pretty much
the same. There's just one thing here, the chart feature tooltip is
set to true, it results that there is this
tooltip that appears on top of the markers if
you hover your mouse over them,
which is great to read, values that might not be
visible. In this case, I think all the data is
visible, but there can be more complex cases, obviously.
Yeah. And that's about it.
The racing bar charts were so
popular a couple of years ago. I think it's a little bit
better that you have the chance to control them.
And it's just, again, a simple example. Okay, third example,
again, built by Zachary. It's a drill down example.
It's a little more complicated, but not the data part, because this
is the whole of the data frame that you can see here, but the interaction
part, it's actually, I'm just going to set
it back to the original state. So this is
how it's set. Originally, we have three series,
a, b and c. Two of them are categories a and c,
and b is a number. So what we have
here is you
call the chart get event, the marker
categories a. So basically it reads what,
what category has been clicked on
from the values within a. And then
it basically applies a filter here so
that it only includes the
records where the category
of a equals the one that you clicked on.
And it also changes the configuration. So originally it's the
a on the x axis and the b on the y axis, but then
it changes to the c being on the x axis. And while
actually b stays on the y axis. This is actually unnecessary
since it remains the same. And so
it means that, again, this is a really short
code, as you can see, like 45
lines. But here you have an interactive drill down functionality
that if you click on any of the markers,
it will just zoom in on that marker
and drills down automatically. And if you click anywhere
else, then it will move back to the
original state. I think it's a great example, and again,
very simple to use and to implement.
We actually did a very popular piece in one of
the local online newspapers where you could zoom into a data set,
seeing the big arrangements
that a company made or big agreements,
and see more details about it. But there are plenty of
examples when you've been drilling down, it makes sense. And this
is a very intuitive way for any business user to drill
down and check for more details. All right.
The fourth example is actually one
of the explorers that I wanted to show you.
I'm going to also show you the code. So the title of the talk
was let them explore. And basically, I think this
is the strongest benefit
of Vizzu Streamlit. So ipizu
being used in streamlit, that now
you can build these explorers using
this technology, which enables basic business users
to just explore, maybe even complex
data sets on their own. Always understanding
where they are, always keeping track of the context,
but still have a lot of different opportunities
for exploration and for applying their business expertise
in finding solutions and finding
new insights. So this is actually a
very simple data set that contains four
products. Sales data, about four products.
How many sales were there? How many units were sold? This is what
we see right now, let's say just last year.
And we can also see
on the chart a couple of interactive
elements. And what we can do here is, for example, switch from
the number of sales to the revenue
that's been generated. We can order the items
alphabetically or by value,
just with the click of a button. We can even
filter categories like this
and whatever vanishes will vanish in an animated sense.
So it's always straightforward what happened?
What changed. We can also check
the data by region or both by region
and product. Now we have four regions,
west southeast, and we can actually just aggregate
the data by region and see
it without the product itself. But still,
I can just remove the accessories. And now I have information
about the revenue generated from these three products
in these
four regions. And I can actually switch
polar coordinates, which in this setting might
not be that crucially important,
but still, it's an opportunity you have there. I think actually
these polar charts work better on mobile because they take up less space.
And yeah, you can actually use stream as
interactive elements to change the styling of the
chart. So you can set the background color, for example,
to a really ugly color.
Luckily you can also change it back quite
easily. You can even write here
code. It looks better with the
original color. Yeah, here we go. But there
are a plethora of different styling options and you can use any
of those. So what happens here code wise is, again,
you read the data, you create the chart, you set
the toolkit to true, and now you have list of
items that you add to a multi select
control, that here you have
five columns where you add radio buttons and color picker.
And basically you just add the options there. These are,
I think, very straightforward to anyone who actually used film it
at any point in time. You set the style
here so that it uses the background color red from
this color picker. I guess the filter
might be the most complicated one, where you need to join the
items here from the products list. And then
the title is also a bit complicated, so it always reflects,
for example, if I remove the handbags from this
chart, then it will vanish from the title as well.
So it's another way of helping the user
always keep track of what they're looking at.
And so the most important part is this if,
else if and else part where basically if the comfort buy
is by product, then let's
show it on the cartesian
coordinate system because it's easier to follow. So then the
product is on the y axis. So shoes and gloves and the measure,
which is either the revenue or the sales, is on the
x axis. It's pretty straightforward and there's nothing on the
color. If the compromise is set to
region, then we
will have the region on the x axis.
West, south, northeast, we have color
data also there. It's also region and measure revenue
or sales independently. So basically whatever you select
is on the y axis. And when
you have both, which is the else option here, then product
is on the y axis, the measure,
and the region is on the x axis and
the region is still on the color. That's why
we get to these stacked bar charts where
the measure and the regions are on the same axis. That's why
it's stacked. And now we build
this config object with all the parameters that
has been set before. You can actually set some opportunities
independently. So if chords are set to color,
then you just add more attributes
to this object coordinate system
and sorting. And then basically you call
this one single line where you call the
animate method, you add the data filter
with the filter that set so far the config. With the config,
the style that's basically just the background color and even
you set a delay to 0.1, you can set
it to zero. Basically it helps
you to be the chart to be more reactive. By default,
the delay is like 1 second. So whenever anything changes, the chart
would only react after a second. And in this interactive setup, it's better
to make delay as short as possible. So this
already belongs to the animation options.
That's about it. If you click on this is again
an example of the bi directional component. If you click on any of
the markers, you have the details about the positions,
about the coordinates, about the market that you clicked, if there's any,
and the value of that marker, and there's even an id
to it. So it's really easy to
get data out of your ifi visual charts and
reuse them within an app. We're actually really looking forward
to have some examples when this capability and
the last app that I wanted to show you is a more complicated explorer.
The code is there, but I don't think it would be a good idea to
go through it in much detail right now.
I'm just going to show you how the explorer works. It again uses the music
history data. I thought it's easier for you to have the
same data set in three different examples. And here
you have two lines. So like it's
a slider with two interactive elements,
which helps you set the years that are being shown
as you can, I'm sure. Imagine it utilizes the
filter option. You can actually adjust the revenue
for inflation or change to volume,
just like with the sales data. And as you can see, it shows a completely
different picture. We use the sidebar now, not only
interactive element on the chart, you can add all the formats that
are in the data set. You can split
the values. You can switch between column chart and streamlit
graph. You can stack
things by year or by format.
So you can even.
Yeah, and now you're going to end up having bar
chart. You can sort these by value.
There are plenty of different opportunities for anyone
actually being really interested, and you can narrow this
down and focus on a smarter period or
just a single year. Lines, basically what you
were also able to do with
the original slider, but you can
also switch between what is being shown and. Yeah, so for
example, what was there with the story
within the notebook that I showed you?
Yeah, the area chart doesn't work very well with a
single year.
So, for example, if I leave
only lines and the
other one,
so we
can get to the
same chart that we saw before and do the same transitions
that we did in the notebook splitting
off. Okay, so basically you're free
to play with it. As you could see, there were some minor
issues with some of the transitions.
You can sometimes, rarely have
these kind of issues. I was actually quite unlucky to click
these buttons in this order, but that's the beauty of
doing a live demo of your technology, I guess.
Okay, so that's about it. I hope you're still
with me. And this is what I wanted to show you.
Please visit the repository if you want to learn
more. As I said, there are a lot of things,
links, useful links for the apps, for the source code
of the app, for the documentation that's
listed here. And so there are two things I really want
to ask you. First one is to spend two, three minutes of your time and
fill out a short Google form that I prepared for.
Just. I would love to know you better.
What do you do, what you think about this presentation,
what you think about this integration of our tool into streamlit?
What kind of ideas you would have? What do you need us
to improve in order to use it? This is all
very much interesting, but still, I can promise you that it wouldn't
take more than two, three minutes of your time. And if you want to
join our community, you'd be, as I said in
the beginning, very welcome. We have a slack workspace.
Here's the link. Just come and join us and
just test our tool or contribute
to it. Both of them are very fine.
So thanks again for your time and again for the invitation from
the comfort of T team. It's been a pleasure,
and I'm looking forward to your questions either
on Discord or on the conference. Discord or
yeah, on Slack, in email at any social network you
can track us down. Thank you very much.