Hello everybody, my name is Luca Mardente. I'm a principal engineer
at Cisco Systems and today I will be presenting Sveltos and
specifically how Sveltos can help platform admin
to onboard tenant admins and allow each
tenant admin to deploy add ons and application
in a subset of managed Kubernetes clusters.
We all know that kubernetes by itself is not a complete solution,
that when you build to build those production clusters
you have to deploy around cell applications. And if you're managing
a fleet of Kubernetes clusters,
managing around cell application is not a critical problem.
So Zveltos wants to help those and the idea behind Sveltos
is simple. Sveltos runs in the management cluster and
from the management clusters a fleet of managed Kubernetes
clusters can be asked and Sveltos
can be easily told what to do.
Essentially select a set of managed
Kubernetes clusters using a Kubernetes selector and
list the advance or application that needs to be deployed and Sveltos
will take care of the rest. So we
have a management cluster where Sveltos is running and we
have a bunch of managed
Kubernetes clusters. Sveltos has built in support
for cluster API, meaning that every clusters which is powered by
cluster API is automatically discovered by Sveltos,
but any other cluster which can
be easily registered to be managed by Sveltos. For instance in this case we
have GK cluster or Siva clusters or
rancher cluster or regiment cluster which are all registered with Sveltos.
And at this point pretty much Sveltos can manage a launch
and application from the management cluster onto
these managed clusters. The only requirement of Sveltos is that there
is a network connectivity between the management cluster in
each one of those managed clusters. Here cluster profile
is the main CRD that is used to instruct Sveltoscore
to do and it has in the spec section like four
main fields. The first field is the cluster selector.
The cluster selector is just a pure Kubernetes label
selector and it selects a subset of
managed Kubernetes cluster. In this case it's selecting all the clusters which
have the label environment set to Fe
stands for functional medication. So first
thing is select a set of clusters and then tell Sveltos
what to do. In this case, what we are telling Zveltos we have an n
charts where section where we can list one or more n charts.
In those case we are asking Zveltos to deploy Caverno version 2.6.0
in every cluster that it's matching the cluster selector EMV
equals Fe. Then there is a customization those where
you can say you can list all your sources
where you have customization file. In this case too much, you have a git repo
containing a customization
files in the path hello world and
what Sventos will do, we'll take all those files, we'll done the customization
SDK and then we'll deploy the output in
the Eng namespace in every cluster matching
the cluster selector. And finally there is a policy wrap section
where you can reference one or
more config maps and or secrets. And the config
map and secrets can contain one or more Kubernetes
resources. In this case I have an example where
there is a config map which is in the default namespace called
Contour gateway which contains a gateway class,
a namespace and a gateway. So if there is a cluster profile
referencing this config map in every cluster
matching the cluster profile, Sveltos will take the content of this
config map so the gateway class, the namespace and gateway
and will deploy those resources in every cluster matching the cluster
provide and you can put in the config
map bot Yaml or JSon.
This essentially a summary of
how Zeltos works. We have a management cluster
where Veltos is running and we have two clusters which
are powered using cluster API.
So we apply in the management cluster a
clusters profile that says select every cluster matching
the labels environment project stands for production and
deploy Caverno version 2.5.0 in every
such cluster. So if we add the label environment
production on the first workflow cluster,
Zveltos will detect that this workflow cluster is a match for this
cluster profile and will take all the
listed add ons and applications and deploy those one. In this case we
only have cavernos as well as will deploy Caverno in those workflow
cluster. Likewise, if we add the label
environment production on the second cluster,
Veltos Financial logic will react
by detecting that this cluster is now a match for this cluster profile and
it will deploy Caverno in this cluster as well.
What differentiates Veltos from all the other tools which
are available today to manage add ons and applications
in a fleet of Kubernetes clusters? Well,
Speltos allows you to express helm
charts and Royam and JSON as template and
instantiate those templates using information which is present
in management in resources which are present
in the management cluster. For instance, in this case we are
asking Sveltos to deploy calico
in every cluster in every production cluster, but those value
section of those helm chart is expressed as a template and
it's referring the cluster. So what Sveltos will do before
we'll find every cluster matching this clusters selector and for
every cluster we'll take the clusters instance which is
present in the management cluster and represents the cluster where Sveltos
is about to deploy this calico.
And we'll take this spec clusters network podcaster
block section of this resource which again is present in the management cluster.
We'll instantiate this value those template
using the information found in the resource present in the management
cluster. And after this instantiation we'll go ahead and deploy
the resources. By default, Veltos is access to
a set of resources that represents the cluster.
If you're familiar with cluster API, the cluster API
cluster instance representing the cluster, the infrastructure provider, the Kubeadm
control plane or this Veltos cluster instance which represents a
cluster which a GK cluster for instance which has been registered to be
managed by Sveltos. But Sveltos can be instructed
to fetch any resource present in the management cluster and
use its content to instantiate those templates.
In this case, for instance, mentors is being
instructed to fetch a secret which is present
in the management cluster which is in the default namespace and code scalar
and instantiate the content of the content
map which expresses a template using information which
is present in the secret. Here. You just have to give
like Sveltos the right permission to fetch those type
of resources if you need like extra resources.
But as Veltos says they have built at those point like to fetch anything.
Now what
if we are a platform admin and we want to onboard a bunch
of tenants? One approach is to give
every tenant a subset of clusters.
So what you can do in this case is that as a platform admins you
can create cluster profile in the management cluster. Those cluster
profile can match any cluster in any namespace,
but then you can import a tenant
by giving every tenant its own namespace. And Sveltos
has another CRD which is called profile the
profile. It's exactly same as a cluster profile.
It has a cluster selector where
you can select clusters where to deploy the add
ons and applications and then it has an answered section, a customization
of sections and a policy intersections. The only difference
between a cluster profile and cluster that a
cluster profile is cluster wide. So I can manage any clusters
in namespace. A profile is a namespace resources,
so I can only match clusters which are
in the same namespace where the profile is defined.
So what happens in this case is that again you
are the platform admin and the platform admin can create cluster
profiles and the advance and applications listed
in those cluster profiles can be deployed like in any cluster,
in any managed cluster because a cluster profile can match any clusters
in any namespace. But then you onboard tenants by giving every tenant his
own namespace. So in this case the tenant one has been given like
the tenant one namespace, those tenant two has been given the tenant two namespace.
So the tenant one at this point can put like his own profile configuration
and his own profile configuration is only going to be
deployed on clusters which are defined in
the same namespace. In this case the clusters which manage
cluster with those blue background, the tenant two namespace
can put the tenant to admin can put its own configuration and
it's going to create like its own profile configuration in the namespace
that has been assigned to tenant two. And this provide configuration
put by the tenant to admins is only going to affect cluster
which are in the same namespace. In this case those tenant, the managed
cluster with the yellow background. So what happens is every name,
every tenant can put his own configuration
listing which advance an application is to be deployed,
but two tenants do not interfere
with each other. The configuration by set by tenant
is only going to be deployed in clusters which have
been assigned by the platform admin to the tenant. This is
one way of doing it, and this works well when you want
to give a clusters to a tenant.
But another scenario is what happens if instead
I have a set of clusters and
I want to give one of those clusters to be
shared across multiple tenants. Well, Sveltos is a solution for that as
well. What Sveltos like introduced
in this case is yet another CRD. It's the role request
CRD and those role request CRD. Again,
it's a cluster wide resource and it contains a
cluster selector which select like a set of
managed clusters. And then it has a role type section
which reference one or more config maps. And in
the reference config map for secrets you can put a
bunch of cluster role and role and then
you have an admin section. The admin section identifies an admin.
In this case I'm saying that the engineering
admin, as in
every cluster matching the cluster selector department equals engineering
as all the permissions that are defined in the config map in
the default namespace called full access.
Let's look at an example before we go there.
How can Zveltos know that a
cluster profile has been created by given admin. Well, Zweltos expects
this folding label to be present in every cluster profile.
So if you want us Veltos
to say to know that those cluster profile has been created
by a given admin, add this label projectsveltos
IO admin name with the name of those admin.
How you can achieve that? Well, if you're a
plugmon admin you can use an admission controller and Sveltos
for instance provides this Caverno cluster policy
that says like every time a cluster provide is created,
take the name of the service account creating this cluster profile
and add this label here. Now let's
see in an example how this works. As a platform admin you
can create a role request that says in every clusters matching the
cluster selector environment pre release give the
admin ange all the permissions
that are defined like in the config map in the default namespace
called clusters. And this config map contains a cluster
role star star which means that we are giving those
engineer mean like cluster admins permission in
every cluster matching the cluster selector environment
pre release. So what happens if later on the
tenant admin inch creates a cluster
profile and we can see that this cluster profile has been created by the
tenant admins inch by the presence of this label project's veltas IO
admin name that the caverno
is going to be deployed in every cluster
that is matching the label environment prerelease. Because we
have given like this admin the previous
slides, we gave this admin ange for
permission like in every cluster matching the label
environment prerelease. But what happens if the same
admin so you see the label, it's again projects
Veltos ao admin name engine tries to deploy caverno
in every cluster matching the label environment production.
Well in this case like this admin here has not been given permission
to deploy anything in this clusters. So Veltos will block
will block that. This concludes
this presentation and thank you for your
time and hope this was useful.
Thanks.