Hello, this is Ludovic Debas. I'm very happy to participate
to conf 42 to present Cryptpad,
the encrypted collaboration suite.
So who am I? I'm Ludovic Dubas, CEO of Xwiki SAS.
I'm the creator of Xwiki, which is an enterprise wiki.
It's wiki sis is a company based in France and Romania,
which has been doing 15 years of open source.
We're 40 employees at Xwiki and we could
set a motto as make a living and contribute.
Xwiki SAS has launched CryptPad as a new tool four
years ago. So why actually
does cryptpad exist? So first, when it comes to
privacy, what we see
now on many websites is
we value your privacy. This is what
most websites are telling us. And unfortunately,
when you look and go a bit deeper, look at the privacy
policies and all the things that is happening
with our data, what they actually mean is that
they use and sell your data for
many things, either for advertisement,
either to sell our contacts or
to understand what exactly we're
doing so that they can sell us more services.
If we look a bit deeper and we look at the big tech.
So Google, Facebook, Apple, Twitter, Amazon, Microsoft,
what we see is what do they actually know about us?
And this has actually a very long list. They know everything
about our identity, but they mostly
also know a lot of things about us, our friends,
the data we share on their systems and everything we
do, including some things that we
don't do on their own website. This is,
for example, the example of Facebook that knows even what we're
doing outside of Facebook. And this list goes
on and goes on. So actually I took this list from security
baron, which made this list and compares a bit everything that
the big providers know about us.
That's the first problem. And the second problem is
generally more what about security?
What we see is that we're using more and more the Internet,
including for our work. We used to have most
of our work on our personal computer or inside the networks
of companies, and now we're having everything
on the Internet, on the cloud. And most of
this data is unencrypted everywhere. The transparency
of what's happening with this data and how
it's being protected or handled is
actually quite low. There is a lot of talking, but if we
actually want to know what's happening,
it's almost impossible. And of course we could
also go back to some sort of self hosting or
use providers that are more ethical. Now, the difficulty is that
it's not actually easy for small actors or even yourself to
secure your own data. Like if you're running your own server,
it requires quite some experience to actually secure it.
Why did we actually do quippad? And so the
question that we ask ourselves is, what can we actually do
to actually enforce users privacy and security using
encryption? Is it actually possible to build a
collaboration software that
take this as a key principle? And this
is how we ended up building Cryptpad as an
alternative to collaboration tools. Xwiki SAS is
a company rooted in collaboration, and so this is the type of
things we do at Xriki, like helping people collaborate
on. So we decided
to build a collaboration tool that is guided by
privacy and security principles.
And the correlation of this is that there is no business
model based on the user's data in what
we do. So what are the key principles
of Cryptpad?
We start by creating encrypted shared
documents that can be edited in real time.
So this actually comes from the history of cryptpad.
We were interested in real time collaboration. How can you edit
documents at the same time for the Quickie software?
And we realized that we were able to actually encrypt that real
time collaboration and use the server as just
storage of encrypted data, while the
handling of the real time collaboration was happening entirely in the
browser. So we decided to actually make a software
that would just work with the encrypted data.
The second key principle is that there is a management of keys.
Encrypted is the first challenge, and handling
real time collaboration is a challenge. But the second challenge
of this type of technology is how do you actually handle the keys,
secure them and share them with other users.
And so we're handling these keys in personal,
shared, or team drives.
So every user has
a personal drive which is itself an encrypted
document, which is protected by your username and
password, for which a key is created.
And the personal drive is stored on the
server and will contain encrypted all the other
references to the other pads or documents that you have,
and the keys are associated to them. But we
also have shared and team drive. And so what's
interesting there is that while a shared and team drive is
a drive that is accessible by multiple users, so whatever you store
in that drive pad and
keys will be accessible to the other users. So once you have
a shared or team drive between users, you're not only sharing
the documents, you're also sharing the
keys of these documents. And the third key principle is that
we have a system to exchange keys using personal
messaging boxes and this is using public privacy key
cryptography. So if you need to send a
document to another user, once you've been
in contact with that user, you have his
public key, and so you can send him a message, and he will receive the
message in his crip pad, and we'll be able to decrypt it.
In this message, there would be the document address,
the pad, and the key associated to it.
So what do we actually know about you
when you're using Tripad?
So there's a few categories, and we have a document on our blog. You can
go see our blog on this subject. And so there's
things we cannot avoid to see, but we actually don't collect.
And so this is ips and public keys.
So we do see the ips of our users
and what documents they actually request,
and we see the public key also associated to this
ip. Now, we're not storing that connection, but ultimately,
if we wanted to do it as a hoster of Pippad,
this is what we could do. Then there's
other things that we store because we actually need it. So we
store the encrypted files, and these encrypted files are linked to the public keys
to the users. We also have the information of the
user's identity when they're paying users, because this is actually required
by law. And we also have statistical
information. So this is not information that we
necessarily would have to store first. This is information that we do see
the ips, the actions that people do on our servers,
and also information that users have allowed
us to access. So, for example, we have
a telemetry setting where you can accept or refuse
to send us the actions that you're doing in the tool, so that no content
is actually shared at that point, only the actions and this
statistical information, including locations. And we're
very interested in that information because it's information that allows
us to understand how is cryptpad progressing and how
is it progressing in different countries.
And we could in the future record
that information less. But it's actually quite useful
for making prepad a success at this point.
And of course, if you host your cryptpad yourself,
then the hoster of that cryptpad becomes the
one that has access to this information and decides
what he stores or not. Now,
it could be possible to potentially have even
less access to this information, but it's quite difficult,
it's much more difficult to not have access to users ips
than that.
So this is things that maybe in the future could
be, can be continuously improved. Now, the thing is,
what we cannot know. So the first thing is we don't know your password.
We don't even know your username. So this is actually something
that's quite interesting, is that most websites,
one of the biggest problem is actually that you're sending
your password to the websites for verification,
while in Cryptpad, where we're doing
an authentication that is based on cryptography and
where your username and passwords are never leaving your
computer. So we're deriving key, and this key represents
data on our server. And the second
part of what we can't know is the actual
content of the documents that you're storing on
cryptpad. All these documents are encrypted,
including the data, the titles, the metadata tags
or all this information. And this is
actually protecting your data way
more than potentially some collaboration software which
encrypted the content, like the text that
you could find in some data structures, but would
keep the structured data
around this data as non encrypted.
And so in cryptpad we've
went in great lengths to actually have as little
information as possible on the content that people collaboration
on. And so when
you're sharing your pad,
we don't know the name of the collaborator that you're sharing it with.
Now what do we actually have in Cryptpad and what care
the collaboration tools that exist. So I'll show
a demo of these. So we started
with a rich text pad,
which is a WYSIWYg document that you
collaborate on in real time. And we have a code pad where you
can do markdown and also include
some specific markup like mermaid, to do some graphs.
We also have a presentation pad which is again
in markdown, but allows to present as slides.
We have sheets which is based on the integration
of only office inside Quickpad. So it's Excel compatible.
You can export and import an Excel file and it
has quite good set of features of
Excel, similar to Excel.
We have a kanban, so similar to Trello,
where you can organize some tasks
in the Kanban form. We have a whiteboard and we have a
poll tool. And all this is organized in
a trip drive, so you can organize your content and add attached
files, pdfs or any types of
file you want. And we have a team feature which
allows to share such a drive and including a chat
with a group of people that you decide. So let's actually
look a bit at these features.
And so if
I go to cryptrive here,
here you can see my drive with
folders. So I can actually organize this in folders,
this specific drive in my
folder list is actually a shared drive. We can recognize it using
the little icon. And so that means that I can actually
share that folder with
other users. So I can actually do that using the share button.
I can share by knowing the people and sending
them a notification in cryptpad on this. But I
can also fabricate a link for
that access, either in view mode or in edit mode. So when
you're sharing a URL which gives
access to paths, you have to be careful to share it
in a secure channel because anybody that could read that
communication channel could access
to the information. The key point here is
the safest way and more secure way to share a
pad in cryptpad is actually having the
other person in your contact and share the pad
using the account that the person has on quipad.
So you have folders and we can actually also
attach images. So I can drag and drop files
in this directory. As I can see, I have some images there
and then I have some pads. So for our most
used pad is actually the
Wysiwyk pad. So let me actually take the example here.
Let's see if I have an example.
So this is a sample documents that we use to work to
show the common features. So this is
our wysIWyg editor. So you can type
content here, and so if you have
two users opening that pad.
So for example here,
if I open that pad in
a second window,
I can make changes here and these changes
will show up on the other screen.
And this wysIwyg
has quite a lot of features. You can insert images here,
you can see an image and I can resize
the image. I can also use
bullet points, I can put equations
in the document, so I can chat around
the pad, and I can also comment the pad.
So if I select some content here,
I can add a comment, I will add a
comment here. And this is actually collaborative
because I can mention some other users and send them
a message telling them that I'd like them to do something
in this path. So there's quite a
lot of features. We have a history feature, so you can roll back
in case of difficulty, you can export import,
you can print, and this way, for example,
extract your pad as pdf.
Another type of pad that we have is actually the code pad.
So you're typing in markdown and you're seeing
the content directly there. What's interesting there is that
you also have color, auto colors, so you can
actually see who has typed what.
So if you have multiple users in your pad, and this is similar to a
feature that exists in Etipad is
that you can see who has added content
in a pad. And this pad is
showing mermaid syntax, which allows to do some graphs,
including Gantt charts and things like that.
So we have also syntax coloring for other languages
and markdown, so you can actually see colors
also of the syntax so that you understand what
you're typing. Another type of pad
is actually a whiteboard. So this is actually quite useful
for education.
You can work in real time on,
on a drawing and show it
to somebody else during a video conference, for example.
Another type of pad is spreadsheets. And so this
has been quite challenging and is actually for us a
breakthrough is that we're integrating the only office
open source software which is built in JavaScript, and we're
integrating this encrypt pad. And everything that is
happening on the document is encrypted and stored encrypted
on the server and even including
images. So it's possible to add images itself
to your spreadsheet and they will be stored in
the trip drive and embedded in your spreadsheet documents.
And we also have an import
export feature. So if I do export
here, I can actually export
in Excel. And so this is actually
using webassembly because this was C
code in onlyoffice
to convert the document from the internal format of
onlyoffice to mid cell format.
Another aspect here is that it's
a spreadsheet. And for example it supports some graphs,
so you can see a chart based on the
spreadsheet data. Let me
see if I have some other things to show here on some examples.
So you can see we have
a pole and we have a kanban. I will actually
show this here going back in the presentation
in here we have
so the homepage of cryptpad that you can see, and you
can see that we have ended our storage limit on
cryptpad Fr, which is our hosted
cryptpad that we provide to the community,
which also has a paying subscription. We have extended the free
subscriptions to 1gb during the COVID outbreak,
as many more users were actually needing online
tools. And so this is the drive again.
So this is the sharing mechanism. I showed that
the code pad, the Kanban, you can see this is actually
our squad Kanban,
which is showing the tasks on which the team is working on.
You can see that it's quite extensive
roadmap, lots of work there. Now I'll detail
a bit what is planned in the future and
the spreadsheets, the whiteboard.
So now after this demo
of the live tool, what I'd like
to show is a bit the technological aspects of
cryptpad. So the first item of the technological
aspects of crypt is user authentication.
So when you log in in cryptPad, you have a username and password,
and use these username and passwords never leave
the user's computer. We're using script to derive a key,
and this key will represent data on our server.
And this data is unique.
This allows to actually bootstrap your storage
space on the Cryptpad server and then
will contain the keys of the different documents that you're
sharing. It's important to understand
that if you lose your password or even your
username, we, the hosters of
Cryptpad instance at Cryptpad Fr, we are unable to
retrieve it. So it's really your job to secure this
properly and make sure you're not losing
them. Now,
when it comes to the documents, what is happening is that
every time a document is changing in your
browser, then we're creating a patch, and this patch is
sent to the server, encrypted using the key
of the document. And we have the changepad algorithm and
also some other algorithms which are used to handle concurrent
changes without the server being involved. So this
algorithm, the merging algorithm,
is making sure that everybody gets to the same results,
even if they are concurrent patches that would be incompatible.
So there is not 100% guarantee that your change
is going to make it through if you're in a collaboration session.
But what is 100% guaranteed is that everybody will be
at the same result in
the end. So there is only one possible outcome of
the collaboration. So for example, if you have a
user that makes a change on a paragraph, and another user that deletes it,
the cryptpad algorithm will choose a
path that will be the same on
all clients. And so either it will be
considered that the change was
done before the deletion, either it will be considered
that deletion is done before the change, and in the end you'll
get the same result.
Another aspect is that we're storing
old documents in quipad, including your drive, as a history
of patches. Now,
in order to avoid coming back to the beginning of every document,
so that we can reconstruct the current state,
we store a full version every 50 patches.
So if you're working on a document,
the general principle is that we're sending patches.
So if you're reloading a
document from scratch, what we will look for is the latest checkpoint and then
the patches, and we will reconstruct the state of your
document at the end of
the last patches, then all
document encryption keys are stored in your drive, and the drive
is a cryptpad document itself, which is protected using the same mechanism.
What is particular in the technology
of Quipad is that all the editors are fully written in JavaScript,
and we have no server component for any of them.
And so everything's running in
your browser and needs to run in your browser
so that we can secure
the collaboration. Now the question
is, how far can this go? Like what can
we do with this technology beyond what it's doing today?
So I've shown in the live demo that we're already doing
quite a lot of things well. We can go much
further in terms of integrating any editors that are building JavaScript.
We've already done some prototypes in the past to integrate
draw IO for example, and we also have prototypes
to integrate the other components of onlyoffice
for presentation. So PowerPoint
compatible and word compatible.
These actually are quite close from working,
but we didn't want to launch them
because the more pads we have, the more support we need to
do to make sure that these all work very well.
And so what we want is first that spreadsheets is
working very well,
that it can scale to many users,
and then we'll potentially deploy more editors.
There could also be contributors that work and support editors
that could run on the same platform.
There is also the possibility to build more advanced applications
that are built on top of the crypt storage. So we have focused
on one advanced application which is managing your drive,
because this is actually something we absolutely needed
to secure the collaboration on the pad. But you could also
imagine calendars, blogs, wikis,
databases that are built on this encrypted storage, or surveys,
and we plan to work on some of them in the
future. But this approach
could be used for any type of application.
But you need to think differently when you build
them, because you need to build them with
the constraint that everything will happen on the client side and nothing
will be done by the server, which is not really the way most
applications have been built in the recent years, where actually
all the providers are trying to build applications that they control on
which users are dependent. Another type
of things we could do is, and we've done some
experiments on this, is encrypted audio video conferencing,
and we find it interesting because it's very interesting to add at
least audio conferencing around the document. When you're working collaborative in
document, it's interesting to be able to talk to each other.
And actually the cripat system can transfer
also audio and video data, and the browser
could implement, playing it.
Another aspect is,
well, we can go very far in terms of what we can build and
new things we can build. Now, the thing is, there is a lot of work
already to bring all editors and applications on par with non encrypted
applications. If we look at what we do in cryptPad,
we have a lot of applications like Wiziwig
editing, Markdown editing,
only office compatible editing.
We also have a kanban, which potentially is a
competitor to Trello. And so all these applications,
they compete with tools that have a very large range
of features, and some of them are not so easy to build.
And so there is a lot of work to bring these editors on par with
non encrypted applications. So we
need to also choose between the number of editors
and the quantity of features in the editor.
Another aspect is that users are also very
interested in mobile and offline access to these documents. So this
is a bit the difference between Google Drive,
Google Docs and Dropbox.
People are also interested to replicate
their data on their computer and to edit it,
potentially offline. And so there is also some
range of work that is significant to
write mobile and desktop clients for Quickpack.
There is also advanced search that will be
an interesting challenge to build. And another
aspect is that it's possible to make cryptpad
a decentralized service.
And so this is also an axis of work, and where
basically cryptpad instances would collaborate, and you
could have a user on one cryptpad instance that is working collaboratively
on a document with a user from another instance, and that's another
access of work for the team.
Now, what is actually our roadmap? So most of our roadmap is
built today on the fundings we
were able to get for the project. I'll mention a bit that funding later.
And so right now we have received funding
from NLNeT and trust.
And so we're very grateful of that funding, which is allowing to
fund a very active roadmap. And so most of the developments
that we're doing care based on the
roadmaps, on the developments we have proposed to these projects.
And so right now we're finishing up the communities project funded
by NLNEt, which already has funded the teams
feature in. So we're finishing
the project and we're finishing implementing document review.
So the comments that I've shown in the Wysiwave
pad have been funded by this project. We also
have improved in the administration panel,
and we're also improving documentation for users and
instance administrators.
Then the second project we will be working on
is called SMC. Secure mobile communication. And the objective
there is to develop a prototype Android application.
And this should also open a lot of things because relying
there is work about making prepad more modular.
The third project is a dialogue project,
which we plan to do in
the second part of this year. And the objective
will be to improve the current poll application and implement a
form application. So what we will implement in the dialogue
project will also open new possibilities in
terms of applications built on top
of the crypt storage. So we'll create some APIs that
can be used by even more complex applications
in parallel. We're always working on
maintenance and performance. This actually has been
super active in the last six months, as I
will show with the usage of cryptpad, which has
grown a lot, and particularly because of the COVID crisis,
we have done a lot of work on performance and we need to continue
to sustain the growth of usage, in particular
of the cryptpad fr instance, so that we can get more
usage. And so if we
look at the Cryptpad fr usage, so we
have about 450 installs in the world,
including Cryptpad is our main
instance that is managed by our team.
And this instance has seen a tremendous
growth when
the COVID crisis started because
of in particular two types of users. One is people working
from home, so needing more collaboration tool, but also the
education space and schools which
needed ways to collaborate with students. And we've
been able to see on
Cryptpad that we had a lot of features that
were using Cryptpad. Another aspect of cryptpad usage
is that Cryptpad is actually heavily used in Germany,
which is the first country where it's being used.
So this is actually not where the Cryptpad
team originates from. The Cryptpad team is, is actually
from a french company based in Paris. So France
is also a big country of usage, but the
german usage is actually much higher.
Since the cryptpad crisis, we've reached about 50,000 users
per week and 350,000 pads open
in a week. And this was actually four
times higher than what we had before.
So what we have seen also is that the
usage of cryptpad has grown a lot
in the US. First it has grown because of COVID and then it has
also more than doubled in
the last two weeks. And we believe that this is linked to the project
in the US and to some
users recommending the usage of encrypted
tool. If we look at
the usage of cryptpad over three years,
we can see that the effect of the COVID crisis
on the amount of pads open on cryptpad,
where we went in a year,
almost tenfold but in the year before, we were
already growing two, three times.
And another thing we see is that we see that many of our users
are actually recommending other users to use prepad,
and we're very grateful for that. And it really helps spreading
the usage and showing that it's
possible to actually use more privacy friendly
tools for collaboration. This data
that I'm showing is only based on the CryptPad LFR data,
and we also have other instances, so there
is 450 other instances and on which
we don't have detailed data on the
usage. The Cryptpad
team is currently three full time developers, so it's actually not a
very big team which is handling the development
and also handling the main crippled FR instance.
The team receives some support from the Suksis team,
so from human resources, from marketing, and also
from me. We have more than 400 independent
instances, and we have a community of users and some administrators
that are participating through our matrix channel and
that are also helping promoting cryptpad.
Cryptpad wouldn't be what it is without the promotion
of all the other users that are making it
known. So when it comes to
the cryptpad funding, and I believe that it's very important to talk
about the funding of open source tools, because it's very important
to have open source tools. We're strong believers of open source tools,
but it's really hard to get
open source tools if we don't manage to fund them properly.
So CryptPad originated initially from a
french funded project by be. So it's a
state organization. Funding R and D out
of this project was
funding Ipswichi and some other companies.
This is how we got Cryptpad bootstrapped.
At the end of March 2019,
this funding ended, and we needed
to find some ways to continue that project. And we've been happy
to candidate to the NGI
pet Zero fund. And NLNet has funded
multiple projects that are improving Cryptpad,
and we also got a funding from NGI Trust,
which has helped us complete the funding for the
year. We also have
been happy to receive a ten k dollar grant from
the Mozilla Open source fund when we candidated
to it that cost them this
year. This is actually very interesting because it
has allowed us to fund the team that was working
on cripple and to be able to continue to fund them now.
What is also very important is what kind of long term funding we're able
to build. So we have a few
strategies in place for that. So the first thing is that Cryptalfr is
a pain service, and for us it's really important
to build it right away as a paid service.
Unlike many, many cloud services that are starting for
free, initially, trying to reach millions of users,
and then are making users discover the paying scheme.
For us, we believe that it was really important to
show how we believe that we can fund that
project long term. So we need funding so
that we can get the software off the ground,
but then we need a model where it can be sustained over time
and we can build a team regularly.
As users have increased,
we've increased subscribers, and we've reached now
170 subscribers.
So now we've reached 170 subscribers on
the CryptPad, for instance, which represents 1000
per month of subscriptions.
And we also have an open collective.
Cryptpad is one of the popular projects on open Collective,
and we have 150 donators on open collective
that represents 500 per month.
All this is evaluated as about twenty k euros for
220. Now, it's important to
understand that this is still ten weeks away from being able to completely
fund the team only based on revenue, and not being
relying on grants to be able to sustain
the development. And now we believe
that it's possible to continue to increase the usage of
the main crypt instance and increase both
subscribers and donators. And there's also possibilities
to package support services for enterprise
instances, which could also bring some revenue to help fund the
technology. Well, we welcome any
help that it can be. We welcome also contributors
that would want to help in continuing
to improve this product,
and also administrators that want to host instances and make
prepad more known and propose a
solution so that we're using less
non privacy friendly tools and we're using more tools
that are protecting our data and our privacy. Thank you very
much, and I've been really happy to participate to this
Conf 42 conference, and I hope you appreciated
this talk.