Are youll an SRE,
a developer, a quality engineer
who wants to tackle the challenge of improving reliability in
your DevOps? You can enable your DevOps for reliability with
chaos native. Create your free account at
Chaos native. Litmus Cloud hello,
my name is Rafael and my talk is titled five levels
of high availability from multi instance to hybrid cloud.
But first a few words about myself. I am the
tech lead of the cloud native team at Hazelcast before
I worked at Google and CERN. I'm also can author
of the book Continuous Delivery with Docker and Jenkins and
from time to time I do conference speaking and trainings,
but on a daily basis. I'm an engineer, I'm a developer
and I live in Krakow in Poland.
A few words about Hazelcast Hazelcast is a distributed company.
We're always distributed, always working remotely, and we
produce distributed software. Our software is
open source. What we do is,
you may know Hazelcast,
it's an in memory data store and stream processing
platform. So people use it for machines,
for processing everything where latency matters.
So please check it out. Our agenda for today for
this talk is pretty simple. So there will be a short introduction about
high availability levels in general, about high availability in general.
And then we will walk through all levels
that you can use in your system while deploying,
while designing your system. And while I'll be talking
about these levels, I will always focus on the solution,
but also on the trade off. So if
you design your system to be available in let's say
multiregion, what does it mean to you? What will you will achieve, but also
what you will lose. So I will focus on the trade offs.
So let's start with the introduction. So currently,
any system, basically any system you want you build currently
is based on services. So in
the center, I mean everything now is a service. Sometimes we
call it a microservice, sometimes we call it
microservice even though it's huge. But it doesn't really matter.
It doesn't matter if it's a microservice macro service
or even a lambda function.
What matters is that this part of the system with
which you communicate is usually stateless.
And stateless mean we can replicate it,
we can deploy it wherever we want. So stateless
thing contains the business logic and it's usually can easy part of
your system. So just imagine for a moment that
our system is just a bunch of stateless services,
like a calculator service that can add two
numbers. So then that
is all your system. Then it's relatively simple, you can deploy it anywhere you
want, it will work the same on my machine, on my laptop it will work
the same on AWS. If you deploy it in
1 million replicas, it will still work the same.
So usually the stateless part,
the service is not a problem, but that is like
usually the stateless service is connected to a bunch of the stateful things
like a data store or a queue
or it can be some other services, internal or external. So something
that has state from our service perspective
and this stateless, stateful things are
the problem in our system. So the data,
we can say that the data is the problem. So if there is no data,
there is no problem in terms of high availability.
So with this in mind,
I will always focus on the data, but I will always give you
the whole picture as well. So with this in mind we can start
from the first high availability level, which is single
instance. Single instance means no high availability at all,
just look at the diagram. So single instance is kind of. If you
deploy your database, can application everything on your laptop that
is a single instance. Now why would
you ever do it? I mean it's not practical but there
are multiple things that becomes very easy when
you deploy everything on a single instance.
One thing is the latency. So I did a latency experiment in
my scenario I deployed an application
with embedded hazelcast. Hazelcast is just a data store,
so it doesn't matter, it's hazelcast, it's just to show you what
happens with the latency if you deploy everything on one machine so you can
say like a service and a database. For us, database is hazelcast
and I measured the latency of the retry write so
it was 80 millisecond per 10,000 of entries.
It doesn't tell us much, you can already see it's a
very low latency but we'll
compare it later to what happens with the latency as we
go farther with our high availability levels.
So if you deploy everything on a single instance,
what it means to you, you have no high
availability or no scalability but you
have very low latency and you always have a data consistency because you
cannot have consistent data if you just have one instance of your
data store. And there are some
valid scenarios for such a deployed even though it may seem
crazy but imagine like let's say edempotent
both job that you can always repeat there's no problem
running this on a single instance. So there might be some cases
where you deployed your system in that way, but okay,
you didn't come here to listen to some development
environment. So let's go straight ahead to multiinstance.
So level one, multi instance. So multi instance means
that if one machines is down, the system is
still available. How can it look like, how will be the
classic diagram for such a system?
So a request goes to our system, it will usually go to a load balancer,
which will forward the traffic to the application service replicas
which are deployed on at least two machines.
And this stateless part of the system uses
some stateful part of the system. So in
our case, let's look at some data store
which is always also deployed on at least
two instances on at least two machines.
If you look at this diagram, there is only one thing that is single on
this diagram and it's load balancer. However, load balancing
is completely separate topic and it's somehow as
a DevOps Persona.
Usually this problem is kind of solved for you because
nowadays these load balancers are super reliable and youll can
just, with a few clicks you can have it done. So we will
not focus on a load balancer so much.
We'll also not focus on the stateless part because we already
said that that is the easy part of our system. So we'll
focus on the database. So in our scenario,
the assumption here we have two database
instances which are connected with a fast and reliable network.
For example, you could start two EC, two instances on AWS.
That is our scenario right now.
So we have two data stores, two databases, and we would
like to use them. So the problem,
what we are trying to solve right now is called data
replication. And at this point, let me
give you a short history and a
very simplified story,
how this data application was approached and used.
So the SQL databases,
not so long time ago, it was the mainstream.
Some may argue that it's still the mainstream,
but with SQL databases, how this problem
was usually approached was that we had
like so called active passive or master slave
replication, meaning that all
application services, they use only one database
instance, at least for the writes.
So you write only to zones replica.
And if anything wrong happens, then we just do a failover
to the second replica. Because all the
it, everything we stored in a machine
one is replicated to machine two. If there is a crash of
machine one, we do a failover so we don't lose any data and
our machine two becomes the active replica.
And that is how most replication looks like nowadays.
You can combine it with sharding, no problem with that.
Now with the movement of NoSQL and people thought like we
need something better, this master slave replication.
So it's maybe too difficult for
developers and sometimes not that good. So most,
like NoSQL databases,
kind of abstract this replication way. They do
so called clustering, which means that your application,
they use all the instances of database, so they connect to each of
the instance of the database, and each of the instance they
stores the
primary partition of the data and also the backups
of some other partitions. We always
store the backup of some partitions. So if one machine is down, no problem with
that, we migrate the data and your application,
they can still use you don't lose any data to go
a little deeper into. And let's look at specific example,
because actually each database solved this
problem a little different. So it's good to focus on one
example. So let's focus on hazelcast, how it looks like if
we go a little deeper. So hazelcast is a key value data store.
So we partition all the data by keys, and now each
member stores some partitions of the data
and backups of some other partitions. So the
rule here is that the backup of
the partition is always stored on another member than the partition itself.
So for example, partition one is stored on member one,
so its backup backup of the partition one will be stored on
member two or three, but never on the member one. In our case, it's stored
on the member two. Now, in any of the member crashes,
at any point of time, you don't lose any data because
the backups are promoted to the main partition and everything
works. So from the client perspective,
from application perspective, you may not even notice that,
okay, we have like this. So this is more or less how this
nosql tried to address this replication problem.
But now the question is, should these backups,
no matter if they are clustered or if they are really
master slave, should they be done synchronously or
asynchronously? In other words, should we favor
consistency, so we do a backup synchronously so we are
sure about the data? Or should we favor latency
and do it asynchronously? And before I answer this question,
I did another latency experiment, and this time I deployed hazelcast
as a database on two machines and
features the latency of
read write again. And as you expect, it's way
worse than a single instance because you cannot beat like one
machine communication, so they will not
beat it. Here you need to have like a network involved.
But if you look at the number, it still doesn't look that bad. It's still
under one millisecond per entry, which is usually acceptable.
And this is with synchronous backups, so we are sure that you will not lose
the data. So this is pretty good.
That is why in most cases in NoSQL databases
like by default, you will see that these backups are done synchronously,
but you can obviously change it. Is it the same
for this SQL and this more
complex databases? Not necessarily. For example
mysql, by default they do it asynchronously.
So you favor latency here because otherwise the latency
would suffer. So a short summary,
what has been level one for you so you can
achieve data consistency because you
can do synchronous backup, it's still an acceptable latency.
Most tools support it, so it's
easy to set up. Most cloud specific toolkits support
it. And even if you've done on premises like
Hazelcut or any other tool, it's usually very simple
to set it up from the downsides. If you would like to
access this, you are still inside one region. So if you youll like to access
the data from another region, then you will have high latency accessing from
another regions. Okay,
let's move forward and from multizone,
from multi instance, one step up is multizone.
Multizone means that if one availability
zone is down, the system is still available.
How does it look like on a diagram?
So here is a diagram for multizone. So again, request goes
to cloud balancer, load balancers forwards to the traffic, to the application services,
they use databases and now the application services,
they need to be deployed in at least two availability
zones. And the same with the databases, they need to be deployed in
at least two availability zones. So if you look at
this diagram, it's pretty similar to what we've seen with multi instance.
That is why the first question you might ask is is it any different
than deploying to multi
instance multizone? Does it make any difference or just do the
same? I just change my configuration file and that's it.
So I would say it's not much different, but there is some difference.
So let me first explain why it's not different.
So I did another latency experiment and this time I deployed
four hazelcast instances, two in each availability zones,
and I measured the latency. And obviously it's
worse than multiinstance, but it's not way worse. It's not
even twice worse and it's still under one millisecond per
entry. So that is actually usually good
enough. That is why you can just
move your deployed to multizone and
do it with the same. But I also mentioned that there is a
difference, there is some difference between multiinstance and multizone.
And to understand the difference,
let's focus on one example. So this is
exactly the scenario I used for experiment. I deployed
four hazelcast instances, two instances in each availability zone.
The assumption here are that the
network between availability zone is fast and reliable because
that's how cloud providers work.
And so if you would like to reproduce such a scenario,
you just deploy four ec, two instances
in one availability zone to another availability zone. And that
is your scenario. You remember this diagram,
probably from a moment ago I presented this.
So we have like partitions and the backups, and the rule is the backup
is always on another member,
so it always works good. But imagine what would happen if
we store the
partition on the member one and the backup of the partition on member
two. However, it happens that machine one
and the machine two, they are in the same availability zone. So now
if zone one crashes, what happens?
We lose the data because we lost both the
primary partition and the partition backup. That is
why the same deployed we moved it from multiinstance to
multi zone and it doesn't work anymore.
We thought how to solve it in hazelcast this
problem and we came up with the idea that
a feature called zone aware, so we groups the
partitions by zones and this is actually how we
enable this in the configuration. And if
you enable this, then hazelcast
will know in which higher verbatim zone it is located
and it will keep the backups
always of the partitions always in a different availability
zone. So that if zones zone is down you never lose
the data, since the concept of the availability
zones is related to the cloud. So it's different in AWS,
different in azure, different in GCP
and in kubernetes. In general we
provided plugins for each environment.
And by the way, these plugins are also used for the
discovery and they
used the given API,
for example AWS API, to check okay, in which zone
I am located. And then Hazelcast knows where
to distribute the partition backups so that in result you
have the partition backup always in another availability zone.
And if one zone is down, you will never lose data.
So that is why I said there's not much difference in terms
of latency and in terms of the configuration. But please make
sure that your data store is zone aware or supports like zone aware
feature and don't take it for granted that
it works this way. Short summary
so level two multizone, I would say it's currently
top one choice because you have very highly
available system youll can keep the
data consistency with synchronous backups and
a lot of cloud specific toolkit that supported.
Now please make sure that your tool really supports
zones aware. So read how it works. You need to go a little deeper.
And from another downside is the same as multiinstance.
So we are still in the one region,
meaning if we deploy our system in Europe
and someone from us accesses our system, then latency
is high. And that is the problem we will
try to solve right now, going from multi zone
to multi region. So multi region will
be. Yeah, it's multi region means that if
the whole geo region is down, our system is still
available how it looks like on the diagram. So that
will be the diagram for us. So usually
a request goes to Geolo balancer, and it's forwarded
to the regions which is the closest to our client,
and then it's forwarded to one of the application services,
and they use some data. And between the data stores in
different regions, we have something called geore application.
So the assumption here we have our data stores deployed
in different regions,
and the network may be slow and unreliable.
For example, if youll would like to simulate, you can deploy
two ec, two instances, one in Europe, one in us.
On each of them, start your database, and that is your deployed.
You may think, but what's the problem of regions?
Like, why multiregion needs
something like georeplication, why is it different?
So the problem is the distance. So the physical distance is something that is
actually the problem. If you look at the map, you look, for example,
two regions, Finland and Oregon, it's like 10,000
between. So even if we calculate, like take
the speed of light in a vacuum and take the distance, so the round
trip time of light
in a vacuum would be 60 milliseconds. So it's already a lot.
If it's not a vacuum, but a fiber, it will be at
least three times more. And it does not takes
any routers root and anything, it's just
light. So this is something that we
cannot solve. That is why we cannot
use just a standard replication in between our data stores.
We need to use something called georeplication.
So georeplication is just like,
you have two data stores, and you would like to have the same data in
both of them. So youll need to replicate them and it needs to be done
asynchronously because of the physical distance,
your latency would suffer too much. If you don't do it asynchronously,
youll data store must support it, and you must be prepared for the data loss,
because you use asynchronous communication and there in
general like two nodes, active passive or active active.
So active passive is like you
write only to one data store and the second one is not used,
or it's used only for reads. And with
such a scenario you need to be prepared for the data loss because maybe you
wrote something to the active cluster and it crashes
before replicating the data.
So you need to be prepared also for eventual consistency.
And in the active active mode means that you
can write to both clusters. And then you
need to be prepared for the data loss, for eventual consistency, but also for the
conflict resolution. Because what happens if you modify the same data
at the same time on two
database clusters? You need to have a strategy
how to solve this conflict. So in
most cases, the simplest strategy is, for example, the last
one wins. But you have to think about it inside your application
logic, because your business logic needs to be aware what to do if you
have a conflicting data. That is why it's actually very complex
to say to reason about active, active georeplication.
In headlocks we call this georeplication one replication.
And this is actually how youll set it up. So it's actually very simple.
You set up the one replication
and the IP or the hostname of the target cluster and that's
it. It will replicate the data.
The only thing with this jury replication, it does not sound
easy. So do I really need to lose the consistency if
I would like to go multiregion? And I
did another latency experiment,
and this time
I did something I should not do. So I've set up one hazelcast
cluster with synchronous backup over two geographical
regions. And I measured the latency and
that was the result. So you see it's
way higher than multizone and it's usually
at the range. That is not acceptable. That is
why you will never use synchronous
replication across multiple geographical regions.
And I did the same with the georeplication, obviously it was synthesis.
The replication is asynchronous, the latency is
the same as multiregion. Now if
you look at this chart, that is the reason
why you will never see a Kubernetes cluster,
which is across multiple geographical
regions. You will see a Kubernetes cluster across
multiple zones, no problem with that. But you will never see a Kubernetes cluster
across multiple geographical regions. And the reason for that
is that internally Kubernetes, cases etCD,
which is data store,
which is consistent. So you cannot have this eTCD across
multiple regions, because it will just be super slow.
So technically you cloud have a Kubernetes cluster across multiple regions,
but it will be so slow that you will not be able to use it.
Yeah. So you will see for kubernetes some
other options, like federations,
but you cannot have one consistent
cluster across multiple regions.
Short summary of the level three multiregion. What does it mean
to you? So we are super high available. You can achieve low latency
when accessed from multiple region. That is great. And sometimes
you can use some cloud specific tools, sometimes not.
But on the downsides, you need to use georeplication, which is asynchronous.
And you need to be prepared for the conflict resolution, eventual consistency.
So it's way more complex to reason about a
system like that. Okay, from multiregion
we go to multicloud. So multicloud
means that if zones cloud provider is down, the system
is still available how it looks like
on the diagram. So again, you will have some load balancer, which load balances the
traffic, and you have basically the clone of the system
on a different cloud providers and a replication in
between. And this replication will be asynchronous,
like a geore replication. So you may ask like
what's different from multiregion? This diagram is actually like
the same before. It's just you have multiple cloud providers, but that's it.
But there are some differences. So if you deploy
the same system on different cloud providers, you cannot use cloud
portfolio and you cannot use VPC
peering, and you increase the cost because you need
to maintain the same infrastructure and the same system on a multiple cloud
providers, which is more complex and costs more
money. But is high availability the only
reason for multicloud? And obviously no,
it's not even the main reason. The main reasons for going multicloud
is like avoiding Vernon lock in. So you
don't want to bind yourself to one cloud provider.
Because for example, imagine you have
the same system deployed in different cloud providers. That is way better for
any cost optimization, for any cloud cost
negotiation, because you can go to AWS saying,
okay, by the way, I'm also deployed on Azure and GCP, so can you
lower the bill? And that is what happens
actually with cloud providers. You negotiate with them
if you are big enough. And it's also
about risk mitigation if youll
don't want to be bound to one cloud provider
for some business reasons. Also,
sometimes it's also about low latency. When we've built hazelcast
cloud, hazelcast cloud is hazelcast
AWS a service, and we build it on top of different cloud providers,
because our users are also deployed on different
cloud providers and they would like to have the lowest latency possible.
So that is why we are built on different cloud providers.
And also some data protection regulations or
sometimes you build like heterogeneous
environment when you use different cloud portfolio for
different parts of the system. If you go multicloud,
what does it mean to you? So you don't have vendor lock in, which is
very good. You are in better position with the cloud cost negotiation,
and you can have low latency of access from multiple cloud,
but the setup is way more complex
and you cannot use cloud portfolio if
you really have the clone of the same environment on different
cloud providers. Okay, and the last
level for today is hybrid cloud. So hybrid
cloud means if all cloud providers are down,
your system will still be available. But really,
is it possible that all cloud providers are down at
the same time? No, it's actually not
even possible. It's not even possible that one cloud provider is
down. I think it never happened that the whole cloud provider, all services were down.
There are different reasons for hybrid cloud. So then
why would you use hybrid cloud?
So it's usually about data requirements, regulations, data security.
Sometimes there are regulations, for example, that the data of your
bank customers needs to be stored in this
country or in this building or in this city.
So then part of your infrastructure is on premises,
on your own servers. The other use case is that you are
moving to the cloud. You had your own infrastructure, but you're moving to the cloud.
And as a process, you build a hybrid cloud environment.
And it's also sometimes about cost reduction. If you are big enough, then cloud
may not be the cheapest thing you can get.
How does it look like on a diagram? So again, youll have load balancer
and the same system deployed on different cloud providers, but also the
same system deployed on your own machines.
So at this point, actually at
this point, but also at the point of multicloud, you will
usually need some abstraction. And this abstraction because it's just not
manageable. When you manage different servers, different machines,
it's just too difficult, too complex at this point. So usually
what people do, they have some abstraction layer
and they interact with this abstraction layer. And so you install kubernetes.
Nowadays this abstraction layer is usually kubernetes
or some derivatives from kubernetes like Openshift or IBM
cloud. And you deployed this kubernetes on each environment,
on the AWS, on GCP, and on your
own machines. So at least you have the same interface to interact with.
And it's actually how most companies now build multi cloud
and hybrid cloud systems.
Short summary so hybrid
cloud means that you have no cloud lock in. You can have
achieve low latency accessed from any custom network because you
are the master of your infrastructure.
But the setup is very complex and it usually requires
this kubernetes or openshift layer.
And it costs a fortune.
So as a short summary,
a short summary. What I propose is not to repeat much
what I've said, because that could be boring, but to at least some,
to summarize basically what I've said. So I propose
like a graph
how I see it. Like comparing complexity and cost to the
high availability level. So this is how
I see it. So at the beginning, single instance is very. It's not
complex at all. But then if you go from single multiinstance to multi
instance, it's actually a big step. Because you
go from nondistributed system to a distributed system.
So you need to think about data, applications and all those things we
mentioned. If you go from multi instance to multizone, actually it's not such
a big step in complexity. In terms of complexity,
you need to make sure that your database is
zone aware. Then from multizone to multiregion,
it's another big step because you have long distance. So you need to be prepared
for georetication. You cannot
have synchronous single point of data going
from multiregion to multicloud. You cannot use cloud
tools. And from multicloud to hybrid cloud is another big step.
Because you need to maintain your own infrastructures,
which high availability level is for me.
So I would say if youll don't know, then this is your level.
This is what I call top one choice. Because multizone
youll are very high available. But you can still use like synchronous
data store, which really simplifies your
reasoning about the system. If you are a software cabo,
you can use single instance. Multiregion is if you need
to go worldwide with your system. So you would like to
achieve low latency from different regions. And multicloud
and hybrid cloud is basically for
the like, for the reason of compliance and security.
So basically banking industry. So youll need to have
a reason to do it. And with this last
slide, I would like to thank you for listening to this talk. It was
a pleasure speaking at Conf 42
conference. Enjoy the rest of the
conference.