You. The imposter syndrome.
Do you happen to know what's the alternative name for imposter syndrome?
It's the you're not good enough syndrome.
You suck. You're a cheater. You're a fraud.
You're just a result of a lucky coincidence. Everything that
you achieved is due to sheer luck. And basically,
if anybody revealed you,
you would be considered a fraud and sent to an exile,
removed from the tribe.
And basically, that creates feelings of anxiousness, of fear,
of self doubt. That's pretty much the
imposter syndrome 101.
Now, the best way to
deal with anything, like to deal with any unknown enemy,
is to learn more about it. And that's pretty much
where I see my job today. My job is to tell
you a bit more about what imposters syndrome
is, how it affects us, and what are
some effective techniques for dealing with imposters syndrome
itself. Now, one bigger
issue than the syndrome itself is the fact
that so many of us are not even aware of it. So many
of us have no idea that it exists at all. And I
generally think that's stupid. And it's stupid because just
by learning more about it or just by educating yourself, you could get yourself way
more prepared. And once the enemy attacks, and trust
me, imposters syndrome is always there. It's always waiting
for an opportunity to attack. So once it does attack,
by being prepared, you can actually have your defense prepared up front.
And that's way better than being attacked by an unknown enemy and
going into a state of complete chaos and kind of running for
your life, which is what you do when something unknown attacks
you. Now, why is it called fighting the syndrome?
Well, the thing is that from my
findings and from spending a lot of time in therapy,
what I came to learn is that it
seems that you're never able to actually overcome the imposters syndrome. Like, get completely
rid of it, like, to conquer it. And it's especially true
if you go and read about some successful people, and if you read
their autobiographies or biographies and assuming they
are honest, what you usually learn is that so many
of them are dealing with the exact same issues of
fear, doubt, you're not good enough, whatever. But it's just,
like, tenfold. The more successful you are, the more of these feelings
you have. So you can't really conquer it,
but you can learn some techniques and tactics for fighting it.
And that's exactly what I will be talking about.
Now, before we jump into what,
how, whatever, I'd like to share a very recent example that
I shared on my Twitter. So I let
the image speak for itself.
It's quite an irony, I know, but just
by preparing this presentation, I has having one of the most massive,
ever biggest attacks of imposter syndrome.
Are you sure that you know about it? Are you sure that you can prepare
enough for it? Are you sure that you know what you're talking about?
What if everybody realizes that you actually have no idea? Maybe you haven't spent
enough time. Maybe you haven't learned enough. All those feelings
of self doubt and questioning yourself and
pretty much being insecure about yourself, they all rise to the top.
And it literally happened just by preparing this presentation about fighting
the imposter syndrome. And another example thats,
I can't say it's recent, but it's more of a recurring problem,
is maybe some of you know,
maybe some don't. But for a while, for two years now,
I've been running a personal blog where I write everything
from programming to mental health to some general
life thoughts. And what's funny about it
is that I would, like, spend hours or
days and sometimes even weeks writing and then editing
and rewriting and thinking about the article.
And the moment I publish
it, it. I would
feel a small amount of excitement the moment I publish
it. But then, God forbid if it generated
some success or some positive feedback, whatever, I would get excited
initially. But then my first next thought would be,
what I'm going to do next. How am I going to repeat this success?
How am I going to do this again? I'll never be able to do this
again. This was just a lucky coincidence, and I'll
never be able to do this again. And what do I do now?
Maybe I should have waited.
All those stupid feelings of I'm not good enough.
Doubting myself, questioning myself.
So, as you can see, you never actually get rid of it.
And there is a but obviously, the good thing is that you
can learn to deal with it. And most importantly,
you can learn how to recognize the patterns,
because impulse syndrome comes in specific patterns.
And by recognizing those patterns, you can say, oh, okay, I see
what this is. I see what this is all about. And usually it
can be actually an indicator that you're on a good path,
because you get those feelings of questioning
yourself only when you are about to leave your comfort zone
or when you're leaving your comfort zone. But the moment you leave it, they actually
disappear. So it's actually just a signal that you are about to leave
your comfort zone, which is usually a good thing, because you do want
to leave that zone. Now, sometimes those feelings can be paralyzing.
I know, but you just have to practice and
push yourself pretty much, but we'll get to that eventually.
Now,
before going into the details, I'd also like to share a personal
story of mine. And the reason why I want to share
this story is because so
many of us, especially in software engineering, so many of us actually
go through some same issues, some same problems,
questions, fears, anxieties,
frustrations, whatever. And yet we never share them.
This is really funny. We never share these findings with others,
and by not sharing them, we feel kind of isolated.
We are the only ones going through this, and the feelings of
isolation leads to even more frustration or whatever.
So whatever the initial feeling was, it just gets emphasized
and the effects
increase just by the fact that you're feeling that you're the only one
going through this. So what
I'm hoping to do is to show you that you're not the only one
and not that you're not the only one. But probably by
hearing this story, you might recognize some of the pet thats you are
having yourself as well.
Now, the story begins probably
around ten years ago or so. Now,
I was doing programming since I was six or whatever. So I just loved
it. I did it my whole life. And just by the sheer fact that
I was doing a lot of it, I sort of became good at it.
And eventually somebody wanted to pay me to do it, which was like
a win win. Somebody was paying me to do something thats I would be doing
in a free time anyway. Now,
when you're investing a lot of time and effort and
energy into something that you're pretty much passionate about, you usually get
results, and you usually get good results. Pretty much.
So I was advancing my career pretty fast,
and by my early to mid 20s,
sort of, I was already a team lead. Well, a lead developer,
a team lead, whatever. And I'm not sure
you could probably call it either the best or worst thing that happened
to me. It's the best thing because obviously my
achievements were recognized. But it could be one of
the worst things because I had no idea what I was doing by
having this imposter syndrome, which I wasn't even aware of.
One of the huge issues with a lot
of things is not being able to name them, because once you can name something,
you can also solve it. But I have no idea what imposters syndrome was.
So I was feeling like I don't deserve this position.
I ended up in this position by a sheer luck, especially given
the fact that I was leading a team of people who were almost double age
of mine, well, not double, but at least ten years older than
me. So I was like, okay, I'm bossing people who are way
more experienced than myself. So I assumed it was a
lucky coincidence, and I had to prove myself.
Obviously, it wasn't enough that I ended up there. I actually felt
like, now I need to prove myself, which is stupid, because I already proved by
the fact that I ended up there. But anyway,
so I started putting crazy long hours into work you
wouldn't believe, to which point, crazy like I would work like ten or 12 hours
a day. And what I also didn't
know at the time, which is something that you should probably learn,
is that maybe you
haven't heard of it, but there is this point of diminishing returns, because usually
you invest some time and work and you get results back.
It's linear, pretty much like, the more work
you put, the more results you get. But there comes this point
of diminishing returns where you actually
start putting more effort, but the results, like the productivity starts falling
down. And I had no idea about it because young
experiences, pretty energetic. So I had no idea about it.
So I noticed my productivity started to drop.
And obviously this inner voice,
the biggest characteristic of imposter syndrome, just increased
its volume, turned the knob to
the right completely, and it just made me feel more
insecure about myself. So I did the only thing that I could do,
that I only knew how to do, and that was putting more work.
So I started putting even more work into that. And by putting
more work, I actually got even worse results.
And this came to a point which
I remember quite clearly. And I
woke up one morning and I
literally felt physically sick about the sheer thought of going to the office
for one more day. Just by thinking about going
to the office and spending one more day there
talking to my boss, I was having
this vomit reflex, this nausea, this pain,
like a physical pain, just by thinking about the office.
And what
I would learn later is thats what I would learn in
the therapy where I eventually ended up, is that there
exists a concept called mental depth,
which is kind of similar to tech depth,
but you just accumulate it by doing intellectual
work and for example, programming, obviously,
or writing or whatever. Whenever you involve your mind
into something like your intellect, you are collecting this
mental depth. And just like with the tech depth, if you're not maintaining
it properly, it threatens to danger
your mental base and eventually to make
it unusable. So some of the common manifestations that
some of you surely know about them are starting to
think that your boss is a dick.
Your organization is a perfect example of a lack of
organization. Management is only thinking.
Management is making stupid decisions, and if they only listen to you or to
developments, things would be different. Then you start thinking that grass is
probably greener on the other side, and things like that. Those are some common
manifestations of mental depth, which I had no idea about.
And as I said, if you keep accumulating
this depth, it eventually threatens to
lead to a burnout, which is pretty much what happened to myself.
And yet again, I don't even think that the
term burnout was even popular at the time. So I
had no idea about it. So I kept accumulating this
debt, which obviously culminated with me waking up one morning
and feeling like I'd rather
die than go to the office for one more day, honestly speaking.
And I can't really remember what I did. Like,
did I go or not? But what I clearly remember that soon
after that, I quit my job. I even broke up with
my long term girlfriend. I bought a motorcycle. I was
kind of having this assumption that I haven't
lived my life, that my work was limiting myself.
I wanted to be a playboy. I wanted to party,
live the life, which kind of, I did,
actually. For a couple of months. I was partying the whole time, driving my motorcycle,
living a bit of locker, pretty much, and that
was cool for a while. But obviously it wasn't
a cause. It was just one of the manifestations of burnout,
like, getting rid of the chains. And I wanted to do everything all
of a sudden. And this
lasted for a couple of months. And then I started waking up
again. And there's nothing crazy about these mornings, apparently.
I started waking up again, and I would wake up super
excited, like, yeah, let's rock the day. Let's do everything,
whatever. And then by the afternoon,
I would be like, my mood would completely plummet.
I would be like, what's the point of everything?
Why am I doing thats? Why did I quit?
Whatever. And then by the evening again,
my mood would completely rock it again. It was completely crazy.
I would be like, yeah, let's go, let's go, let's drink, let's party,
whatever. All those kinds of stupid things and this stuff that's always
first. But over time, these oscillations actually started
getting more and more crazy. And it
came to a point again where I was literally feeling like,
I just can't go through one more day like this, honestly speaking.
And the funny thing about these intense emotions
is that about these thoughts and
memories of intense emotions is thats every time you
actually remember them, you can pretty much relieve them. So every
time I share this story, I kind of relieve it. And it's
still the same intensity every single time. It's pretty much the same
intensity as on the first days. So this is generally a funny thing
about mind itself.
So I eventually ended up,
like my friend suggested, that maybe I should seek professional
assistance. And I ended up in a therapy thinking
that I'm going to solve just this single issue
of oscillating mood, whatever,
and this would actually convert into seven years, well over seven years of
active therapy. And I can definitely tell you,
going to a therapy was one of the best things
ever I did for my personal life, my relationships and my career,
pretty much because years there were times when there
wasn't much progress. But overall I think it pushed me to do something
that some things that I would never even consider doing because of
the self doubt. So obviously
I learned that what was happening to me was a burnout,
quite a massive one. And honestly speaking, if you never felt this,
like, if you never felt physically sick about going to a job,
I would absolutely advise you to do everything to prevent thats
because the feeling is awful. What I also learned has
that a lot of us, especially in software engineering or
in any kind of art, I would pretty much
say like anybody doing any kind of art
creational work, could suffer from
this imposters syndrome and from perfectionism.
Perfectionism is a really big thing among developers.
And I'll give you a really quick self test to test if
you have the perfectionist. Thats so just think about
it. Have you ever brought a piece of code that
was perfectly solving the problem
that it was supposed to solve, that was done
in time, whatever. And yet, since you haven't hit the deadline, you actually decided
to rewrite it. And you kept rewriting it until you hit
the deadline. If this ever happened to you, and I'm
pretty sure that at least for most of you did, you most
certainly have at least perfectionist traits,
if not complete perfectionism. And this could be good.
Perfectionism could be good because it
forces you to improve yourself. But on the other hand, it can
be really exhausting because you never can finish the things
and it can be really a burden on your mind.
And finally, obviously, the third thing I learned is that there
is this concept of imposter syndrome,
which I had no idea about and which is pretty much what I'm
going to cover now, right now.
Funny thing about imposters syndrome itself
is that the term was coined
somewhere in late seventy s.
It was probably known before, but the official term was introduced in
late seventy s. And it was actually a result
of a study that was run with
around 150 highly successful women, believe it
or not. And what you have to understand is these
are the women who are highly successful in their work. They were
highly accomplished. They were recognized for their successes,
and yet by interviewing and
studying how they feel, all of them
on a higher or a lower scale, but all of them express some
feelings of self doubt, feeling like imposters,
feeling like frauds, feeling like they're all
having to wear a mask the whole day. And if they remove this
mask,
pretty much everybody would reveal what kind of frauds they are and things like
that. And this is really funny,
because obviously they were highly respected
for what they were doing, and yet they had complete feelings of
self doubt, which just obviously tells you that no
matter how successful you are, well, actually, the more successful you are,
the more intense feelings of imposter are.
Now, the study later has expanded and it
was concluded that it's completely gender neutral.
So it doesn't have anything to do with genders. Everybody have these feelings. And as
I said, the more successful you are,
the more intense these emotions and feelings of imposter
are. Now,
just in case you can't even identify it, I'll give you some ideas
of what some of the feelings of imposter
could be. So, for example, one very common
example that I keep hearing and seeing and feeling occasionally
is the job change. So many of us advance
through our career, especially in the same company, and yet
we sometimes tend to stay in the same company because we
feel thats we feel pretty much lucky,
right? And we are feeling that our successes are due to the
fact that we have been here for a long time, that if
you tried changing the job, it would turn out that we are not as good
as we think and stuff like that. So what I would like
to encourage you now is to go to a discord channel like
hashtag python. And I'd like you to give it a quick
thought, like what are some feelings of imposters
that you've experiences? Try to identify them. Try to write about
them. I encourage you to write about them because by sharing,
we should help others feel the same. And while you are doing that, I'll get
a quick sip of water, if you don't mind.
I had to get a sip of coffee as well.
So I hope you brought some things.
If not, feel free to write them at any time during this presentation.
I will be more than happy to discuss it with you once
the presentation is done.
Apologies. So a
natural question would become like, okay, we all have
it, we all feel it, but why?
What is the reason that we have these thoughts, right? And what
I came to learn and conclude,
both through therapy and through reading
and through doing some thinking and writing, obviously, is that,
well, this is not my conclusion, but most of the things and most of the
manifestations of human beings are due to evolution,
believe it or not, pretty much lots of stuff
is all about making you survive and reproduce. And some
of you don't like it, I understand, but that's how it
seems to be. Now, what's the use of
feeling like a fraud, right? What's the use of feeling
paralyzed? To do anything, to move, to change job, to change
a partner, to start something new? Right? What could be a
benefit to this? What could be a benefit to feeling like a fraud?
And I'll give you sort of a counterexample,
which I found really interesting. There was a
study,
lab study, controlled lab study
done in a lab mice. I don't really know the name of
the study, but I know that it happened run with a lab
mice. And they pretty much put electrodes to
brains of mice. And they wanted to see what happens when
they stimulated the brain parts that are in charge of releasing
dopamine, the neurotransmitter thats eventually
makes you feel good about, makes you feel satisfied, happy, whatever.
So they run this study, and they made these mice
by external stimulation, obviously, by using the currents to
actually stimulate their brain, they made them feel good all the time.
They made them feel happy and satisfied all the time.
And you might be surprised to
years that most or all of these
mice thats felt good and happy and satisfied
all the time, eventually died from starvation.
Like all of them died from starvation because just by feeling good all the time,
they didn't have a need to actually go and search for the food, or to
go and reproduce, or to go find the food, whatever. They just
felt good and they starved themselves to death.
Which could be, on one hand,
could be really weird to hear, because we all think
that we are all aiming towards this zen like
feeling whatever, which is stupid, to be honest, but that's a different story.
But this should tell you that the
aim should not be to feel good all the time.
And the reason why you feel pain
and doubt and whatever is. It's a
complex process, but most of it is actually a natural mechanism to make
you move. And that's what I want you.
If there is one thing thats I want you to get out of this presentation
is that you
really need to change your perspective about all those,
what we call negative emotions like imposter syndrome after all,
because they are others, to actually
push you to change or to push you to
keep doing something, whatever. Because feeling of a hunger actually
pushes you to go find the food so that you don't die from starvation.
So most of the time, if you feel like an imposter in your
career, that's most likely a signal that you're doing a
good job, but you're interpreting it wrongly because
if you sucked at your job, you wouldn't feel like a fraud, right? Or a
cheater or whatever. So you're most likely feeling like sucker
because you're actually good at your job. So next time
you feel the imposters syndrome and next time you identify this inner voice asking
you like, are you sure about thats? Or are you sure that's good?
Or are you sure that you can change the job or break up
or start a new relationship, wherever thats exactly means.
That means that you are about to move out from your comfort zone.
And every time you move out of your comfort zone, that's actually a
good thing. Trust me. Now one
might ask, and rightfully so, but what if I'm paralyzed
by these thoughts, right? What if I'm completely paralyzed
by these thoughts of impulses that I can't even move?
So I obviously see a signal that what I want to do
is good, but what if I can't make thats move, right?
And that's exactly what you should.
Well, that's exactly what I'm going
to talk about now. Like some of the techniques that you can use,
and by using them, you should be able to better
approach the issue, obviously. But in the worst case, you should always seek a therapy,
right? Like a professional assistance. So let's
talk about the imposter syndrome fighting tools. Now,
the first tool in our toolbox
is the easiest one, believe it or not, and it's acknowledgment.
So what I really want you to acknowledge is that
we all have it. We all had it and we will
all have it forever. So imposters syndrome is not going anywhere.
It's others. It will be with you. And you should really treat it
as a mechanism that tells you whether you are on a more
or less righteous path or not. So acknowledge it.
Everybody has it. Everybody lives with it. So you're
not isolated. We are all there. And I'm really hoping that some of
you shared something on the Discord channel. If not, now's the time
to show everybody that we are in the same boat, right? So,
acknowledgement. The next thing which I
really found useful and comforting is reading
biographies or autobiographies because nobody really
reads biographies or writes biographies for that
purpose, about the people who were unsuccessful or know, like your average
Joe from the neighborhood. So biographies are usually written about people
who actually did something like good or bad doesn't matter,
but they did something which was worth sharing.
And what you will learn if you read at least
honest biographies. Is that all? I won't say some.
I'll say like, well,
99.99% of these people actually
felt quite intense feelings of impulsive,
felt like frauds, like whatever they all did.
The only thing that distinguishes them
is how they dealt with it, which are some techniques.
Some of them use some positive things, some use negative things like alcohol
and stuff. But overall they all felt it and they all were
searching and using some techniques to fight with it.
Now, the technique that I
personally think is most useful and yet
most difficult to implement is discipline.
Believe it or not, discipline, from my point of view,
is absolutely the number one tool for beating
any procrastination, any laziness, any feelings of
imposter. And it's actually really simple. And I'll give you
a perfect example. So whenever I'm about to start
writing new article, for example,
or whenever I'm about to involve myself
in fixing some incident or whatever, like anything
that is unknown to myself,
whenever I think about going that
route, involving myself in it, I would feel like,
can I do it? Should I do it? And there's this procrastination
and feelings of doubt. Whatever, discipline is
the best antidote. Because just by committing yourself to doing it daily,
regularly, like for example, I'm going to write every day from 09:00 a.m.
To 10:00 a.m. I'm going to fix incidents every single day from
12:00 p.m. To 02:00 p.m.. Whatever. Just by being disciplined
and making yourself committed to it, you actually don't like
yes, you will feel these feelings of imposter, but still you just have to do
it. It's like going to a job.
You don't have to feel like doing it, you just have to do it.
That's pretty much. So it's easier said. Thats done.
I agree. But you should really consider it has making yourself
disciplined. So it's not about becoming motivated, it's about being
disciplined. So commit yourself to, if it's a job change,
commit yourself to every single day from, I don't know,
06:00 p.m. To 07:00 p.m. I will send one job application
or if it's about writing every day from 06:00
p.m. To 07:00 p.m. I'm going to write whatever it is, but I'm going to
write even if it's just bullshit, I'm still going to write it from
06:00 p.m. To 07:00 p.m. And trust me, the results are amazing just
by being disciplined about thats. Now a
next tool which is quite underappreciated and yet
awesome is occasionally reviewing your successes.
And this is really funny because we sometimes tend
to forget the good things that we achieved and we
always focus on things that we haven't achieved, which is good
because it keeps pushing you to do more. But on the other hand it's
bad because sometimes you just completely forget what you achieved
at all and you really sometimes need to feel good about
what you already achieved. So one
of the things that I'm doing is I used to
journal Daily but I slowed
it down a bit. So I'm journaling maybe a couple of couple of times a
week. I'm using by the way, day one application
which is amazing. It's a free app, it's an awesome tool for journaling.
But point is, just occasionally write good things that
you achieved. Like today, I don't know, brought this
or I sent this many applications or I fixed this many incidents
or bugs, whatever. Just write down your successes and
schedule time like once a month,
once a quarter, whatever. Schedule time to actually review
your successes. Because you would be surprised how much you
are achieving and how much you're forgetting that you are achieving because you're
focusing what you haven't achieved yet.
And another one,
almost the last technique, the last but
not the least pretty much is doing something that you suck at
honestly. And this is definitely one that's
easier written than done. But what's really interesting about
doing things thats we suck at is
seeing how we improve. I'll give you an example.
I wrote an article about this actually with the same name, like do something
that you suck at. And I took it as a challenge to try playing
guitar and I
always did suck. And just by assuming that I suck,
I never did it again. But I wanted to try playing guitar again.
And what is funny is that I has obviously all these feelings about
I will never learn it, I will never be able to do it whatever.
And that's still true. But what's really funny is when you see
yourself having these feelings of doubt, of anxiousness,
of questioning yourself, and yet when you do it and
when you see yourself improve, like go from .0 point
of no results to points of some results, and when
you observe that you still have these same feelings of imposter,
you can actually feel thats no matter, you can improve.
That's when you can feel great about it and the imposter feelings will still
be there. So I think thats one of the best antidotes
for generally beating anything is doing
things that you think you suck at. You get
those beginner results and you learn a lot about yourself, which you
probably forgot from the time that you were a kid. So take it
as a challenge and if you feel brave enough,
write it to a python channel, do something that you suck
at and tell us what it is. And finally, obviously there is
just no replacement for the ultimate king of fighting
the imposters or anything. That's therapy. So as I said, I highly suggest
it. I've been doing rational emotional behavior
therapy like crept ive also years positive
experiences with gestalt,
psychodrama and I don't know what there is, but whatever
it is, give it a shot and if you can afford it, it can
be one of the best things that you did for yourself recently.
Just take my word for it. And we
pretty much came to the end. I just like to share
a couple of books in case you are not feeling like doing
something that you suck at or going for a therapy. So I have four
books here. I would obviously suggest a lot more,
but these
four are nitpicks, so to say. So, first one is tools of
titans by Tim Ferriss. It's a summary of,
I don't know, he interviewed a bunch of people, but this is a summary
of, I think 150 or 100 people, highly successful
people. And he summarized pretty much the interview with
their daily rituals, how they go through life,
how they handle the feelings of imposters. So just by seeing some
people that you definitely heard or know about,
how they deal with it and what they do, I think it's pretty
powerful thing to have
in your toolbox. Second book, extreme ownership.
Amazing book about owing everything that you
do pretty much from how you dress to how you lead the team.
Absolutely amazing book. Changed a lot of my perspectives and gave me
some really amazing tools. So highly suggested give it a shot.
Amazing book. If you're feeling for something more
complex and more in depth. There is just no
replacement for thinking fast and slow. It's just
a bible, literally a Bible. And pretty complex book
about how we feel and how we process
things and how we make conclusions and how
to say if you engross yourself in this book,
what you will get to learn is that our
thinking process is just incredibly flawed and
there are just some crazy things that you just won't believe but and yet
they happen again. Don't underestimate this book. It's really complex book.
It took me around four months, I think, to read it and it deserves
time and processing. So take it in a bite sized
session, so to say. And finally,
if you're a person who struggles with discipline or
forming habits or moving from a .0 to point
to moving, overcoming that static
motion, whatever, getting that initial
movement, others is just no replacement for atomic habits.
It's an amazing book. It tells you how habits
are created and what are some techniques
that you can do to help yourself create
some if you don't have them already. So four books,
absolutely highly recommended by myself and many people around
me. Go check them on Goodreads, go purchase them and let
me know what you think. And with that,
I'd like to thank you very much for
watching this, for attending this conference. It was
an amazing pleasure to talk about this.
And since this is the first time I'm doing this lecture about this
topic, you can find this QR code on the
right hand side of the screen. If you scan it with your
mobile phone, it will take you to a Google form where it's
like a 1 minute survey.
You would do me an amazing favor if you let me know how I
did, what you think about the presentation and what are some of the
things that I could improve. High appreciate
it. I would really be thankful if you do it
and that's it. I'll join you on the
Discord channel and let's discuss more
if there is anything more to be discussed. Thank you very much and see ya.
Bye.