Hi everyone, my name is Alvarivas and today
I'm going to talk to you about elastic compute
with Salesforce functions.
I am a develop developer advocate at Salesforce
and here you have my contact details in case
that you want to ask me anything later or to contact
me later.
This is a slide that I need to include because I am a Salesforce
employee, which just means that as Salesforce
is a publicly traded company, you should make
purchasing decisions based on the functionality that is currently
available. And with that,
let's start talking about functions.
But what is a function?
A function is a short lived
executable that is invoked on
demand. Functions are serverless,
which means that developers can build applications
without having to manage infrastructure or
servers, and this reduces a lot the operational
costs. Functions are also
elastic, which means that they will scale,
taking more resources or less resources
as needed based on demand.
And what are Salesforce functions?
Salesforce functions is a feature that we have created
in Salesforce to provide functions as a
service. In case
that you don't know what Salesforce is, I'm going to
give you a quick introduction. So Salesforce
obviously is the name of a company, but also is a name for
a CRM, a CRM that offers products
for managing your relationships with
your customers and clients, such as an application for
sales, another one for service, for customer service,
another one for marketing, for commerce
and for much more. But Salesforce,
on top of being a CRM, is also an application
development platform. If you want to
build applications on top of Salesforce,
you can do that two ways. You can use low
code tools or you can use code.
I am a Salesforce developer, so I normally use code.
The technologies that you can use to build applications
with code in the platform are JavaScript.
For the front end we use JavaScript and web
components based framework called Lightning
web components. And for the backend we
have historically used Apex.
Apex is an object oriented language very
similar to Java and it's been there from the beginning.
But for the backend since November
last year, we are also able to develop Salesforce
functions, right? So as I mentioned
before, a Salesforce function is a short
lived on purpose executable that is
going to be invoked. Star and Phoenix,
right? They are going to be invoked and run
in a serverless way in which we are not going to
need to manage the infrastructure that's behind
the scenes. And they are going to be elastic,
which means that they are going to scale, taking more or
less resources depending on the demand.
What else is special about Salesforce
functions? Well, first of all,
Salesforce functions run within the
Salesforce trusted boundary. This means
that from a function you are going to be able to work with Salesforce
data, Salesforce records as your accounts
or your leads, or whatever data you are storing
in Salesforce, you are going to be able to
work with those records in your function and then you
are going to be able to send that data back to
Salesforce. If you wanted to do some updates
or insert some new data, whatever, right?
This is possible thanks to an SDK that we
use within the function and everything.
This is very important. Everything runs within the
Salesforce trusted infrastructure. Your data never goes
out from Salesforce, which means that it's going to be
safe. And third,
I wanted to mention the different languages in
which you can write Salesforce functions, because on
the platform we only had apex in the past,
but now with Salesforce functions you can write
that code, the code that a function will run
in JavaScript and Java for now, but we
are also working in supporting more
languages in the future.
Now I want to talk a little bit about the open
source technologies that we have used to
build the feature to build Salesforce functions.
First of all, we are using kubernetes.
Kubernetes is an open source
container orchestration engine that
you can use to deploy,
scale and manage your applications
automatically, right? When they are containerized
applications. We are also using cloud
native buildpacks. Cloud native buildpacks is
a technology that allows you to transform
your application source code into a containerized
application that then can run in any cloud,
in our case a Kubernetes infrastructure.
And finally, I wanted to mention cloud events.
Cloud events is not really a technology, it's more a specification,
right? But this specification will help
you standardize the way in which we
describe event data, and that way
we will improve and standardize how
systems and servers communicate this event
data. So this specification, we are following it
also in Salesforce function. Now let's
take a look at a demo in which I'm going to show you the anatomy
of a salesforce function. So here I
have a set of functions that I have created
both in Java and JavaScript. Let's take a look at a
function in JavaScript. This function here as it is
a node function, the entry point will
be the index js file.
In this file, first we are reading
a JSON. This JSON contains thousands
of records that correspond to schools,
and for each school we have the latitude and longitude.
Then we have the definition of the function.
A function is an async function that
you define in JavaScript that receives three parameters.
It receives the event parameter, context parameter
and logger parameter. The event parameter
contains the payload with which the function has
been invoked. The context parameter is
the way in which we can link back to salesforce.
If we want to do a query, for instance to retrieve salesforce
records, we are going to do that through the context parameter.
And finally the logger parameter helps us
logging. For instance, if we want to drop our
logs into a log drain, we can do that by configuring
the lower parameter.
So what does this function do? This function
receives in its payload, in the payload
with which it is invoked, a latitude
and a longitude. Then the function is going to
compute, it's going to take a look at the JSON file and it's
going to compute which are the five
closest schools to the latitude and longitude
provided. This is a compute intensive
operation. That is the reason we
decided to create a salesforce function instead of
doing this calculation in apex.
Finally, the function returns the calculated
schools, those schools that are more closer.
Let's take a look at the same function but
written in Java. This is a
function we can open the entry point here
and as you can see the
function is really similar. We need
to override an apply method that
receives as a parameter the event and the context,
same as it happened with the Javascript function.
In this case the logger is not received as a parameter
because it's a log for j instance.
Then in the function we can
perform exactly the same calculations but written
in Java. Great. So now that
you know how a function looks like, let's take
a look at the different ways in which you can
invoked a salesforce function.
Functions need to be invoked from
apex. You can invoke them synchronously
or asynchronously. At the moment this
is the only way in which you can invoke them,
but we are planning to have other entry points
in the future. Then on the platform you can
create a lining web component or a piece
of UI with a low code tool that invokes that
apex code. This is what this screenshot represents.
So now let's take a look at a demo in
which we will see how to invoke a salesforce function.
So, same as we had our functions folder here,
which is what you deploy to your compute environment,
we have another folder that contains all the code that
is deployed to Salesforce. In that
folder you are going to find all your apex classes.
So let's open up this apex class in which
we are invoking the process large data
function. First of all notice
that apex classes are very similar
to Java classes. You have classes, you have methods
that can be static, that have a return value and
receive a parameter. I mentioned in this
so that you have an idea of the syntax of
the language, and then in the body of the method you
can invoke the function. If you invoke
the function synchronously, what you do is that you first
instantiate the function using the name of
the project and the name of the function. Then you
can invoked the function this way, calling the
invoke method and passing in a payload.
In our case, the payload will contain the latitude and
longitude with which we want to compare those
schools, and then we
will receive a result when the
invocation finishes. In the case of
invoking your function asynchronously, you just move
this last part to a callback method that will execute
once the function finishes.
Fantastic. So now let me give you some
information so that you can get started with Salesforce
functions. First of all, I wanted to share
the link to the developer guide. You will find
the documentation at SFDC co functions
guide and there you will find all the prerequisites
and the guides that
will show you how to get started. One of the prerequisites
is to install the Salesforce CLI.
This is a command line tool that we use in Salesforce
to manage how we deploy and retrieve
metadata from our Salesforce instances
that we call organizations. And we also use
the Salesforce CLI to work with Salesforce functions.
I also recommend you to use vs code
as an ide because we have a set
of extensions that we help you with
Salesforce development in general. We have a portion of
these extensions that is meant to help you
write salesforce functions and that's
why we normally use vs code with this extension
installed. And also I wanted to
tell you that trying out Salesforce is free and
trying out Salesforce functions is also
free. To ask for a developer
in which functions is enabled. You can go to
this URL here, functions,
salesforce.com signapps
and there you are going to be able to request an
environment and to play with functions for free.
So now let's take a look at how to use the
Salesforce CLI to deploy a salesforce function.
So the first thing that we need to do to deploy a
salesforce function is to create a scratch
or a scratch or is an ephemeral
development environment that gets associated
with your trial or we are creating a scratch
or called functions or.
Fantastic. The next thing that we need to do is to
create a compute environment a
compute environment is a secure salesforce managed infrastructure
which is different from your salesforce.org.
This is where functions are deployed to and run
in. This is the infrastructure that is built with cloud native
build packs and kubernetes. The deploy
process uses changes tracked in git to
know what to deploy. This is similar to how Heroku
works. So let's commit our changes to a git repo.
Great, so now we
can write the Salesforce CLI command to
deploy functions to our compute environment.
For that we will write sf deploy functions
minus o and the name of the scratcher
to which you have linked your compute environment.
As this is going to take a while, let's take a look
at an organization which is linked to a compute
environment in which I already deployed the function
I created. Here some implementation examples
this is aligning web component. Remember this is our framework
for front end development. And from the lining web component you
can invoke the function passing in a
number of results that the function should return.
So let's invoke the function and see
the results. The function is
taking my current latitude and longitude and
it's returning the ten closest schools
in the JSON file.
Great, so if I go back to vs code we can see
that the function has been correctly deployed.
In this demo, I decided to deploy the function because
I wanted to show you the final result when we
invoke the function from the salesforce organization.
However, bear in mind that you can also run
functions locally. This is very useful
at the time of testing and development.
All the code that we have seen today is public.
You can find the functions recipes sample app@GitHub.com
trailheadapps functions recipes and there
you will find many more sample apps that will help
you get started with Salesforce development.
To finalize, I want to share some resources to
summarize really the resources that I have shared
along the talk. First of all, you have the documentation,
the developer guide. Take a look at it to get started.
You also have the sign up page in
which you will be able to request a trial or
for free to try out Salesforce functions.
Also, I leave you here again the link to the
sample app that we created to help you get started with
functions functions recipes and the
last link is a trailhead module called
Discover Salesforce functions Trailhead
is our tutorized learning platform
in which you are going to find more than 1000
modules to learn Salesforce in general and also Salesforce
development. Finally, I want
to share the different ways in which you can connect with
us. You can find us at developer
salesforce.com. We have there a blog,
a podcast and all the documentation for developers.
You can also follow us on Twitter at
salesforce and you can also follow us on
Facebook, YouTube and LinkedIn. We publish
videos on YouTube regularly. We do live streaming
and if you subscribe to the channel and click on the
bell, you will receive notifications about those videos.
Thank you so much and I
hope that you enjoyed my talk at least a little bit.
Have a good day.