It. Welcome to this session where I'll talk as
mentioned about threats hunting and how basically
you can automate that. And I'm saying stay ahead of the game,
just as sort of a fun title, but obviously it has a
meaning. You somehow need to stay ahead of hackers.
It's obviously not a game, but they're getting smarter and smarter every
day. And they have basically they can do a million attempts
to hack you, but they only need one to succeed. You need
to stop all of them or you'll have a
compromise. So I'm going to teach you in this session
a little bit more how to proactively hunt for
threats. So as mentioned, my name Christopher van der made.
I'm based out of the Netherlands and I'm a developer advocate security.
If you have any questions, please drop them in. I'll also pause
here and there during the session to
make sure that all of them are answered.
So before I start, I would
like to make a statement, and that is that there's
simply too much information out there.
And that is obviously quite a broad statement.
But I'm meaning specifically threats
intelligence. So information about new threats
that might be going on, new malware campaigns,
and specifically as audience, I mean, security operations
center analysts. So there's literally too much information
to consciously process. So therefore
we need to automate as much of this analysis
and enrichment so that your analysts,
human beings, only have to look at the things that
actually matter. So hopefully at the end of this session,
this statement will make more sense
and probably you'll already agree with me.
All right, so the agenda for today?
Yeah, first of all, I'll do a quick introduction into threats
hunting. I'll then do an introduction into
Securex and threats response, which will be
basically main topics that I'll talk about today.
I'll then talk about two use cases,
one using Twitter, the other one using Talos blogs,
but also more as source of Fred
intel. And it will make a little bit more sense as we go along.
And obviously we'll finish off with a conclusion
and I'll save some time if there are any questions for at the end there.
So the introduction to fret hunting, probably if you
ask five different people what fret hunting is, they'll all
say something different. But I think
everyone will agree that fret hunting usually involves
proactively hunting for something. So that means you're not
reacting, but you're proactively going out and
looking for threats instead of waiting until an alert
pops up. So there is actually a very
smart person that
wrote basically an article about fret
hunting. I would definitely recommend checking it out. And I'm just
using this as an example because he had a pretty good threats
hunting loop, which I thought was quite interesting.
And this is basically a continuous process which you will
should at least be doing at all times if you
have a good security operations center.
And I have to say, I'm a developer advocate right
now. Before I was five years in the field as
a consulting systems engineer, and I
did not get in contact with a lot of customers that really
had a very good security operations center because
people are scarce, they are expensive because they are scarce.
And some people do have the money but just can't find them.
So basically what you should be doing is you
should create hypotheses. For example,
a hypotheses could be,
I have the feeling we are attacked by a certain type
of new malware campaign.
Well, next up, you go and investigate this malware campaign.
So you're going to see what tools and techniques did they use?
What kind of patterns can you uncover?
Finally, you'll start enriching and do
analysts. So basically, your investigation so far, you're going
to test against your own data and global data
to see if you can find any correlations. And with
that information, you can then either confirm or deny
your hypotheses. Now, especially that
part,
this part, the analytics part, and the enrichment
part specifically, you can do a lot of automated
methods here. And during this session today,
I'm going to tell you a couple of them, but obviously there
are way more that we can cover. So this
is also quite interesting. In that same article
about fret hunting, the writer or the
author talks about different levels that you might have
in maturity of threats hunting.
And basically, if you look at level zero,
relies primarily on automated
alerting, little or no data connections.
So basically this means you install firewall and you just wait
until an alert pops up. Level four,
if you see that,
level four actually says that a
majority of the successful data analysis procedures are automated.
And I really like that word of automation of
the data analysis. And actually
doing data analysts in
an automated way with tools like Securex is actually not
that hard. So getting from level zero to four
obviously takes quite some governance
and right procedures and the right people, but you can
actually take some stuff from level four quite easily.
Now just finally, last couple of
slides on fret hunting here. I mentioned this in the beginning
already. I see like two types of threat hunting.
You have on demand hunting, which is basically more
reactive. So something has happened,
something was triggered, and you go and do more research.
The other one is more automated, continuous hunting.
And that's what I'll show you two demos
of today. And that more resides
around taking in data and automatically cross
correlating this or cross referencing this against your
own data and see if youve might have
compromises in your organization.
Now this is also interesting.
This is the pyramid of pain. If you google the pyramid of pain,
well, maybe add cybersecurity. I'm not sure what else you'll find
if you google the pyramid of pain, but you'll find this
pyramid. And basically they talk about this
is how you can hurt a hacker. So if you
look at the bottom, you see hash values and IP addresses.
For a hacker, it is like the most trivial thing ever.
If their malware file is found
by security systems, and that file
hash is basically added to a block list
somewhere, for example, talos also does this with our amp
infrastructure. It literally takes maybe one
click of a button in their comments, in their code,
of their malware, and the file hash will be different.
So people, if you understand how hashing algorithms work,
if you make minor changes, the file hash will change.
So if you find their file hash, they're like, okay,
fine, I'll just generate a new one. That's what we call polymorphic
malware, basically malware that can keep changing
so that it's difficult to detect.
Now, IP addresses, similar and domain names,
if you find these from a hacker, they can generate new domain names,
host their stuff on a different IP address. So still
quite simple and easy. If you really find out their network
and host artifacts, this starts to get annoying,
finding out their tools, their techniques, et center
and procedures. The last one, if you find
out what they're actually doing, how they operate.
Yeah, that's killing for hackers,
if you ask me.
These first four layers, you can probably automate
a lot of this stuff around here, finding these, blocking them,
et cetera, up in the chain. This probably requires
human interaction. So here you probably need to
get your analysts and let them analysts what is going on?
So we'll be talking mainly about the first
four layers first. And what we want to do is create bite
size chunks for your analysts so that they can do
the top two layers. So,
yeah, let's find out what we can do.
Now in this session, we will use two tools,
basically. Well, probably more, but two main tools.
One is Python, my favorite programming language
right now, which I switched to a
couple of years ago. Well, actually probably seven
or eight years ago, I switched to python from other languages.
And yeah, I prefer it a lot, and within Cisco we
use it a lot, so it makes sense to talk about it today.
The other one is Securex. Securex was launched,
well, specifically threats response was
launched a couple of years ago. Securex is basically now the
platform within our Cisco security portfolio.
And threats response is one of the applications or features
of Securex. But mind you, fret response
was there actually earlier. Now that we talked about
threats hunting, I want to dive a little bit more into Securex
and fret response. Just quick summary,
fret hunting. In my opinion, what we'll be
talking about today is more the continuous automate fret hunting.
And that means that you're proactively looking
for threats in your environment.
And yeah, the enrichment of data
and the cross referencing of data, we can very well
automate. And obviously we're going to use Curex
and threats response for it. So if you look at Securex,
I prefer not to use marketing slides. So I usually dive into
this slide.
Securex is an architecture. It's not really
a product. We actually offer it for free to customers.
So if you buy one Cisco security product, you get
Securex included. And it's basically an architecture
or a platform that contains multiple features.
First of all, you need to log in into the dashboard.
We do that with duo. You then have features
like threat response, Securex threat response, and Securex
orchestration. These are two big
applications within the Securex architecture.
For those that know, the orchestrator is actually
based on action orchestrator, which has now been
sort of internally acquired by the security business group
and it's now fully integrated into Securex. And this is
basically a low to no code orchestrator.
Threats response we'll talk about a little bit in more detail later.
But basically it allows youve to investigate
threats and respond to threats as well. So this is also that
response. You can also trigger orchestration
workflows from threat response. Now, on the right here
we see our Cisco products and we see important arrows
going back and forth. On the one hand we see local threat
intelligence, for example, this can be firewall logs that
we query from Securex. It can also be global
threat intelligence that we query for example from Talos or
AMP, advanced malware protection. But we can also
back and forth send response actions and triggers.
So basically we can
do read operations but also write operations if
you make it very simple. On the same hand, we can do that on the
left as well, with third party products as well.
So we don't just do it with Cisco, we do it with third party as
well. And yeah, we have a
ribbon framework, which is sort of a
pop up window that you have in Securex and now in the whole of Cisco's
secure portfolio. And it's basically you can cross
launch into other applications with the ribbon.
You can also cross launch into threats response
et center. So it's quite a cool framework, and I'll show you it in
a demo later.
What Securex basically does, and specifically also threats response,
is API aggregation. So Securex
pulls data and pushes data through APIs.
If I were to do anything in Securex, and I click the
close tab button, then the tab
will be closed and the data will be gone. Or maybe it will be temporarily
stored somewhere in cache. Well, actually, I don't think we
do that. So we are not a sim. So it's
security intelligence and event management system. We don't gather
data. We pull data when we
need it, and we push data when we need it. And that is actually quite
powerful platform. You cloud call
Securex a soar, a security orchestration,
automation and response platform. There are
discussions you can have whether we are soar,
but we're definitely not a sim. And in
a lot of organizations, we can actually replace SIM,
or there is no need for a sim because we only pull the
data when we have to directly from the products.
So we leave the data at where it's being
generated. Now, an important piece,
without going too much into detail, unnecessary detail,
is CTIM. And CTIM is probably one of the most important
things that is foundation of Securex.
And this is basically a data model. It stands for Cisco threat
intelligence model. And this allows
us to describe threat intelligence. Now, don't look
at all the details here, but you'll probably hear me say observable
ones. An observable can
be a domain name, IP address, et cetera. And all of
these objects, data objects that you see here,
they can have a relationship with observables, or observables can
be a part of those objects and
a verdict and judgments. So a judgment is, hey,
this IP address is bad. So a judgment
can be about an observable. A verdict can be like,
hey, we have five judgments, but this is our final verdict.
Exciting means, hey, this was seen in my organization.
Someone reached out to that observable. We have
a couple of others, we'll talk about that later. But just know
that this data model is very important because you
have dozens, hundreds of security products
that all use their own data model. And if you want to be a platform,
you need to have a standardized, reliable model
where you can translate everything into and in the end that's what
we do with Securex. We translate back and forth
in CTIM, which allows us to do that cross referencing
because everyone speaks the same language within air quotes.
So you can also recognize CTIM in securex threat response,
for example, you can see the judgment verdicts and sightings.
Sightings or target sightings actually show up
as a target. And this basically means it's
a sighting which actually has a host device
of youve organization, for example an
iPhone or a MacBook or a server which
has actually reached out to a domain or something
similar like that. So targets and signings are very important
because if we have them, it means we need to probably do some
more investigation.
Now we can also interact with CDEM from the
API, obviously. So everything in Securex is built on
top of APIs. It's built with open API spec
and it uses Oauth
two as authentication, so standardized API
method. And you can also interact with the Swagger UI
or I think it's called the open API Explorer. Now you
can also interact with it. And here you'll see some raw
CTIm JsOn. And this is how you describe observables
in JSOn. You give it a value and the type.
Now obviously you can also interact with CTIM from Vidy
API in Python or in any language that can do
an API call. So here you see a couple of
examples of that.
So yeah, that is all quite interesting
ways of interacting with CTM. I see
the arrows stayed behind, but this is just
to show youve a workflow that you could use in fret
response is you can use intel resources,
casebook or incidents as basically source
of your investigation. From there,
Securex will pull information from all kinds of threat
intelligence sources, but also from local threats
intelligence. So has it been seen in your environments?
And finally, you can actually take actions like blocking
something all from threats response and
all of this because it's API first
built, we can also do from Python.
And yeah, that is quite interesting.
Yeah. So now let's talk more about integrating with Securex.
So I talked about the APIs. I just also wanted to mention two other
ways that you can integrate with Securex.
In the end, everything works based on the API. So number one is the
real one. But you can use Securex orchestration
as a cloud to no code orchestrator which is now inside of Securex
to interact with these APIs in a
low to no code way. So you don't need to actually write any
syntax. You still need to know sort of how programmability
works, of course, but that is also a great
way to get started. And finally, we also have Securex
relay modules, and this is the most native way of integrating with
Securex. It is built on top of the Securex APIs,
and it allows you to add an extra module which
is being queried. And basically all our third party integrations,
they work with these Securex relay modules
and all of our products in the end as well. Probably they
just built in a relay module into the amp cloud, for example,
but they all work in a similar way.
The relay modules is all open source, so you can find it on
GitHub. There is a Cisco security GitHub which we can
share in the chat.
And actually, if you're interested into looking into that, and maybe
you are here from Engineering and you're like, hey, let's see
if we can integrate our product into it. I would definitely check that out.
And on developer Cisco.com curex,
we actually have a learning lab that teaches you to work with the APIs,
the orchestrator, or with the relay modules. So all
of these methods.
All right, so now we talked about threats hunting. We talked about Securex
and threats response. Now let's more dive into an actual use
case where we're going to combine threats hunting with Securex.
And the first one is going to be Twitter. And probably
you all know Twitter or use Twitter,
and we're going to ingest Twitter to look for
threats intelligence. Then we're coping to do automated enrichment,
and we're going to take some actions, and I'm coping to also attempt to
do a live demo. But everything will be around open deer.
I'm not sure if you guys know the hashtag open deer,
but it's quite an interesting hashtag because it's used by
basically, how do you call it, white hat hackers or ethical
hackers or cybersecurity analysts to
basically make a new
research about fresh malware available
to the public. Here's an example of the timeline.
This was a while ago, but as you can see, I'm searching
for the hashtag open there. And you can find
people posting like, hey, this domain I found
is actually malicious. Or here,
hey, these IP addresses, they're trying to exploit from
this. So that's actually quite interesting. As a demo,
I actually did this tweet,
was this like an hour and a half ago, and we're going
to try in my demo to also find this. And specifically,
we're going to look for this observable, which can be
a malicious observable. And actually it is a malicious observable.
So I did this tweet. Let me quickly jump over actually to
show you it live. Here's that tweet. I also
tagged Stuart into it. I see
he might have quoted it as well. So we're going to see
what this demo looks like with this live
tweet. There are actually many tweets out there,
as you can see. So they're not necessarily,
I think a couple of them per day, but still too much information
to check every day,
right? Or every hour. So you
want to automate stuff like this.
So we're going to try and find that. So I
built a script that does exactly this. So the first time the script runs,
it's going to retrieve all the tweets possible from that hashtag.
You can also add more hashtags. Obviously it's then
going to parse and clean the tweets.
If it wasn't the first time the script runs, it will actually
check if there's new tweets available. I'll talk to you a little bit about the
Twitter API, but youve can sort of say,
oh, give me only the tweets that have
been tweeted since this time.
Probably you want to run it every day or every couple of hours.
If there are no new tweets, we're going to sleep and we're
going to wait until the scheduled interval hits again.
Now we're going to then actually retrieve
observables with the Securex Inspect
API. And this is an API that you can give a blob of
text and it will give you back domains, IP addresses,
file hashes that it finds into it, email addresses. It's a
very powerful regex API, basically,
which Securex threats response uses a lot.
It will then check are there any observables? If so,
we're going to enrich these observables. If not, we're going
to skip the tweet and we're going
to give some user feedback. Now this
is important. When we actually find observables
in the tweet, we enrich the data and we find that we
actually have target sightings in our environment.
This is interesting because this means an ethical hacker
tweeted about a new domain name, for example,
like I just did, and someone in your organization actually
made a connection to that domain. What we then do is we
create a case in casebook in Securex and
we send a Webex teams alert with a high priority tag.
If not, we'll still create a case. You can actually
turn this off and we'll send a Webex teams
alert, but it probably requires less work or no work
because you don't have anyone in your organization who reached out to it.
Now if there are any more tweets in the queue, we're going to go like
this. If not, it's going to sleep. So this is sort of what the script
looks like. This is the result
which you'll get. So you'll get a high priority tweet.
You'll see that my tweet is actually here. If you click on this link,
it will jump to the actual tweet
and it will do the research.
You can actually investigate this and it will find if someone reached
out to that observable. If someone
did, you'll get this and I'll
actually post a tweet in Webex teams
and then say like, hey, you have from the amp module free targets,
three different targets. So you probably want to check this out quickly.
Now let's go over to the demo. So on
the basis of this, we have the Twitter search API
and it just allows you to basically query hashtags.
Et center if you want to get access to this, it's definitely
cool. You do need to get a developer account on Twitter.
You can just request this and say, hey, I'm doing research or
whatever and I'm not going to use it for commercial purposes
and they will give access to it.
And let me jump to the actual script. Here is the
python script. I'm not
going to walk with you through every line. I just want to mention
to you that all of it is on my GitHub here,
so you can check it out. I think we can also drop
a link in the chat and basically
I explain youve everything, how to install it. Et center, it's not that
hard if you understand python,
but basically I have a config file with three different
parts, one for fret response, webex and Twitter.
And this synth id is definitely important. Per default
it's set to zero, but the first time you run it will
be set to, I think it's using the epoch time or
whatever epoch time, however you pronounce that
and it will use that to see if you need to find new
tweets. So now let's actually run
it right, because we
want to find more tweets. So I do need to do one thing,
and luckily we're internal. I just ran this
earlier and I want to set it to zero again.
And we're going to run the file. So you see that the config file was
loaded. You see a new tweet was detected.
And what it's going to do now is it's going
to clean the tweet,
find observables, find sightings,
if there are any. And if there are, it will
then create a case in casebook and send a Webex team's
message. So you see here that actually, since I tweeted,
you see now that I was retweeted as well,
and probably the tweet after this will be my tweet that I did just before
the session. And you see here that Stuart
Clark, that his tweet was parsed. So what you can see here is that
they are actually being created. And you see here, this is
my tweet by Cisco Devnet.
And not all of them are high priority. So this one
is not high priority. This one is because
there are actual target sightings. This one doesn't
have that. What we can actually do is from
here, I could start immediately an investigation.
I can also, for the sake of the environment,
let's not burn more cycles than needed. You've seen
how it goes. What we can also do is we can find them
here, of course. So here we are in Securex and
we have Facebook. And here you see actually all of them being
added. Now you see my and
Stewart tweet being high priority because that
tweet contains internetbackeys.com.
And Internetbackeys.com is actually something
that I've triggered an alert on earlier in my demo environment.
So this is quite interesting. You see obviously also
a couple of other tweets. So you can check them out
here. If they are interesting, you can still investigate them.
So you can click on investigate. But probably we're not going to
find any targets because we already did this investigation
with the API.
So we actually saved a lot of work here
for our security operations center workers
because they don't need to manually grab data from that tweet
and then put it in fret response and see if
we have targets. All they need to do is they need to
monitor this space. And whenever something with high priority code
in, they need to click the link and it will automatically start
that investigation, as you can see here.
So, yeah, I hope this was a cool demo.
I always really like it because you can do a live
tweet and it will actually find it if you add that hashtag.
I don't want to convolute this. So I do always add
something that is actually malicious. I don't want to be adding
google.com or whatever here in case some other
person is doing something with this API.
So again, everything is on my
GitHub, which is over here.
And you can definitely check it out if you're interested into
it. Basically, there's a lot of
connections which you can just take from me and
reuse as you see fit. And you can just use
different sources than tweets, right?
In the end, this is where that magic happens, where I'm doing,
checking if we have returned sightings or not. If there
are zero, which is usually the case, hopefully we'll
just send a normal message and otherwise we'll
send the high priority message. As you can see
here, it actually took me quite a while to
make all of this markdown, which was
quite fun to work with to make sure that you get that line
and et cetera. All right, so this brings
me to the second use case, which will be a bit shorter because
I'm not going to do as extensive of a demo
on this one, but I do wanted to share this
one. So Talos intelligence probably
is known to everyone, but is Cisco's threat intelligence organization.
They have a pretty epic blog where they post
blog posts about new malware campaigns.
They sometimes are like referenced in New York Times
et Center when there's a new outbreak. So they're
really cool. Now you
could say, why would I care about that blog? Because everything
that's in that block is already blocked by Cisco, right?
Well, it could be if something is a zero
day and there is being blocked about and someone reached
out to that domain or an IP address or file hash 29
days ago or whatever the time limit is on that product,
you might get a hit from a while back, which still is very
important. So what we're going to do is we're going to
use this as a resources as well. This is a
little bit of an older screenshot. As you can see, this is
the first iteration of my script. They post a
couple of blog posts per week. Often they
contain insights and they contain many interesting observables,
as you can see here at the bottom, also called indicators
of compromise. And now there's many more blogs out there
like talos. So yeah, here you see those
observables. So how can anyone keep
track of and following certain hashtags and certain
blog posts? How can you do that and also respond to alerts?
Well, the answer youve can't unless you maybe can hire
100 people. So I did a very similar
script. I'm going to go a little bit more
quick through it,
but basically the tweet is now
a blog and we can go through multiple
blog posts, actually. So I've also added 40 guard from
40. Net and unit 42 from Palo Alto as well,
which are obviously our competitors.
But I mean, they might also have interesting information that
we should look at.
So yeah, here you just see some code snippets when
we're creating a case in casebook. How simple that is. All you
need to give it is some JSON and we're basically
doing a post with that JSON message or
JSON payload. I mean, and this
is basically how to extract observables.
So this is that inspect API endpoint that
I talked about earlier. We can give that broad text,
as you can see here, and even defanged
IP address as it's sometimes called. We are able
to parse out as observables.
So all you need to do is send that blob of text as data payload
and it will return you observables in the exact CTM data
format that we need. All right,
so I'm not going to show you the entire demo of this, but I
do wanted to share with you that this is also
on GitHub. There is a demo which you can watch,
but we're nearing the end also of that presentation.
I think the demo is, what is it,
15 minutes or something? Yes, so let's not
check that 15 minutes right now. But I
just wanted to mention I have a similar config file
like I did with the Twitter script.
But what I do here is I loop through RSS feeds
and what I then do is I grab the body
of a block and send that as raw text to
the inspect API just to show you how powerful that
is. And I do that for all of these. And similarly,
like with the Twitter API, there is an
RSS feed or an RSS,
I forgot the name of it. It's called feed
parser. This is basically a python library or Python module
which you can import and it will
actually be able to look at some metadata of an RSS
feed so that you only import the latest blog post.
And that is again a measure I took against noise. You don't want
to import the same one twice.
And just to show you how that works,
as soon as the script runs, it will actually write
this here. This is for Twitter,
but I'm doing the exact same thing for the
Dallas blog poster as well, as you can see
here, which I actually renamed to RSS feed since we
can do new. So I'm actually writing the config back
all the way at the end, as you can see here.
So let me just show you here. I'm writing the
config all the way at the end to make sure that the
last etech and last modified is checked. And that is also something
that I'm checking at the beginning.
Has there been a new blog posted? Yes or
no? All right, so I promised this was
a little bit of a shorter demo,
but I hope that you believe me that I can do the exact same
thing. And actually, by the way, to prove that,
I think I saw some in my casebook,
actually. So here you see,
for example, the 40 guard RSS
feed. And if I scroll further down, you'll probably see
the Talos one as well.
So without further ado, I'll move to some conclusions,
which I hope you agree with.
So we're nearing the end of the presentation, but I still have
some stuff I wanted to show. Is this easier than
manually searching Twitter? I'm very curious if you agree.
If so, I really hope that we can get our customers
to start working with this as
well. And asking Cisco and our
partners to either build stuff for this or
to do it themselves, that would just be awesome.
Some other summaries. Threat hunting is all about gathering data
from internal monitoring and intelligence, or global
and local threat intelligence, as it sometimes is called, and then cross
referencing it. Threat hunting is not something you just do
on demand. It should be something that you continuously
do in the back end. Skierx and
Skierx threats response can help with this, and the Securex
API definitely can help automate a lot of this.
So with that, we have also covered the conclusion,
and I hope that this statement now makes a little bit more
sense than in the beginning. With that, I would like
to thank everyone for watching and listening. I hope you enjoyed the
session and learned something new. If you do have any further
questions, please feel free to reach out. Thank you very much and have a great
rest of your day.