Um,
hello, everyone at Conf 42. My name is Cambodwai and
I am so excited to be speaking with you today. Today we're going to be
talking about how to build a sustainable accessibility program without wasting
a ton of time and money. And really, that this
is a smart business conversation. Let's get started here.
Look, I'll be the first to say disability and
accessibility. Disability, inclusion. It's hard,
right? Even that word disability has some weight to it,
some connotation, and it may make people feel
uncomfortable on the inside. I want to say that's
okay. That's normal. It's not a bad word.
I think that's something that we all kind of get stuck on, right? We just
shouldn't even know if we should say the word disability.
But the truth is, it describes somebody,
whether it's acquired over time, something like a stroke or a car
accident. Disabilities may be acquired in many ways, or it's
something that you're bored with. Maybe you had the cord wrapped around
your neck as a child when you were born, or you were born with an
extra chromosome. It's part of someone's identity.
It's kind of like being short or preferring video
captions or having glasses, which, by the way, is a disability as
well. It's okay to feel awkward or cautious
or maybe even ashamed when you're thinking your private
thoughts around disabilities. That's normal.
We don't talk enough about it, and we don't want to offend people in
our daily lives. We don't want to say the wrong thing.
And that, my friends, means it comes from a good place.
Ultimately, though, it is that self consciousness that keeps us
from asking the right questions and therefore creating
an unconscious bias and exclusions
towards people with disabilities. Plus, nobody in our society
really talks about disabilities, right? We normally don't learn
it from our parents. We don't talk about it at school, we don't go to
university and have classes on it. And plus, our HR departments
don't talk about it either. So my
goal for this presentation is to help two types
of people. Number one, if you are brand new to accessibility, if you've never
heard of disability inclusion before, I want to spark
some curiosity inside you. I want to talk to you about what the future
could hold and what maybe becoming a champion inside your
organization would entail, and the possibilities that could come from
that as well. Number two, if you already know a
little bit of accessibility, if that's something that your organization has already
started, or if you yourself are a champion inside that organization,
I want to teach you a little bit of implementation techniques and
how to accelerate your plans going forward. I want to know what's
holding you back from creating a successful program.
Let's get started. All right.
In and over the next 45 to 60
minutes, my goal is to get you to believe that
a proper accessibility program is the key to being a differentiator
in your market. And I'm going to show you how we can do that
with a framework that will make it straightforward and simple to understand,
easy to achieve that result.
And now I'm really lucky. In the past nine years,
I've had some amazing opportunities to research
and run and practice accessibility programs within
large organizations like IBM, to speak at conferences,
major accessibility conferences, even like CSUN,
and go and help large organizations as well coach their teams
and employees who are already in the accessibility programs like VMware.
So I've been hosting a weekly podcast, Vodcast called
Normalize it, which speaks to the business of disability,
inclusion and accessibility. And I teach and coach people on
the same topics as well. But I started off much
like everybody else, right? I was ignorant,
totally ignorant towards what accessibility is, even how to spell it
right? Because everything for me started
with the handshake. Back when I was at IBM,
I was brought in as a junior developer to go work on an
accessibility project. We had a large banking organization
who had hired us to do something. Right, the typical analogy, nobody gets fired
for hiring IBM, right? In this project we had
the client who was doing a lot of analysis and a lot of testing for
accessibility. We wanted to get on top of that because it was unacceptable
for us to be releasing a product that had bugs contained
with it. There was a little bit of embarrassment. So I was brought in and
I read something called the web content accessibility guidelines,
the wikag for short. And this thing, when printed out, comes out to about
an inch thick. It's not a small document. I read
this, I was going through, I learned about it,
and I started to build accessibility into our
product. I started to fix those defects that the organization
thought were the first ones to fix. What was interesting,
though, is I'd never actually met an end user who
would benefit from my work around accessibility.
That wasn't until I met my friend Tom. Now it's important to
know that Tom is blind, and he travels around different IBM offices
to go and teach people about accessibility. When he finally
arrived at the Toronto office, my boss, who was a
suave, kind of ex salesperson type,
have you ever had a boss like that, right? Walks around the office with a
popped collar. I know you have. I know you have. And he walked up to
Tom and his a type personality and stuck his hand in Tom's face
and said, hi, tom. My name is Jim. And there was this stare
down that happened because my boss,
Jim, had his hand stretched out, and Tom didn't
even know that hand was outstretched. I think I
died of embarrassment. I ran back to my desk and I walked, opened up YouTube,
and typed in how to shake a blind person's hand.
And it was really at that moment that I realized that this
is all about people. Our products, our tools, the things that
we build, the things that we work on are really only out there
to benefit people, right?
We want our product and service and technology and apps and all these things to
be used by as many people as possible. It doesn't make any sense for us
to build something that only works for a certain subsection of
the population. And by the way, if you ever want
to know how to meet somebody or greet somebody who's blind,
you can just say, can I shake your hand? And that'll cue
them up to extend their hand, and a connection has been made.
And if I could just make people see,
if I could just make people realize that people with disabilities care real people,
right? Then we would start to do this automatically.
If we could take out that uncomfortableness, that discomfort in thinking about
disabilities, then this, all of a sudden would start to become natural.
So the lesson here is that it's okay to talk about disability, it's okay to
ask questions, it's okay to be wrong, and it's also okay to
learn. So at that time,
I started to work on a framework, because in Canada, here, we are still so
much very compliant and regulatory based in
Canada. If you work in Canada, or if you sell products to Canada, you must
comply with something called AOTA, the Accessibility Frontiers with Disabilities
act. I'll get into a few more details as we go through the presentation,
but I was starting to be invited to all clients who had
regulatory buy in. That means airlines, that means banks, that means
insurance companies, transportation organizations, things like that.
They were starting to look for an accessibility tilt to
their projects. So this actually carried me throughout
my IBM career. I started to build a framework on how to
apply a repeatable process towards accessibility.
So here are the three secrets to accessibility success.
Number one, stop the guesswork. How to make accessibility
simple to understand, quick to adopt, and easy to implement in as little
as eight weeks. So what does that mean? What if you
were confident to take the next step on your journey? And took out all
the guesswork that comes with starting a new initiative and were just given
the right tools and the right vehicle to get moving in the right direction.
That's step number one. Number two, make you
say, wow. How a culture of dignity and
delight keeps your best talent and employees.
What if you implemented all the best outcomes from companies like
Intuit and Netflix, PepsiCo, Walt Disney, VMware, Capital one,
Accenture, Slack, Mattel. Yes, even Barbie has
accessibility features and recognizes that disability
inclusion matters. Really, the list goes on and on and on.
And you create an organization that focuses on disabilities
inclusion and gives people right. People and clients,
employees that truly great experience. Get your people to say wow.
Number three, a $13 trillion market.
That's right, trillion with a t. How the world's best companies
are leveraging accessibility and winning because of it.
What if you could establish a unique marketing position that
grows revenue and makes you stand out from the crowd? Because your competitors are
not doing this, by the way, and it could highlight some of
the best efforts that you've made and opens you up to an entirely new
market. All right, secret number one, let's stop the
guesswork. How do we make accessibility simple to understand, quick to
adopt, and easy to implement in as little as eight weeks?
All right, so remember I told you a little bit about that framework
that I developed while I was at IBM and started consulting with other organizations?
Well, how do we start to apply this in a
repeatable way? So, take out your pens and paper, because I'm going to walk you
through this framework. I call it the accelerated 180 framework,
and it's going to help you out with a bit more of a step by
step process. All right.
First, though, got to take a few steps back. Whenever I
show this slide, people always ask me, like, why do you have
pictures of two senior citizens on there?
Well, as we go through life, we start to acquire disabilities
right where we need glasses.
Arthritis sets in. We're not as mobile.
We're confined to our homes. Or maybe we have cognitive impairments
or disabilities that start to accumulate over time.
This is normal. This is natural. This is part of being
human. So when I was the accessibility lead
for IBM Canada, I was working on a project for bank of Montreal,
BMO apparent Canada. And accessibility was always kind
of approached in a haphazard kind of way, an ad hoc
kind of way. BMO blanket Montreal, at the time,
had purchased an accessibility audit for some of their
programs, some of their applications. And can you imagine if
you're a developer and all of a sudden you get slammed with an excel file
that has 800 defects on it, and they just didn't
know how to figure it out. There was no implementation, there was no
process, there was no structure in how to tackle that and
how to work on it as well. And it
sucked. I went to the 33rd
CSUN Assistive Technology conference. That's down in,
well, that was in San Diego, now it's in Anaheim in 2018.
And I actually spoke at that conference as well on colorblindness.
But what's really interesting is that gathering of so many other
accessibility professionals I got to meet and chat
with, talk to learn from chief accessibility
officers, from some of these large organizations that I previously talked about,
including though, like Microsoft and Hilton, Slack,
Adobe and Walmart. And these are all organizations that are leading the
charge for accessibility programs inside their organization.
And it's amazing. There are a lot of similarities
between all these organizations and how they tackle
and apply accessibility. One of them, for example,
is this hub and spoke model where you have a centralized
team for accessibility in the organization, and they tend to, in quotes,
loan out their professionals to different parts of the
organization. Now, that works really well for large
organizations, maybe that's not you, but even for smaller organizations,
having one, two or three champions who can go and consult
and are passionate about accessibility, are passionate about
helping people and disability inclusion, and they could be brought into other
projects throughout the organization, be it for HR or development
or procurement or any of these other types of processes. And what's
nice about this is that once you start to study and research
all these different patterns, a path and a plan
tends to be laid out in front of you.
So what is the framework itself?
So let's go through some of these, and I'll talk about
each point as I go through. So, number one, if you're going to apply
accessibility inside your organization, you need to know your current situation.
Right? What are the laws and regulatory considerations
for your projects? I talked a little bit before about AOTA
accessibility frontiers with Disabilities act. If you do
business in the province of Ontario, up here in Canada,
you must be accessible.
Furthermore, there is the Accessible Canada act, the ACA,
which is really coming into effect in 2035, and that's going to have a much
higher prerogative for accessibility throughout
the country. Next up,
having an assessment, a maturity model assessment, to understand
every part of the business, every part of the organization, to understand
where they are in terms of accessibility. Now,
you may only be focused on products, and that's okay.
Are there checks and balances? Are there gates
involved in checking the accessibility for each part of
your process. That is all kind of considered in a maturity model.
Identify DEi initiatives. Now it's pretty amazing when I start to talk about
DEi, that this is the perfect place for
accessibility to sit inside. Many people even will
change DeI to idea Ida,
and the a includes accessibility in that conversation.
It's 2023. If your organization doesn't have a DEI
initiative, they're way behind the pack. Like, we've got to get moving on that first.
This current situation starts to form the
framework, starts to form the baseline towards what you
can be working towards, because there's no sense in shooting out in all different parts
of procurement. Let's go find some tools. Let's go do these
tests and audits if you don't even know where you currently are.
Next up, where's the destination? Where are you trying to go? Let's define
that future state so you can understand exactly where your
organization wants to go and where it should be. Now, every single
country in the world has different laws around
accessibility. I talked to them a little bit earlier on when I talked about laws
and regulatory if you're in the US, which you most likely are, section 508
is something that you need to pay attention to, as well as the ADA,
the Americans with Disabilities act. These both outline certain
criteria and regulations and guidelines as to how to
make your software, your technology, and your organization accessible
for more users. You should be deciding on stakeholder
reporting as well. And I really believe that this is where a lot of people
get stuck. They don't realize that stakeholders,
executives, c suite people, they need buy in
and they need reporting. They need to know what's the business benefits of
it as well. So you should be deciding on that early on and
getting feedback from that leadership team to understand what they want
to know about what they care about as well. And also building
that coalition. You can find people inside your organization,
peers and colleagues and allies to help you as
you're moving forward in the organization, to get your team members and
the rest of your organization to realize that they're not alone
in doing this. And finally, secure that buy in.
Prepare that executive presentation. Don't just go in there blindly.
Pull in and get buy in a little bit beforehand. Go for a soft close.
Have conversations with your leader, your engineering
team, your directors, your vps
of product engineering, maybe even HR, to kind of understand
and get an idea of where that presentation will land and
who care the best people to apply that for. And this,
by the way, can be applied anywhere. There's no sense in starting an initiative.
If you don't get a little bit of prior buy in before that, you want
to make sure you gather your timelines. Be very realistic.
Smaller organizations are a lot more agile, as we know. You don't need
meetings to start meetings. As anyone who's in a larger conversation
knows, your timeline really needs to be thought
out. Well, I usually plan for a six to 18 month rollout whenever I'm
talking about this framework, and that is tends to be a nice
idea. But it's really important to know as well,
accessibility work is never done. Finally,
start to focus on a single measurable outcome that
you can do. There's no sense in calling and saying that we're going to make
the entire organization accessible. That's very
difficult to do. That is not really even a final goal. We can
really hone in on one specific part of the organization.
We can say in twelve months our HR department will
incorporate accessible hiring practices. Or maybe our CI
CD continuous integration deployment pipeline will include some automated
tools to check for accessibility, and we're going to reduce
that defect count from whatever,
300 down to 80 within the next six months. That is a
measurable, attainable goal. I know what
you're probably thinking. This sounds pretty expensive,
right? For time and money to implement. And not going to lie,
that's probably correct. Every project, every new initiative
costs time and money. But I want to
talk to you about the alternative. What if you didn't do
this? What if you didn't apply this? What if you didn't start to consider this
now? Have you ever heard of Target? Of course you have. If you're in the
US large box store, right? Sells lots of products. In 2008,
they received a class action lawsuit because blind
users couldn't use screen reader technology, and they
claimed that they wanted to acquire the same information and
engage in the same transaction as are available to
cited use guests with substantially equivalent ease.
Now that's a pretty loaded statement. Basically what it means is
that we want equivalent access. We don't want barriers or blockers
or any kind of blocks to access
the same things, right? Even the checkout wasn't possible. You can imagine
you're trying to buy something, you add things to the cart, and then finally,
just before you're ready to purchase something, you hit the submit button,
you hit the buy now button, and that buy now button doesn't
work. That's how frustrating would that be?
So the suit against Target was
first filed early in 2006, and that Baltimore
based National Federation of the Blind, which claimed that Target contained
thousands. That's right. Thousands of access barriers,
making it difficult, if not impossible, for blind customers
to use. That's bad.
It was a $6 million lawsuit.
That can get pretty expensive. So what was the action here?
They built an accessibility program. Without this plan,
without this rollout, none of this would have worked if they just started to audit
and figure this out. Well, you don't even know where you are. You're not involving
the community. You're not getting feedback from users
who will benefit from that fix.
The program manager, who, by the way, I met at that CSUN conference
in 2018, he was talking about how he
had to hold off lawyers on one side, had to hold off lawmakers
on the other side, had to hold off his managers and his stakeholders on the
other side because he didn't want to just do a bunch
of stuff. He wanted to roll this out with thought and clarity,
because without a functional plan, they never would have achieved
success. And now Target goes and
speaks at CSUN. Target goes and talks about their progress towards a
more accessible, equitable,
inclusive organization. And now, look, they're even
using it as a benefit. Up on screen here, I've got their bullseye
view, which is their corporate website,
and it talks about how Target's inclusive costumes are back
with double the Halloween fun. This is reality.
This is real life. Here, look. They now have an accessibility plan.
They're committed to a web content accessibility guidelines, a Wakag
standard. They work with advocacy groups,
they work with people who are users of their
products. They have an accessibility center of excellence, they have an accommodation policy,
and they're an inclusive work environment, which, by the way,
talk about a little bit more about that afterwards.
Secret number two, make you say,
wow, how a culture of dignity and delight keeps
your best talent and employees and clients.
So I used to not know about
or care about people with disabilities, either. All right, I'll be the first to admit
that. Before 2014, before I joined IBM, before I started to pay attention to
this, I was totally ignorant towards the world of disabilities as
well. I didn't have any family members who had a disability.
I'm colorblind, but I never really thought of that as a disability
either. But with just a few adjustments
and few small changes to my mindset and approach to accessibility,
I didn't only make this easy, but I made it fun as
well. Right? If I could just get into
the habit of questioning what I did before I
released something, just for a moment, thought of if I was
in a wheelchair, would I be able to access this if I had
a heavy cognitive load which, by the way, I don't
talk about it very much in this presentation, but in other presentations, I remind everybody
that we've all experienced a disability at some point.
If you're walking outside when the sun's shining down on your phone and you can't
read it, yeah. You've become temporarily disabled to
booking a flight or checking your transit times, things like that.
Or if you've had a heavy cognitive load, you're worried
about things at home. You just had a baby. You haven't slept very much,
by the way. They've even done tests to show
that you can be drunk. And that's pretty much equivalent to
the mental state of someone who is extremely tired. So you have no doubt been
disabled at some point before. So what if we could just think
of people like that? What if we could just acknowledge that one day we
will all also be permanently disabled through just
age related disabilities and we can start thinking about that a
little bit earlier. Why would it
be a problem to think about something at the end? I mean, that's really where
a lot of our problems start.
When at the end of the project, we're going to go submit code, we think
our project is done. Then all of a sudden accessibility comes in and says,
well, you didn't do this, you didn't fix that. That's a feel bad. So lessons
to you all, think about this a little bit earlier in your projects,
in your processes, and in your deliverables, because then you won't
have to worry about this so much at the end. Look,
if we can just get people excited about doing the right thing,
then disability, inclusion, accessibility becomes natural,
it becomes simple and becomes easy.
So really we're talking about breaking and fixing. There care only
two reasons that people and companies fail at
accessibility. That's it. Number one is attitude,
number two is expertise. That's it. So what
I do when I go and help organizations, I help them decouple
this negative attitude towards accessibility,
right? And again, a lot of these are just natural thoughts. This is boring,
right? Developers say, I just want to do my own thing. Stop trying to tell
me how to write my code. This takes too much work.
It's not going to work. And especially this is difficult when a developer takes
designs, takes patterns from a designer,
and those haven't been made accessible either. And the tester comes back
and says, hey, you didn't make this work. He's like, I didn't even make this.
I'm just following what was given to me,
right? We don't talk about those disabilities and thoughts of like who
cares about this doesn't really benefit anybody.
Instead, we need to decouple and break all those have
conversations around what that negativity is so that people realize that they're
not alone in those thoughts. And I start to attach it
to positive ideas of opportunity,
things around social justice. We want to live in a world where
justice is right. We want to live in a fair and equitable environment,
fair and equitable organizations and society
as well, right? Many people who care about accessibility,
many people who think about this a little bit earlier and are accessible professionals
do this because they feel like they take a stand. This is the
right way to do things. This is the best way to do things. And it
is simply the right thing to do. Right. We can build a
better code base. If you're more an engineer or product person,
if you are building something with a standard which is following
the HTML standard is 99% of the problem. That's it.
If you start to follow that standard to the t and not add create
buttons that are made of divs and things like that, you care going to create
naturally a better code base and a better product
for people with disabilities to use, right? And not thinking
about only that I'm doing this for someone other,
that we're doing this for ourselves, our future selves. If we want to continue banking
using the same applications that we're currently using or run
and use the products or services that we currently use, we got to start thinking
about this a little bit earlier as well. Number two, around that
expertise, removing those knowledge barriers.
Accessibility can usually and often think of this as
this ambiguous, amorphous, nebulous kind of
target. I don't know where to go. I'm not sure exactly where
to proceed with this. I don't know where to get the knowledge. I don't know
where to get answers. This person is telling me one thing, this person is
telling me something else. What do I do? Right? I'll admit
this work is complicated and it can be nebulous,
ambiguous as well. So we need to attach
that to knowing exactly where to get that
knowledge. Building internal knowledge bases involving
people with disabilities to get their proper feedback
on the products that you're building. Because then you'll
understand exactly what it's like to have somebody use your product.
It'll start to make you think, because we need to start to make
this availability. You need to know exactly where to go, who to listen to,
where to get more information.
So around that idea of clarity, getting clarity
of exactly where to go next is really, really important.
And again, I know what you're probably thinking, again, okay, but who is an
example of someone who builds this at scale? Well,
intuit, they own turbotax, credit karma, Mint,
QuickBooks, Mailchimp. Right? 100 million customers,
both individuals and organizations. Small businesses,
self employed individuals, not a small company. This,
what we're talking about here, is the same problem that Intuit
was facing back in 2015.
So the chief diversity, equity and inclusion
officer, she even has in her statement, which is right on the Intuit website,
underrepresented groups. And that is
exactly what people with disabilities are. It's really difficult when
you have a statement such as this and such a strong inclusion
statement on your website to not care about accessibility.
I would challenge you. I would challenge you to go and look at your corporate
company website and see if there's anything on inclusion there. I will bet
you there is. I'll bet you there's a
diversity group. I'll bet you there's groups for families or things
like that. It's 2023. Organizations are
paying attention to this. Accessibility goes hand in
hand with DEi. So what
did they do? The global accessibility and inclusion design
leader for Intuit, his name is Ted Drake. He needed this built in
a certain way.
First, they built it into their tech, they put gates into
their processes so code can't be released. They included
it into their design systems, into how they write text on
there. And as you can see here, they have this even posted on
their website as well. I love this accessibility inclusion. And if
you look at the four links below, we've got accessible content,
we've got alt text, antiracist language. Inclusive content readability
is down there as well. These are all guidelines on how to create
better experiences for, again, clients and
employees alike. They built it into their culture,
which speaks to this. And again, now all this culture of
belonging and all this culture of evolution is all on their website,
available to read. And they've made it public. They've made this absolutely public on how
to make their organization better. They went
from three people caring about accessibility to
now over 1200 accessibility champions inside that organization.
It's really hard to not care about accessibility
when everywhere you look, there's someone else who
cares about accessibility. That's called pervasive
and that's called a pervasive organizational change.
It's pretty cool, too. Intuit made it okay to
talk about up on screen,
I've got a picture of the Intuit CEO, Sassan Gudarsi,
and he talks about the mission to power prosperity around
the world and doing things for their customers, that network
of 1200 accessibility champions, it really goes beyond
compliance. What we're really talking about here is the
future of work. What kind of organizations do we want to be a part
of in the future? Do we want to help build?
Look, they didn't say we want to give wealth or increase
wealth or things like that. They talked about powering prosperity. And prosperity
means different things to different people. And he didn't say just to
some customers or a small segment of the population. He said
our customers, all customers.
Accessibility is part of the daily conversation across the company at
Intuit, says Ted Drake. And when you can
start to have this, you can start to really start to change the way that
your organization evolves. And by the way, they're not
perfect. Accessibility, like everything else, it doesn't matter what you're doing,
whether you're implementing a new Javascript framework and
stuff like this, the work is never done and we need to stop thinking about
this is a one and done exercise. They recently hired an
intern who is deaf, and he talked about how there were
no captions on any of the onboarding videos.
Well, they got that fixed. And this is valuable feedback,
having that conversation and not being afraid to give that conversation.
This really is a two way street.
All right, secret number three, this is a $13 trillion
global market and how the world's best companies are leveraging accessibility and
winning because of it. All right.
I used to also think that accessibility was just a nice to have.
Even when I just got started and I was doing some of the development,
I was fixing those bugs. Many people would come to me and say, this is
just nice to have. There's no business benefits to considering
accessibility. And at
that time I didn't really see any other company either. Large know,
maybe there's some nonprofits doing this,
or maybe there's the organizations like the Canadian National Institute
of the Blind, the CNIB. Maybe they cared about it. But why does
that matter to large organizations?
Well, once I started to learn more about these opportunities, once I
started to dig in a little bit deeper, I found that there's lots of organizations
who were doing this and they were winning clients because of it
too. They were using this as a differentiator on
how to use a marketing term or how
to set themselves apart. By the way,
the US Office of Disabilities Employment Policy categorizes
persons with disabilities as the third largest
market segment in the US, after Hispanics and African
Americans. The discretionary income for
persons of working age with disabilities is
$21 billion. And that's greater than
the african american and hispanic segments combined.
Now that's a market opportunity. We can
be differentiators. We can stand apart from the crowd, and this
becomes a positive feedback loop that works for us and
defends us also in the future against legal battles. And by the way, if you're
an individual contributor, maybe you don't manage a team, maybe you
don't really have any bind with the stakeholders. That's okay.
You're part of this conversation too. You yourself can make
this part of your own work. Become that
differentiator, become essential.
I've survived layoffs because I've cared about
accessibility and I was the only one who did. I was that expert
and that became my differentiator. That's how I became essential.
So distinguish and differentiate. Market growth opportunities
do exist for people who care and organizations
who care about accessibility. They care access to a broader market.
One in seven people have disabilities around the world. This is not a small number.
They have access to innovation and talent.
Also talent retention. If your best talent
understands that they belong in the organization and there may be
people who you don't even know have disabilities inside your organization,
someone may be sitting next to you right now and they care.
Neurodiverse, that may be you as well. When your organization
cares about people, when they start to incorporate these types of
things, naturally your best talent will want to stay and you'll attract
better people as well. Once you start to fix things like the job application process,
there is opportunities to identify lost revenue.
Selling into government requires something called a VPAT. If you sell a product,
a voluntary product accessibility template,
this is just a self assessment, a self testament to the facts that you've
assessed your product for accessibility and you can sell towards government
now. Also, higher education is now requiring a
VPAT in many snares as well and larger organizations.
I know the bank that I just left recently, they would
ask for a VPAT as well. You're not allowed to apply to
become a vendor towards this organization unless you have that in hand.
We talked about this a little bit about some of the risks around compliance and
brings like that, but really understanding that risk assessment, what are the laws,
what are the penalties, what are the fines involved? If you do not comply,
this starts to hurt your bottom line. But finally though, and this is my
favorite one, plan your success story, right?
Your opposition, your competitors are not doing this. Stand apart
from the crowd and like I said before, use this to focus on your career
as well. You're probably know
this probably isn't worth the effort. There's no business gains for accessibility.
There's a small company that puts a lot of effort towards accessibility.
Microsoft probably heard of them before. Satya Nadella,
the CEO of Microsoft. His son was severely disabled
with cerebral palsy when he became CEO.
This truly was a top down driver from the
top to care about accessibility. As a result,
Microsoft president Brad Smith prioritized accessibility
across all products. He funded
the AI for Accessibility program as part of Microsoft's
AI for good initiative. That is a $25 million
investment over five years. That is not a small chunk of change.
Look at this. What the heck is this thing? This is the Microsoft
adaptive controller. And you start to see these cool little brings that come out
of Microsoft. Bryce Johnson is an employee. He invented
this controller, and if you want to know a little bit about this,
it's almost looks like a tablet. It's got two large buttons on
it, a and b buttons, a dpad, but there's
a bunch of icons near the top. And what that is, is those are
all inputs you can plug in, plug and play
devices of your own assistive technology. There's buttons
and tabs, sip puff devices just like they sound, eye tracking.
They can all go in there and create the inputs
for Microsoft. For the Xbox.
That's really cool. They've got seeing AI, which uses
computer vision, can speak the text as soon as it appears on screen,
can even identify color. They've got automatic captions for teams. They've got accessibility
checkers on all Microsoft 365 products.
Accessibility features an edge. I know a lot of people are like, who uses edge?
But fact is, when you start to think about an
organization like Microsoft implementing accessibility into all
their products, they've got a differentiator. I'm just going to show a
quick video. This is a Microsoft video. My name
is Grover. Sean. My name is Ian. I'm Taylor. My name
is Owen, and I am nine and a half years old.
So Owen was born with a rare genetic disorder called Escobar syndrome.
He's had 33 surgeries to
date. I love video games, my friends,
my family, and again, video games. It's his
way of interacting with his friends when he can't physically otherwise do
it. What I like about the adaptive controller
is now everyone's companies. You can just say, all right,
that's that button. That's that button. That's that button.
Perfect. One of the biggest fears early on is how
will Owen be viewed by the other kids? He's not
different when he plays. No matter
how your body is or how fast you are, you can
play. It's a really good thing to have in this world,
right? When everybody plays, we all win.
This is beyond compliance, my friends. This is differentiating
yourselves from your competitors.
I've got a friend at Microsoft. He's the director of product accessibility
up here in Canada. His name is Dave Dame and he himself is disabled.
He has cerebral palsy and he says,
we will all become disabled one day. Just some of us
got here first.
So, quick summary here, three secrets to accessibility success. Number one,
stop the guesswork. Let's plan for and develop for
accessibility. Let's create a roadmap towards accessibility success.
Make it simple to understand, quick to adopt and easy to implement.
Number two, make you say wow. Create delightful experiences
for both customers and employees. And finally,
number three, it's a $13 trillion global market.
Create and stand out from the crowd.
The world's best companies are already leveraging accessibility, and they care winning
because of it. Nobody wants to be
excluded from anything. I want you to take a moment here to think about a
time that you were excluded. Maybe it was in the past, it was a
party back in the days. Maybe it was an event
that you really wanted to go to and you're told you weren't supposed to.
Maybe it was a promotion. That's a big one.
And I think if we don't consciously think about the exclusions
that we create in our own environments, our own products and tools,
services, job descriptions, employment opportunities,
then we can leave people behind. And nobody wants to do that. I know
nobody wants to do that.
One in seven people around the world have a disability.
And this is from the World Health Organization. And this
includes people who wear glasses,
who have anxiety, who have long Covid, have experienced
trauma, mental health conditions, who have experienced a stroke, who have
Alzheimer's, who have heart disease. It's veterans who have PTSD.
It's amputees. People, of course, who are born blind, who have become blind over
time, people who born with hearing loss or
develop hearing loss over time as well.
This means that in a group of 100 people,
15 or so care going to have a disability. Something to think about.
My name is Cambodwain. I am a disability inclusion and accessibility
expert. If you want more information, feel free to
scan the QR code up on screen. Right now we
can continue the conversation. I help socially responsible
people in organizations become leaders in inclusivity
by building sustainable accessibility strategies for employees and
customers with disabilities alike. You can
enhance your brand reputation, increase your customer loyalty and retention,
and avoid costly legal consequences, all while
gaining a competitive advantage and access to a growing $16
trillion global market. I do a lot of stuff on LinkedIn.
Follow me on LinkedIn. That's where I do most of my posting. You can also
come listen to my podcast. If you scan the QR code, all the information is
there. And with that, thank you so much. Have a great day.