Terra and security researcher and industry. I will show
how to secrets, keys in Docker containers and
kubernetes in different environments and
also comment best practice for saving and securing
distribution of secrets using specific tools in the devsecops
ecosystem. BSDR have written
public is this book with Italy implemented
Docker and Kubernetes. In this book, basically you
will learn about Docker and Kubernetes as a platform for the development
of containers taking into account the security of
applications. Also you will learn
for example how to secure your Docker and Kubernetes environments and
discover vulnerabilities and threads with specific tools
like Falco, three eco events and so on.
These could be the main points of the tools. First,
I will commend the challenge of security and
secret keys in containers ladder.
I will commend the best practice for securing a security distributing
of secrets in Docker containers. For example,
with Docker secrets we can manage information
that is needed at real time but cannot
be exposed in the Dockerimas or
source code repository. We continue with
managing secrets in Kubernetes using volumes
and sales secrets and finally I will comment
other tools for distributing secrets in containers like
Hashicorp but and keyword we
start commenting the tools factor the tools factor is a methodology that allows
to create software service applications that are
deployed that are usually deployed
in encloded environments. These methodology includes best
practice for applications are developed with
maximum portability, stability, security and fault tolerance.
One of the many philosophy of twelve factor
apps is that configuration should be stored
in the environment. In practical terms, these means
storing configuration separating from other source code.
In general, secrets provide a
mechanism to store data that can be read by application
at runtime and secrets play a critical
role in security when storing sensitive data separately
from application code. This include data such as passwords,
hostname, key certificates and so on. For example,
if your application requires a database connection to
this, usually you need a hostname, a username, a password
for connecting these database.
Furthermore, there's a different database server for development,
testing, production and so on.
And in this way secrets with secrets
you can meet that each environment can provide
its own database information to the applications and the application code
doesn't needed to know which environment it is securing.
Basically, a credential manager or secrets manager
basically is an administrator of credential
passwords, configurations or certificates. The main reason
why our applications are going to need a
secret manager is mainly to
prevent the most sensitive information from being leaked.
In this way we can compare a secrets manager to a user password
manager. These a secrets manager will work at the application
level, sharing credential and connect and connecting certificates
in this way. For example, Docker secrets
is a treaty that can help us to store any type
of data that can be represented as a string or a binary.
At this point, we can include username and passwords, hostname and port
sh keys, TLA certificates,
and so on. The following diagram shows how
Docker use RAF that is a consensus algorithm
for managing a replicated log in a distributed
system to ensure that data remains consistent in the
NT swart and all the service running on
it. Basically, the RAF algorithm transmits a secret in
an incretive way to all the manager nodes.
Other diagrams also shows the worker
nodes which are instances of Docker engine securing
these containers. At this point, Docker secrets works
like a bolt where you can pull sensitive data and
you can only use it if you have the bolt
keys. You can only access this
data if you have the master key or
the bulk keys, which you must
get from the service code to which you actually need
other key. Currently, Docker secrets are
only available to swar service. This means that standalone
containers cannot access Siggrass. Therefore,
to use Sigress, we must configure our cluster for
swar for Docker swar using the Docker swar init command
where the manager IP is
the IP address accented by Docker to the managing node.
And when you add a secret to the swar,
Docker sends the secret to the
swarmanager over a mutual delays connection. For example,
we could use the contents
of a file to create a secret and when you
grant a newly created or running
service access to a secret, the secret
is mounted into the container
in can in memory file system. The location of
the mount point within the containers by default is
secrets name. Due to Docker secrets require
our cluster to be in Swarmode, we cannot access
other secrets from the normal Docker run command.
Instead, we have to create services and we
can specify when creating services.
At this moment we
can create secrets associated
to these services. In this example we are creating ready
services and granting access to other secret that
we have created. Next, we can for example
get the identifier of the ready service tax container
using the Docker PS command and at
this point you can use Docker containers, a command
to connect to the container and read the context
of the secret data file.
When you add or inspect an individual secret at
any time or list all secrets,
the limitation is that you
cannot remove a secret that is running services
is using. If you try removing the secret,
the removal file because other Reddit service is running
and has access to the secret.
In this example, we are removing the secret by the service
and to remove normally what is we
want to remove a secret without distributing
the running service. You can use other techniques like rotating secrets
using other techniques. For example, establishing a policy
of your secret keys.
Next, for example, we call verify other
service no longer has access to the secrets.
In this way a node only has access to
encrypt secrets and if the code only
has access to a secret, if other node is
a swarm manager or if this is running service
tasks which have been rated access to the secret and
when a container tasks stop running,
the decrypted secrets are unmounted from the
memory system file system for that container
and fluid from the code memory.
We continue commenting. Best practice associated
with when we needed to secure
this kind of information. For example, is it considered a
best practice to remove a secret once it's no longer
needed? For example, we can permanently remove a secret
using the command Docker secret
rein secrets.
At this point it's important to remember that before
remove the secret, we need to stop and remove
services that are using this secret
docker. Another best practice for example
is relative with Docker that makes
secrets available to our application as files.
As we have seen before, the could behavior is
to make each secret its own file in the
directory run secrets. But this
default behavior can be changed if
we change the location of the file by securing it
with our service. For example, the following command is useful
is the secret if the secret contains information
that our application expects in a specific location.
The secret functionalities are available using Docker compose
the following file configuration we define two secrets other
first one is external, meaning it refers to a secret created
using the docker secret command and the second one refers to
a file and doesn't require any initial
setup with Docker. Keep in mind that using
the file approach bypass most of other benefits of
using Docker secret. Also, other file
must be available to all hosts where the service might
run my execute and we must take care to
protect the content of the file using mechanisms
other than Docker. For example, using encryption techniques
over this file that we are sharing in the docker host.
For example, docker composite tasks can
be deployed using other docker client and
as part of the developed deployment other
stack will be configured with access to
the secret and the following commas allow deploying
the services and access other secrets that
we are deploying with
Docker stack. Now we are commenting the
same button in Kubernetes when working with Kubernetes well,
the most easy way to create a secret is using the Kubectl command
to reference the manifest file you just created
and the request will be sent to the APA server
in the Kubernetes control plane for the request to be action.
Afterward, other data will be stored in the ETC
data store of your cluster when worker go in.
Kubernetes secrets also can also be passed
to containers using mounted
volumes. This will cause the configuration
data to appear in files available to the container file system and
each top level k in the configuration data will appear as a
file containing all case below that top
level k. Within the Kubernetes ecosystem
we can find other projects that allow the management
of secrets. For example, Seal secrets
project is a tool that allows to encrypt secrets using
a resource called seed secrets. This tool can be used
to encrypt Kubernetes secrets and store it
on the GitHub repository. In this way seed
secret encrypts the secret data and
it can be decrypt using the Kubernetes crusted
controller. The main components of these solutions are the
client used to generate encrypted secrets.
At this point the user don't have the capacity to
decrypt except the secret controller and
the other components is other Kubernetes secret controller used to
decrypt the seal secret and store it as
a secret in the Kubernetes cluster.
The solution is based on a publicly infrastructure
and serves a public key to encrypt and install a
private key on the cluster. Basically this tool encrypts
data using a public key for the cluster using
the certificate of the Kubernetes cluster when it's applied
in the following configuration file we are defining a secret
that containers user key and password in
base 64 format which are easily
reversible for
securing this configuration file that
containers critical
information. You can other create a secret and
seal it with Kubernetes solute that can be found in
the GitHub repository of the project and the following command
generates encrypt data for the secret and is not
possible to decrypt except using the
sealed secret controller. This is the encrypt data
for the secret generated with the Kubernetes
Seal command and at this point no
one can decrypt except the CFC controller.
The previous manifest file for example can be used.
We can use the previous manifest file to create the seal secret
in your cluster and can be executed
using the Kubectl apply command and at this point this
seal secret can be used to be
pushed to the jeep repository without the
consent of any individual accessing other
original volumes. Docker and Kubernetes secrets are
SLS solutions, but you can also consider third
party secret restoration solutions. Some popular secrets
management alternatives include Hashicorp,
Kweeth,
Achilles, Bolt. Also we have
cloud provider solutions, specific solutions for
AWS,
Google Cloud, Google Cloud and so on,
Azure and so on. For example, we can start with a
tool for storing and accessing secrets in a securing way that
offers an interface for storing secrets while providing
an access control system and an access lock system.
In these diagram we highlight how Bolt make a separation
between the different components. On one hand we have the
storage component and on the other hand we have the components
to generate the secrets and credentials to
access these secrets. When bolt is start
for the fish time, an encryption key generated and
is used to protect all information.
This key is protected by a master key which by default
is split into five shaded keys and at these point
we will be able to generate the master keys with three of these
five shaded keys and with this case we
could access the secrets.
Secrets are encrypted outside bowel using what
is called Bowel's transit secrets giant
is can encryption as a service solution to
be secure? Bowl performs cryptographic funtios
on data intransit and doesn't store data
while the data is intransit. Bow, like other hashicorp
tools such as console and Nomad, provides a
graphical user interface accessible
through the roster that allows other same operations to be executed through
the API or from the command line.
These are the keys features of other valve. We can highlight features
like the capacity to encrypt and decrypt data
without storing it. Other data
have the capacity also to generate secrets on
demand for certain operations. Also allows
the replication across multiple data centers,
offers protection for secret renovation and
ships as a secret repository with
access control details and another interesting tool
is keyword in a similar way that we have
seen with all kwith helps with
infrastructure tools, secrets, GPG carriers,
database credentials, tilly certificates and
so on. These are the
main components of these solutions are the kwith server
that provides JSON API for accessing and managing
the secrets KCNC that is
a kwith client that retrieves secrets from
the keyword server using tools with a client
certificates. Other client Other K with CLE is
the main tool for managing the secrets for
managing the secrets and the users that can now take
these secrets and the automotive API
is the API we can use for request access to
these secrets. For example,
in this script capture, we can see where we can add
a secret using K with clip
and the K with automation API
for making a request using
a client certificate. The main features of kwith
are basically kwith helps
with the main advantage of this tool
is that has the capacity to store all secrets
in memory only. Another interesting solution that
provides cloud providers, for example IBls
secret managers lets you quickly rotate, manage and
retrieve database credentials, APK and passwords.
Using these solutions you can secure, analyze and manage
secrets needed to access the AWS
cloud capabilities on third party service and
on premise. This is the main features
of these solutions. It has the capacity to encrypt other secrets
transmitting over TLS in a way that we have seen
with Hashicorp and Kwith also
provides client side catching libraries
to improve the availability and reduce the latency
of using your secret. And obviously you can use
a specific service from AWS.
For example you can use BPC
virtual private club.
You can configure this service these
close service to keep traffic within the
OS network. If you are hosting your application on
Azure, for example, there is a tool specific called
Azure cable that enables users to manage
all secrets for their applications that are deployed in
the Azure cloud provider. This tool
has the capacity to ensure that all your secrets are managing
in a single repository. This includes key certificates,
connection strings and password and you can use K Vault's
Rest API for connecting your application with the Azure
cable. Another tool that we can see
in this ecosystem is Aki less but that is
similar tool that basically provides sower
as a service platform that has the capacity to
protect credentials both static dynamic including
third certificate, automatician and encryption keys.
This platform supports the
main features of this tool that provides a serotras
application access by providing unify authentication
and provides also an encryption as a service allowing
customers to protect sensitive data and useless
data by applying feeds
142 certificate
certified up level encryption.
This kind of certificate or
certificate is a security standard for accreditation
of cryptographic models used in
other cryptography industry mainly. And finally
for concluding remember that not stored
secrets in the application system environment variables or
source code managing system and the main recommendation
is using secrets
as a main tool for any container based architecture
application because they help to achieve the goal of
keeping code and configurations in asylum separate and
recommend adopt some of these managing
solutions because sensitive information can be
easily leaked and out of the credentials
could make applications vulnerable.
And that's all. Thank you very much.