With GitHub actions. A Prometheus deployments example the agenda
for today is we will deploy Prometheus in AWS
EC two instance using Bitovi's seamless GitHub action
we will explore Bitovi's open source deploy Prometheus GitHub
action. We will also explore Bitovi's open source framework,
referred as commons, which ensures seamless integration
of IAC tools such as terraform and
ansible. At the end of this session,
you'll be able to leverage the power of GitHub actions
as a platform engineering. You'll also witness live deployment
of Prometheus using Bitovis GitHub action. You will get insights
into the Bitovis action repository. You will also discover
that how Bitovi's internal frameworks commons
ensure seamless integration of tools such as terraform
and ansible without user worrying about installing
or setup of these tools. Here we have a deployments
repository in which user defines workflow, which would
call Bitovi's GitHub action to deploy Prometheus
and Grafana. Let's see the content of this repository.
Under observability folder we have configuration
related to Prometheus and Grafana, such as under Prometheus
we have scrape targets for Prometheus to scrape
metrics from. Similarly, under Grafana we have a data
source for Grafana. Let's see the content of
workflow file. Under workflow
file we are calling Bitovi's
GitHub action to deploy Prometheus and Grafana.
You can also see that we are providing mandatory
parameters aw access key id and
secret access key to deploy Prometheus and Grafana
in AWS EC two instance. Along with this, you can also
pass AWS default region to deploy Prometheus
in and similarly you can also specify which EC two instance
type you want. Finally, you can see that we are passing
the path for our configuration files here.
Let's make a small change into the workflow file.
I'm going to comment this line and I'm going to commit these changes directly
into the main.
Once these changes are committed directly into the main branch,
the workflow would make use of Bitovis GitHub
action and Commons to deploy Prometheus and
Grafana in EC two instance.
In the meantime, till this workflow is complex,
let's see what's inside the action repository and what is
Commons framework. We will start
by exploring Bitovis GitHub action
repository. Let's see the action file for the
Bitovis GitHub action repository. Here you can see that
we have all the inputs are exposed to make use by
developers. Any steps such
as ISE, any scripts or commands are defined
into the steps. For example, we are copying all the
configuration later to Prometheus and Grafana at
appropriate destination. Similarly,
we are also calling Bitovi's internal framework named
as GitHub action Commons. Here you can see
that we have passed this input parameter where
we are specifying that the input for our ansible is
at path. This in the similar
way you can specify your path for other tools such
as terraform and helm. And then Commons would make
sure that your
deployments are ready without you to concern about deploying
or installing terraform, ansible or any IAC tools.
Let's see the overall structure of
commons repository as I shown you that in action
we have certain kind of parameter. You can see that
if your deployment require terraforms,
you can specify the path of terraform using
this input parameter. Similarly, you can specify the input
for ansible and helm, and then Commons would make sure
that the deployment is ready using appropriate IAC tools.
Commons is trying to run few scripts
and these scripts make sure that the code from deployment
and action repo is merged together and
it's defined in an order way for Bitovis to
construct Ise as infrastructure as code.
Let's explore all these repositories from diagram
point of view. You can see that we have three repositories
deployment repository, action Repo and comma repo.
Deployment repo is used by user user would create
workflow which would further call Bitovi's internal GitHub action.
In Bintovi's internal GitHub action, we specify the deployments
of tools such as Prometheus and Grafana, which further
call Bitovi's internal framework referred as common, which is can
open source framework commons. Make sure
that your deployments is ready without you worrying
about installing or setup any of IAC tools
such as terraform or ansible.
Commons is a wrapper around the bitops.
Bitops has baked in terraform and ansible
as containers commons also make sure to organize
the structure of repository by merging the content of deployment repository
and action repository commons also expose the
output in a way so that they can be reused.
This is all about deployments. Repository action repository common
repository you can very easily leverage
the power of commons and action without setting up any
of IAC tools. Let's see the
status of our actions. You can see that
our action has been completed successfully. Now let's see the status
of this into the EC two instance,
our deployment for Prometheus and Grafana would be accessible
at this IP address along with its respective port
such as for Prometheus. We are making use of port number 9090
here you can see that we have our Prometheus deployments ready
and from our status we can see the targets
and we have our target up and healthy. So this is all about
Bitovis GitHub action and Bitovis Open source
framework Commons.
Let us know if you have any questions or you need help setting your
environment using platform Engineering. Thank you.