All right, let's talk about geodistributed applications
and see how to build those by using the global
cloud infrastructure. In this session,
we are going to talk about high level architectural design
patterns and consideration. This session
is not tailored to any specific programming language.
Instead, we will see how to build those applications,
how to design the data layer, how to arrange
our microservices, and there are other parts of the application stack.
But then when it comes to the development, it will be up to
you. You will decide how to take these design patterns and
considerations and implement with your favorite programming language.
All right, so, speaking about their
agenda, we will walk through three
steps. Step number one, we need to remind
ourselves of the global cloud infrastructure that is provided
by major cloud vendors. We are going to
talk about different resources, about regions and zones.
After that, we will do an introduction to geodistributed
applications, how those applications are different from standard
applications, what are the benefits, what are the tradeoffs?
And eventually, with step number three, we will practice
in designing and architecting a geodistributed
application by taking a slate like corporate
messenger as an example. Okay,
so the global cloud infrastructure when it comes to
the infrastructure, you know that every cloud
provides various resources. We have virtual
machines, we have network, we have disks
and other types of hardware. And those resources
are grouped and located within regions.
A region is an independent geographic location, such as
US west one, Europe west two. On this map, we have regions in
North America and South America, Africa and other continents.
When it comes to their speed and latency
within your region, all the resources of a single
region are interconnected through a high performance network.
But what if you need to send, let's say,
requests from one region to another
region? The latency will vary. The latency will depend
on how far each regions are located from each
other. If to take Google compute platform as an
example, then the numbers as follows.
Let's say that we have an instance of application running
in Oregon us west, and we want to send the request
and get an acknowledgment or response from North Virginia.
The average round trip is around 60 milliseconds pretty
fast, right across the country. But if the
same application from Oregon needs to send a request
to London, the latency will double. It will be around
zones hundred and 30 milliseconds. The latency
will be even worse. If our application from Oregon
needs to go to Mumbai in India, the latency will be
around 220 milliseconds. But at the same time,
if your application needs to go to Tokyo through the Pacific,
somewhere here, then the latency will be 90 milliseconds,
much faster than a request and response to
and from Mumbai. So what the conclusion can we make?
All the regions are interconnected through different
networking channels. Some of the channels are
faster, some of the channels are slower. That's why when we
will be talking about geodistributed applications,
the components of those applications, such as the data layer,
application layer microservices will span across the globe.
And you need to be careful about when you pick
specific remote regions because you
have various regions and the connectivity between those regions varies.
Or you need just to apply different patterns that we are going to discuss
going from the regions. Every region consists
of zones and zone is a separate physical
location within a regions. So on this
map we have proximity boundaries
of the US west zones. We have three zones in
this regions. And usually you have three or more zones
for the high availability needs. If you, let's say deploy your
application, your solution across
three zones, like instance of the application such as NgINX web
server is running zone one, zones two and zone three.
Then you can withstand zone level outages.
If this zone goes down, your application web server is still running
because it's running in other zones. That's why we have zones.
The latency between the zones is
extremely low. All the resources within the zones are interconnected
through a high performance network. If to refer to Google cloud platform
again, and to talk about Google's infrastructure, then the
round trip network latency is under 55 milliseconds
on the 95th percentile. And that's extremely fast. It's just the
round trip between the zones.
And finally, we have regions. Every resources
within a region are scattered across the zones.
But also many cloud providers expand
their infrastructure to densely populated metropolitan
areas. And they have services or
like products named as local zones or local edges or
edge nodes. What's the purpose of those local
zones? They are usually required for
applications that are looking for single digit
millisecond latency for their end users. The best example
here is gaming applications or streaming applications.
So if you have a lot of the users who live in Seattle,
Atlanta, London or New York, you want
them just to consume, to use your service
the fastest way possible. And you want to store the data. You want
to run instances of your microservices the closest way
possible. That's what those local zones are designed for
anyway. As you see, the global cloud infrastructure
is really broad. And with that infrastructure,
we as architects can design and build application.
They have several characteristics.
First, your global or geodistributed
applications can provide similar performance and experience
to your end users without, regardless of
the user's whereabouts. So let's say that
you have an application, and originally this application was launched
in use by your customers from Europe. But right now it's
gaining popularity in Asia and you want your users from
Asia to have the same level of experience as your european
users have. And with the global cloud infrastructure, it's extremely easy
to do this if your application, your data layer,
your application layer parents and also
exists, has a representation in your
asian data center. The second
benefit of the global cloud infrastructure that we can take advantage of is
you can comply with data residency requirements.
Let's take another approach. Let's say that you launch an application primarily
for APEC asian market,
but right now you see that citizens from Europe
kind of looking at it, you see a lot of the demand
from Europe. And if you want to launch and expand this application
to Europe, it's highly likely that you have to comply with the
local requirements such as GDPR.
And again, the cloud infrastructure allows us to do that. Right?
You can have, let's say you can keep the data of your application
in the european data centers and you can deploy instances of your microservices.
The only topic that is left is how to architect such a geodistributed
application. And finally, with this architecture you can tolerate
cloud failures. For instance, what if,
let's say you have us west and you
have a region in US west and you have a region in US
south? If the region in US west goes down, your traffic
for north american users can redirect it to another region. It's possible
to do. It's all about how to implement it, as can application and
data layer. The infrastructure exists.
Having said that, let's do a quick introduction to
the geodistributed applications.
A geodistributed application is the application that spans
across multiple geographic applications. For what
reasons? For high availability, compliance and performance
needs. On this picture, we will start talking about our geodistributed
corporate messenger. And this picture shows that our
messenger instances and
components of this solution run across the globe. We have North America,
South America, Asia and other locations.
But let's quickly step back and review
what are the downsides of standard applications,
the applications that are usually deployed and run in
a single vulnerability zone of your cloud environment.
On this picture we have the same corporate messenger,
but it's deployed in one of the regions and it's deployed in one of the
availability zones. That's a default actually deployment
mode and configuration for most of the applications. And what happens,
what are the downsides? If the zone goes
down, so does your application. Your application, your messenger becomes
unavailable. Your users will be disappointed,
at least disappointed. Some of them will never return.
If the outage takes a lot of time to recover from
other downsides that you can, or roadblocks that
you can experience later. Let's say that initially this application
messenger was designed for your north american market
and their startup founders told you, hey, no worries,
we're just going to build and break and disrupt. But let's do this incrementally.
Let's kind of build this application and deploy it and test it with
our north american users. But then what
happens in, let's say, in half a year, the plans are changed and you suddenly
have to expand this application to Europe. How are
you going to comply with the local data
residency requirements? How much effort and time should you put
in redesigning your architecture? Okay, so that's the
problem with single zone applications and data layers.
And final one is user experience. Again, the same application.
But then let's say in a year and a half you decided
to expand to asian market, to Japan, to Singapore,
to India. And you want those users from
those locations to have the same level of experience, the same speed
and the same scale. But if those users from Japan or India
needs to send the applications need to send requests
to your data center in Europe or in America,
then the experience will not be the same, it will be poor.
So that's what geodistributed applications are
dealing with. And when it comes to geodistributed apps, there are
two primary deployment modes, right?
When we are talking about geodistributed apps,
they have to be resilient and withstand various cloud outages.
They have to be performant even if you deploy them across multiple
zones or regions. And they have to comply with data residency requirements
if necessary. So let's quickly review multi zones
type of deployment because the multiregion one we will review in detail
while designing the slack like corporate messenger. So on
this picture, we have the same messenger application, but right now it's
deployed within the same regions, but across multiple availability
zones. You have, let's say instances and
data layer in zone one, zone two and zone three. So what
are the advantages and disadvantages? So from the resilience
system point, such architecture is much better than a
single zone deployment. Because if any of these zones goes down,
the other zones alive and you are happy,
right? And your customers and users are happy. So this configuration can withstand
tolerate zones, level outages from the performance standpoint remember
if to speak for the Google cloud platform,
a round trip is under five milliseconds. So the
communication, if you have the data layer here, the communication, you need
to replicate changes. You need to keep copy for the same message across
multiple zones. It's fast. It's like extremely fast
from the data residency requirements. The thing is not the trivial. I mean,
it depends on where your region is. If your region is in North
America and then in half a year you need to expand
your messenger to Europe, then it's going
to be a little bit complicated because this solution is in
North America. But you need to keep data of your
european users in the european data centers. That's where the
multi region deployments come into play. With multi region deployments,
from the resilience system point, you can tolerate region level outages.
If let's say your US west coast region is completely down,
then your users can be directed and read and
write messages to, let's say Midwest
regions. From that performance point,
as long as your deployment deployment spans
multiple regions, on average,
the performance will be lower if you compare to multizone
deployments and latencies will be higher. But with multiregion deployments,
there are multiple deployment options and we are going to review those a little
bit later. Just fasten your seatbelts and wait.
So it's not that standard.
And from the data residency requirement, we are good.
I mean, if you deploy across multiple regions, if one day you need to scale
to Europe or to Asia,
you can easily do that, right? So now let's
architect that slack like corporate messenger to
remind you most likely, I believe that most of you have heard about
Slack or use this messenger daily. With that messenger,
your company, your employer,
creates a workspace, you create channels and you communicate
and chat and talk with your colleagues. Also, like many
communities, open source communities or other communities use
slack for conversation between their members.
And Slack, believe me or not, actually is A-J-O distributed
application. So if you check this engineering
block by the Slack team, you'll see how their story eventually
they started, let's say standard application with MySqL,
but then they scaled, they turned their architecture into a geodistributed
one. In our case, we are not going to replicate like we are going to
use other components. But at least let's review
when we will be architecting our messenger. We are
going to look at several microservices. So like our application,
our messenger will be comprised of four microservices.
The first one is the messaging one, the primary one.
It allows our users to exchange messages in channels within workspaces.
Across workspaces we have the profile
that keeps your data, such as email,
name, age, et cetera, whatever you think is reasonable to
share. Also, we have two utility microservices
reminders and the status one with the reminders microservice,
you can ask the messenger to remind about any
discussion a little bit later. For instance, right now you're extremely busy,
you're doing something and you want to return to this conversation,
let's say next week. And you can use a special service, you can use reminders
for that. With the status microservice,
your colleagues can see what are you busy with, whether you are available or
not. So generally, if you're on vacation, you can change the status to
vacationing. If you are in a meeting, the status can be
in the meeting. Simple. And when it comes to the
architecture, we need to review and consider
and talk about all the components. We are going to talk about the data
layer that needs to deploy and span across multiple regions.
It needs to be highly available, comply with local data residency requirements,
and remain high performance. Right then we will have the application
there. These four microservices need to deploy their instances
across the globe so that the requests from users from
Europe, Asia and America are processed the fastest way possible.
And finally, the cloud cloud balancer. That's a special service
that is provided by major cloud vendors
that captures traffic from your users and redirects
the traffic in those queries to their microservice instances
into the database instances closest to the user's
location. Okay, let's move forward. Let's talk about
the data layer. In our case, for the data layer,
we are going to use Yugabyte DB, which is a distributed
postgres compliance SQL database. Our messaging,
our corporate messenger is a transactional application.
We cannot afford losing any message. We cannot allow ourselves
to any inconsistencies. But we have to be global.
That's why we selected Yugabyte. Yugabyte consists
of two primary components. The first
one is the pluggable query layer, and presently
the query layer supports SQL.
Yugabyte picks the postgres dialect of SQL, and also
those of you who use Cassandra. You can find Cassandra
APIs handy. Under the pluggable query layer,
we have the storage layer. That's the layer that
is different from what vanilla postgres has.
That's where your data is located. Your data will be sharded and
partitioned automatically for you across your zones and regions.
Your requests will be load balanced and also all
the changes all the messages that you're going to send to
your microservices will be transactional
regardless of how far the nodes of your database are
located. Speaking about the
compatibility level of how
what it is. So generally speaking, Yugabyte DB
reuses postgres source code Yugabyte
query layer uses the writer, planner executed
and optimizer of postgres.
It's basically the same postgres, but with several components that
are enhanced so that they can interact
and take advantage of their underlying distributed
storage layer. So for instance, we enhance the planner,
executor and optimizer so that whenever
you execute your SQL queries across a Yugabyte DB cluster,
the planner and optimizer can come up with the best execution
plan and the executor can send this execution plan
to your distributed cluster properly. Okay,
so to repeat, our geodistributed messenger
will spread across multiple regions.
And this time let's talk about the messaging and profile microservices.
Those are the key microservices of our application.
They are mission critical for the success of our application.
They will be experiencing thousands of requests per second.
They have to remain highly available events if regions go
down. Because if your microservice is not
available, if your messaging service is not available, then the impact
and reputation and business of our company will be
in danger. Also, when it comes to
the data residency requirements, the messages and
profile data of our users have to reside in
their locations of
the locations where they live. If for instance, we have
users from european region, we have to comply with the JDPR
requirements and the data of those folks have to be
located in european cloud regions.
So what happens? What do we do? From the architectural standpoint,
those are requirements. We are going to deploy a single cluster of
yugabyte that spans multiple continents.
But there is one important note.
In this cluster, there will be a group of nodes
that keep data from specific geographic applications.
So a group of nodes from Europe will
keep messages and profiles for the european citizens.
And there will be a group of zones who keep data and messages
for the asian customers.
Which means that whenever you have,
everything will be distributed and executed for
us transparently. We just need to deploy this geodistributed cluster.
The data will be partitioned based on the value of the
country column. If the country column is
set to UK, France,
Italy or Germany, then these messages will reside
and will be kept in our european
nodes. And that's done for you. We just need to configure
this database. We need to create these tables and we need to specify
and say that the country is our partitioning column.
When it comes to the performance, when it comes to the latency,
it's obvious that if you have users from
Europe and all those users work from company that is based in
Europe, all the messages and all the data will be here locally.
So that whenever you insert messages, whenever you share messages,
or do like perform any other tasks, the performance will be high.
The latency will be low because the users from Europe will be interacting
and reading and writing data to the european nodes of
Yugabyte. And the same is true for North America.
Colleagues, let's say that you have people in North America. You need to send
messages. You need to send and read and write
channels from your database. You will be communicating to your
north american group of nodes. Excellent.
Another type of multi regions database deployment.
It is when we deploy a primary cluster in one
geographic location and in other distant geographic locations,
we configure read replicas. We are going
to use this deployment mode of Yugabyte for the reminders
microservice. Again with the reminders
microservice, we can ask the messenger to remind us
about any specific conversation in an
hour, next day, or any week.
And generally what happens here.
All the reminders, whenever someone will be creating a reminder,
this write operation will be handled in the primary
cluster. So if you have, let's say, a user who lives
in South Korea and this
guy schedules a reminder, this reminder will
be written automatically forwarded from the read replica
in this location to the primary cluster in North America.
But whenever you are going to read any data from this local
read replicas, such as in Europe and Asia, the data
will be retrieved extremely fast using the local data,
and this data will be synchronously replicated from the primary cluster
to the read replicas. For instance, we are
expecting batch reads. It's when in every location,
close to every read replica, we will have a special walker that's a
process that wakes up every minute, connects to
the database, and pulls all the reminders that have
just expired. And it will be doing this only for
the local data. So in Asia, we will have a special worker that will connect
to the replica, read all this data in bulk,
and then we'll notify those users whose reminders
have just expired within the last minute. So that's how
you can minimize network traffic from the primary cluster to
the distant locations if you need to read a lot of the data.
And another, the third final multiregion deployment mode
for our data layer for our database is when we are deploying
multiple standalone databases in every distant location,
and if necessary, we can synchronize
those databases using can asynchronous protocol.
In our case, with our messenger, we are going to use this deployment
mode for the data layer when it comes to the status microservice.
Again, if you're on vacation, you want your colleagues to know about that.
If you are in a meeting also, you want to change your status respectively.
Or if you are active and ready to chat, your status also will
be set to active. And in this case,
we decided, all right, we do expect that
we still have high availability, right?
But we're not expecting that the status will be changed, let's say thousands
of times a second. It will happen, but it will happen. Not that
requests. At the same time, when my colleague connects to
the opens my messenger, he wants to see statuses
of all the colleagues. So, like, I want to have fast reads, but when it
comes to writes, I don't care. And also,
asynchronous replication is suitable here. For instance, let's say
that someone who lives in Europe went
to a meeting and his status is changed accordingly.
This information will be written to the European data Center, because that's
where this user resides. But then this information,
if necessary, can be replicated to North America and to APAC.
The replication can take, let's say like few seconds,
like 510, and depends on how fast the connectivity between
these users. But generally it's not a big deal.
Let's say if a teammate of this guy who lives in North America
will see his colleague from Europe start
to channels in five or 10 seconds, right? It's not a big deal. So that's
why it's totally fine to use the asynchronous applications between
these distant clusters. That's why we selected this for
the status microservice. Okay, to conclude, that's it
for the data layer component of our geodistributed application
for this. As I said, when it come, there are two
primary deployment modes. You have a multizone deployment
for your data layer, or you have multiregion.
Multizone is easy, but with multiregion, we also have three options.
We can deploy a single geodistributed cluster, and every data
will be pinned automatically based on the value of your
partitioning column, such as the country one. We use it for our mission
critical microservices, messaging and the profile one.
Also, the other deployment mode for the multiregion databases is
the primary cluster with read replicas in distant location.
We use that for the reminders. Keep this in your toolbox as well.
And the final one when you don't actually care about,
let's say, if you allow, let's say, distant locations,
read stale data that will be synchronized later. Then you
can use multiple standalone clusters
in every location and then set up bi directional or unidirectional
replication between them. It's enough for the data layer.
Let's talk about the application layer when it comes to the application.
Again, we have four microservices, messaging, profile,
reminders and status, and we have customers across the
globe. We are going to deploy an instance of every
microservice in every location in
North America, Europe and Asia.
Also, we are going to allocate those
instances with the local yugabyte
nodes. For instance, if my Yugabyte
DB zones are deployed in the London data center cloud
region, then I want the instance of the microservice
for the messaging and for the reminders to be located in the same region.
Why? So that the latency, the performance remember if,
even if to take Google compute platform as an example,
the latency between the availability zones within the same
regions is under five milliseconds, which is excellent. So like whenever
our messaging microservice instance receives a request
to write or read the message from
a european customer, it will get it and it will instantaneously
request or write data to or from the database
fast, right? It's calculated.
So here is what technology to use. How exactly do
you deploy your microservice instances?
It's up to you. You can use, let's say app engine
of Google Cloud platform or a similar service
in AWS or Microsoft Azure. Or you can deploy everything
in Kubernetes. It's highly likely that Kubernetes like containers
and Kubernetes as an orchestration layer are the best option
here. But anyway, we will leave this question and
answer it's up to you, literally whatever is more
preferable for your architecture. It's just that you need to deploy
those instances across various locations.
Same for the communication and the connectivity
layers and patterns between your different microservices.
It's true that the messaging microservice needs to read profiles
from the profile microservices. The reminders microservices
need to kind of pin the reminders to a specific message
and it will communicate the message in microservices. So here
is again, I'll give you flexibility.
Use a communication pattern that works best for
your deployment. You can use message brokers to communicate between microservices.
GrPC like sidecar or whatever is
more applicable. Okay, data layer,
application layer, and finally we have the cloud cloud
balancer because right now we have a global architecture,
we have database zones, we have microservice instances
across various continents, but we want this
back end and data layer to be as simple as
possible for our front end, for our end users.
That's why my suggestion would be to have a look and benefit
from the global cloud load balancers.
It's usually like every major cloud provider has them.
So what's the purpose of their global load balancers?
Load balancer provides you with any cast
IP address, that's a single external IP address that
can be used by your front end applications and your mobile applications,
and when someone, let's say,
connects to your front end. Depending on
the location of this user, the global cloud balancer will
send this request to the closest microservices and to
the closest database nodes that are located
close to this user. Let's take an example. Let's say
that we have a user who is based off Europe and this user opens
up your messaging application on iPhone,
iPhone, uses this anycast ip address and
connects to the global load balancer. The user refreshes
a discussion in one of the channels and you want to read all the
messages from this channel. So the global load balancer received
this request. It sees that, okay, the request comes from a person
in Europe. So then we have an instance of
our microservice in Europe. Let's forward this request there.
This microservice instance received this request and
it's already connected to our geodistributed database and it will send
this request to our local database nodes.
Easy right? So that's how you can take advantage of the global
cloud load balancers. Also, this load balancer
is fault tolerant. Basically it supports automatic
failover in case of outages. If, let's say,
your data center or instance of your
microservice is down here due to different zone or region level outages,
the global cloud balancer can redirect the user's traffic to the
other nearby location to the other nearby instance. It's all
done for you. Wonderful. So as a summary,
geodistributed applications are becoming a new norma, new normal
when we are building cloud native applications,
because usually the user base for our applications is global.
Even if you're planning that your application is going to be
used primarily in North America or in Asia,
it's highly likely that on some day, if you become successful,
then you will become the victim of your own success. You will get a global
user base. And it matters a lot what was
the foundation of your architecture, even if the first
version of your application was deploying your messenger application
and your database within a single region across multiple zones.
But if it can scale to other regions and
to other locations easily, then you are in a win win situation.
So right now you're using the resources that you need. But let's say in a
month or like in a week, you need to expand to Europe. You just spans
your database across, let's say North America, in Europe, or use
let's say any other multi region deployment mode that we discussed.
So that's why think globally when you're building
new cloud native applications and have a look and consider
the different design and consideration
patterns when you're building geodistributed applications.
If you want to learn more, my advice would be to check these two
books by Orali architecting for scale in designing data intensive
applications. They give us more
details on how to design highly available
and high performance distributed applications, and that
resonates really well with the topic of today with the geodistributed
apps. Also, if you are curious about the
data layer component, about the yugabyte, how it works,
how to deploy it, and how those multi region deployment
mode works, just my suggestion would
be go and complete one of our free courses. That's the easiest way
to get to know our database data and this
corporate messenger flag. Like corporate messenger, we have a gitpod sandbox
environment. Go to this GitHub project
and you can run this in your Gitpad
workspace. So right now we support as of
time of this recording, you would be able to start to
deploy your various you would be able to
deploy Yugo by DB in various configuration modes for multiregion
deployment like geode distributed primary cluster with red
replica, et cetera. And then over the time we are planning to improve this
sandbox, we are going to add the front end and the back end, et cetera.
So you can subscribe and watch to the changes. If you
have any other questions, you can always find tag me and send me
a message on Twitter. Or if you are particularly interested in
Yugabyte DB then join our communication like community. And the
easiest way to experiment with Yugabyte is by using our cloud
product. Thanks for joining, thanks for watching and
enjoy the rest of the conference.