Jamaica real
time feedback into the behavior of your distributed systems
and observing changes exceptions errors in
real time allows you to not only experiment with confidence, but respond
instantly to get things working again.
Youre hey,
how's it going today? I want to talk to you about JSDoCs.
It's sort of like typescript, but without all of
the typescript tooling. So if you
use typescript and you love it, maybe JS docs won't be
for you. But if you have either heard of typescript and have not tried it
yet, or you're curious, or you tried it and you didn't like it,
we're going to look at JS Docs and maybe it's going to be something that
youre interested in. Before we get into
that, two things I want to share with you.
One, I have a really awesome dog, super cute,
his name is Nugget. He's going to be in the presentation today. And two,
I actually really like JavaScript, so let's see how
those two things combine. First of all,
there's nugget. I told you he was cute. I hope I delivered.
He actually has an instagram. So side note, I do these presentations
halfway as a way to get him more followers, so make sure to
check him out later. And yeah,
like I said, I like JavaScript. I think there's a lot of cool things about
it. For example, it runs everywhere. I think this is probably
the number one feature that I like about JavaScript is that I
can take the same JavaScript code and run it in the browser on
the server, in an embedded device in freaking space.
For NASA it's doing all of those things, which is really cool.
Also, it only requires very minimal tooling.
I mean, you really just need
a browser to get started writing JavaScript. You can open up the
console and start playing around, and if you're on a computer you
probably have some sort of browser already available.
It also has a really huge community, which has
a lot of benefits in terms of providing more tooling or frameworks
or libraries, or if you need help debugging something.
Just having a rich community allows for all of these other resources
around the actual programming language.
But JavaScript has its quirks and its flaws and things that I
don't think are quite so cool. For example,
when I'm working in my editor, I really like having those little red squigglies
that tell me when I'm doing something wrong. And JavaScript is a
loosely typed language, which means it doesn't give us
quite as many hints of when those red squigglies should be
there, as it could be. This makes
it a little bit more difficult if you want to refactor a code base,
because you might introduce some bugs or errors that could
otherwise be caught by a more strongly typed language, such as
typescript, which we'll look at in a moment.
Part of these errors youre can also have introduced
with type mismatches, meaning if you have a function that
expects an input like a string, and you pass it a number,
JavaScript is not going to help you with that. And then you
can introduce a bug to your code that could otherwise have
been caught. In addition to introducing
these bugs, there's also scenarios
where you make chances to your code base, which could happen both internally
or from external code bases. So if you're working with a libraries, maybe they publish
new changes and you upgraded and you didn't catch some of those changes that
they made, you're not going to see those errors that could have been
caught. And again, this is where typescript comes
in. These are the things that make typescript super cool.
It's a strongly typed language, so because everything is typed,
the language processor knows what to expect of certain types,
which means it can help you catch things like typos or errors.
Like if you have an object that you're trying to access
a method and you accidentally misspell it, typescript is going to
give you that little red squiggly and say hey, that's not a
property on this object. In addition to
helping you catch those errors, it can improve the developer
experience by providing intellisense or autocomplete. So again,
if you're accessing properties on an object, you can
enter the object, the variable name, hit that period,
and then vs code could throw up a little prompt that says,
oh, do you want all of these properties that are available? It can really
help you learn the API of a system, which makes it
easier or better for onboarding and collaboration,
because people don't have to be as entirely familiar with
a code base before
they can start contributing to it.
Typescript also has some features that work really well for CI
CD. You can set up your system such that if
you introduce an error that could be caught by this strong
typing language, meaning you have like a type mismatch, you can actually set
up your delivery pipeline such that if those
errors exist, you don't actually push them to production,
and it kind of sends a warning or sends you an email that something's not
right. And finally,
having typescript or strong types available in the JavaScript
project makes maintenance a lot easier, because not only is it safer that
youre not going to introduce errors, it can help you catch or
get familiar with a code base that maybe you haven't touched in like six months.
And the other thing is, having these strong types can actually
be really cool because there's some tooling around typescript or strongly typed
languages that serve well for documentation, in that they can automatically
generate documentation for you.
All right, so I've been talking about all the cool things I like about typescript,
but there's still some things that I don't like as well, particularly around
the tooling. I really love that when I write
javascript, I can take it and copy and paste it to all of those different
environments that I talked about, and it's just going to work
because that's the underlying language. That's not the case
for typescript. You have to have a transpolation step
that takes your typescript code and then converts it to javascript,
which is the language that browsers understand.
There's also the learning curve that if I
am a lead developer and I want to bring on junior developers,
there's probably more people that are familiar with javascript today than
there are typescript, which means to introduce them to a typescript code base,
there's going to be a little bit of friction to get them up to speed
with learning the typescript ways.
I also think that typescript is more complex than JavaScript because
it introduces a lot of noise by having the type definitions
embedded into the code base, and it adds a sort of complexity that never
really got over. Also, typescript doesn't work everywhere.
Like I said, you can't copy and paste typescript from your code
base into the browser to debug things or to put them in other systems
or runtimes. And this
sort of pros and cons list of JavaScript on
its own, or typescript as a superset of JavaScript had
me kind of thinking like why not try and take the best of both and
sort of combine it? And we can do that
thanks to vs code. So we're going to look at JS
Doc today, but the only tool that we're going to begin with is vs code.
It's an editor that I think most JavaScript developers today are using.
Hopefully, if you're already using it, then you've already gotten started on
the path that I'm going to recommend. And vs code
is really cool because it actually has the typescript language
engine sort of powering its features like intellisense or
autocomplete. When you see those auto suggestions in vs code,
that's actually the typescript language saying or analyzing
your code and giving you those prompts. So what
that looks like is if you have a variable such as my object
here that has a property of hello, when you
try and access the properties on my object vs code
is going to prompt you hey, do you want to use the hello property?
Here it is. It's a type of string, and that's super handy
to know, especially if you have an object with, I don't know, tens or
dozens or hundreds of properties on it.
But there's one issue the intellisense
doesn't go so far to help catch when you have errors
such as type errors. So if we have a function here
called yell that expects a string and returns a string,
you could accidentally introduce an error if you pass a number
to that function. So if we pass
the number two to yell. So the
first step on my journey of getting
this type checking sort of strongly typed
in JavaScript path is to just enable typescript
checking more strict checking on individual files.
So you can do that at the file level by putting this comment
at the top of the file that is the at symbol with
PS check. And once you do that,
you can see already more little
red squigglies are going to appear in your code. For example,
if we have that object with a property of hello and we try and reassign
that property, typescript is going to say hold on,
that property is supposed to be a string, and now you're trying to convert it
to a number, and you can configure it such that hello
can be one or the other, but by default it's going to assume that
you have introduced a bug to your code. That's super handy.
So how do we sort of get that
feature where we can say, well actually that wasn't an error, we want to be
able to use a string or a number in that case, and this is where
JS doc comes in. JSDocs is a markup language used
to annotate JavaScript, where we use the comments
in JavaScript to add the type annotations
to our code. So it's not any different than JavaScript,
it actually works within JavaScript, and because it works within the comment
system, you can copy and paste it to different code bases, and it's
not going to actually do anything, but it can be used by
typescript to understand the
types of your project. The official typescript team
actually enabling using
JSDoCs so here's
sort of the example of JSDocs. We have a variable called age,
and we have a comment right above it where we say the type
of this variable is either a string or a number, which means that we
assign it to the number one. It's totally fine when we assign it to a
string of two. That's fine when we try to reassign it
to a boolean of false. Then we get the little red squiggly,
because that's not the type that age is supposed to be.
We can also see how we can add type definitions to our functions
with this documentation block where we define the
first parameter, which is a string and
has the name str, and this function returns a string.
So the function yell now can be passed a number.
But if you pass that number to the function,
you're going to get a little red squiggly that says hey, you're trying to use
a number, but this function only accepts a string. It's very handy
to catch those errors that we talked about before.
So once you start enabling JSDocs
or typescript checking on a file by file level,
you may find that it gets kind of tedious to add the comment at the
top of every single file. That is a nice way to incrementally start introducing
it. But eventually, if you're on a JavaScript project, you probably want to start enabling
it for the entire project, and you can do that a number of ways.
Number one, in vs code if you just want to enable it for yourself,
your instance of vs code, I'd recommend going into the settings and
checking the box js ts Chevron
implicit project config check js, turn that sucker
on and it's going to start checking all of your JavaScript
or using the typescript checker on all of your
JavaScript files without having
to use those comments. Option number two is great
if you actually want to enable this for yourself or for your team,
or your team that's using vs code, at least you can
add a file to your project called tsconfig JSOn
and put in the compiler options to check js and set
that to true. And this is again handy if youre are working on a
team, or if you want to do it for yourself as well. This is the
option that I actually prefer.
Now JSDocs has some native types built in
string number boolean array promise basically any
of the primitives that you're going to find in typescript. But then most
JavaScript projects are not built using just these primitives, you usually
have complex types such as objects, and you want
to be able to define those. Now typescript has that support built in,
and so does JS docs with
the typedef little tool.
So you can create a new type definition which is a type of
object and his name is dog, and that
object can expect to have properties of breed,
which is a string age which is a number and name,
which is an optional string. And we
can use that in
our code by creating a variable and assigning it the type of dog.
And we can say in this case we have a variable called my dog,
which is an object that is the breed of chihuini, age of four,
and name is nugget. And this is also a good example
here where you can define your types in one file
and actually import them to another file.
In fact, you can even combine typescript and js docs
by using, let's say a types D ts
file and define youre types in there and import them into a JavaScript
file using this syntax.
So as I mentioned, jsdocs,
I'm not going to dig into too much of the
syntax today. I think there's a lot of documentation out there, and I
have an article that I wrote that I'll link to for actually
learning the syntax, but I want to walk through the different
processes or phases of including it into a project. So we talked about
into files into an entire project, and then I feel like the next phase
is as part of a CI CD pipeline. This is going to be a
little bit different because up until now we haven't used any other
tooling additional besides vs code.
So we've done everything that's already built in. We haven't had to NPM install anything,
we haven't had to run any sort of other process in our
terminal or anything like that. That changes with CI CD,
because in a CI CD pipeline it's not
going to have the typescript language engine built in,
so we have to provide that for it. To do that
we can NPM install and save as a dependency or a dev dependency
the typescript compiler. Once we
do that, we can also go to a package JSON file. We can add
a script that I like to call TS, and we can
see that the dev dependencies include typescript.
Now, because we are now using the typescript compiler,
we probably want to start adding more configuration options
to our TS config file. One is we want to tell it which
files to actually check. So our index file, for example,
and we want to pass two new configuration
options to it. One is to allow JS,
even though we had checked JS before, but now we want to allow it for
the compiler, and we also want to turn
on the noemit flag. Now by default the typescript compiler
is going to take typescript source code and convert it
to or output JavaScript. We are going to
be starting with JavaScript, so we don't actually have to output anything,
unless you did want to do some transforms. I don't like to do that.
So once we have this typescript compiler in place,
we can actually open up our terminal and run that TS command.
And if we have errors in our code base we're going to be able to,
or it's going to tell us where those errors are, what file,
what line, what column, things like that. And this is again particularly
helpful if you want to build a pipeline. You can put this as
a step in the pipeline that
is required before deploying your code. And if this
step runs into one of these errors, it's not going to go to the next
step, which could be to again deploy your code super handy
to avoid type checking errors in production.
So now that we've introduced that type checking into our
CI CD pipeline, we can actually take it a step further and
include it into generating types
for our libraries. Now this is going to be something that is unique to library
authors like myself, but again, this is kind
of as we are going the next incremental step that I see.
So I want to be able to generate type definitions to provide to
my library's consumers.
We can do that once again by going back to that ts config
file. And now instead of turning on that no emit rule,
we actually want the typescript compiler to emit those type
definition files. However, we only want those type definition
files. So we're going to set declaration to true for the type
declarations. We're going to set emit declaration
only to true so that it doesn't actually output any javascript.
Because again, I'm already writing javascript, I don't need typescript
to turn it into more javascript, and I'm going to
define a folder where I want those type definitions to exist.
And with that I can go back to my package Json file and I can
tell package Json where my type definition files exist,
in this case in the disk folder, so that when I publish my package and
people are going to be consuming it, they can grab the type definitions for
my library from the disk folder.
So that is essentially the roadmap that I've followed through
my journey and I've felt that it works just fine.
I've started as just enabling type checking on
individual files and then on the entire project, and then
figured out how to incorporate it into a CitV pipeline and
then generate type definitions for the libraries that I'm publishing,
and it's been really awesome. I like
this approach because you can do it incrementally and you don't have to
rewrite your whole code base all at once. You can just kind of fix bugs
as they arise. So a
couple of closing points that I want to make is
that in this case you
don't have to pick well, with this approach you don't have to pick
either typescript or JS docs.
I really like this because it is an incremental adoption strategy. If youre
starting from JavaScript, you can just start adding these type annotations
with JSDocs to your JavaScript files,
and eventually you can start introducing more
and more typescript if you like that. In fact, you can
do a little bit of both. You can start with JavaScript and
then slowly incorporate more typescript. And then eventually,
if you like the typescript syntax better, you can transition into
typescript. I personally find that
JS docs works better for adding more descriptions
to things like objects or methods,
because I don't know if typescript has a syntax for
adding extended definitions to what an object property
is, for example, or what a type property is.
However, typescript is certainly kind
of the underlying engine that's powering all of this, and therefore it's going to be
better at some other things. For example, typecasting in
typescript is just way better. And if you
don't know what typecasting is, I don't think I need to get into it now.
But if you go down this route, you are going to find that as well.
There are some things that the typescript team
is not going to support that is part of JSDOCs, or things
that typescript has that they are not going to implement if
you're using the JSDOCs syntax. That said, I haven't
had any problem yet having large JavaScript
projects that are using JSDOCs and using typescript to
do the type checking on it. Either way,
you're probably still going to push some errors to production
typescript JSDocs. They're not going to help you catch every single
but, and they both can get extremely complicated.
It is a wonderful way to waste a whole bunch of
time on things that are not going to add any value to the actual user,
but is going to take hours and hours and hours of your day.
So either way, it's fun,
I guess, and it helps me catch a lot of errors that I would otherwise
not have caught. So I hope that you found that this talk
interesting, and I hope that you practice some of these things and it can help
you catch some otherwise or some errors that
would otherwise have gotten through. So that's all I've
got for you today. If you want to learn more, I do have a blog
post that I wrote about this that basically outlines in more detail this
process. It's Austin gil.com typescript theeasyway
and if you have any questions, I would love to connect with you.
I'm looking to do these talks that I can talk to more people in the
community. So if you like the talk, if you hated it, if you have corrections
that you want me to make, reach out to me on Twitter. I'd love to
chat with you about this or anything else related to
web development. And don't forget my dog is
really cute. If you like the pictures of Nugget and you want more, head to
instagram.com at nuggetthemighty.
So I hope you enjoy this talk and I will catch you out on the
Internet.