Whatever problem you want to solve, these are hundreds of
potential open source tools that can help you. Some are
better, some are worse, but when it comes to security,
you don't want to mess around. We at JIT
build a security platform that leverages open source security
tools in order to figure out the best ones we
needed to go on a tool checking journey. I would
love to share that with you. Hi, my name
is Avi Ram. I'm co founder and chief product officer at
JIT, which is a continuous security platform for developers.
What this means is we help dev organizations build secure
applications from day zero by automating security
plans using open source tool that we have curated.
We have researched and tried hundreds of tools to
choose the best ones for our needs. We tested
the tools on real projects and got real results.
This means that we are very much
familiar with various open source security tools
that the market has to offer and I would like to share
insights with you and generate interest among
you regarding these tools.
There are many properties we use to rank the security
tools. Here are some of them. We want to
see a tool that actually detects what it
should true positive rate high true positive rate
and that it has low ratio of false positive.
We want tools that are easy to use. Their output
makes sense and the tools in general should
be easily integrated into these. CI we
want a tool that is supported by large communities of developers
and that in general is maintained
on a regular basis.
In terms of ownership. We see some advantage
when there is a prestigious company behind a tool
because it creates a standard.
In terms of GitHub stacks, these stacks
are a good indicator that the tool is popular.
We also consider that as one important property and
also licensing. We want tools that are free and we have
some preferences to permissive licenses
such as MIT and Apache.
These are the security categories that we will focus at.
These five, though there are many, I believe
these five categories are a good starting point.
So let's start with dependency check.
The mission of dependency check, also known as SCA
software composition analysis, is to detect publicly
disclosed vulnerabilities in project dependencies like
packages, libraries and so forth.
In our list of contestants, we have three tools
which all of them are good retire, JS,
OS dependency check and NPM audit.
All of them detect code vulnerable dependencies.
We decided to go with OS
dependency check. Yeah, that's because of few reasons.
Usability is super efficacy
is very good, high rate of true positive yeah, there are
comes false positive but very good.
Very good rate of true positive.
It's very easy to use and it's
also very popular tool, so we recommend
using it.
In this example we see that there is a dependency named ADM
zap. It's a JavaScript implementation for Zip, data compression
for node JS and it is used in this
project. The dependency I'm
telling you in advance, the dependency contains vulnerabilities.
So let's see how OS dependency check faces
that.
So you can see these is the output of our dependency check and
it identified that this dependency day ADM
Zip is associated with three cvs with
severity level of critical okay,
let's move on to the next category, which is secret detection.
The mission here is to detect hard coded secrets in various
formats. So this could be password,
ssH keys, AWS credentials and more.
The tools do that by employing regular expressions,
many various regular expressions and
by calculation of entropy.
We compared between three tools git
secrets by AWS labs detect secrets by
Yelp and Gitlix, which is owned by individual
developer. All of them are good and free.
We decided to go with, so we chose
Gitlix. It detects hard coded secrets like password,
API keys and tokens in local and GitHub
repositories, private and public. Some pros
for Gitlix very good detection rate. It's very
easy to integrate to the CI.
It is developed with almost 100
contributors and it provides reporting in various
formats. When compared with the other two tools, we prefer
to go with Gitlix even though the others are good
as well.
So this is an example of a key and
this is the output of Gitlix. You can see that Gitlix identified
these secret and associated with a rule that is called AWS
access token because it obviously matched a
regular expression built
for AWS access token structure.
Okay,
so the next category is terraform scanning.
The mission here is to detect security vulnerabilities,
cloud misconfiguration issues and all that by analyzing
the infrastructure as code, which is very important.
Security capabilities security capability for
those of you who work with infrastructure as code,
we have compared many tools. The top were check by bridge crew,
now Palo Alto Kix by checkmarks and TFSec
by Aqua Security. The good news here is that
all tools are great. They are backed by good companies
and they constantly improve and they do their
job. All of them, by the way, are either MIT or
Apache. Matwizi decided to
go with Kix and
that is for two reasons. First, Kix has
exceptional detection rate that we love and
the other reason is that it includes indication of
severity, which is very useful for prioritization
for DevOps people who are not security experts. So the
indication of severity was for us an
important property of KiCs.
So in this example we have a terraform model where EBS data is
not encrypted, as you can see in this example.
And Kix identifies this misconfiguration and ranks
it as medium,
together with sharing detailed description and guidance
how to fix it see
medium and the relevant description.
Next category is the runtime scanning.
The mission here is detecting vulnerabilities in web applications
while they are running. That includes also API
scanning and it can run in a nonauthenticated code, what we
call black box testing, or authenticated mod,
what we call gray box testing.
The contestants here
were OWASP, Nikto and Arachni.
All these tools can help you evaluate the security of web applications
and each of them has above three k stars so
they do their job and they are popular.
In this category we decided to go with zap.
It's a very popular open source Das
tool. It is container by the Ops Owasp foundation
and has been around over a decade. We chose it over
the others for these reasons. It includes
authenticated and non authenticated web
app scanning. It includes API scanning. It has
good range of features like vulnerability scanning,
fuzzing reporting, and is well supported by a
large community.
In this example, Zap scanned a web application and detected
that the content security policy CSP header
is not present in the server response.
Essentially, the CSP is used to prevent cross site
scripting, click jacking and other code injection stacks.
So it's great that Zap identified it.
And final category for today, container scanning.
The mission here is to detect vulnerabilities from all
sorts in container images.
We reviewed and tested various tools, but two
topped the chart trivy by Aqua and Claire by
quie, now part of red hat.
We decided to go with Trivy due to its efficacy and
easy integrated with the CI.
Here is an example of output when Trivy
was scanning a docker image that
I created based on Debian 11.3.
So you can see that trivy identified
the vulnerable library.
Now let me show you a quick
demo about integrated these five security tools into
the CI pipeline. I'm using GitHub
and GitHub actions and you
can view the demo repository in
this link I created.
So first let's take a look at
the workflow file.
So you can see that the workflow file,
the jobs here are triggered by push.
Okay, and these are five jobs here,
one which deals with secret detection. These we
run Gitlix. The next one,
the dust, the runtime scanning, we use
zap. For the infrastructure code
scanning, we use kics,
for the FCA we use dependency check.
And for container scanning we use
three d.
All these jobs run in parallel whenever I
commit a new change.
So let me do that, I will just
add a space here,
commit a change.
And you see that these workflow kicks in JIT.
So you see that all the jobs run in parallel.
And I see that secret scanner finished.
So if we drill down, we can see that what
we can see that a password,
a secret was detected in
a file named Docker file. The secret
itself does not appear here, but you
can see that JIT gitleaks actually
detect the secret. And now you can see it
gives also the line number, line eight. So if
we'll go to the docker
file, line number eight.
Cool.
So we see that dependency check
also finished. If we drill down, we will see that
the report was uploaded and
show you later on. And container scanning
also finished. So we see the detection of Otrivi
in here,
the dependency check.
This is the dependency check report
that all dependency check created.
And this is the report that's
upgraded.
And let's
see also the infrastructure
scotscanner in here you
can see for example that Kics
found dynamodb table not encrypted, it gave it medium
and provided some details about JIT.
And also the
alerts also appear here as annotations.
Cool. So you have access to this repo,
you can clone it and play with it.
Okay, let's go back to the deck.
Okay. Like you see, there are plenty of excellent open source tools
that can be used. Yes, even for things as important as
security. And it's very possible to build an
entire security program only by using open
source solutions. At JIT we took it into
the next level. We enable users to manage
a security plan and fully automate it
with a continuous security mindset.
We do that in conjunction with providing a
dev native experience by adding comes inside
the pr. So developer can have a great
user experience more than just drilling
down into the output of every
tool in the CI itself. At JIT,
we automate security plans and provide a great
dev experience.
So that's about it for today. I hope
it was interesting for
you and thank you very
much for joining.