Hello friends. I hope you are doing well and you're healthy
and you're keeping safety. So I'm Abisheks
Doshi and today's talk is on block or you can manage blocks
of your app app with blocks. So first of all,
who am I exactly? I am a Google developer
expert for Dart and Flutter. I am also a Google
mentor. So basically I mentor individuals
as well as startups to migrate to flutter or learn flutter.
I am also Flutter vulsar organizer, co organizer
of Flutter India and I have been working in Flutter
since almost past three years now and professionally
I am a senior flutter engineer at Somnia
Software. I've been writing event tech articles on Flutter
since past six to one year,
six months to one year now. So yeah, you can say
that I'm suitable for taking this session.
So what is flutter exactly?
And why is it trending so much? So first of all,
Flutter was released in around 2018 and
it is developed by Google and it is a UI toolkit
that supports multiple platforms like Android,
iOS, Web, macOS, Windows, Fuchsia OS,
Linux embedded systems,
et cetera. And it is trending because one of
the reason is it is open source and it has
a large community support and it is easy to use.
So coming to today's topic, what are the points
for discussion then? So first we would see what is state,
what is state management, why state management
is needed, and if we need state management,
then what is block exactly? And some terminologies related to block.
And then if time permits we would be doing live coding or I
would show you the code. So first
of all, what is state? So in flutter, everything is
widget. Widget, you can say is a smallest
form of UI that you can show on the screen. If you
are from web development background, you can compare widget as a tag.
So in web development we have button as a tag. In flutter
we have different kinds of buttons,
has a widgets, raised button, elevated button, text button,
et cetera. So in the same way, every widget
would be having a state. Or you can say every widget has properties,
or the properties of a widget considers to be a
state. Now let's suppose you have a text field.
So the text that you enter becomes the state of
that particular text field. So every properties related to that
widget becomes the state. And the state can
be independent. The state can be dependent on one another.
It is also possible to have a single state in the entire application.
It is also possible to have a single state in a one particular
widget or one particular file. Based on how you manage your state
or based on how you lay out your UI.
Also, it is possible to manipulate the state
throughout the lifecycle. So yeah, when you're handling with
state or when you are working with state,
you should keep in mind that there are
chances that you might face issues or
your app can crash if the state is not managed properly.
So what is the role of state then and how is it useful?
So basically there are three points that we can consider for
the state. That is, information about widget can
rebuild UI whenever we need and gives control over
the entire lifecycle of the widget. Now going deeper with
the state object, we can access the information about
that particular widget, or we can even access the information
about the widgets, about the parent widget.
So yeah, state is the information that can be read synchronously
when the widget is built, it holds the properties of the widget.
So as I said, state can be considered as the properties of the widget
and we can access that properties with the state.
So second point is it can rebuild UI
whenever we need. So basically state object is responsible
for rebuilding your UI. That's the reason we call set state.
We have a set state method,
we have a set state method that updates
your UI or recalls or rebuilds your
UI. And the third point is gives control over
lifecycle. State can change during the lifetime of the widget.
If you don't utilize it properly, you can
have adverse effect on your app. Basically your app
can crash, you can have memory,
lets, et cetera, et cetera.
So now what is state management then?
Basically has the name suggests managing the state properly
so that you don't face any issues in your app
and you can rebuild your UI whenever you need.
Then why state management? Why is it needed? Or why is
it a really hot topic in flutter? So if data
changes or new data is being added, then and only then the request to
the server will be sent. So for example, let's suppose you
want to update your UI
when your API call is successful. So in
this case data management will be important because let's
say you call the API, it takes time to get the
data and then you want to update the UI. Or let's say
when the app is being hit, you want to show a loader so
that the user gets to know that the API
is being hit, the data is being fetched, and then you
can update the UI. So in this case, state management is important.
State management helps to centralize and make the
maintenance of code very easy. Also improves the quality of code by
reducing the code size and making it more readable as well.
Let's take an example. Let's suppose that you have an
application where there are only two screens, page one and page
two. Now you want to pass data from page one to page two.
It becomes very easy, right? You can pass it when you navigate
to page two. But what if you have a screen? What if
you have an app? These, there are five pages and you
want to pass data from page one to page five. So you can't
pass the data from page one to page two to three to four to five,
right? You have to pass data from page one to directly
to page five. So in these case, state management helps.
State management basically will help you to allow excess
of data wherever you want.
So what is block then? Basically, state management can be
implemented using many techniques. One is block
provider Riverpod Redux Rxdart.
Many such packages are available for implementing state
management, and one of that is block. Basically block stands for business
logic components. Block basically uses the concept of inherited widget.
Not only block, but any state management package that
you check will use inherited widget concept.
We can implement blocks using stream and sync, but we
already have a package called flutter, underscore block, which is a wrapper of stream
and sync.
So there are a few terminologies related to block,
which is event, state block provider, block builder,
blocks listener and block consumer. We'd go through them one by one.
So first is event.
Now what exactly do you mean by event? Event you
can say is a class or
a trigger that you pass through the block and
based on that block manages the data. So let's
suppose you are having a login functionality, Google sign
in, let's say. So what your app would be
doing is on the UI part, it adds an event or
sends an event to the block. Let's suppose the name of the event is
Google sign. In event it sends the event to the blocks,
blocks matches that event or takes that event. And from
that basically you can also pass parameters like
any user id, email id, et cetera, et cetera to the
event. So block would take that parameters, it would
process that parameters, or it would process based
on that data, maybe an API call
or anything that you want. And once
the process has been successfully completed, it would send
a successful state to the UI, back to the UI.
If it fails, it will send a failure state.
So to summarize, we can say that event is something
that you send from UI to block, and state is something that
you send from block to UI.
Now what is block provider. Then basically blocks provider is a
widget that provides the instance of your blocks to the widget
tree. Now the normal practice is to wrap
the material app that is the root of our widget root of our
application with the block provider and provide the blocks
to the entire widgets tree. But this would create a single state for the entire
widget tree. Now if you want to have multiple instances
of the same block, it would be good to wrap the page root
root of the page with block provider. Next is block
builder. Basically block builder is responsible for
rebuilding your UI. Block builder is a widget that
matches state and rebuilds these UI
based on the state that is available from the
block. Block listener is something same
to block builder, but it doesn't rebuild your UI,
it just listens to states and performs some action. So let's suppose
you want to navigate to a page. Navigate to home page. When Google
sign in is successful then you would use block listener because you're not rebuilding
your UI, you are navigating to a different page. But let's suppose you
want to rebuild your UI. You want to show something
different on your UI based on success rate of the
Google sign in, then you would be using block builder.
Now what is block consumer then? Basically block consumer
is block builder plus blocks listener.
Block builder, the combination of block builder and block listener.
Basically when you need to use both, when you want
to process some data on the UI part as well as rebuild your UI,
it is preferable to use block consumer.
So I hope these terminologies are clear because these are
the base of blocks, you can say.
So yeah, enough of talk. Now let's check
some work these. So basically whenever
we create an application, our first,
or you can say our basic app
that we have is counter application.
So what we are doing right now is
to have the counter application to update
the counter application into block.
So I hope the vs code is visible and
let me zoom a bit.
Yeah,
okay, so there is one class called main dart
which just provides my home page.
So you can see here we have the block provider and I have
provided the counter blocks to my home page. Now what
is inside the counterblock? So what
counterblock does is it
maps the event to state. This is the older version of block.
The newer version has very simple code. But yeah, basically the
concept remains same. It maps the event to state.
So if event is counterevent increment,
then yield the state with an incremented value.
So what is the event then? Basically it's just an NM where
we have added an increment part. Now in
the home part you can see I have created a
variable for counter blocks and
inside the build method I have initialized it.
This can be done even in your init state as well.
Basically we are providing the instance of blocks from the parent
to this variable.
Now the code is pretty simple. You can see just 43
lines of code with all the formatting and stuff.
So the scaffold and everything remains same.
What I have done here is in the body part I have
added a block builder and in that return
a text widget which displays the state. Now the state is
just an integer value over here, but we can have multiple states
based on our use case. Now when the user clicks on
the button, the floating action button, a counterblock
event is being added over here. So you can see in the entire
application set, state is not used, which means that
I am not rebuilding the UI using setstate.
So I hope the code looks good and it's
pretty simple.
I guess the code is very simple
for the counter blocks. But yeah, when your application goes
in bigger size it is possible that you would get
confused with all the blocks, elements, event, state, et cetera, et cetera.
Basically that was it. But the
work that we have, you can see you saw that
the code was very less to just update
these counter application with
the block part. So yeah,
if you have any questions, feel free to ask.
I hope you learned something new and
feel free to connect with me on Instagram, Twitter,
LinkedIn, GitHub, Medium, et cetera.
And the username remains same, that is Abisheks Doshi 26.
Yeah, you can read my articles on medium and
these also username remains same Abisheks Doshi 26 so
you can go abhishek Doshi 26 medium.com
for my medium articles, I guess.
Thank you so much for joining today's session
and I hope you learned something and I hope that you
stay safe and maybe migrate to flutter as
well. Thank you so much.