Are actually going to start off today with a little bit of a game.
I'm going to give you about 15 seconds to go around your house and
find two major items. See, the first item
is going to be something in your household that begins
with the first letter of your first name. The second
item that you're going to grab is going to be an item that begins with
the first letter of your last name. Ready?
Go. Okay, let me
share the items that I brought with me. See, my first name
is Amber, and so I brought an apple because both begin
with the letter a. My last name, amber Vanderburg,
which is actually Dutch, and it means from the castle.
And V was a little bit tricky for me, but I found
a vinyl record. So I have an apple
for Ember and a vinyl record.
Amber Vanderburg. And this is
just a fun way to really
get to know one another. See, I've worked with teams from
all over the world. I'm actually the owner of a company called the Pathwayz Group,
and we work with teams all over the world, helping in effective
leadership training and team building and strategic human resources.
And one thing that we found, especially in this remote time,
is that many are suffering from a little bit of
screen fatigue. And this is a
very practical and fun way that we can get
our team members up, moving around and also
keeping them engaged, and then also being able to
bring back the personality and the relationship aspect
of youre meetings. See, it's so important
that we are so intentional about building those
relationships and having that personal communication
beyond professional gap.
And this is one game that I really encourage you
to use within your meetings to continue
to be intentional in building that relationship. Whether it be a fun
game like this or a show and tell or telling
funny stories or dressing up, these are fun
and, dare I say, innovative ways to
bring back the personality and the relationship side
of our meetings. So I guess we've done innovative
problem solving in the first, oh, I guess, minute of
this presentation. But being innovative,
and you see, innovation really comes down to problem
solving. And it's so important in our innovation
methods to first identify what type
of problem that we're solving.
See, if youre looking for an answer,
you're probably going to find an answer. But if you're not asking the right
questions and clearly identifying what types of problems
that you're solving, then the answer that you seek
might not be the solution. The answer that you
get might not be the solution that you're seeking. So it's
really important that we first get specific so
that we can get strategic in our innovation methods.
We don't want to be innovative just for innovation's sake,
we want to be innovative. That way we can
be strategic and be creative in our problem solving.
What I founder with, working with teams all over the world, is that there
are three major types of problems that many
teams will solve. The first is to fix
or repair can existing system,
process or product. And it's in
these scenarios that we are fixing something that is existing
and that is the type of problem that we're solving that I
would really encourage your team to do a causal analysis and
really get down to the root cause of what that
problem actually is that way. Again, youre can
be specific so that you can be strategic in
your innovation efforts. So the first type of problem
is to fix an existing product,
system or process. The next is to improve
or build upon an existing product,
system or service. And in these scenarios,
your innovation methods are going to be a little bit different
from fixing a problem. Here you're actually
improving upon a problem or
you're improving upon a product. And so in these scenarios,
I highly suggest a bit of value engineering and
identifying what about your product is great
now that you can improve upon. And it's in
these scenarios that we oftentimes seek to be more innovative
and improve upon our products so that we can stay
competitive, so that we can stay relevant and
we can stay engaged with our target audience.
It's for reasons like this that we have an iPhone 5678,
ninja ten. We have variations.
As our technology is improving, we are
seeking to be more innovative so that we can improve youre
products to, again, stay relevant and to stay engaged.
This method and this product and this process is going to
be a little bit different than fixing an existing problem.
So the first is to fix an existing problem. The second is to
improve upon an existing product or service.
And then the third is to create something totally
new. And it's in these scenarios that I think of
great inventors like Edison and Tesla and Disney
that created something totally new and
that were very innovative within their own efforts.
And so again, it's very important that we identify
the types of problems that we are solving and
really bring a purpose to our innovation.
That way we can be strategic in our
innovation efforts. And this really boils
down to asking the right questions
so that we can identify the problems that we
are solving. And this comes in a few different ways.
First, I'm very specific in the way that I am
asking my question. This isn't a dramatic shift. It's a
slight pivot. I'll give you an example.
What is five plus five? The answer
is ten. But what if I ask the question this
way? What two numbers equal ten?
By asking this question just slightly differently, I've opened
up the doors to more possible answers.
Yes, there is five plus five, but there's also six plus four.
Seven plus three. Ninja plus one. There's a variety
of different answers that
we can bring to the table, depending on the way that we ask the question.
And then also, I encourage your team to ask a series of
whys and whats, and asking it at least
three to five times to really get down to the root cause.
Again, it's so important that we have a purpose behind our
innovation. The more and more I work with teams, I find that the
biggest oversight to innovation efforts really
is in the beginning and identifying exactly
what problem you are solving.
So it's important to first identify the problem
that youre are solving,
and then after you have identified the problem that youre solving,
it is so important that we can create an environment where
people can truly thrive.
Now, this comes from building a
type of balance within your team, and balance is
going to come in a few different ways. First,
it's important that we try to create
an environment and take on a challenge that will allow us to enter
into our flow state. Now, flow is a
concept by a psychologist named Mihai
Shishek. Mihai. I think I said that right?
And he writes about this concept of flow,
meaning that it is important
that we try to find a level of challenge that
meets our current ability. So if I
have a current ability of running a
mile, then taking on a challenge of running 15
miles is probably going to be very
frustrating for me. It's going to be a little
bit disheartening, and I will more than likely not be
into my flow state. More than likely,
I'll probably give up at some point in that
project because it is significantly above
my current level. In the same regard,
if I am used to running 10 miles and then I
run a half a mile, then more than likely I'll become
a little bit bored and disengaged and disinterested
and not really enter into that flow state either.
The key is to find something that
takes into consideration our current ability and then challenges
us just a little bit higher so that we are challenged
and we do feel that challenge, but it also is within our
ability. And so that is how we can enter in, really,
through our biggest flow state. So it's
important, whenever we are creating our environment, that we
create an environment that will allow people to enter in through their
flow state. The next balance
that we can seek within our teams is to create a
balance within our existing systems
and really creating an
environment that has a balance within our framework.
And this just means having a balance within the constraints.
So we want to clearly identify
the goal, we want to clearly identify the problem, and then also
clearly identify the framework in which we are working.
It is very critical for our leaders to identify
the what and the why, and then provide
opportunity for ownership within the how,
within the processes and the methods and the projects and the roles
within that framework. So having an open
framework with no constraints at all
is actually limiting for creativity.
True creativity actually thrives with some constraints,
and so it's important that we take that time to identify the framework.
Of course, in the same regard, if we go on the other end and
provide so many constraints, that can be very frustrating
to our team members as well. And so what
I would recommend for your team is to clearly identify
that what and that why and then clearly
outline what the framework is and what those constraints are, and then
provide opportunity for ownership within the
how. So provide. Seek balance
within flow. Also seek balance within your framework.
Finally, seek balance within your feedback loops.
Now, many of you are within our developers
and are within the development industry, and so you
know a lot about feedback loops, and especially in
youre ideation phase, it is very critical
that we are mindful of a balance within the
span of time within our feedback loops.
So if you are in a brainstorming session and
every idea is shut down before it is
even fully said, if everything is
being criticized directly
every single time, then that can actually create an environment
where team members are less likely to
share their ideas and are less likely to enter into
that flow state and less likely to share their
most innovative ideas. And so it's important that we have a balance that
we are taking in a lot of ideas, that we
are, especially in this ideation phase,
that we are listening to those ideas, and then having that
feedback loop of analyzing the idea after
it has been fully, after it's been formated,
after it's been vocalized to a certain degree. So it's important that we
have a balance within those feedback loops of providing feedback.
Yes, we don't want an idea, a single idea, to go
all the way through completion and then having a
feedback loop, but saying, oh, let's actually analyze this. No, let's still
analyze this in the ideation phase, but let's not
squash every idea as soon as it is being said. So seeking
that balance between getting all the ideas out and then having
a balance within the feedback loop. So that's just
another area that it's really important to have a balance
in your feedback loops to create an environment where people can truly thrive,
especially specifically in that
ideation phase. So create that
environment where people can truly thrive.
Now, I began this session by talking
about adding the personality and the relationship back
into our meetings, especially within our virtual
work right now and our remote work teams.
And it is so critical that we have a relationship
with our teams and that we can truly assess our team dynamics.
See, creativity and innovation actually goes through ebbs
and flows of individual thought and having time
for self reflection and to spend time by yourself. But it
also requires time for us to collaborate
with other individuals and to work within a team.
It is not a one or the other. It is actually both
working together. And so it's important that we
take the time to assess our different team
dynamics, especially within those innovation teams.
And you can assess your team dynamics in a few different ways.
So I'm going to give you a couple of different activities that we use within
our remote teams that youre can actually pause
the video right now and you can do, or you can save till later
and you can actually do within your team. Now,
whenever I am working within a team that is within a brick and
mortar institution, everyone is together and physically
close. Then I'll have people stand on different sides of the room. We'll stand up,
we'll sit down, but we can do something very similar within remote
teams. And we can do this through conference calling and through Zoom calls.
And the first activity that I do is very simple.
See, I'll ask my team members while everyone is in
a gallery setting on zoom.
If they are youre comfortable. If they're very comfortable with
confrontation, to lean towards the right side of the screen. If they
are not comfortable at all with confrontation, lean more towards the
left side of the screen. And then in a snapshot,
I can get a clear idea of my team dynamics,
of a very specific aspect of my team dynamics.
Other questions I'll ask is, if you prefer phone calls
and zoom meetings, go to the right side of your screen. If you prefer teams
and emails, go to the left side of your screen. If you
are more of a morning person, go to the right
side. If you're more of an evening person, go to the left side.
If you prefer public praise, go to the right side.
If you prefer personal praise, go to the left side. Right. And so
I'll go through a series of these questions,
naturally very specific towards the actual project
that you are working on. But as a leader, this is
really powerful. And as a team member, this is really important to
know. If most of my team prefers
emails and I'm calling on the phone every time,
then that might be a source of maybe some frustration
or some tension. Or if I'm scheduling all of my meetings in the morning
and everyone is more evening people or late afternoon people,
then this is a quick snapshot that I can use
to help be very intentional in my leadership
and time as a team member within my
team. And so this can be a really great, very simple,
less than a minute to get can idea of the team dynamics
within your innovation team and within your organization.
That's a really quick way that youre can get those ideas.
A second activity that I use within my team requires
a little bit more than leaning left and right.
See, in this activity, I am going to ask
that everybody grab a piece of paper and
a writing utensil and
I'm going to leave it up to youre to be a good steward of
your time. But in this activity, I ask
team members to draw as many circle
item objects as they can in
90 seconds. So it's very quick.
You have a minute and a half to draw as many circle
item objects as you can. Ready?
Go.
All right. If you pause the video and did it right, then well done.
If you save this until later, then yeah, I really do encourage you
to do that activity. It can be very exhilarating.
And one thing that I do within teams is I then ask
the team members to, if they would
like they can share their results, whether that
be on slack, they can share them on Microsoft Teams,
Google teams, they can share their results.
There are some teams that feel more comfortable just sharing the number of
I drew eleven objects. Most people will
share what they drew and my bold team
members will actually share the pictures.
So definitely look at the comfort level of your team members
generally there's actually a little bit of all three of
sharing the number, sharing what you actually drew and then sharing the pictures.
There's a couple of different insights that you can get about youre team
dynamics in this activity. See, more than
likely you'll have some members of your team that actually
drew a
lot of different circle objects and they
may have drawn 1520 different
objects. And more than likely those
objects that were drawn are going to be very simple,
very quick and not have a lot of detail to them. And in
the same regard, there are some people on your team that might
have only drawn six, seven, eight different
objects, but more than likely, they will be a little bit more detail oriented.
And so it's in this dynamic, again, in less
than two minutes, more than likely, you can get a snapshot on the
ideation process of your different teams, members of
those that can think of a lot of different ideas,
but maybe not all of the details, all in that moment. And then
there are some people that will think more of the details first,
including those details even within a time constraint, and there
isn't one that is better than the other. It's actually really
important that you have both within the team.
And so that's a really powerful activity. Again, less than
two minutes that I do within teams to get a really
clear insight about the type of ideation that my
teams members will more than likely bring to the table as
we are doing a little bit more in depth ideation for
the actual problem that we are solving. This is just a fun activity
that we can do within our teams today.
The third major activity that I do within
teams to really get an assessment of team dynamics is
to have my team members pull out an index card or a
note card, and on one side write the
strengths or the areas of strength that they
believe that they can bring to the team. So these are
specific to the project, and these are areas that they believe
that they will be an asset to the team. And so they write that on
one side of the card, and then on the opposite side of the card,
I ask team members to write a strength that they really
hope that somebody else in the team has.
Right. So what's a strength that you really hope there's somebody else on my team
that can bring to this table? I'll give you an example
using myself. See, my ideation
is drawing 20 different circle item objects,
but none of them have much detail at all.
See, I am more of a visionary type person.
I can see the forest, but I don't always see the
trees. And so I long for
somebody on my teams to help provide that balance of someone
that is more detail oriented, that is really good at the follow through,
and asking those questions to get really down to
those details. And so I always
write on the backside that I really long
for someone that is detail oriented.
And it's in these note cards that you can
get a good idea of ways that team members will
more than likely complement each other in the
same regard areas in which there might be
tension and there might be conflict. And it's from
these types of team dynamic assessments
that I then move in to proactive conversations.
Now, proactive conversations is just
a very simple conversation in which I go into any
teams at the beginning of a project, at the beginning of a new
team, or whenever I'm taking on a new client
and the conversation goes like this,
at some point in this project I'm going to fail you.
At some point in this relationship, there's going to be tension,
there's going to be heat. And so
while the emotions are low now,
if you've done, say, the note card, if you've
done the note card where you have the strengths and weaknesses on both sides,
or the strengths and the strengths you hope someone else has on both sides,
then you can even be specific and say, our emotions are low now.
But I know at some point my
lack of attention to some details is probably going
to frustrate you and
you not always seeing the big picture and the big vision is maybe going to
frustrate me, but the emotions are low now. So let
us proactively discuss how we're going to handle that
situation whenever it arises. Let us
set up a script of how we are going to handle that
situation. And this is a really powerful conversation because
it does a couple of things. First, it normalizes
conflict, which is so important,
oftentimes conflict in teams is avoided because we don't want
to admit that there was a problem. But by having
a proactive conversation, we have already
said not only is this normal, it's actually expected
within our team. And the second thing is that
it is expected and we already have a game plan.
We know how we are going to handle conflict whenever it
arises. See if you are
providing opportunities for ownership within your team.
With these opportunities for ownership within your team, there's also
greater opportunity for conflict.
See, innovation and healthy teams engage
in healthy conflict. And with a greater
opportunity for conflict comes a greater opportunity
for conversations over complacency.
Say that again. With an opportunity for ownership comes
a greater opportunity for conflict. With an opportunity
for conflict comes a greater opportunity for conversations
over complacency. And so
it's so critical in these times
that we equip and prepare our teams to be
successful to engage in that healthy conflict.
A few years ago, I was actually an academy football coach
or soccer coach for the Adidas game day academies and Paris
Saint Germain academies in Bengalur, India. To coach
widely the first generation of athletes on both an elite and a grassroots
level. I coached about a dozen teams, mostly boys with a
few girls. And as I joined the team, I noticed that many
of our players would come and they would stand on a line, kick a
ball, wait for instruction, and they
would come to our sessions. They would stand on a line, kick a ball,
wait for direction. They would stand on the line, kick a
ball, wait for feedback. And while this may have been the
most efficient way to teach a skill in a game
scenario, it was a disaster.
Oftentimes our players would come to sessions and they would stand
in a line, they would come to games and they would
kick the ball perfectly, exactly the way that we taught them.
And then before the play was even over, they would turn to the sideline,
to the coach for further direction and feedback. See, they had
mastered the task, but they didn't quite understand how it applied to the
overall game scenario. And so we were
able to transform the way that we were training our players.
And so, rather than stand on the line, kick a ball, wait for instruction,
we provided challenges. So from here,
kick the ball to knock down those three cones, because in order
to do that, you're going to have to kick with power and precision.
So how are you going to kick the ball with
power and precision? Because in a game scenario, whenever you pass, whenever you
kick, whenever you shoot, you're also going to have to kick the ball with power
and precision. And so youre players
tried to find the best way to kick the ball. And from this I saw
some of the most heated debates I'd ever seen amongst seven year
olds trying to decide if the best way to kick the ball
was with the in foot or with the laces.
In reality, both ways were right. And so our
players were able to expand the
tools in their toolbox to be successful footballers.
And it was so important for our players to then
have proactive conversations because they knew that
now they were no longer just standing in line, kicking a ball, waiting for instruction.
They were engaging in conversations
rather than complacency, and they were having healthy
conflict because they were given more opportunities for
ownership within their methods and their processes
and their projects and their roles. We did
that by identifying the what and the why and giving opportunities
for ownership within the how. And it's so important that
we do that within our teams today. Going to
give you one more activity that I use within teams and organizations.
See, I challenge teams to get a
piece of paper and draw eight boxes. So draw one
line horizontally and then three lines vertically.
I'm going to give you a challenge. See, again,
you can pause the video now, or you can do this with your team
after this session, but I challenge you to set
your phone, set your watch to beep every 15 or
20 seconds, depending on what level of challenge youre want to take on.
So you have your eight boxes,
and I challenge you to draw a different picture of
a dog. All right, draw a different
picture of a dog. See, I was working for a veterinarian
clinic, and they had a dog as a mascot,
except the dog was not smiling. It actually looked like it
was frowning a little bit. But the customers,
they did not like the frowning dog, but they loved
the fact that it was a dog, and they loved the fact that the dog
had floppy teams. And so I'm
going to give you two minutes,
15 seconds per box to draw a picture
of a dog on each box.
As the timer beeps after 15 seconds,
you immediately move to the next box and you draw another
dog for 15 seconds. As soon as it beeps again, you go to the next
box, and we do this over and over and over again till we have eight
boxes ready. Go.
Okay, either you pause the video or you so welcome
back. If you pause the video or youre doing this at the end of the
session. See, in this situation, we now have eight
different pictures of dogs. I will use different
scenarios depending on the problem that we're solving here. We are fixing a problem
so we know exactly the purpose behind our innovation. But you can use
this for design. You can use this especially on front end development
of designing new products, coming up with effective
ways to solve different problems.
You can use the a box challenge, usually within
my teams. I will then challenge team members to place
their pictures or their a box within a slack channel or
within a collaborative channel, so that you can then start threads
to make comments on what you liked about certain aspects
of different boxes. And you can pick out the best parts
of different ideation phases and come up with a better product
altogether. And again, it's a very simple way
to come up with a lot of different ideas. Depending on
the dynamic of the team. I will sometimes
give this challenge, give my
teams members what we are going to be brainstorming about a couple of days
before, because there are some people in teams that like to mole
on the ideas a little bit longer. That way they can come to the table
with those well thought out ideas while there are other people that come to
the table, and they are better at coming up with a lot of ideas
very quickly on their feet. And so I will sometimes
send that email out early for
team members that want to spend a little bit more time thinking about
those different challenges that they want to take on, and then
we'll take all of the ideas, put them in a collaborative channel, whether that
be Slack or Microsoft Teams or whatever collaboration
software that you use or method that you use to share all those
ideas all at once.
And that's a really simple way that
you can again, first identify the problem, be very
clear in identifying the problem, and then being
strategic in creating an environment where people can be their
most innovative self and then also take into
account the relationship side of innovation within
teams. See, relationships are so critical
within those team dynamics, because if you can achieve youre dreams
all on your own, then youre probably not dreaming
big enough. It all comes back to relationships.
If you want to do something bigger than yourself, then you
have to include more than yourself. And we are in a
very unique and exciting time right now.
You see, in decades past, in recent decades past,
our creativity was really born out of opportunity.
But in this season, our creativity will be born out of
necessity. We have a new season of innovation
and creativity within our teams.
Albert Einstein wrote that you can't solve a problem
on the same level that it was created. You have
to rise up above it to the next level.
So come on, let's rise up.