Hi everyone. My name is Gong. I'm a product manager at Spotify
and today I'm really happy to be here to discuss product discovery and
in particular a data driven approach to product discovery.
So my talk will be divided into three main parts.
Firstly, I will discuss, based on my experience,
how we can leverage data in product discovery.
Secondly, we will look into a few examples where companies like
Netflix or Spotify were able to leverage
the data that they collect in order to further strengthen their product mode.
And finally, we will also look into factors in
order for us to run data driven product discovery
effectively. So without further ado, let's jump
right in with the first part, how we can use data in product discovery.
So product discovery is essentially a decision making
process, which means it requires
data as inputs in order for us to make informed decision.
I think all product teams will agree with me on the importance of
data in product management and more particularly in product
discovery. We all want to leverage data
as much as possible. So the question is how can we do that effectively?
So I could argue that one of the biggest challenges
for product teams when they look for answers to these questions
is the abundance of data. To the extent that we
are all overloaded with data in the digital world
nowadays. Take established large
scale products for example. We are probably looking at like
millions of data attributes and billions of data points being collected
every single day. So it can easily feel overwhelming for
product teams not knowing which data is relevant and
important in order for us to identify which problems
and subsequently which solutions to work on during the product discovery
process. So how can this be avoided?
To answer this question, lets take a step back and look into
the definition of the product discovery. So I
recognize that different organizations might have slightly different understanding
of product discovery. So to make it easier for us in
this talk, I could define product discovery as a process of identifying
key problems and their optimal solutions in order to achieve
the desired outcome. So it all starts with the desired outcomes
and we need to work from there in order to identify which data is
relevant and important for us during the product discovery process.
So lets discuss this further in the next slide.
So Im quoting Tyriasautorrus, the author of Continuous Discovery
Habit. Good discovery starts with a clear desired outcome.
So what I would like to add here is that even though it is important
to have clear desired outcomes, it is often just a
starting point for the product teams. And this is because
for product teams nowadays, more often than not, we are given
desired business outcomes, not desired product outcomes.
So whats the difference between these two? So again, im quoting Teresa
here, a business outcome is a metric that moves
the business forward, while the product outcomes helps us
understand if the product is moving the business forward.
Some examples of the business outcome include
to grow the user base, to grow the revenue, to grow the
profit, or to increase the retention.
So business outcomes are lacking indicators.
Once you are able to measure it, it is often too late
to do anything about it. And this is why it is
critical for product teams to be able to define desired
product outcomes based on the desired business outcomes
that they are given. For example, if the desired business
outcomes is to grow the revenue, some potential desired
product outcomes could be like existing customer will
buy more, or existing customer will be willing
to pay more for the same product, or new customers
from new countries will start buying products or new customers
from new segments will start buying products.
So defining desired product outcomes based on the
desired business outcomes is a major step toward effective
product discovery. And this is because product
outcomes are often leading indicators which enables
product team to learn about the impacts and reiterate
in quick cycle feedback. More importantly,
product outcomes are most within the influence of the product teams.
So once the desired product outcomes are defined,
product teams should also make sure to translate
those outcomes into appropriate product metrics.
And this is to ensure that we can measure the current situation
as well as validating any future impact of your
work. So one tip, I have to select
the right metrics to optimize for to select those
metrics based on the product life cycle. And this is
of course in addition to the desired business outcome that we were
given. So if your product is still in its early
phase, the focus is usually on
the retention. This is because you want to ensure that
the users can perceive the value of your product before doing anything else.
Subsequently, the product metrics could be on the
churn rate, on the daily active user,
weekly active user ratio, or on the user engagement.
So once a job business has achieved their product market fit,
the focus of the business usually shifts towards scaling
the business. So for product teams, metrics like
sign ups, conversion or customer acquisition costs
become more relevant now. And this is because it
will provide valuable insights into how effective it
is in terms of your customer acquisition strategy and
how effective it is for you to convert them into engaged
users. So for established businesses,
the focus now would be on the revenue and profitability.
Consequently, for product teams, you can track metrics like
average revenue per user, customer lifetime value,
or free to pay conversions. These metrics tell you
whether the product and the business is
financially sustainable and whether we can
extract value for the business. So now that we have identified all
the product metrics, do we think we have all the data we need
in order to run the product discovery? Maybe not quite yet.
So, with product metrics, we often measure quantitative data
like clicks, reactions or source query, and they
tell you a lot about the what of the user behavior.
However, they also do not tell you about the why behind those actions
like motivations, frustrations or emotions of the users.
And this is where the qualitative data will come into play.
So, user interviews, usability tests or customer support
interactions are really good examples of qualitative data
that help us understand the user perspective. They comprehend
the quantitative data that are being collected automatically
from our product in order for us to have a full picture of users
when doing product discovery. So now that we have discussed how
we can leverage data in product discovery, let's take a closer look
at some examples of companies like Netflix or Spotify were
able to leverage the enormous amount of data that they
collect in order to further strengthen their product mode.
So content is the most important product of Netflix, and they have really
disrupted the entertainment industry by leveraging a vast amount of
data to inform their decision on personalization
and the content acquisition strategy. So Netflix
invests heavily into personalization in order to improve
user engagement and retention. For example, on the
film recommendations, best layouts or thumbnail
images were decided based on individual user behavior,
and on this effort create a tremendous value.
It is estimated that an uplift of $1 billion
in revenue was created thanks to these improved retentions.
Another way Netflix uses data is to guide their content acquisition,
that is, to decide which title to acquire or to produce.
So they have an enormous amount of data on user viewing
habits, preference or user behavior, which then
can be used for them to identify the gaps in
their current offering and then make strategic investments
in producing original series or acquiring
existing content. So as a result, they were able to
produce or acquire widely successful series that
I'm sure all of us have heard of, like House
of Cards, Stranger Things, and Orange is a new
black. Quite similar to Netflix actually.
Spotify is also famous for the ability to leverage
a vast amount of data that they can collect on user listening habits,
preference and user behavior to identify and
build highly engaging features to make users
come back for more so their widely successful features.
Discovery Weekly is a prime example of personalization
in action. So every Monday, users will receive a
brand new playlist of songs that Spotify things that
you will love based on your history. Its like you
are having a dj personally DJ actually, who knows
your music test better than you do.
Spotifys data driven approach actually goes
way beyond the personalized playlist.
They use data to inform their overall product strategy and their content
offerings. For example, they notice that users are
manually creating different playlists for different activities,
for example, like work out. So they
decided to create automatic playlists catering
to those needs. And Spotify does not give this data
and insights for themselves. They actually use it
to empower the artists on the platforms. For example, in the
Spotify for artists app, those insights are being used for artists
to better understand their fans and which lead to better
targeted marketing and tour planning. Now that
we are moving on to the final part of this presentation, let's discuss
the factors required in order to effectively run
a data driven product discovery. But first,
let's quickly go through the common mistakes or the challenges when it
comes to leveraging data in product discovery, the first mistake
is to focus on the wrong metrics. We actually talk
about this a lot at the very beginning of this presentation, so it
is critical to prioritize metrics that actually align with
the desired outcomes. The second mistake is actually being
too reliant on data to the extent that data becomes
a blocker instead of a leverage. This is particularly critical
for product teams working on early stage products where
data is usually limited. All the
product teams should be comfortable making decisions with imperfect
information that are required to build truly remarkable
products. So one challenge I would like to highlight here
is the potentially low quality of data. So when we use
data, make sure that the data is accurate and of
high quality because inaccurate data can lead to
misthalted measurements which subsequently lead
to sub optimal product decisions, keeping those
are mistakes and challenges in mind. Lets discuss the
factors required in order for us to effectively run
a data driven product discovery. The foundational factors
is to have clear goals and metrics in mind.
Basically, you need a sharp vision for your product and
define success metric based on that vision.
This subsequently will enable you to select the appropriate
data, point to measures and to check the progress.
The second factor that I would like to highlight here is actually to
ensure that you had the right tool sets in order to transform
the raw data that you collect into valuable insights.
They could be like bi platforms, could be user research
tools or a B testing framework.
Not only that you have the right data and valuable insights attend,
you also need to ensure that you are promoting a data driven
culture so that data is valued not only within
your product team, but across the organization.
Factor number four is about experimentation.
The beauty of data is that it enables you to quantify
the impact of the experimentation, validating your assumptions
which later optimize product decision during
the product discovery process. Last but not least
is about the data hygiene. A robust data collection
and validation process will ensure the accuracy
and the consistency of the raw data and subsequently the
high quality of your insights during the
product discovery process. And this brings me to
the end of my presentation today. Thank you very much for
your attention and if you have any questions, please share with me
over the email. Thank you and have a nice day.