Hey everyone, so glad to be here in this cool conference
speaking about the way that my team is developing in
the day to day with calling, sharing with you the
experience that we have in the way that we are working on local
development. So before we starting, let me introduce
myself. My name is Matan Cohen and I'm software development team lead
lead at the production platform in Wix and my team is called Dev
Extra production. We are responsible for the dev experience
of the production engineers in the group. We are responsible for some automation
and make the life easier. Ciscds and a bunch of other
stuff before that. I've been in Walkme also for several
other years now. The agenda for today is that we're going to discuss
about Skaffold and Scaffold is this amazing tool made by Google
for local Kubernetes development.
And we're going to discuss about it of course today. And we're going
to discuss also about two great integrations that Scaffold
have, which is helm and Basel, helm for deployment
and Basel as a builder. And we're going to discuss this as
well. Now let's start from
discussing about local development in general. Now I
know that every team or company doesn't really matter, have its own
way how to develop. But in my point of view
you must take into consideration three things. When you
are thinking about the way that you are going to use the tools, you must
have velocity, good experience and a fast feedback
loop. Now if you would put it on a scala between,
the way you are working is exactly like production or
nothing like production. You can think about it in a very general
way in those four options.
First of all, you can run your code just via test. You are running this
exact code that you wrote with the test and you want to
see if it's working or not. A second option is running
the service now. It can be a binary, it can be a dockerized stuff,
whatever, but you are running all the service now.
Something that it's more like production can be like
dockerizing all the environment. When you
want to work on your environment, you are going to work with your
service and maybe some external dependencies like database or message queues
and other stuff. And the Thor option,
it's running all the services with all the stuff with
local full integration, maybe the environment variables would be a little
bit different. Now, when we thought
about which way we should take in order
to develop in Golang in our local development experience,
we wanted to take into those three points that we
discussed about velocity, good experience and fast feed the clue.
But also we want to make it as much as possible like production.
And now this is where Skaffold helped us with
this concept. What is Skaffold? Actually Skaffold
is a local development Kubernetes tool that
you are using in order to run your services.
And basically what it does scuffled
is watching your files and every change that you are made
it's going to continuously deploying
to your local Kubernetes cluster. Now it can be a remote Kubernetes
cluster but today we're going to see it like just
from local Kubernetes cluster in Docker for Mac.
And actually what it does is pay attention that
you changed your service and then is doing
a very fast build of the docker image and it
pushes to your Kubernetes cluster and we're going to see it
in a second. Now when you finish it's automatically clean up
for you. This concept that's called continuous development.
Now I've seen it in several places and
it's like a general concept continuous development.
But this concept, the way that I'm
taking this phrase is to you want to
work continuously when you are developing and get this
fast feedback loop inside the Kubernetes cluster
and you constantly deploying your code and getting
the feedback. So let's see the first demo
very very fast. Let's take a look how scaffold can
help us with a local development experience.
Now before the demo I have installed several stuff. First of
all I installed Docker for Mac and I enabled kubernetes.
Also you can install scaffold very easily with brew, install Skaffold.
And last thing, I installed a Google cloud extension
on my vs code and you can use it also
in Intellij. Okay guys, so as I said before the
talk, I have installed Docker on the machine docker for Mac and
also I enabled kubernetes.
Here I enabled kubernetes. Now let's see scuffled
in action. Now in order to have this quick
template of how scuffled is working, let me
open this cloud code new application.
This is an extension that also was made by Google just to
download a template. So it will be Kubernetes application
of course and we want to have a go guest list. So let
me open this one. Let's give it a sec.
You can see on the bottom right that it's
downloading. Now this is the template
and this is basically a
very simple skaffold project. Now this
skaffold project, as you can see here, have two main
artifacts, which is the backend and the front end.
And if you would go to the Kubernetes manifest, you would see also there is
MongoDB and what scuffle does.
The way that scuffle is working is that you have two
main parts inside scuffle. You have the
build and the deploy. Now the build case
is in the build phase. You need to point where are
your artifacts. Now you are pointing on the back end and the front end.
Cool. Now in order to deploy those artifacts you need to
point on the Kubernetes manifest which
is in the Kubernetes manifest directory.
So in order to unscaffle and see all
the magic, you just need to do scaffold dev and then Scaffold
will start running and building
the artifacts. And also it will deploy to
my local Kubernetes cluster. So let's give it a second and
you can see that those back end and front end
services are being built now became,
now you can see that it's actually building because it's the first time it's
actually building from those containers,
those images, sorry. And then it will deploy the
containers to my local Kubernetes cluster. Now we are
waiting for the deployment to stabilize. Let's give it a second because
it's the first time, it's taking a little bit more time, but next time
it will have catch of course, and it will be very fast.
Let's give it one more second.
Okay, now we can see the logs. We can see that we have
the backend and the front end logs. And also we
can see that MongoDB already deployed. So we can see
it. I have Lance which is local id
for Kubernetes. And you can see in the pods that we have now go
gasp. Backend, front end and Mongodb. And everything is
working. Now let's run on the browser localhost,
which is the service that the front end is listening.
And then we can see that we have this, my guestbook.
So now we can run post
guest book and then you can see that it works.
Now let's
see what scuffle gives us actually. Now if I'm going
to change, for example, you can see here that the
name of the app is called my guestbook. And if
I want to change this, let's search
for this one, my guest book, let's call it Conf
42 guestbook. Now you would see that
stuffel noticed that just
the front end need to be built and it
automatically rebuild our
front end and it's already been deployed to our Kubernetes
cluster. Now if I would go to lens you would see that now
we have a new pod with a new front end production.
It was very fast, I don't know if you catched it. And actually now
we have a new application
with a new deployment and we can refresh. And now we have conf
fourty two. Now we change just the front end. Now let's do something
a little bit different.
Let's add a back end stuff or a method in
the main review. Now let's
see the handlers here. And you can see that it's using this
HTTP handler. So let's create another one.
Let's call it, let's have a ping.
Okay now
you can see that it's automatically paying
to build and it's rebuild for every change that I'm doing.
So let's do this function called
ping and let's just
return second it.
It's
now let's give it a second and
let it finish to be deployed.
And that's it. Now we can do bingo
tooling and it will work as expected.
Okay now it's worked. We can see that probably
it took a second for the service to be stabilized and
that's it. Now it's been redeployed. So the
thing is that when I'm working with scaffold it's
always rebuild the environment that I'm
working. It doesn't really matter if it's front end code or
back end code and even kubernetes stuff. So if
I would go here and I would go to the front end service for example,
and I would change it from 80
80 to for example 3000.
It will also will pay attention to that and it
will be very fast deployed.
You could see that because it was not a change in the artifact.
It was like amazingly fast.
So if I would go now to the browser it
should not be worried. Just a step.
It took it a second to pay attention to
it. Now we can change it to 3000.
What I've done here.
Oh I changed the back end. Sorry for that.
Let's change the front end.
Okay, now it will be, now it will
work. Just one
sec.
And now it's working on local 3000.
And probably you are asking yourself, I can't hear
you but how
can I debug inside
scaffold? Because there is part of the local
experience is to have a great debug skill.
Now you can do
also with Skaffold a remote debug inside the Kubernetes cluster.
And let's see how it looks like you can see you have run on kubernetes.
By the way, if you would go to the vs code, you can check
the configuration. So let's run on kubernetes now.
It will redeploy a new pod
in order to do the remote debugging. So yes,
and I'm going to wait for a second to
wait it to work.
Now it's building the front end again and
it will deploy to my local Kubernetes cluster.
Okay, cool. It's finished with the front end. Now it's building the
back end.
In the meanwhile I would go to the front end app and
let's search for the post.
Let's debug the post process and run from the front end to the back
end. So I would go to the back end as well.
And let's search for the post message
handprint. So I created two breaks.
Now I'm waiting for scuffled for the first time to
build those remote debugging containers,
pods. So we're going to
wait until it's going to say that it was finished.
Let's give it another second.
Okay, now we are doing the mapping
inside the remote debugging and
hopefully now everything will be working. Now let's try
to add something here. Post yesbook
and the debug didn't started yet. Let's see why.
Let's try again.
Okay. And now you can see that I'm on the front end
app and I have a breakpoint and
now I can jump over the lines and debug
like I wanted to. And if I would go play I
would go to the backend app as you can see now, giving me
the ability to do a debugging cross
microservices, which is amazing.
And this is one of the things that SafO gives
me on my local experience working
with. Go.
Cool. So let's continue.
I'm just playing up the stuff and also in
the terminal here and clean up everything when
you are finishing with coupled is
cleaning up for you. So it's very tools. You can see that everything is
clean when I finish.
Cool. Actually what scuffled
gave us, the way scuffled works
is it's pluggable. Now I don't
know if you notice, but the parts in the scuffled yaml
file are very easy to
extend. For example, if you want to use another build
tool, it's like Skaffold gives you the ability
to choose which build tool you want to use.
Now you can use the local docker demo that you have, like I just did.
But you can use other ways to build your artifacts,
like Bazel for example. And we're going to see it later on.
Also, it gives you a few options how
you want to deploy your artifacts
through the Kubernetes that you are using now. It can be in Kubectl like we
just saw, but we can use helm for example. And we're going to discuss this
as well. So scaffold is very pluggable,
which you can use it in different places, in different
teams in other ways, which is very useful.
Now let's say that you have this microservice that you are working
on, but you need an external dependency, for example, you need the message
box or you need for example a
mysql database or something like that. And this
is where helm getting into the picture.
Now we're going to discuss how we can use helm to
integrate with Skaffold in order to help us in the deployment phase.
So what is helm in general? Helm is
the Kubernetes package manager that
is commonly used when you are using
Kubernetes. Actually what it means,
like you can do NPM, install something or
use other package managers like Nugget and C sharp or pin Python
doesn't really matter. You can use helm for kubernetes. So you
can do like helm install MySQl. And then
you have MySQl in your Kubernetes
cluster, which is very cool. This is a very high level of
helm. Now let's see how Helm can
integrate with scuffled and how easy it is
working with scuffled and Helm.
By the way, for those of you who don't know helm, there is something called
Helm Hub, which you change the name to Artifact hub.
And here you can search for all the artifacts
that you want to install via helm. For example, we're going to go
for PostgreSQL for example.
And you can see here if you want to use Helm,
you can just do helm repo edit for this repo
and then you can do helm installed for example, for that.
So now let's write this in
our Skaffold project that we just created.
So I'm returning to the project that we
just saw. And now we can inside
the Skaffold here, let's have another file. Let's call
it Skaffold services,
yaml for example. And here I
have an extension here for writing and stuff.
It's also the cloud code.
Now I would go for shuffled
Helm deployment and you can see that it gave me a cool template
out of the box. So let's remove all of this
for now. And the chart path would
be. No, the values, I don't need those values as
well. And also I don't need this build artifact.
I just want to have here box
and the chart path will be. Let's take it
from here.
I already done this before the talk,
so after you run it, it will be very easy to use. So we're going
to use it here. And we should say that this chart is denote.
So let's say true. Now in
order to use it, we can just run
skaffold. Now I will not run Skaffold
dev this time. Now I will just do.
Now we can use scuffled run. Now the difference between
scuffle dev and scuffled run is scuffled dev is like watching your files,
but scuffled run is not watching your files.
It's like one time deployment. So you
can do scaffold run to Skaffold services.
Skaffold service yaml
minus f. If you are not using scuffle yaml, we must
pass the minus fuffle
run minus f.
And now you would see that scuffled is using helm to deploy
this service to my local Kubernetes cluster.
Now you can see that this is a regular helmet install
if you're familiar with it. And what can actually
reduce is actually connecting
to this very easily. And for example,
if we want to have a few other stuff,
let's say for example that I'm using Kafka, for example,
so I can have here Kafka and I
think it would be kafta again. And also if you are using redis,
you can do this as well. I mean, you should change
the parameters and pass maybe a different
port or you want to have some reverse proxy for the
URL or something, but you get the idea. So here
you can have redis for example.
And if I would run Skaffold run again, now I'm going
to have Redis Kafka and process like
very easily, which is giving me so much
power when I'm working locally. So if I would
check this inside lens, you would see that Kafka
is starting and zookeeper as well, and also Redis
master and redisplay. Of course you must do some fine
tuning to the parameters that you are passing. But this
is the general idea of how scuffled integrating with helm,
which can help us a lot in the
way we are working with
external stuff. Now let's clean everything here.
We can run scuffled instead of run. We can run
scuffle delete. Scuffle delete
minus f scuffle.
Cool. Now it will clean up everything and you will see that all
the things here are going to be removed in a few
seconds. You can see that the pods are
terminating and we finished.
Cool. So after we saw how
Skaffold is integrating with helm, let's check
out another amazing tool called Bazel and
how it's integrating with staff. Now,
Bazel in general is agnostic
build tool and also by google. And I think
in Google, internally in Google, it's called Bazel.
And what actually Bazel gives us is
this very efficient way that it builds
the artifacts. And we're going to see it in a few seconds.
In very general idea, you're going
to have on each directory, a basel file that you can
connect between the artifacts, each directory having its own
bazel file. And then when you want to build the artifact,
it's building it very efficiently.
And in the tree that you can see here, it has a cache for
each layer in the tree, meaning that if you already
have it cached, Bazel will not build it again.
And we are using Basel a
lot in wix. And for example, there are some
groups that most of the groups in wix on the back end using Scala.
And when they moved to Basel, it changed the
time that they are doing the CI of building
all the artifacts and the cv from hours to minutes.
So it's amazing in a very
large monorepos and big
repos. So the things we're going to discuss
now is that what buzzer gives us in
the local dev experience, why it's helpful. So let's say that we have
two services, right? We have service one and service two. Very easy.
Now, service one is dependent on very
simple sum package, and service two is dependent
on some and more packages.
Now, if I'm changing just service one,
so we saw that before, Skaffold already knows
to change service one now. And if I change service two
again, it will rebuild service two and
redeploy. But what's going to happen if I'm
changing the dependencies of those services,
how skaffold or any other tools is
known, which service you need to build. So, for example, if I'm
changing the mole package, so of course I
need to build just service two. And if
I'm changing the code of the sum package, then I should
rebuild service one and service two. And because
of the power of Bazel, Bazel knows because of all
the targets, which packages and services I
should build in the local
development. And this has improved dramatically the
local experience of the
way that I'm working. So, let's see in action,
skaffold and Basel together. Okay, so let's see how
Skaffold is integrating with Bazel.
So, before the demo I created, this very simple project
includes Basel and Skaffold.
So let's see how this project tools like we have again,
this skaffold file, which contains the main parts, which is
build and deploy, and the deploy is
via Kubectl and the build. Now,
as you can see here, it's made via buzzword.
Now let's open the directories and see
what this project contains. So, as we saw in the slide,
we have two services and two packages. Which service one is
dependent on the sum package.
Very easy. One and service two. It depends on
mold and sum. Now, as you can
see here, each directory holds a bazel file, which declare
the targets inside the directory. You can see here,
we will not cover it in this talk, but in general,
you are not writing those bazel files. It's generating with generating
it for you. Now, if I want to run this
project, we will do as we've done before, stuff like that. As you can see
here, the service one and service two already
been in the cache,
and that's it. They have been deployed. Now, if I change
in service one,
we know that just service one needs to be redeployed.
So you can see here that service one is now rebuild
and will redeploy again. But what's going to happen?
And it's going to change the dependency,
the modules, and this is where Bazel
can help us and in other places in the local
experience, of course. So let's change this
package here,
and let's see what's happening. Because service one
and service two is dependent on this package.
Scaffold knows to build them. And this is
where Basel gives the strength to scaffold in this situation.
And if I would change the multiply,
for example, you would see
that only service two that rely
on the multiple packages
will be changed. And this gives
a lot of strength to scaffold
and to the local development experience.
So with Skaffold, it feels like you're writing coin
production. I mean, if before people worked with
dockerizing their environments in order to be like production,
now we can actually work with Netflix and helm
and some other tools that can make my local experience else
like production, which give me a lot of strength.
So thank you very much for your time.
You can ask me questions on Twitter.
I will be glad to answer. And that's it. Thank you
very much,