Hello everyone, I am Srijan Rastogi. Thanks for joining in on my
presentation on the topic no more flying blind, unlock observability
for smooth selling with GoFr. Here we will be
discussing about observability, what are its building blocks? How it benefits
the developer to gain insights of the application and then we will
dive into GoFr and its features regarding observability. In
todays digital age, applications are becoming increasingly
complex, often built using microservices architecture.
This complexity makes it challenging to understand how these systems behave
and identify issues when they arise. Thats where observability comes
in for your help. What is observability?
Observability is ability to understand the internal state
of the system. By examining its external output.
It provides a holistic view of your system health,
enabling us to troubleshoot problems, optimize performance and ensure
application reliability.
The building blocks of observability are considered to be metrics,
logs and traces. These three building blocks work together
to provide a comprehensive view of your system.
Metrics offer a high level overview. Logs provide
detailed information about specific events and traces help us
understand the flow of execution across services.
What are the benefits of observability? By having a clear understanding
of our systems behavior, you can identify and fix problems
much faster. Observability helps you optimize your applications
performance and stability, leading to a better user experience.
Additionally, you can proactively identify potential
issues before even they impact users, which causes
to reduce your downtime and ensuring business continuity.
Now let's get started with GoFr. GoFr is an
open source and it has a large and active community of users who
are happy to help. GoFr also provides comprehensive documentation,
tutorials and forums to guide you through the installation and configuration process.
You can visit us on the mentioned website or our GitHub repo.
Let's see how we can build a simple hello API
using GoFr. I have created a directory of the name GoFr
hello API. Let's initialize the gomod for it with the same
name.
So to get GoFr as a dependency we would need to
run command go get gofr.dev. Also to add
the configs of the application we would need to add a configs directory
in which we can add a .env file which
will have configs for our application regarding
HTTP server, databases and also we
are adding trace exporter which we will discuss later.
Now let's get started with the main file main.go.
In the main function we would be initializing a
app which is returned by the
GoFr new function. It gives us an instance of a GoFr application
using which we can register handlers,
run DB migrations, or start the server here in hello
server hello handler. We are returning hello
world and nil as the error all the
GoFr handlers return interface and error type.
Now let's get started with the server.
Before that we need to run go mod tidy. Now let's get started
with the server. As you can see,
the server is getting initialized at 9000.
The metrics are already being initialized at 2121,
and our traces are being exported to the mentioned website.
So let's hit the server and
see what we get in return. So as you can see we
are getting hello world. Now let's check the metrics server.
Here you can see GoFr provides the
memory metrics. Also you can see the HTTP
response with the specific routes
with the status port, how much time it took, and all
the go routines. Memory related metrics
now we can hit more request and see if the metrics are updated.
Yes. Now the GoFr also provides you with the
health check functionality. You can hit
that on the server dot well known
slash alive endpoint so
it returns that the status is for the service.
Also you can see that these are the logs which are
perfectly formatted on the terminal for our application.
Now let's see how the traces are being shown in our
GoFr tracer UI. These are the
correlation ids which are respect, which are
unique for all the requests and which are used to track the
application flow. Let's search for that. Here you
can see that we have the traces like we hit
the get endpoint at hello and the GoFr router,
how much time it took, and all the other necessary details.
Now as we have seen the implementation from GoFr,
let's see how GoFr helps you overcome the challenges of observability.
It provides a centralized inbuilt platform for all your observability
needs. Lets explore how GoFr can empower
your development and operations teams. It collects
metrics, data which can be used to identify bottlenecks and track
the health of your application over time logs which can
be helpful for debugging and troubleshooting issues. Distributed tracing
helps you pinpoint the root cause of issues in complex
systems. Now lets get started with
the building blocks of observability. Let's start with metrics.
Metrics are the foundation of observability. They provide us
with quantifiable data points that allows us to
measure the performance and health of your system. Think of metrics
as gauges on your car's dashboard. They tell us how fast
you are going, how much fuel you have left, and if there
are any potential problems. In GoFr's perspective,
there are many different types of metrics that can be used in GoFr,
but some of the most common ones falls into three categories,
application performance, infrastructure performance and user behavior.
By analyzing these metrics in GoFr, you can gain valuable
insights into how your system is performing,
identify potential issues, and ultimately deliver a better
user experience. GoFr also empowers you to create custom
metrics for your specific use, case and needs.
Now let's discuss about logging think of logs as
your application diary. They capture what's happening
inside your code at a different point of time. Logs are the
one of the three pillars of observability alongside with metrics and traces.
While metrics offer high level overviews and traces shows
request flows, logs provide the detailed stories behind the
scene. In GoFr's perspective, it provides
logs for every single detail of your application,
like reading of configs, databases,
server starts, etcetera. It provides beautiful
terminal logs as shown in the image. The logs
can also be exported in a well structured JSON format
which helps you in filtering on the basis of keys.
Now let's talk about traces. Distributed tracing
is a powerful technique for monitoring and debugging applications,
especially those built with microservices architecture.
By tracing requests across different services, we gain
valuable insights into how our application is functioning
as a whole. GoFr highlights
the integration with tracing tools like Zipkin
and Jaeger. It also has a internal
tracing tool which we will discuss later and
also trace ids are used to track requests
across microservices. Visualizing the request
flow helps pinpointing the bottleneckness and performance
issues, leading to faster debugging and improved application
health. Overall, distributed tracing empowers developments
developers to build robust and scalable applications
with the help of GoFr. So as we discussed in
now, the benefits of observability features in GoFr and how
it enhances the efficiency of developing an application.
Here is a quick summary of them. GoFr removes the
need for multiple tools and provide a uniform platform for
all your observability needs. It quickly identify and
resolve issues. With GoFr's powerful analytics and visualization
capabilities, you can also gain deeper insights
into application behavior to make informed development
decisions. GoFr is also an open source platform,
eliminating the need for expensive propriety solutions.
Now let's see. In live action
for the microservices. Here I have created two microservices
order func and order data so
let's see, for order data configs we have app name,
app version, HTTP port and the DB configurations.
Similarly, like we have created the migration also to create the
orders table. And if we go to orders func,
we have added the same configurations here where data service being the
URL for the downstream service. So let's start the
order data service. So if we see like
the DB is connected because the log migration that we wrote
successfully, so the table would have been created. Let's run the order func
service. Now the service is being started on
port 8080. Now let's hit some requests.
We are using jmeter for that.
So now we can see that there are multiple
requests coming on both the order data service and
the order the function. Here we can see the downstream URL also
for the data service.
So now if we go to check the metrics here, we have
used Grafana to visualize the metrics. I will
attach the dashboard JSON file in my repo so you
can take a look over that. So let's see how metrics visualization
comes into play. So we can see that go
routines memory utilization is being visualized using
GoFr metrics. We are also showing the response
time SLA for the metrics and the heat
map for them. Request count and request code is also
shown. So this would be helpful. Like to know
the service how many requests came, which type of request it got.
We can see like it is showing the path, it is showing the method over
that. And in the status code we can see like this type of status code
it responded with. Similarly we see
like p 90, p 95, all of those percentiles.
Also like we can also see like which route and which path
combo combination return, which status code, how many times.
So here we only have two execs, 200 and
201s. So yeah, for outbound request,
since it is a data layer, we will have SQL DB
metrics. We can also see like we are showing how many, how much time
did the DB took to respond, like which
type of queries we ran on the Db and
how many DB connections were open. Same as we
can also see the order
func here we can see like we can see the versions also similarly
go routines, memory inbound request.
Here there is a point that we can notice, like this
point of time. We can see that it took a lot of time to
process the request at 99.9%. So here we
can debug like and like find
the root cause for that. What would be the reason like for this much
time of the request for responding and see like
how many requests are being hit. What is this response code for that?
Similarly, as we discussed for order data,
we can see like post was the main culprit for the response
time. Similarly, we can see the response
codes and output. So here we can see like order data was
the culprit. So we can see like DB was taking a lot of time.
Like it took around 4.5 seconds. So we can see.
And regarding the next peak,
we will need to check with order func. So here, let's check with order func
tracer. Also, we will add a trace exporter config
equal to GoFr. So yeah, let's restart the
services again. First we will restart the order
data service showing
these sales. Yeah, so now tracer
is being exported. Let's start this service as well.
So yeah, again, we will be making some requests on
the services. Use jmeter again for that.
Yeah, and now since we have these trace ids, correlation ids,
so we can use any one of that to see the traces at the
tracer dot gofr dot dev. Let me just copy paste it.
Let's see, like first of all, let's see the response of
the service.
So yeah, as we discussed further, like we have a health check
endpoint. It shows like the downstream service order data is up.
Now we can see the tracer UI.
We just need to go to this URL, copy paste the tracer
id, and we can see like this
type of request we hid from where it circulates, like from where it went,
all the details like method schema, status code.
Thank you for joining in.
You can explore all the content being used on this
given GitHub repo. Also do visit GoFr dot
dev and give us a star to support us. Thank you.