Jamaica. Make a real
time feedback into the behavior of your distributed systems and observing
changes exceptions errors in real time allows
you to not only experiment with confidence, but respond instantly
to get things working again.
Close hi
everyone, thank you so much for watching my session at
Conf 42 Javascript 2022
edition. Today I'm going to talk to you about how to create
Slack apps with Boltjs.
So my name is Alba Rivas, am a developer advocate
at Salesforce and here you have my contact details
in case that you want to ask me anything later.
I need to include this slide because Salesforce
is a publicly traded company and it just means
that you should make purchasing decisions based on the functionality
that is currently available. And with that,
let's start by giving a quick introduction
about Salesforce. What is Salesforce?
Well, Salesforce is a company, of course,
but the company has a CRM that helps
you manage your relationship with your customers,
with your partners and much more.
Right? It includes applications for sales,
service, marketing, commerce and more.
And it's also an app development platform.
So it happens that last year Salesforce
acquired Slack. I'm sure that some
of you are familiar with Slacks is
an enterprise messaging platform in
which you can strengthen your collaboration within
your employees, with your customers, as well
with your partners, and anyone involved
in your ecosystem, in your company ecosystem.
So Slack has a lot of great
default features already implemented to strengthen
collaboration. But third party
vendors or solo developers can create custom
applications over Slack to extend
that native functionality. There are already
great integrations out there. There are integrations
for Google Drive, there are integrations for GitHub
and many, many more. So today what
I'm going to do is to explain to you how to
create one of these integrations.
Really. We are going to create a custom app and we
are going to start by demoing the app.
The app that we have created is called
ready to fly. Ready to fly allows you
to create, approve and reject
travel approval requests that are stored in
Salesforce right away from slacks on
the screen, we can see slack on the left hand side and
salesforce on the right hand side.
In my case, for simplicity, I used Salesforce as
the backend. But you can use any platform or database
of your choice. So here on the right hand side I have some
travel approval requests. Salesforce is where
we store that information and we can see that those
travel approval requests have an origin and start and
end date. So our app is going to
show those travel approval requests on slack. And the first thing
that we need to do is to authorize with Salesforce because
travel approval requests belong to a
user. We need to map the Salesforce user to
the slacks user somehow. This is something that
is particular to my use case and that you can skip
if you are working with a different platform.
So now I've authorized correctly. And on the left
hand side we can see the travel approval
requests that belong to my user that were created by
my user, Alba Rivas. So now
what we are going to do is to take a look at our second tab
in which we can see the travel request to review.
It happens that I'm a manager of other users
and I can approve or react the travel request
that those users have created.
Yeah, I successfully approved one of them.
Okay, so from my travel request screen I
can also create a new travel request.
So what I'm going to do is to say that I want to go
from Heiway to New Zealand.
I am going to pick an arbitrary date,
I'm going to indicate the estimated cost and
I'm going to pick the approver. The approver
is my manager and that approver list is
being populated also from Salesforce.
Great. So our travel request has been successfully created
and I can take a look at it in Salesforce.
Now let's try to start an interaction
from Salesforce instead of from slacks.
We can do that by changing the status
of my newly created approval request.
So let's imagine for a second that I am the manager
and let's approve this request. And yeah, we receive
a notification on Slack saying that my travel request
has been approved. So with
this app we've been able to reduce
context switching and improve the productivity of
the users that are working with approvals on
Slack. Great. So now let's take a look at how
Slack apps work behind the scenes.
Normally everything starts with the interaction of a
user. A user types something on Slack.
A user responds to a message, something like that.
So normally when you create Slack app,
you define which events
do you want slacks to publish.
And those events are going to represent the interactions that the user
does. So for instance, let's imagine that
our user has written a message. That means that the Slack
servers are going to publish the
message. Events follow a JSON
format and in an event you can find
all the relevant information for that interaction.
And the way in which you implement the
business logic for your app is by creating
a custom client app in which you
listen to those events. So normally when you
receive an event, you execute some business logic,
right? And when our business logic finishes
normally, you will want to go back to slack
and inform the user somehow.
That the business logic finished executing.
We do that by using another app,
which is the web API through which we
can take action on slacks. We can post a message and
we can do many more things. So in summary,
there are two APIs that you need to interact with
when you are working with Slack on your
applications. One is the events API,
which is subscription based and it's going to fire
those events to which your app
is subscribed. Some examples are the message
event that we saw before, or the reaction added
event, or the user join event
that is fired when a user joins a Slack channel.
And then we have the web API which allows
you to take action on Slack. It allows you to post
messaging, to add reactions to messaging, and also if
you need to query some information you can do it through the web
API. Here at the bottom I leave you
the URL in which you can find the documentation for
those APIs.
So if you pay attention to the previous slide,
you see that there is an icon on the
right hand side block, the one that requests your client
app, and that icon represents something
called boltjs. Boltjs is a framework
that you can use to interact with these two APIs
more easily. Boltjs is written in
JavaScript, Python and Java right,
and it abstracts you from the implementation details
of those APIs. It also follows
a very intuitive and readable listener pattern
that allows you to listen for those events and
to respond to them when you need to. And also
I have to share that it's maintained
by the slack developer relation teams,
which means that it always incorporates
the latest features.
So in our case what we did was to create
a node JS application that uses
the JavaScript version of the Boltjs framework,
and I'm running that app on Heroku.
Amazing. So something else to highlight
is that when you interact with the web API
normally, because you want to update this black
application UI, to say to the customer, yeah,
your operation was successful, or this is the
data that you needed, something like that, right?
You can use plain text, but also you
can send more advanced
surfaces and you create those surfaces
using something called blockit.
So blockit is a framework to create uis in
slack and is a framework in
which you can use JSON to define the different slacks
that are part of a piece of UI.
And there is something great that I love called blockkit
builder. This is the URL app slack.com Slash blockkitbuilder
that you can use to create your
blockit code without having to remember
every single block syntax.
So for instance here on the left hand side there are
different elements that you can drag and drop into
this area here and the blocky code on the right
hand side is going to be auto generated so
you don't have to take care of that. I love these tools.
These surfaces that you create with blockkit can
be sent to slack through the web API
and can be rendered on a
mobile for instance, or in a message or also
in your application home tab. And this is
what we are using exactly in ready
to fly. Fantastic. So now let's take a
look at the code. This is the
code for ready to fly.
In this force app folder is where you are going to
find all the code for the Salesforce part of the app.
But I'm not going to focus on that. I'm going to focus
rather on the Nodejs app,
which is my purpose for today's talk.
So if you want to take a look at that app code
is on the app ready to fly folder. This is a
regular node app in which the app js
file is the entry point and in that app
js file you can find the imports from
the Slack boltjs module. Those are
the classes and modules that we are going to use to start
our app. And if you take a look at this
specific file, I have a bunch of lines, but this is
just because I'm integrating with Salesforce. If you want to
use the bold JS framework without Salesforce,
then you are going to have just a few lines.
Let me highlight some of the lines that are relevant
to you. So first of all, here we are initializing
the app and this is something I imported from Boltjs.
Next we are registering some listeners and
then we start the app by running boldapp.
Start in a port of your choice.
So this is basically how the entry point
for the application is written. Now you can see here
that I have a group of folders. This is because
I'm following a structure that was recommended
by the slack developing relations team.
It's an opinionated structure in which our code is divided
into different folders depending on what
it is used for. So for instance, we have
the listeners folder in which I have the definition of all the
listeners for the different interactions that the user may perform
on the Slack app. I also have
a user interface folder
in which I have the definition of those
surfaces that I'm posting to slack.
Remember I do that thanks to blockkit. And well,
I have other folders that are more
specific to the interaction that we do with Salesforce.
So let's take a look at one of the listeners. For instance,
this app home open listener is
the code that will execute when the user opens
the home page of our app. Remember that
when I'm on that home page, what happens is that my
application brings my travel approval request
from Salesforce, right? And this is
exactly the logic that executes. So let's
take a look at this callback, the code that executes
when the user opens the homepage. And here what
happens is that we are doing an authorization with Salesforce using
some special code for that, and then we
are querying for our travel request.
As I told you, this is the way in which we query Salesforce,
but you could do exactly the same with a postgres
or any other kind of database. So once
that we have queried those travel approval
requests from Salesforce, we need to format them
into a format that's understood by
slacks. And that format is blockit.
The way in which I first created that blockit
code was mocking it through that
blockkit builder web page that I referenced
before. But once you do that,
you have two options. You can hard code the blockkit
code here directly, or if you are
using nodejs, there is a very nice
open source library called Slack block builder which
is maintained by the slacks community with
which you can create that blockkit code like in a more
robust way using something similar
to the Swift UI syntax.
So once you have that created, look that here we
convert to JSON because this is the format
that we are really expecting to send to
slacks. Then once we have done that, what we do
is to use the web API to send that
JSOn to slack and post it
into the app homepage by using the
web API. Remember, we use first
the events API to listen to the app home opened
event. And finally we respond updating
that homepage UI by using the web API.
And of course we only refresh the screen for
the relevant slack user, the one that made
the event fire. All the code for
this app is available at this URL.
Here on the readme you will find instructions on how to
set it up. So I recommend you to go there, clone the
app and try it out yourself. If you want to take a look at more
apps, more sample code, you can go to
this official Slack samples URL.
And finally, I wanted to highlight that today
everything that I shared was regarding the
currently generally available platform
and way of creating slack apps.
But there is something else that Slack have been working
on, which is like a new version, a new generation
of the Slacks development platform. They have done that
in collaboration with Dino. And if you want to take
a look at that new Slack development platform
which is currently in beta. You can do that at app
slack.com slash future.
Finally, I want to share some resources. I didn't build
this app myself, I did it with some colleagues and
they live streamed some avoiding
of the app. So if you are the kind of person who likes live
streaming, I recommend you to take a look at those
chapters here on the first resource.
Also, I created a series of blog posts
explaining all the details of the app. That is
what you can find on the second resource. And finally,
we have a project on trailhead. Trailhead is our learning
platform, is a gamified platform
in which you have tutorials to learn everything about Salesforce
development and also now Slack development. So I recommend
you to go there and check it out.
Finally, if you want to connect with Salesforce developers,
you can do that in our website. You can
follow us on Twitter and also Facebook,
LinkedIn and YouTube. It. Thank you very
much for watching my session and I hope
that you enjoyed.