Are you an sre?
A developer? A quality
engineer who wants to tackle the challenge of improving reliability
in your DevOps? You can enable your DevOps for reliability
with chaos native. Create your free account at
Chaos native. Litmus Cloud my
name is Alicia Nyton, and I'm an engineering team lead at Honeycombio,
where I specialize in assisting customers in this sticky but quite
satisfying space called observability. I bring customers to
the hive, where they are lost, and I help them understand that they're humans,
too. My background consists of physics, a little biology,
DevOps engineering, and a splash of trash talking. Today we
will be discussing SLI negotiation tactics for
engineers. Service level indicators
are quantitative measures of a service, which in turn are
measured by slos. Whoa. My apologies.
This is not the talk that you actually think seriously.
This is about survival level indicators
that are prescribed to everyone who has a pause.
It's a mental measure to indicate, hey, self,
am I okay? Like real life okay,
if you are flaming dog, this is fine meme
several times throughout the course of the day, then you're not okay.
My friend, a person is only great as their best
cup of coffee is a fact set approximately by
no one. I hope, at least if
this has become your mantra of drinking coffee to
stay awake and stay alive. Hopefully caffeine is not
this hypothetical liquid that is gluing your eyes open in
such a way that it creates pillows for your tiredness.
Well, those are bags, folks, and they're
indicators that you need to get some rest.
This talk is specifically designed
to address engineers.
So, slos measure customer
success. But if we think
about it, customers are as successful, are only
as successful as the people that we put in front of them
and the people that are helping create these systems
that they can use and love on a day to day basis. So let's focus
on that for a moment.
So we've talked about survival level
indicators for 2 seconds, right? So let's
define that. It's the me factor
divided by valid moments. So what is that exactly?
The me factor is basically core values plus
what intrigues you, your mantra, and your tolerance levels.
The me factors are the good parts of you and what you
stand for. If at any point in time, your me
factor is compromised, then the best parts of you cannot be brought
to the table. Imagine if your job
told you something like, hi, you're probably going to have to
miss out on your child's graduation or the
trip you've been planning for several months. Yeah, we have
things to do, so you can cancel that. I'm pretty sure
you'll go Super Saiyan in the office and are talk smack
in those private back slack channels.
So it's important to keep your me factor in
mind and keep those
things in perspective.
So I've talked about the me factor. So what are valid moments?
Valid moments are things that you've considered to be
justifiable for you. For example,
some people prefer to not have a job that's
on call, but maybe in your situation it's okay that you're
on call. Or maybe it may be
okay for you to work extra hours temporarily,
as it's something that needs to be done that
will be beneficial later.
So what are invalid moments? Well, my friend, that's up
to you. My tolerance on
invalid, non justifiable moments is pretty
low nowadays. But some may feel otherwise
and that's okay. It's all about your survival, and you
should always keep your survival in mind.
So we've gotten our mind around surviving
in the workplace and in general. So how do we calibrate
that? Well, I want to provide a few tips for that.
So let's define mutualistic expectations.
So as soon as you humanly can define your expectations
and then calibrate them. As dynamic as life
is, so are adults. We have
needs, whether it's wanting to be a part of leadership,
having more technical challenges at work, or easier workload,
especially if you're doing a job of nine people, et cetera.
Hey, boss, I'm tired of your shit is
definitely not a way to approach your boss
yet. You may want to indicate to your boss
that I see myself in x situation and
I feel that I'm in X place. Do you
agree? This sparks the conversation of discovering
where you are and where you can go. And it also gets
your boss thinking, hey, this person is actually thinking about this and
it's proactive. So let's approach these things together.
This works the other way around as well. And what I mean
by that is, as a boss, it's not cool to
force someone into leadership, yet it's totally cool
to encourage them and to ask the person where
would they like to be and what are their current
limitations. At work, you never know until you ask someone
what's going on. And this is a good way to approach that.
There's a great way to define basic expectations so
you can do something like a readme of
yourself, to introduce yourself to people so they
know how you work, what your values are,
ways to reach you. That's okay and plausible for
you, et cetera. This is a way to set
boundaries in a very meaningful way with people
understanding who you are at a very basic level.
The next thing I want to talk about is calibrating no
meeting Wednesdays. So if you understand
this concept or you have it, stick to it.
If you don't have it, please create
it. The notion of picking a day without a meeting without
meetings is the beginning of something
beautiful and it provides a sense of normalcy.
You can drive your productivity throughout the day without
being distracted.
Defining weekly tasks spend
a little time during working hours at
the beginning of the work week or towards the end of the previous work
week to calibrate your calendar for the upcoming days.
You can determine which tasks are
actually required for the week as well as
the level of detail and attention it requires.
Not all of the meetings on your calendar at times require
you to be there, and so you can gauge that to taken free up
yourself and have that sense of clarity to
allow yourself that ability to prioritize
without jamming up your time. Hobby fishing
sparking up with a hobby is a way to give yourself,
literally yourself, something to look forward to that has nothing to
do with work. This is the time to think about yourself
and fine tune that me factor myself.
I just purchased a Kamado grill and so I'm
planning on being a grill guru. Have no idea how this
is going to work, but I've done all of this research and time and I've
constructed on what I want to do. And so when
I need to formulate what I want to do
outside of work, this provides that foreground. To do
that without putting busy, meaningless tasks in front of me.
This is something that I really want to do and
right now this is my yoga.
Nudge your friends. So being healthy for
yourself also requires those around you to be healthy
as well. So tap your friend.
They may actually need it. I've had work friends
previously who've cried out
for help, indirectly, directly,
whatever the case may be, sending out smoke signals.
Typically I'd sense them and I may nudge them back and
say, hey, would you like to participate
in doing something non work related on Zoom for 30 minutes?
And this is simply because work has been challenging and
they may not know how to depress or they may not
know how to reach out. And this is a way,
if they're your friend, this is a way to do so. Also,
as a friend, if someone hasn't taken off that
you know of, whether they're your friend or not, to be honest,
tell them to take off. It's quite okay to do that.
Life happens regardless if they're at work,
not, and the work will be there regardless. And your sanity may
not always be there. If required,
suggest places for them to go. And this
may also be an opportunity to get to know a person as well. Who knows?
Sometimes people need to be reminded from humans that show general
interest in them that it's okay
to think about yourself, to think about your mental health,
to think about your survival.
So the last part here for me is tasting the gumbo.
So I'm from Louisiana, so any chance I get,
I love to throw a splash of Louisiana in there.
So if we look at the me factor as a gumbo,
there are many ingredients in the me factor that define a person.
Besides calibrating yourself, there could be moments where the components
have changed. So gauge yourself
and taste those ingredients to ensure that the components that make
up who you are as a great worker, friend, parent,
lover, et cetera, are still flavorful to not only
yourself, but to others as well. I mean, people have to
love you and stomach you to a certain degree. No one is perfect,
so use your experiences and feedback to add a little salt to
your recipe. Check yourself before you break yourself,
if you're familiar with that terminology, surviving is about patience
and endurance under the right circumstances.
If your job is no longer for you based on your expectations
and needs, that's okay people.
Sometimes we outgrow the seasons that we use.
Have those conversations with your boss to see if it's feasible to
add this to your gumbo. Or is it suitable to replace
that seasoning with something more complementary? This tech
stuff that's always easy. Life is hard but challenging
and rewarding, so let's make sure we're all surviving.
Thanks for joining.