Hi everyone, welcome to my talk. Today we'll
review platform engineering concept, how it's connected
with DevOps. Furthermore, I brought up some practices
I hope will ensure you a smooth adopting
of platform engineering. My name is Caillou
Medeiros and currently I'm leading the DevOps adoption at
Citi. And why me to talk about this concept
today? Well, I had the chances to work
directly with the stream aligned teams, enabling them,
participating with them to generate it products
and have the happy customer at the
end. But also I had the chance to work with
platform teams at Citi, Red Hat and Slay.
Actually I lead one of them generating a
DevOps tool chain for ensuring this
platform reliable and stable for all decision
alignment teams we had inside the company. If you
want to know more about me, you have here my LinkedIn,
my email and my web portfolio in
GitHub pages. So let's
start what I have prepared for you today. Usually I
start generating shared
understanding on the concepts we will review. So I will introduce DevOps
and platform engineering. For sure you have an understanding of this,
but usually different people
will have different definitions. I like to start generating
this shared understanding and then we will go
to the adoption journey. Why and how they
should be together. Finally, I will introduce the three practices.
I promise you, I hope them ensure
this smooth adoption. As I mentioned at great.
So let's start with the introduction to DevOps and platform engineering.
What is DevOps? First, if I ask to anyone
here for sure you will say your understanding of DevOps.
But I like to introduce DevOps using the first phrase of the
DevOps handbook, which is the main
source of knowledge about DevOps. It starts
with this. Imagine a world where pos dev engineers,
qa it ops and infosec engineers.
All the roles, the typical roles we have inside a traditional
or even a modern IT organization.
Imagine them working together without
barriers, without sidos,
without the normal
boundaries we have defined by the traditional organization
or the topologies we have inside the organization,
not only to help each other with their needs,
but also to ensure the overall organization succeed.
Which basically means have our end user
or our customers happy with the id products we
are generating as it organization.
So that's the understanding that Jenny King,
John Witties, Patrick Devois and Nicole Forrest Green tried to
bring to us in this book.
But when we have this kind of adoptions,
the DevOps adoptions, right, the adoption inside
companies. Basically people will try to
implement different ways of working. For sure
it will be connected with agile adoptions,
lean the software development, adopting, design thinking,
adoption and it will be connected also with technologies,
not just a matter of cultural norms and ways of working.
We will have libraries, tools to go from ideation,
to understand the needs of our customers,
to have something in production solving
the problems of our customers. So we will go
into this mobile loop that DevOps provides to us
to plan, code, build, test, release, deploy, operate and
monitor, and we will be there till the product ends
his time. The problem will be
that where each of these
roles, they will need to
have the set of cultural norms,
the ways of working and the tools they require each
role, right? Furthermore, of the mindset,
the DevOps mindset and principles.
But when we are talking about the DevOps world,
we are talking about a lot, a large list of tools we can use,
right? We need to decide which one we will use and
when. We have different teams inside our organization.
For sure, one team will use one tool, another teams,
they will use other tools because if you don't have management
and standardization, it will happen. I already had this
experience mainly when the organizations
are lead by different managers.
In addition to that, the teams will need
to support these platforms to keep them working,
reliable and stable to use them during the
whole lifecycle of the software development. If not,
something will block the generation of value there
is where platform engineering born. The first introduction
of platform team was in
the team topologies book written by
Matthew Skelton and Manuel Pais. They described
platform teams as this string
alignment team, this product team that will provide an internal product
as platform which these string alignment
teams, these teams with different roles working together, will use as
a service. So platform engineering was described as
a discipline to design and build these tool chains,
these platforms that will be used
as self service to help the engineering
teams that are generating it products for end users
to phase out this new cloud native era.
You will find this description in the platform engineering community page.
You can just type platformengineering.org there.
There are much more information about platform engineering. I encourage
you to go there and investigate on why
not participate in the community. So platform engineering
is that idea where we have an internal team inside the company
and they are solving and reducing the cognitive load of string
alignment teams to only focus and have
their real needed skills to work in their
specific IT product. So the platform teams just
giving an example will provide these tool
chains or the set of tools needed to
perform the typical tasks, repetitive tasks
that the stream aligner teams have,
providing not only the platforms itself but also
the templates, the golden paths and managing
these platforms to keep them reliable and
stable. So more or
less we can understand where they are connected, right? The adoption
journey on why and how they work together is
clear now, more or less. So let's go into the
benefits if we have platform teams supporting
these stream aligned teams which are trying to
work together with all these roles to make the organization succeed.
First of all, as I mentioned before, if you have different teams
without a clear management and aligned management,
for sure they will start to use different platforms
to do the same thing. Let's have an example to
build and deploy one software component. I already
had experience in other companies where
one team was using Jenkins, another team was using
Travis CI or any other tool,
right? Basically in the same company they are using different tools.
So for sure they will face different
issues that will block them and will not
have a chance to share
knowledge, share learning lessons because they are using different tools.
The chance will be a
bit more or less right at the end, the standardization is
needed to have the right control over
the practices we are implementing inside the company and to have success
on a DevOps adoption for sure. I don't want to remove the freedom
of teams, but they should have boundaries.
Platform engineering will provide these boundaries because at the end
we will have an internal team trying to generate an internal
product and combines the rest of the teams to use
this tool, this platform. They will provide a
standardization ways of working standardization and
also they will provide this control to understand who is doing
what, how they are doing and where is the boundaries
they have to manage the different ways of working. Also we
will have reduction of the cognitive load because
in the beginning without platform teams, if we
are in a DevOps adoption journey, we had to
hire engineers with knowledge not only in develop
code but also to operate the software
or even to manage the
CI CD tool.
Removing this dependency or the requirement of
these skills, we will be able to find more
engineers. And also we will reduce the
stress of our engineers inside product teams
to not only develop the active product but
also to maintain their own tools. And finally,
the tools will be more reliable, the platforms will be
more reliable and stable,
avoiding any blocker in the software development
lifecycle related to the platforms needed to
build, develop, verify the code
or even operate the code.
So let's take an example of these two lines.
Right where we have in the first line is
Rina line, a team trying to take one idea from
left and generate a product to have a happy customer to the
right. In any process to generate an
IT product we will have rocks on the wall and
sometimes we will have mountains. So only
having string aligned teams,
if you are entering to a traditional organization and breaking
down the barriers and rearming all the teams
to have all these roles together, to work together,
as DevOps description express,
to generate success inside the company.
Sometimes we will have the people going
outside of the stream aligner team to push the rest
of the team because they will depend on the specific knowledge
of that person. Mainly if we are
talking about platforms that will support the work that the
stream aligned teams are doing. If you need someone that will restart
the Jenkins instance, or if you need someone
that will manage the configuration of your kubernetes or
graphana stack at the end,
someone inside the team will have the specific knowledge and
they will waste their time. They were focusing on generate
value for the end customer to support the daily
work of the team. It's different if we have
a platform team looking to all these issues, possible issues
for sure. It will not remove the whole rocks on the road or
the whole mountains we need to cross over,
but they will simplify the path to be faster
than just having a screen aligned things and reach
before the success. Having our happy
customer at the end of the path. And even they will
be faster to have a fast or quick
feedback loops which will generate better software
and more satisfaction in the customer
to make our organization win in the marketplace.
So if you want to go deeper in this concept and
the connection between DevOps and platform engineering,
I will recommend you the talks of Manual
PI's platform as a product and mayori high DevOps
ain't that but we got a talk because they introduce
more and more on this concept. And finally the state of
DevOps. The report from 2023. They focus 100%
on platform engineering and how this practice is important
to face out the challenges proposed by DevOps
in the last years.
So now we reach the three practices I
had prepared for you. I used these practices in
the past, but first I want to generate a
sense of why we need these practices. So I will introduce some challenges behind
platform engineering. Adopting first
of all, DevOps and platform engineering is
not something that is easy to do, right? It seems
like we need to do that will be a total
success. That is what I need to have.
And after this talk, you will reach your manager. You will
try to push the platform engineering ideas inside your company.
But it's not an easier thing, right? Probably will
be harder.
But don't get sad, right?
There are ways to face out the challenges we usually
will have. Not only the platform engineering adoption, some of
them are related to any transformation process. First of all,
lack of time and high demand because when we are introducing a platform
team inside a company, first of all,
everyone will be busy. So it's difficult to
motivate people to adopt a new platform and the demand
will just increase. If you have success with one team,
everyone will want to have this platform as well.
Ways of working and thinking usually we don't have just one
team inside a company. We will have a lot of teams and they will bring
with their ideas, their BSS, their ways
of working, because they work like that in
other companies. And these platform teams,
they will be in the middle. So the facilitation will
be a mess if you don't have the platform team prepared.
And finally, the people motivation and the rotation of
IT engineers is a huge problem for
all initiatives we have today inside the IT organization.
So let's go a bit deeper inside each of these challenges.
First of all, if we have platform teams,
they will need to manage platforms. And platforms
are not just one tool. The expertise on these
tools will be one of the challenges. How you can keep
the expertise inside the team, how this expertise can be
put in benefit of the internal customers,
the swing alignment teams, and to develop these skills
inside the string alignment teams. Because even
when we are providing a platform with templates and golden pads
inside the srina teams, they need to develop some skills
to take real profit of the platforms that platform
thinking provide. How we can reply in
front of failures and outages, because they
will happen and the documentation that needs to be updated.
Everything will go so fast.
At the same time we need to manage the demand, because if we
are introducing a platform team inside a company,
usually if
it ends in a success case, for sure,
managers will try to push this to the rest of the teams.
So more users means more doubts, more requests
and the team need to be prepared for these challenges.
In other side, we have the ways of working the facilitation between
teams, right? Because several ways of doing the same thing. As I
mentioned before, sometimes we will have just a simple
case, sometimes we will have one team using one
CI tool, another teams using other CI
tools, and the different ways of configuring and provide environments
and provide resources will
be a mess. So the facilitation to put the
platform team in middle of this will be a
challenge for sure. Also they will need to face out complex compliance
flows. Because in all companies we have these
kind of problems with specific requirements,
distorted perspectives of priorities.
And the last thing I had seen in the last companies
and teams I had worked after the COVID we
start working globally with people from different countries
and the languages and the understanding
barriers sometimes generate a lot of confusion.
Finally, keep team engaged. This is another
challenge, a huge challenge, because not only related with platform engineering,
it's in all cases inside the IT organization.
People is burning out and
the cognitive load is directly related to this.
How the platform teams can manage this cognitive load, as I
mentioned it, the time will be a problem, the demand would be a problem.
So it's super easy to get burned
out. Of course, the technical and practice
debts will add more
challenges to this. So how we can face it.
There you have my three practices. The first one is customer
centric leadership. Right inside each platform team,
we should have a leader with a design thinking mindset to
identify the customers, the internal customers. These string alignment teams
understand the real needs because for sure, if we have
platform teams in different companies to
provide the same type of platform, they will identify
different objectives, different needs, because each
organization has their own conditions,
their own requirements. So it's super important to put in
the place of the customers and understand their
objectives, to guide the priorities of the team.
And also this leader should connect the
platform team, the whole platform team with the customers.
How this leader can do that promoting
inside the team to map and make it visible,
the profile of our end users. You can
use empathy mapping proto or user Persona.
For mapping these profiles, it's crucial to have
the design thinking mindset. It will provide you this perspective that
this is my end user and I want to satisfy their needs.
The second practice is practice what you preach sounds super
logical, but I had a lot
of experiences where the platform teams, they were not using their
own platform and was a mess because at the end they
don't know what is happening, really happening in production.
The better way to understand how users are living
or they are implementing the platform is using it.
Metrics is the perfect way to measure this, to take a
control of this. So setting the right metrics will be
good to identify and monitor during the time
if the team is really using the platform and it
can be complemented with the internal and external usability
testing. I mean you will invite not only
people outside of your team, but inside your team to execute
and run usability testing. Go navigate
through the platform and the offering the platform team is
providing and test it before to release
a new version to reduction. Also have showcases
and demo days to promote your platform and motivate people
to get into the platform and start using and
finally run this kind of lighting talks or tech talks
because then you will share your knowledge to the rest of
the teams on how this platform should be used.
It will generate a better understanding of
your end user and how to
improve the platform experience. Finally,
form champions. This is the
practice that I love more because when
we are talking about platform teams, usually it's not
just one technology. We will have more than one
technology, more than one library, more than one platform to generate
one single platform to support different
needs of these.
So the knowledge needed to manage all these platforms
is crazy, right? I had the chance to lead a
platform team where we were providing
DevOps tool chain to versionate their code,
to build their code, deploy their code. So a
lot of platforms in all these stages,
right? Not only to build, but also to scan
and generate automation in
the test phases. So what
is the keys there of this practice?
The whole team should be generalist.
I'm talking about the t shaped people, right? They should be generalist
in all tools and platforms you have inside the platform team.
And some of them will be deeper in specific
platforms to generate ownership and
delegate the responsibilities and keep the documentation
updated and bring news to the team,
solve issues and generate more expertise
in the rest of the team.
So with this, you will stop to search for experts
and you need to start forming them stop
to search for experts because for sure you will find some experts
in the marketplace, but they will be so expensive.
I will not say that you need to stop to search for experts and
sometimes it will be needed. But if you can avoid it,
try to find people that you can form and generate the t
shaped people inside your platform team because it will maintain
low the cognitive load and
hide the expertise for that. First of all,
you need to have a career path for each member and this
career path should be aligned with the
team needs. And at the end, the end user needs
the internal teams, right? The stream aligned teams with that
career. You will have certification training paths for
all members inside your team, not only to be generalists in the platform,
but also to be deeper in one specific platform.
Complement that with game days and Chow's engineering sessions where
they will need to prepare the platform to fail
and solve it during a real and
live moment. Finally,
assign and create a calendar of lighting talks and tech talks that is connected
with the other practices to these champions, to be
led by these champions, because then they will learn more
to be prepared to talk about those concepts.
So, to summarize the three practices I broke to you today
and ensure a smooth adoption of platform engineering
inside your company. As you already reviewed with me,
platform engineering is useful to
support the DevOps adoption and ensure that
the whole organization the IT organization. All the different roles we
have inside work together to make the
organization succeed. Try to bring this to your teams
right? And also you can use it in other teams as well if
you feel that is useful. First of all,
customer centric leadership. We need to have one leader with design
thinking mindset, with a clear vision of our customers and
sharing this information with the rest of the platform team, promoting the
closeness with the customers and
setting and aligning the objectives and goals to
address the platform team success. Because at the
end, if a platform is not good enough, it will not
be adapted and it will be a failure.
Then let's practice what you preach. If you are
proposing a platform to the internal users internal
teams, then you need to use it as an internal team
as well. Set some shared metrics
with you and the end users and recognize
and show the achievements because then people will
get more motivated to find improvements inside
the platform. Finally, form champions
because it's super hard to find people ready to work
in a platform team. So find generalist formed
experts by two and delegate and trust
on them. Trust on them that the documentation will be updated.
They will bring the ideas to work in the specific platforms
they are expert and to make the platform better.
Finally, just to close this talk,
I will empower you to go to the platform engineering community
page, read the nagging steps
to platform engineering hell that Lucas Galante
published some time ago. You will find there are some
mistakes in the platform engineering adoption
you can avoid, and also I empower you to watch the Nick
Watt talk about people, process and platform.
Finally, if you want to join the platform engineering YouTube
chat channel, there you will find much more content to
prepare your path or your career as platform
engineer. Thanks for joining. Thanks for participating.
I hope you are enjoying this event and have a nice day.