Welcome. My name is Jonathan Williams and I'm in the
product manager team within the IoT and wireless business unit at Twilio
and I'm here to talk about the challenges around overcoming IoT
security threats from the start. Now you may know Twilio
for our fantastic communications APIs, bringing easy
to use connectivity so SMS, voice, WhatsApp chats,
etc. To apps and websites, enabling billions
of customer interactions to take place every day.
Well, just as we enable simple and easy connectivity for
people and applications, what you might not know
is that we also power connectivity for millions of devices across the
Internet of Things, both with our super sim connectivity
solution as well as our microvisor device builder platform.
But enough about that. Today I really want to talk about the
sobering reality when it comes to IoT devices and
security across the Internet of Things,
security has been overlooked. An amazing 1.51
billion IoT devices were breached in the first six months of 2021,
and this itself was an increase
from 639,000,000 breached in the same time period
in 2020. So this is a growing problem and
with the anticipated number of connected devices worldwide predicted
to reach 50 billion by 2030, there is still a
lot that needs to be done to ensure that these devices are protected from attacks
and things includes ensuring the security of your connected
devices and your data lives up to the promise you make to
your customers. The impact of your devices being compromised
is a big one and can often be ignored until it is
too late. So I think we know that both us
as device builders and now consumers are increasingly aware of
the importance of device security. But it can be challenging
to know which devices are secure by design and
which just haven't been targeted yet. For many
device builders, security can become an afterthought as
you prioritize the features of the product or service itself
when working towards a minimum viable product. Equally,
security can sometimes be considered a necessary but
unexciting piece of the product development. These hoops that you unfortunately
have to jump through. It can also be hard and therefore expensive to
retrofit security into an existing product properly.
And maybe these are some of the reasons why we sometimes see insecure products
released to market. But it is worth remembering that the risk
profile of a security incident is high and the impact can
be extremely severe. If the worst was to
happen and a breach or hack occurs, you may well
end up suffering company damaging impacts.
Really because of this high level of risk, these security
of your data and of your device must be foundational and must
be built in from the start. Security really does need to be
considered as a necessary system component within your device or
system architecture. Now, I thought it might be interesting to
take a look at a few high promise incidents that have happened in the last
few years. Now. I think these are interesting to look at as whilst they're
not necessarily exactly IoT use cases, I think the
lessons learned are directly applicable to what we need to
think about when securing our IoT devices. So before
Zoom became a household name, there were a series of
security loopholes discovered within the Zoom client implementations.
So across several platforms, Mac, Windows, et cetera,
and within the AV industry, there was a lot of comment, news articles
and concerns being raised around the general security of the Zoom
implementation. This in turn was arguably starting to cause
the reputational damage that can be so, so damaging for a growing company.
In many ways, how Zoom responded to the security concerns
was pretty damn impressive. By zoom
pivoting to take security seriously and addressing the issues
raised in a timely fashion, they did manage to turn the problem
into an opportunity to excel, which is no mean
feat. I can only imagine the stress and sleepless
nights that occurred whilst these high profile software fixes were being
worked on. And I'm sure many a Zoom executive would much
rather have seen security as a core feature of the initial product rather
than the afterthought that IoT effectively was. So,
taking a look at another one, several years ago,
the connected security cameras from Hicvision were compromised through
a weak password implementation and a backdoor misuse of a
cookie, which resulted in devices being compromised.
The Department of Homeland Security characterized the vulnerability as remotely
exploitable with a low level of skill to exploit, I.
E. Anyone with a computer can reproduce this and
remotely access another user's camera footage.
Now, rather than this just being a security incident
that was raised and publicized and fixed before it became an
actual issue, as so many are here,
hackers did start accessing camera footage and actual
users were targeted after their device security was
exploited. So their hypothetical worst case
scenario of real users and their data being hacked
became reality. And it's not just reputational damage
that can happen, there can be a huge financial cost
to a security incident as well. Only this year the
well documented colonial pipeline cyber attack took
place and ransomware impacted computerized equipment managing the Texas
based pipeline so kind of a bit like a connected IoT style device
if I squint a bit. But here the attackers stole nearly
100gb of data and threatened to release it on the Internet
if a ransom was not paid. Having caused the shutdown of
the pipeline for six days and compromised these billing system. The only
way out of this situation, in the end has to pay that ransom and
that cost them 75 bitcoin or at the time, $4.4 million.
Now, these are just some of the many, many security incidents or
CVE vulnerabilities that are exploited or design mistakes
that affect products somewhere in the world every single day.
And as someone responsible for a connected device, the risk of
a security incident should be enough to keep you awake at night.
The important thing here, though, is certainly not to throw stones
at others. Those examples I used a moment ago,
it really is to learn, appreciate and understand that
similar things happen all the time. And to that
extent, unless you are really conscious about security as a
core Internet of your product development, this too could happen to
you. So perhaps as an embedded software engineer
or a device developer, a CEO or product manager responsible
for a connected device, what must you think about and
look for to make sure that your device is one of the secure ones?
First, when it comes to security, you really must
start by considering the threat model that you're actually connected about,
I. E. What are you trying to protect and who are you trying to protect
against? And this essentially boils down to,
at one end of the scale, protecting against accidental
misuse or a sloppy implementation that hick vision default
password, for example, through bad actors and rogue
employees, untrusted manufacturing partner access, the kind of thing iso
27,001 help protects against all the
way through to the hypothetical government sponsored hacking where
silicon chips will be decapped and power supply
injection used to read flash contents. And obviously,
the approach that you would consider necessary to protect against accidental
misuse is somewhat different to that required to protect against
statesponsored hacking. Now, the basics of
IoT device security can consider somewhat
covered by legislation or certification in standards.
For example, the most obvious weak authentication,
which in general means a poor or default password approach and must
for obvious reasons be avoided, is increasingly being included
in new IoT legislation around the world. So, for example in
California or Australia and more recently in the United
Kingdom, IoT device legislation is attempting to banish
the weak or default password approach. But there are lots
of devices out there that are still affected by this, and obviously this will
still take time for everyone to adopt it and
standards, be them specific security standards, for example
ARMPSA or the multitude of others, or be it ISO
implementation standards, ISO 27,001
for example. These can also help with some of the specific issues
and people based risks putting in processes around which employees
have access to which systems and the data within them now, many of
these are essentially hoops that you need to jump through, but it could
be said that if you can't jump through the hoop, then you probably
aren't ready to release your product to market,
specifically in terms of the device itself.
And as an example of these things that you need to think about,
Microsoft laid out one approach in their white paper, the seven
properties of highly secure devices. And here Microsoft
identifies and discusses seven properties that they
think must be shared by all highly secure
network connected devices.
And these are a hardware based route of trust that
you have a small trusted computing base, defense,
in depth compartmentalization of code, certificate based
authentication, renewable security and
built in failure reporting. And this does form
a great basis for considering what your device needs to do
in order to be secure. It's important to note that
Microsoft uses a custom silicon part to support these seven
properties, but these can be achieved in a variety of ways,
and I think I agree with them that these should all be considered necessary for
IoT devices today. But I think
there's more to think about as well. So has well as the above seven properties,
I think there are some other things that we should consider necessary for
a secure device implementation, and this includes things like
secure boot and secure factory provisioning.
As manufacturing secure products at scale requires
a well designed production process that allows secure products
to be built in insecure factories. And this
protects customer IP and prevents gray market devices from
ever existing. So whatever you're thinking your threat model is,
whether it's accidental misuse, rogue employees at the factory,
or the manufacturing partner, or the government sponsored hacking
I things, it's fair to say that it is vital that you control and
manage the code that's running on your device. I mean,
if you cannot trust that the device is running the code that you think it
is, I. E. Your code, then pretty much you cannot trust
anything about that device. So to this end, I think
you must have a method of secure boot and secure factory provisioning.
And this is a must have for you to be able to trust the device
and the device code itself. As it's the combination of these features
that ensure that you can guarantee that your device is running
your code. I like to think if you can't manufacture it securely
then it certainly isn't secure. A good example
of this, or can be, is where the need to
get something up and running quickly does not lead to a secure implementation.
And an example of this is the many industrial use cases built on top of
the Raspberry PI. And this does not support either secure,
brute or a secure factory provisioning step. So it's absolutely
great at what it does do in getting a use case up and running quickly,
but kind of secure by design? Not really.
What can we do about it? So the challenge can be
that once you have committed to an approach, be it a hardware
or software approach, then switching or changing your development
can be seen as both a hard and b costly.
The inertia and the sunk cost of development so far,
combined with that pressure to get a product out of the door, often means
that companies, engineering teams and devices tend to stick with
a relatively insecure approach as they look to move to production.
Maybe that's something we saw in some of those examples earlier.
So I think it's important, or perhaps crucial to ask yourself,
how important is it that we have a secured device implementation?
Is the approach that we're taking properly secure,
and are we happy with that level of risk that
were taking security rise? What would the outcome be?
What would happen if our devices were hacked or compromised?
And probably crucially or most importantly, is the cost and
risk of not having a secure approach and potentially having
one of those security incidents really worth it? I would
say don't be afraid to ask these questions, whatever stage
of the development process you're at, and don't be afraid to come to the conclusion
that security must matter. And these earlier
you do this, ideally right at the start, the better it
will be for you, your devices and your customers,
and ultimately your overall business. And if it
seems too hard, don't worry, switching to a secure
architecture doesn't need to be as hard as it seems. And if
you do want to take a look at our approach to a true end to
end embedded security based on our Twilio microvisor,
which is essentially a hypervisor for microcontrollers,
providing a secure implementation at the edge all
the way through to the cloud, or our supersim connectivity for
enabling global cellular connectivity for IoT devices,
then please do check us out@Twilio.com.
Slash IoT so thank you very much
for your time and I hope you enjoy, enjoyed that quick look at what it
takes to consider IoT security from the
start. Thank you very much.