Hi Kim fan here. Welcome to ML
enhanced event streaming apps with Python microservices
because I couldn't fit any more words in that title.
I'm a principal developer advocate for
all the major streaming technologies. Flink, Kafka,
Pulsar, Nifi. When you use a lot of these together,
I like to give them a catchy little name either. Flip,
flippin flank, all kinds of cool stuff. I've been doing
lots of different streaming stuff for a number of
years, trying to grow the open source streaming
and doing that for a lot of different companies. Applications all over
in the community put out a newsletter every week
called the Flipstack Weekly. Covers all the cool tech out
there. Scan it, check it out. It is
easy to check out. If you don't want to subscribe, just look at GitHub.
I put all the previous 71 episodes there.
Easy to read, get through quickly.
Great stuff. So when you're building
these type of real time applications, you need a team for
your stream. And now that team is a bunch of open source tools like
Nifi, Flank, Pulsar, Kafka, Spark,
Python, of course, Trino,
and also other people you work with. So I
thought I would pull in one of the top experts in
Apache Pulsar to cover that section. So make it
a little more understandable. I'm going to bring in my friend David,
who literally wrote the book on Pulsar to
give us a little background on that. Figured might as well go to
the source and not have me go through that secondary.
And while that's loading, we'll get I'm a committer
on the Apache Pulsar project and also author of the book
Pulsar in action by Manning Press. I formerly worked at Splunk
as a principal software engineer with the day to day operations
of the Pulsar as a service platform within that organization
and served in several director and leadership roles
at startups including Streamlio and Hortonworks.
So I want to talk to you today about Apache Pulsar and why it
has a growing and vibrant community. As you can see from these statistics here,
we have a large number of contributors. We're up over 600 contributors now
to the Pulsar project, 7000 plus Slack members in
our open source Apache Slack channel, where our day to day Q and
A questions are answered vibrantly throughout the community themselves,
10,000 plus individual commits and back into the project and growing.
And over 1000 organizations worldwide are using Apache Pulsar
to solve their event streaming and messaging use cases. So why
is Apache Pulsar growing in such popularity and gaining traction
out there. It really comes down to the feature set that Apache Pulsar offers
and some of its architectural differences that make it stand out from the other
messaging solutions in the market today.
Chief among them is the ability to scale elastically
both horizontally and vertically to meet
your peak demand, and then scale back down to minimize
your infrastructure spend after your peak demand workload
has been processed. And this is only capable due to
the fact that we've architected Apache Pulsar in a cloud
native way from day one. And what I mean by that is that we've completely
decoupled the storage and compute layers in such a way that they
can scale up independently from one another,
so that if you have a burst of demand,
brokers can be scaled up to serve the incoming request and
then they can be scaled back down and the data retains there
in the storage layer. This allows for seamless and instant partitioning
and rebalancing of partition topics within pulsar without
stop the world event. That's common in Apache Pulsar, where the
entire topic is down until the data can be repartitioned and a new partition
added as data is shuffled across the different brokers. That is
not the case for pulsar, but it's more than just that. If it was just
that, that wouldn't be really interesting. It's also built in georeplication
and geographic redundancy and continuous availability
features built into the Apache Pulsar framework that are second to none.
That was a primary use case for Apache Pulsar back in 2012 when
it was developed internally inside of Yahoo was for full mesh georeplication
across eight data eight data centers that are geographically distributed
across the globe. This capability is second to none
in the messaging system today and allows you to replicate data very
easily from point to point and is built in natively to the system,
and it goes beyond just the ability to copy the data from
one cluster to another. We also have what we call replicated
subscriptions, so you keep track of where you are in that processing model as
well as you transition clients over. And last but not least,
we have failure aware clients built into the Apache Pulsar library
where you can specify this is my preferred active primary cluster,
and if you lose connectivity to that cluster, you can immediately
switch those clients over to what you configure to be a secondary standby cluster
so they can continuously operate without any need to doing
the DNS entry shuffling or things like that. The clients
themselves take care of it and then they switch back when they detect that primaries
come back online. Last but not least is we support a
flexible subscription model. So Hatchie Pulsar is
defined as the cloud native messaging and event streaming
platform, meaning they can support both your traditional messaging
use cases like pub sub work
queue sort of semantics with these different subscription models. And we also support the
more modern use cases of event streaming, where processing
of the data in order and retaining it in order is critical.
Both of those are available with Apache Pulsar, and it's built in natively
through what we call subscription models where you specify, this is how I want to
subscribe to the data, and both those messaging and event streaming semantics are
supported. Another key feature of Apache
Pulsar is that we integrate the schema registry natively into the platform itself.
Unlike other messaging systems which acted as
an add on after the fact, you have to pay additional
monies to get these capabilities. That's not the case with Apache Pulsar.
Just like other messaging systems, we support schema
aware producers and consumers so that when they connect,
they can verify that the schema they're publishing with conforms to the
expected schema of the downstream consumer, so that there's a data integrity
between the two. Also support schema
enforcement and auto updating. So if you publish by default
a schema of the producer, let's say you connect a producer with a schema
that adds a field and you're looking for a backwards compatible schema
strategy, then that will be enforced because the consumers aren't aware of that,
weren't aware of that field to begin with. They can continue processing using the old
Schema version two while you're publishing messages with schema version three,
and it interacts seamlessly and this is all built in out of the box
and it's stored internally inside of Pulsar and you get these capabilities for free.
Another really key feature that I'm high on among so many,
that's what I want to call out, is what we call Kafka on Pulsar.
Now, Pulsar is the first and only messaging system that supports
multiple messaging protocols natively.
And what I mean by that is other messaging systems that have
been developed thus far usually have a low level wire
transfer protocol that's unique to them. For example,
RabbitMQ uses an AMQP protocol spec that
sends commands back and forth to publish and retrieve data.
Kafka similarly has a similar protocol for publishing and subscribing
data. Pulsar has what's called a protocol handler framework shown
here in this yellow box that would automatically take the commands from one
protocol, in this case Kafka, and translate those automatically
into the commands that Pulsar needs to handle in order to
store data and retrieve data. Whatever the case may be. This allows
you to natively take your existing Kafka applications using
a Kafka library that you already tested and vetted out,
and switch it to. Point to Apache Pulsar and you can
operate seamlessly. This is a great use case. So if you've invested a significant
amount of time into one of these messaging technologies, or maybe many of them,
you can simply change a few
configurations and reuse all that code and not have to rip it out and replace
it because you want to use a new messaging system. So the barrier to adoption
is much lower with this, as we mentioned
before, the key to having a really good, strong streaming foundation
is a teamwork, and in
patchy pulsar that's reflected as a strong and thriving
ecosystem across different components, as shown here. So as I mentioned
before, the protocol handlers in addition to Kafka we spoke about
in the previous slide, we have one for MQTT, we have one for AMQP
as well. So you can speak all these different messaging protocols, a single system to
speak them all. Multiple client libraries this is just a sampling
of some of the ones that are supported. As you can see, all the more
popular ones are supported. Java Python for those of you using Python,
it's a very big deal. Python is a first order
client library and has unique features that we will talk about connectors
and sync so you can move your data into and out of these other systems.
Process data inside using different stream processing engines
shown there down below like flink, do some analytics on it and then push it
to your delta lake. That's all very easy to do natively
with these connectors. You also have pulsar
functions, which is a lightweight stream processing framework. I'll talk about in the
next slide that supports Python as
a development language for one of these particular features, and we'll get into
that in a little bit and how you can leverage those for machine learning applications
out at the edge. And last but not least, tiered storage offload. So as I
mentioned before, Pulsar is architected in such a way that your
storage and compute layers are separated. You can take full advantage of that by
moving older data, retaining it beyond the traditional seven days
you do in something like a Kafka, 30 days, 90 days, however long you want,
by moving it to more cost effective storage. Cloud storage this blob,
this object store cloud providers like S three or
Google Cloud storage, you can have it internally. If you have an existing hdfs
cluster sitting around, you have nat network attached storage sitting around.
You can offload that data and use this lower cost storage to put the data
there. And Pulsar can read it natively. It doesn't really need to reconstitute
it or spin up some clusters to put it back in first. Like other messaging
systems, you can offload it to s three, but step one is to create a
new broker and load it first. You don't have to do that since
we're just reading it from a pointer, whether it's on our local storage,
in our bookie layer, what we call bookkeeper, or if it's on s three,
it doesn't matter, it's transparent to the end user and all these connectors
and documentation and the source code and the download is available at hub
streamnative IO here shown on the left. So if you want to learn more about
them, get some more information, download them, try them out, it's all
available for you to use.
I mentioned pulsar functions in the previous slide and it
has a very simplistic programming model. So for those of you familiar with AWS,
lambdas or maybe Azure functions, it's very simple.
You give a single, you provide a user provided function,
a single method implemented, and this,
that individual piece of code gets executed every time a
new event arrives on one or more input topics that you configure
the function to listen to. So you can say whatever these
topics come in. When an event comes in, I want to execute this logic and
boom, it happens. And again, there's three languages supported, Java,
Python and go. And more importantly, even though
they're simple single method pieces of code, so they're very
easy to write, very easy to learn. You can still leverage the full power
of any third party libraries you want to use inside this code itself. So we
support the importing of these different third party machine learning execution
models, for example. So you can do more complex stream processing,
machine learning on these individual streams,
data streams as they come in very easily on that. So it's a
very nice framework for doing that. Here's an example of
a pulsar function written in Python. As you can see
here we have a couple of different import statements. We brought in a sentiment
analysis tool in this regard,
and as you can see we've imported the function definition
and have a class that implements it here chat. The method
there, called process, is the code that actually gets executed every time a
new method arrives on one of the input topics, and the input,
as you can expect, is that second parameter there called input, and you can manipulate
that data as you see fit in this particular code example here,
we parse it out as JSON. We know it's JSON. We pull
out some individual fields that we know are there, we run some analysis on it,
we determine if the sentiment is positive or negative, and then as a result of
that we can publish those results to an output topic. And that's where
this return statement comes in. So when you run the return statement,
that's where the outputting of the data to a downstream topic has occurred.
You don't have to do a return every time, but if you do, that constitutes
the publishing of a new message at that point in time. So it's a really
great feature. Again, this is for Python, and Tim will talk more about
it in the presentation about how we're going to leverage these and
Python library to do some cool machine learning
models and machine learning processing with Python.
So thanks David. Let's get to the next slide here.
Always fun. Let me get out of full screen mode
here, and we'll get to some of the other
libraries here. So at a minimum you'll have your Python
three environment on whatever kind of machine it is. Mac, windows,
raspberry, PI, ubuntu, whatever it is, you do a pip
install. 211 is the latest.
Now if you're in an exotic platform, weird hardware,
you might have to do a build. You can get the
source code, do a c plus plus build, and then from there build
the python one. Pretty straightforward, but for most platforms
you won't need to do that, including Mac, M,
one, silicon or intel doesn't matter. The code itself,
really simple. You import pulsar,
create a client, connect to your cluster on your port,
then create a producer for that particular
topic. Now the format for that is persistent.
Most topics persist the data for as long as it needs to be.
You can make it non persistent, not very common, but if you
don't care about the messages, you just want fast throughput. Maybe you've
got something that's always on, just as on some kind
of IoT device. Maybe you don't need to persist it,
send it, encode it, close the client, done.
That's the simplest way to send messages with Python.
That's probably not your production use case. You probably have to log in.
So say I wanted to log into a secure cluster running
in the cloud. I could use SSL,
pick my port there again, connect to that topic.
If I'm going to use Oauth, put out the issuer URL
for that OAuth provider, point to my private key,
set up what my audience is for that cluster when
that data comes in. Same idea here,
but I'm also importing authentication. It's going to
authenticate against that. Got a number of examples on how to
do that. If you're trying that out for yourself, you can get a free pulsar
cluster at stream native to try this. It's a great way to
learn it without having to install stuff or set up your own docker.
There's also a cluster available if you do the free training
at stream native. Now, if I want to use one of those schemas
that I talked about before,
Avro is one type, I'll import schema,
I'll create a schema. It's a very simple class.
Give it a name record which comes from the pulsar schema,
and put all my field names and what type they are. You'd also
specify if they're nullable or not.
Connect to the client again and you could do oauth if you want.
And then for thermal, I'll create the schema
based on this over here and send that.
When I create my producer, I'll specify the schema that way,
put in a couple of extra parameters so people know who I
am, and then create my record by setting
a couple of fields and then send that here. I'm also setting
a key. It's good so I can uniquely identify my records,
and then bang, it's ready to go. If you've
never sent a schema to that topic before, it'll create the
first version of it. If this is an update, it'll add a new version.
If you haven't created that topic before, if you have permissions, it'll create
that topic under that tenant and namespace
specified there, and set up that schema for you.
It's really easy, especially for development. Once you're in production, you probably
want someone to control who creates those schemas
and topics and when and who has permissions. All that fun
security stuff that people love out there. Now, if I want to do the same
thing with Jason, it is not drastically different.
I recommend you keep these topics separate,
because I can have millions of topics, no reason to get in trouble
and trying to put two different types of schema on the same topic.
Create a new topic for everything you're doing. So if we want to do
JSON schema almost identical, we just use
JSON again. I could use that same class, put that in a separate file,
and create one topic that has the JSON schema. One has Avro,
one has protobuff. Whatever. Your downstream system
is happier. Know Nifi really likes the JSON
or Avro one. Flink might be better with know you
might have a tool that works better with JSOn. Find that out,
send that data that way. Very easy to do that.
If you want to get data back, you subscribe to it, give it
a subscription name. There's different types of subscriptions,
it'll default to different types. And I could just go
in a loop here, receive it, display it, and very important
here acknowledge once I acknowledge a message for
my subscription, mine for this topic, under that tenant
and namespace, that message has been received and
I acknowledged I received it. That means if there's no new messages out
there, that data could be expired away if you want,
or sent to long term storage,
depending on your purpose out there. As long as no one else has a
subscription that has unacknowledged messages. This is
nice. I can acknowledge messages one at a time. It's not
a build like in Kafka. This comes out very handy.
If maybe you want to skip a message because it looks a little odd,
maybe have someone else look at those later.
Lots of reasons why you might want to not acknowledge messages,
and you can unacknowledge them, and that way they'll live as long
as your system allows them to live, which is configurable.
Now, we talked about those other protocols, very important with ML.
You may be grabbing stuff off devices, you may want to send things
to a device. Maybe it only supports MQTT,
use that protocol. And I could still point to pulsar, use those
native python libraries, doesn't matter, point to those
same topics. It is a very good way to have
different protocols as part of your ML stream.
Very common for IoT sensor use cases.
This does come up a lot. This is a good protocol
for that.
It is perfect if you're sending a lot of data.
It's not my favorite because it can be a little
lossy. So be warned. If you're sending
data with MQTT, keep an eye on it. But it is a nice way to
do that. Now, another great thing, it's very easy to do
websockets in Python, so we could use the websocket client
to connect to pulsar as well. And we point to our topic.
This will go over, rest, encode the data and send it.
Very easy to do. We'll get a response back saying that it was
received. Great way to get your data into
pulsar. Also a great way to communicate with say a
front end client which could be pure javascript.
Nothing fancy there and we've got some examples later.
It's a good way to communicate between apps written and say node js and Python.
That can happen a lot in different ways that you want
to display machine learning applications. Something to think about.
I can get events and switch them over to Websocket style
communications without having to add other servers,
fancy libraries, or any kind of weirdness straight
out of the box. Standard websockets and base 64 encoding.
Boom. We can have as much security as you want as well. And including encryption.
Of course those things get a little more complex now
Kafka is huge and has a lot of great use
cases. If I have an existing Kafka
app in python, could use that same library port,
those things get my data, use the standard Kafka producer.
But I'm going to point now to pulsar which will act as
those kafka bootstrap ones. Very straightforward,
nothing to worry about there. And then do a flush.
So real easy to do Kafka and Pulsar and
I link to some resources there, show you how you do it again, the same
code could just point to a Kafka cluster as well,
so no reason to write any custom code.
Point it to whatever Kafka compliant broker
that you have out there. Really nice.
Now I want to show a couple simple DevOps here
just to show you that this is a modern system. Now we
could use a lot of different ways to deploy things.
One way is command line and that could be interactive.
It could be command at a time. Obviously this could
be automated a ton of different ways. Whatever automation
DevOps tool you like, this can also be done through rest
endpoints or through different cloud uis.
There's a really nice one in the open source for
doing pulsar administration. You could look at that one.
This is as hard as it is to deploy a function and
do a create set auto acknowledge.
So when event comes into a function we acknowledge it right away.
Point to my python script, give it the
class name that I'm using in that application. Point to as
many topics as I want to come in here for this one. It's just one.
I could change that on the fly later. Also through
DevOps add more easily.
I had a log topic, so anywhere I use the context
to log it will go to a topic. So you don't have to search through
logs or write a third party logging system.
These will be just data in a topic which I could have a function read
or just any app, doesn't matter, including a Kafka
app. Give it a name so I know what my functions is
and put it an output now inside the
code. I could send it to any other topic if I wanted to,
including create topics on the fly. Source code for this one
is down the bottom. This one's a cool little ML app. What happens
is I connect a front end web page and
it sends to a kafka topic which you can see here is chat.
That triggers an event into this sentiment.
Python app which reads that looks at
your text there and applies the sentiment,
puts the results of that and some other fields in an output
topic which it also displays in
that front end. Again, a great way to communicate between Python
and JavaScript, even if that's in a phone app
or a web app, or in a notebook, wherever it happens to be.
Great way to communicate between systems. Do that asynchronously
and apply ML in different pieces depending on
where it makes sense. I don't know what that one
was. We're going to walk through some code here. We saw this
before. If I'm going to set up a schema, give it a name.
Record comes from the schema library. That's important.
We set our different types here. These are the names we're using.
Very straightforward, but that is my schema. I don't have to know how
to build an Avro schema or how to build JSon or protobuff.
It'll be build from this, which is very nice.
You just write some Python code, create connection
here to that server. We'll build a JSON schema off
of that, give it a name. You could put some other fields in here for
tracking that doesn't affect the data here
I like to create a unique key, or relatively unique
doing a build in standard Python library
format. The time put that together as a big key
that's reasonably unique. Create a new
instance of my stock, set some values.
These are getting pulled off of a rest endpoint.
I'm reading format these in the right format,
clean them up, add my uuId. I'm also sending
that as the partition key. If I got my stock data,
send it, and then this could be sent to another processor
to read this. And then the end result of this can be
displayed in a front end. Because we could read websockets,
you could also read rest. Reading websockets from
Javascript is really easy. And I apply that with
a table library. Boom. You could get
live data. So as events come in, the websocket
is subscribed and it'll just get more and more data and it'll come into this
table and you could sort it. All that kind of fun stuff.
Search it. Nice way to do that. When you're setting up these web
pages, it could not be easier. You point to
a style sheet out there. You could either download it locally or point to
the CDN. I'm using jquery
to do my formatting. Pretty straightforward. The data
table library I'm using is also using jquery.
Pretty simple here, and I point to it down the bottom.
This also has my function that's doing some processing of some
data that's coming from one of our friends in
the streaming library. That's Apache nifi. Gets that
data into the funnel for me. Very easy to
format my table. Set up a head and a foot with
some ths in the field names. Make sure I give it an id.
I need that later so I can get access to that data
table. Connect to Pulsar over that websocket.
Set up a subscription name. I also say I'm
a consumer for the persistent tenant
namespace and topic here, and I give it the subscription
name of TC reader and say it shares. If I want
multiple people reading these at once, I could do that.
Connect open my websocket. If there's an error, print out the errors
here. When a message comes in, I parse that JSON data.
If everything looks good, I'm going to
take the payload that comes from that request,
parse that as JSON, and get all these fields out of it.
That's how we sent our message. Add a row to the screen,
boom, it's displayed. Article shows you some details on
that. Very cool way to display your data. Now to
get data in, apply some machine learning,
get data between different systems, maybe move it from pulsar
to data store or say Apache iceberg.
Data flows are a great way to do that. We ingest the data, move it
around, routing all of it. Visual, very easy to do.
We guarantee the data is delivered. We have buffering
and backpress is supported. You could prioritize the
queuing of data. You pick how much latency or throughput
you need. We get data provenance lineage on everything.
So I could track everything that happened. Someone tells me the data didn't
show up downstream. I could look in the data provenance,
which can also be programmatically looked at very easily.
Data can be pushed or pulled. Hundreds of different ways to process
your data, lots of different sources with version control,
clustering, extensibility expands out to
support millions of events a second.
What's nice with Nifi is I could also move binary data,
unstructured data, image data, PDF word
documents, as well as data we traditionally think of
as tabular data, table data, stuff that
you might want to be working with usually. But this is a nice
way to move some of that data you might need for machine learning and deep
learning. Because I can move images, I could pull stuff off web cameras,
you could pull stuff off street cameras very easily. Do some enrichment.
I'll do it all visually, do some simple event processing,
get that data into some central messaging system, lots of
protocols supported Kafka, Pulsar,
MQTT, Rabbit, all those sort of things. TCP,
IP logs, all those sort of things.
Simple architecture, but expands out to as many nodes
as I need and could do all that with kubernetes
or get some commercial hosting out there very easily in all
the big clouds with no headaches. I have
been Tim Spann, got all my contact information here.
I do meetups like once a month. Definitely would like to
see people. We do Python, we do
nifi, Spark, Pulsar, Kafka,
Iceberg, all the cool tech here. This is Nifi.
It is a great way to integrate with Python and there's some
new features coming out soon which will be out
in the next release that lets you integrate Python and
extend Nifi using Python apps.
You just drop it in a directory and it'll automatically show up in this list.
Or you could just use something like this thing
here and this will execute your Python script
or other languages. But face it, most people use Python.
It's probably the best language for integrating anything
and doing DevOps. But I just wanted to show you that.
Give you an idea what you could do with something like
Nifi and all the different things you can connect to
kafka, pulsar,
know Amazon,
azure, google, lots of cool
stuff there. I have example codes out there
in GitHub. So if you go to my GitHub t span,
hw, I've got a ton of stuff out there. One of them is
for reading weather sensor data.
Again, using pulsar part is easy.
Connect into various libraries, create my schema
from the fields, connect to all kinds of stuff there,
build up my connection and my producer get
my sensor data, get some other data like temperatures and
other stuff on that device, format them all, send a
record, print them very easily. Could also do
things like do SQl against these
live events with something like flink. Pretty easy
to set up. We've got examples with the full docker
here. Download those, get going.
I've got other ones for doing different things like grabbing
live thermal images,
sending them up to imager, sending them slack discord email,
and sending all the metadata to Kafka or something that
looks like Kafka. And we could process with Spark or Flink or whatever.
You could also send other data into Kafka. Pretty easy.
Got the breakdown of the hardware here. You want to do that on your own.
You could find yourself a raspberry PI somewhere.
Example apps tend to be Nifi produces into Pulsar.
And then maybe I'll do SQL with Flink. Maybe I'll be
producing data with Python. Lots of different options
here. Lots of examples out there.
Thanks for joining me. If you have any questions,
drop them in the system there or check me
online. You can get me on Twitter, GitHub, any of my
blogs out there. If you search Tim span and anything streaming you will find
me. Thanks a lot.