Welcome everybody to the mega Flask machine.
Welcome to Conf 42 Python site.
I come from the Python user group of Mauritius.
Mauritius which is a small island in the Indian Ocean.
About me I'm a Python developer for my own account
and also a flask on organised member and a
flask community work group member. Flask one is a yearly event
which hosts some nice talk.
We've had a first edition last year and we hope to
have another edition this year. Hands I'm also a shopyo
maintainer. Shopyo which is a web framework. It's actually
a mega machine for Flask. You can see we just
moved from a personal repo to an organization
repo. Along with the documentations. We now host
it on reader docs. And this talk is about version
three nine four. The story begins with web
frameworks. Currently, if you analyze the stack overflow
survey, if you just see the stats for the most popular
web frameworks in the world, and among them Python
ones, you will see that Flask and Django unsurprisingly
come up was the top most popular web
frameworks. And we might analyze like a bit
what drives people to choose web frameworks.
For example, we have Django. So why do people use Django?
What factors do they consider before using Django?
The first one is the ability to get started quick.
It was developed to be used under pressure and people find
it really awesome, really useful to just get
started with Django. You spin websites
really fast and also in
the people take into account a frameworks.
The time development has been
going on, active development, I mean people have been
presenting, there have been releases hands, all these strengthened
project people look at these version number certainly
like some people take it as a hint, but also whether
the package has been adopted by the community,
by companies, whether or not the app is
being used in production. And in that sense we
can say that Django is a pretty much solid choice.
It's pretty old also, and also about the Django ecosystem,
which is strong, you want to build a feature, you know that
there must be a package which already implemented the feature.
You just go and grab the package and use it in your own project and
you're good to go. That's why people choose
Django, because you can customize your projects,
sometimes many times easily. And also it's
scalable. That is you have your app here,
you want to make complex app, you want to make a big app, you just
continue developing. You don't have to find a
better architecture, not in terms of infrastructure,
but in terms of code organization. So you
just focus on developing. And also, since Django
is a widely used package,
it's powering many websites.
So obviously it integrated common security
fixers, common security flaws, it addressed those
flaws. And maybe if you were to start off on your
own, you would have you yourself to address those
issues, to provide the lines to those common
issues. Because these are common issues, they're bound to be recurring
or it's within reach of people to breach.
So Django got you covered up.
It's also because of the wide range of apps available. Like you have
e commerce, you have pretty much everything you have
for manipulating jurispatial data. You have quality packages.
Sometimes among all Python frameworks, you can find
packages for certain fields only in Django,
geospatial, for example. So we can say that
we have a wide range of app for Django. Now comes
to the question, why flask like? You have Django here?
Why do people still go for flask? Like,
is Django not the answer to no?
Obviously people choose flask for a reason. The first is
that it's very easy to pick up flask,
ten lines. You get your flask app running these yourself,
right? And it's awesome. It's amazing. You want
an endpoint to return some text or something like that,
something simple, something basic. Flask is really easy
to pick up, and floss gets out of
your way. You want to program, you want to do something.
So floss is not here to actually prevent
you from doing the way you want to
do. Important for people who have grown big enough
so that the Framework doesn't get you see,
that was is better. So with Flask to
do that, you can actually roll out your style.
It's about doing it and also enjoying your development time.
The flask kind of let you enjoy
the way you want, and also about customization,
much like Django. But Flask also has,
since Flask is a very simple,
a very bare bones framework, you have to customize
it. And for that purpose, you have an awesome collection
of plugins. You have an awesome range of
plugins available for you to customize. These really
make. It's like cooking. You have to find the right ingredients,
in what quantity, in what proportion. You want this in
your app, you want that in your app, you have to
decide on the ingredients of your app.
You can have the perfect meal. In other words,
then let's say that we have flask,
we have Django. But what if we could have both?
What if we could have the power of Django?
The incredible development speed of
Django, the head started of Django
with the flexibility, the customizability of
flask. Like what if you could have both?
That's precisely what Shopyo is. It allows
you to have the organization, the cross sharing
of modules of Django, features found in
Django, like main entry points, commands used by
Django, pretty much everything which
characterizes Django and Django
apps. Well, those and these, you still
retain flask. You retain the flexibility of
flask, you retain the customizing power.
If we can put it like that of flask, what if you could just merge
both? That's what Shopyo is. And conceptually
speaking, what is a Shopyo app?
Well, you can think of a shop you app
as an app which has different modules.
That's how you picture a shop you app in your
mind. And when we say like, why Shopyo?
We were saying we have flask, we have Django. But from the perspective
of a flask developer, why would you want to use Shopyo?
It's because Shopyo has modules. And who says modules?
You can share it between projects.
You have superpowers found in Django. You have
the organization of very, very organized
code base. We even have a concept called boxes which
allows you to organize your apps
up to a higher level so you have a
great level of organization. It's feature packed. Like if
you were to add all the features that Shopview provides
you, it would have taken you a lot of time, lots of trial and
errors, and each time redoing it, it becomes boring. For example,
you have migration. Shopyo provides you with migration,
with the migration mechanism, with assets management,
with modules. And you also have docs,
hands tests included. What I mean by docs and
tests, I don't mean the Django documentation,
the shopping documentation or flux documentation I'm talking about
for your project. I'm not talking about framework documentation, I'm talking
documentation for your project. Like you have a project which
does something and you want to set up some instructions
about a specific part to how to connect to a specific API,
how to do this and that. So you have to write some documentation. And another
great place besides the readme is a proper
doc system. So for example, you have Sphinx.
Shopyo comes with Sphinx loaded by default,
and also tests, tests and test fixtures, things you
need to get started to writing tests.
Everything is set up for you to continue on expanding
and so that you don't forget those two important
aspects of a project. So documentation
and tests are included. The basics of it are included
so that you can continue development. And also Shopyo,
though it provides you with awesome powers.
Shopyo is transparent. It leaves much
power of usage in your hands,
rather than in our hands, in Shopu's hands.
And also whatever is going on is clear.
You can see in the app py how Shopyo accomplishes
this, how it accomplishes that, and you are free
to change it if ever you want. But the
idea is to have something that people can relate
to. Let's say that yes, it gives you all those powers,
but you have to learn, you have to do
something here and there, so it's not kind of worth
it. But Shopview preserves the
simplicity of if you were going bare
bones floss. So what does a shop you project
looks like? As you can see, this is how
you conceptual Shopview app in its full
picture. You have modules, you have boxes. Boxes is a
way to organize modules. You can share modules among projects,
among Shopyo, your projects, or you can share boxes among Shopview
projects. They will work. And then you have fixtures,
some common fixtures for login, logout, et cetera, admin user,
et cetera. It's already included, you can use it. You cannot use it
if you want, it's up to you. But they are included if
you want to go. The Django was, they are included.
You also have the basics of documentations already available.
Shopping also comes with a theming system. Let's say
you have a site, you want to change themes. It was a
way to customize everything with a we can say
whatever and however you want it. You just
need to sit down and take the time to really
write your theme and then you can use it. And it even
has an admin panel whereby you can change
the themes. It has module related utilities,
migration, set management. So these are some utilities present.
You have utilities sections, tests and docs
and tests. You have themes, you have mail that
yes, it comes integrated with mail.
You have secrets management, you have config profiles, you have
of course the application factory. I mean a shop.
Your project is an advanced flosk app from the
beginning. You want to have a super advanced Flask
app. So feel free to use Shopyo. You get it for free
from day one. And if you don't like some pictorial
representation of what a project looks like,
you certainly have this representation
here which you can pose, you can see, you can go
more into depth to see exactly what
these shop you app looks like. Lines, that's vanilla,
that's without anything. You just have those.
And then as to a module focusing on a module,
well, a module actually makes up of different parts.
And unsurprisingly like Django,
you can relate. If you've used Django, you have a static folder,
your templates folder, your tests folder that's included
by default by Shopyo. When you create a new module,
then view models, forms upload upload is for dbcding
and info. JSON is about more information, gives more
information on the module. As you can see you can get pretty much
organised codes hands among that. Your static folder
is optional, even the view file is
optional. You can have an endpoint or you can
use a package solely for the purpose
of organization. You don't need to have an endpoint associated.
And then as for the commands you have run debug, you have run server.
Much like there is a subtle difference,
but you get it, you won't even know
whether it was Shopyo or not. And then
you have basically collect static just like
Django. Those are some commands supported by Shopyo.
But most importantly here you can
see how you start Shopyo, your new for example blog. Then you
see the inside two directories to finally
arrive at your focus starting point I
can say of the app. So try it, drop your project
name. So that's it. Those are some commands that
we support. Initialize basically instantiates
the DB and collect static,
collects your assets and then in your code you can use
get asset so that your code remains
the same for development and production. You also have
migrate commands which you can use. And then one
question which always nearly comes out
when I do presentations of Shopyo is
why not use Django? You have all the mechanisms of Django,
you have everything here. Why use Shopview?
Like why a new framework that is built on
top of flask? Well dancer is because flask because of the spirit
of flosk, because of the floss ecosystem, because of for
example sqlalchemy. That's why you
would want to stick with flask. But at the same time as
a flask user, you want to get more powers. That's where
Shopview comes in. The other questions that people
ask silently inside them themselves, whether or not
the packages is reliable, we are happy to say that we don't maintain middlewares,
we use flask login for login we use Flask admin, migrate,
WTF, WTF, Sqlalchemy, emailman. These are
popular, reliable, solid packages
which have been going strong for years.
Since we don't maintain our middle west, there are less
chance of doing something really damaging to
a project. But at least our tech stack is quite interesting,
stable and we've reached the
end of the slides, hands the end of the presentation.
And I can say that maybe one point which I did not
touch, it's about what's the big deal about going flask
bare boots. This project looks intimidating
to get started with. It's like you have all these
files just to get started with. Well, to tackle
this one first, we'll say that shopyo these is not for every
project. You need to know when it will benefit you, when it
will be great, when it makes sense to use it.
If you want something maybe very simple,
maybe this is not the project. But even
if someone wants to use it in every case, so he can.
But you really need to know when
to use it, whether it will benefit me. What are the advantages?
You can compare it to Django to get an idea.
I think we can finish.