Hello everyone. In this video we're going to see
this open source project that we built, Kubernetes Bootstrapper,
an extendable framework to set up production grade kubernetes
cluster. Before we head into the project,
we'll just give you an overview of what
is a production ready kubernetes stack. As you can see, I really like
this for graphic from Cloudnative where
in the center you have Kubernetes which is basically a framework,
but you need all the other facets such
as infrastructure, security,
authentication, observability releases and deployments
and development on a really high level. These are the
facets that are needed to set
up a production ready kubernetes cluster.
But is it easy? If you look at the cloud native landscape,
you really can't fit the whole landscape into a single
page. There are so many applications and tools
that are popping up in the cloud native world these days,
so it can be quite daunting for engineers and organizations
to pick and choose the right tool and to put everything together
so that they work together as an integrated package
in order to solve this problem. And that was like problem statement
that we wanted to address with this open source framework that
we're working on is how do people
can quickly set up and
integrate all these applications so that they can get day two operations
ready, right? That's the birth of the Kubernetes bootstrapper.
We've leveraged tools such as Terraform
and Argo CD. For those of you who aren't aware
of Terraform and Argo CD, Terraform is an open source
infrastructure as code software that enables you to safely
and predictably create, change and improve
the infrastructure. Argo CD, on the other hand,
is a Gitops continuous delivery tool for Kubernetes.
It allows developers to declaratively manage the
desired state of their Kubernetes applications and automatically
synchronize that state with the actual state of the
cluster. Terraform and Argo CD can help
improve the development and deployment process for Kubernetes
application by automating and standardizing the management
of infrastructure and application resources,
respectively. The bootstrapper project combines
terraform and Argo CD to build an infrastructure automation
and application delivery platform for Kubernetes.
This project integrates popular open source applications.
As you can see here, we have battle tested open
source apps that have been integrated into this project.
Being a flexible and extendable framework,
it is really easy to add or disable
applications into it. We've leveraged Argocd's app
of app pattern to build this framework.
So are you all excited? Let's head straight to the
GitHub repository where I'm going to walk you through the repository,
the workflow, and then we're going to get our hands dirty
and spin up this bad boy. You can
head to GitHub under Kubernetes KDEs
bootstrapper. That's the project. So we expect minimum
knowledge on Kubernetes and also familiarize
yourself with tools such as terraform, because we're going to use terraform to spin
up the infrastructure and then use Argo CD to spin up
other components. Here's the overview of the repository.
We have an Argo CD directory. We're going to keep the configurations of
Argo CD that's optional. And you have the bootstrap directory
where all the templates required. The bootstrap
resources, which we'll go in detail, are stored docs
directory for documents and other images and assets.
The infrastructure directory where you have all the terraform modules to
spin up your infrastructure on digitalocean. And you have the
observability directory where we're going to use an open
source tool called robusta to set up our observability
stack. It's going to be like a three step process.
First the infra and
then bootstrap process, and then set up the
observability stack. This is the end architecture
that we aim to achieve. So let's head straight
into our infrastructure directory terraform.
And here you have all the terraform modules
and all the instructions that you can copy,
paste and modify a bit to set
up this infrastructure. So what we're going to do now,
we'll head to visual studio code where I've checked out this repository
and we're going to perform the terraform commands, spin up this
infrastructure, and then we'll come back to go ahead with the
bootstrapper process and to set up the observability stack.
So let's head to our vs code. So you have the infrastructure
directory and you have terraform.
Click readme and give it a preview.
All right, I'm inside it. I'll just make sure I'm up
to date. I'm right now going to head into
infrastructure terraform.
Okay, I'm going to perform terraform in
it. I'm just going to follow along the guide.
Awesome. So the bootstrapper TFRS
sample file. Let's open that first.
So it's the variables
file here where we've defined the configurations
of our infrastructure. You can change it and modify
it however you deem fit. I have my own configurations
here. Take a copy of this file, modify changes
if need be, and then you're going to plan and then apply. Let's go back
here. I already have the bootstrap TFRS
file with me, so I'm just going to go ahead and copy this command.
All right. Terraform throws
out the entire plan for me. Pretty much what we saw in the figure.
It's going to spin up a Kubernetes cluster, it's going to spin up a digitalocean
container registry and then it's going to automatically
install Argo CD as we saw
here. Okay, I'm just going
to go ahead and apply this,
copy the command paste.
It takes some time to set up your infrastructure.
Once it's successfully done, you will have your cluster id
in the terminal. So you could just update your kubecontext
so that we can start accessing and observing our Kubernetes
cluster. I'm using to
go ahead and copy the cluster id. Going to paste it.
Updated my kubecontext.
So if I open canines, I should
be seeing the Kubernetes cluster. Yes.
Which has Argo CD installed.
Awesome. So right now our infrastructure
is ready and Argo CD has been installed successfully.
Let's check out our next steps.
All right, we are heading into the bootstrapper
territory. The bootstrap process is not
something new. It's been there. You could
check out the documentation on how Argo
CD suggests. So it's called cluster bootstrapping.
So basically what this means is there
is a parent app. In our case it's going to be the bootstrap
and then you declare all the dependent child
apps beneath it, which we will see
right now. So what this means is Argo.
And we ask Argo to go ahead and install the parent
app. And once the parent app is installed, it goes
ahead and starts installing all the child apps.
The app of apps pattern can be structured
in several ways and we've used helm to
do so. That's why you see the helm structure in the repositories
here as like any helm chart, right?
We have a values file and in this values file,
yaml, we set some flags that makes it easy
for us to enable or disable the apps that we
want. We have logging, we have observability.
There is traffic, traffic is can controller and
trivi is a security operator. So we
can extendable or disable them here. And then if you
enable them, arco picks it up and installs it.
If you've disabled it, of course it won't. What you need to
understand is there is
a strict Gitops workflow here. What this means is ArcoCd
that's installed in our Kubernetes cluster, right, is constantly looking at
this repository, at the configurations, at the flags.
If you want to make a change, if you want to extendable
or disable the apps, you set the values in the file
and you push the code to git to
your branch that argo CD is looking into.
Otherwise you will
not have the end state reflected because
you want to have all the configurations as code stored in
Git. There are huge benefits for it. I don't want
to go into details, but it's great for auditing.
You have a clean track of who's committed what,
and git being your source of truth.
So whatever is in git is going to be synchronized with your cluster.
So any changes you make to the values file, make sure or
any file in this repository when you check out,
make sure you push the changes to git so
that Argo can do its magic. So I'm
going to copy this and I'm assuming you have all
the command line tools and clients installed
that's needed. I'm going to go ahead and.
All right, while it's getting installed, let's log into
the argo CD UI and see what's happening. Since we installed Argo,
Argo generates a default password. You can change it,
let's grab it and then let's run
this command. I'm just basically port forwarding it
so that we can access it in localhost. There is
also a section on how to configure it so that you can access
Argo CdyR domain. Feel free to check that out
as well. Open Argo here's
your Argo UI.
The default username is admin and
we just generated got the password from the command.
So this is the Argo UI. And here if you see you
have the parent bootstrap project. So I'm clicking this and
then the bootstrap project goes ahead and installs an
application called Bootstrap Resources, which is going to be your ingress resource,
your certificates, and you have your cert manager,
it's installed. You have your metrics server, you have
traffic as your ingress controller, and you have trivia operator
as your runtime security operator. So you can see that the
sync is okay, everything seems healthy.
And all these components are
now installed, which means if we head back to the git
repository, right, let's head back to the bootstrapper
project.
All these apps here as you see, cert manager
traffic, let's encrypt and your trivia
runtime security app. All that's remaining now is
to install our observability stack.
So hope everything is clear. Up till now infrastructure
automation done through terraform and then the bootstrapping
process was done via CD.
Now we're going to install our observability stack into
Kubernetes. And now let's head to our observability stack setup
using robusta robusta is an open source Kubernetes monitoring
automation platform and it comes pre baked with Prometheus
stack. You also have Grafana dashboards
and it also has seamless integration with slack.
So if anything goes wrong in your Kubernetes cluster,
you get slack notifications. A huge shout out
to these folks at Robusta. You need to set
some things up in order to access the platform.
Let's go ahead and do that.
I'm going to head back to vs code and then we're going to do it
from there. We're going to observe multistag
readme.
Right? Let's open a new session.
You need to generate a configuration file once you've
installed the robusta client. It's as simple as
just type in robusta gen config and it takes you
through an interactive session.
So let's do that.
Let's say yes to slack integration.
Add to slack,
you can configure your slack channels. I'm going to give allow
and let's head back to our terminal. As it
says, let's do observability no
yes, asking me whether I want
to install the cube prompt stack and I'm going to go ahead and say
yes here. So now that's done, let's copy
commands and update it. As you can see, it's now generated
files called generated underscore values Yaml. So we're
going to use that to install robusta.
So let's do set cluster name
equal to our cluster name. And while
it's installing, let's head to our
canines and see what's going on there.
Okay, there are pods running.
You have like cert manager and all other components installed.
You have traffic, you have the trivia operator running,
and if you check the charts it might take a while
to so Argo CD chart has been installed
and once I think robust has successfully installed,
we'll see that in a minute. All right,
as you can see, now that robusta is going
ahead and installing Grafana, the Kuberom
stack, Kuberom operator. So everything is being installed in
the background. Once it's successfully installed, we'll be
able to log in to a web UI
where we can access the metrics of our Kubernetes
cluster. So let's wait for that. Looks like
robusta helm chart has been successfully deployed.
We should be able to head to.
So you have all our services here
and we could monitor them. This is pretty neat. I'll leave it
to you folks to explore robusta. So what's now
happened is we have set up the observability stack onto
our Kubernetes cluster. So this is the third step in our process.
We also have the Grafana dashboards that can be
accessed pretty much. So if I go into services,
right, and should have let
me expose it and access it now,
Fana, that would be default? Would be, I think,
admin and. Awesome.
So you have some dashboard. So let's just click one of
them. Look into August CD default.
Yeah. Cool. So if we
head back to our project,
right? Yeah, I have my observability slack
channel here. Yes. So it's
configured. So if there's some warning or alerts,
I'll receive the message here in
this slack channel. Pretty neat. Let's head back
to our project.
Okay, so as you can see, we've done
the infrastructure automation, we've done the bootstrapping using Argo,
and we've set up the observability stack using robusta.
This is the end state of our architecture, so you
can see how it's really simple and straightforward
to set up such can infrastructure, along with
all the applications and configurations neatly packaged.
So try out the bootstrapper, let us know what you think. If you have any
questions, feel free to reach out to me on socials.
I'm Diab and yeah, thanks. I hope
you enjoyed it and we look forward to hearing your feedback.
Do try it out. Give us a star, check it out.
If you have some suggestions on adding different apps
to it, let us know know. Thank you
very much.