You. Hey, everyone. Today I am
talking about why are people developing inside containers
and how GitHub code spaces takes containerization to
the next level. Now, I have a bit of
a confession. It's that in 2018,
about five years ago, when I started my software engineers career,
I had no clue what containers were like. I received a list
of install instructions on my first day. It was talking
about install Docker and do this with containers and kubernetes.
And I was like, what are containers? I don't really
understand or why people are developing inside containers.
But I was like, fake it till you make it. Fake it till
you make it. Doesn't matter. But then I went
back to it, and I was like, you know what? It does matter. I want
to know why. So the first half of this talk is to
kind of explain that for folks who
might have related with me. And then the second half of this talk is to
talk about GitHub code spaces. So let's get into it. The way I
like to illustrate what container's purpose
and usage is for is this line.
It works on my machine. So either you found yourself
saying that before, or you've heard somebody say that,
and if not, it's soon to come.
And you might be like, why would somebody say it works on my machine?
So when you start coding at a
company or for an open source project or whatever, maybe your configurations
are sometimes a little bit different. So sometimes
when you fix a bug or add a new feature, and then you push
it up to production or staging, or you share it with a coworker
or teammate, they're like, it's not working for me. It's not working
here. It's broken. And that is because you might have slightly
different containerization settings or environment variables, or something's
just a little bit different, which is causing your
feature or your bug to not be reflected in the same way as
it was on your local machine. So then it makes you say,
wait, but it works on my computer. It works on my machine. Like, I swear.
Yeah. So that's kind of
why containers were created. Or part of it, right? Is to
stabilize or create some consistent within
environments. And what
is a container? Right. So, according to Docker,
a container is a standard unit of software that packages
up code and all its dependencies so applications
can run quickly and reliably from one computing environment
to another. And what is
Docker? Docker is an open source
platform or product that was founded in March 2013
by Solomon Hykes. And when
people think of containers, they immediately go to Docker but
Docker didn't create containers or the idea of containers.
It only popularized the use of containers because
Docker made it so much easier. It's more of like a suite
of different management tools for containers.
And it made it way easier for developers to be able to
containerize or package up all their software and
ship it. So just
reiterating the users of containers and why they exist.
So containers enable software engineers to program in
a consistent environment. So for example, your dev environment
may mirror, or will now mirror your production environment with
the same operating system configurations and dependencies.
And this will enable all bugs and features that
behave the same across all environments.
So now you don't have to say it works on my machine, it works
on everybody's now. So let's go back in time. Little history
lesson of the origination or how containers
were created. So we start in 1979
with this command called Shrut. I think
some people pronounce it differently, but your girl says Shrut.
But basically this command allowed you to change the root directory
for any given process. And the benefit here is that
it gave you an isolated environment for build processes and
dependencies. Then in 2000 came freebsd
jails. And these were pretty similar where they allowed developers
to isolate and test updates and changes
without jeopardizing the integrity of the system. The cool
thing is these came with some designated IP addresses.
Then in 2006, Google created this thing called process containers,
which have now been renamed to control groups,
aka c groups. And basically this isolated resource
usage of like hours, cpu, memory, disk, I o and
network. Basically this is just giving developers a chance
to be like, hey, here's this container
or area where this resource is.
And I want to test and debug and figure out what's going on
without touching the rest of the system. And then comes
in Docker. So I kind of skipped a lot, but there were other implementations
of different type of container management and containers.
But Docker came in in 2013 and this
was way easier to use and people were like,
okay, I can dig it. And introduced a suite of
management and packaging tools for containerization.
Essentially all of this is to say, this has been
a pursuit of figuring out how we can run software
reliably from one environment to another.
And I think code spaces takes containerization
to the next level. And we're going to talk about how right after
I introduce myself a little bit more, I like to introduce myself,
you're like, who is this person that's talking? Who's this amazing
person? So my name is Rizel Scarlett. I'm a junior developer
advocate at GitHub. Before that I was a software engineer for about
three years. I'm an advisor, and I was a director at
an organization called Code, which introduces women of color
and non binary people of color to web development for free.
I'm also pretty passionate, or some might say
addicted to social media. So if you are also on
the interwebs, you can go ahead and follow me at black girl Hykes
on Twitter, mastodon, Instagram dev two hash node,
literally anything you could think of except on Twitch. I am black girl hykes.
One because I forgot my password and got myself locked
out of my account. All right, let's jump back
into it. So we're going to talk about what is GitHub codespaces and how it
takes development to the next level, how it's taking containerization
to the next level. First of all, what is it,
right, essentially to not even make it complicated.
It's just an ide in your browser.
So whether that's vs. Code, jetbrains,
Jupyterlab, you can get that in your browser.
And I hope y'all like my meme of Tyra Banks saying vs.
Code, but make it fashion. All right, so why would
this be helpful to you? Like vs. Code in your browser?
So when you work in a code space, the environment you're working in
is created using a development container, and that development container
is hosted on a virtual machine. So this is allowing
you to code in a container that's hosted on
the cloud, as everyone says.
And what is the cloud? Right? If you're like, what is this cloud thing?
It's just can environment that doesn't reside on your computer,
but rather on the Internet. It's not with you,
that server, that environment is not with you. It's in the cloud.
Okay, so I do want to specify
like codespaces is not the GitHub web editor. I've called
to a couple people and they've thought it's the GitHub
web editor. So the GitHub web editor is when you go
to a repository and then you press the period button and
it opens up a web editor like view
for you. And this just allows you to edit your
files, right? But you can't, like if you just had a formatting problem
or something and you wanted to quickly edit your files
without ruining the spacing for Yaml, because we
know Yaml is a little picky or any other thing,
right? We don't want prettier to yell at us and we want to edit the
code without opening up our editor and
cloning things and doing all that, you just go into the
GitHub web editor and edit it and then commit
it. But it has no terminal. You can't
run the code. You can't really do much. That is the GitHub web editor
as opposed to GitHub code spaces. It has a terminal,
you can run your code there, you can
set up what machine type you're using,
right? You can use GPU, you can use a whole bunch of different
things on GitHub code spaces.
And GitHub code spaces is not necessarily free.
So you do get 60 hours of free usage
per month. So that's a good amount. But GitHub web editor
is free forever for all time.
All right, so the benefits of GitHub code spaces,
why would you want to code in a
development container that's hosted on the cloud and now you're
in your browser? Well, you get faster,
right? Or you can automate the onboarding process
for folks. If you've ever joined a new job, they give
you this document of like, here's all the steps you got
to do to be able to code in this code base. And it can take
forever, like a day to a week. And with
this, your manager or coworker or whatever can
set up all the environment variables.
You'll need all the dependencies all in one go.
And then when you start your new job, you can open it up and be
like, wow, I can commit code day one. I don't need to do the
setup stuff. It allows you to code from anywhere
as well. Because it's browser based. You don't have to download your
repo or clone your repo onto your local machine and
then start installing things again because you have that automated configuration
file that's setting everything up for you. It's all in there,
believe me. I've coded in codespaces
on a plane, on my iPad.
So wherever you have Internet access, and if you have access to that repository,
you can open that bad boy up. And then because it's using
containers again, you don't have that problem
of it works on my machine because it's bringing that uniformity to
your developers environments. All right,
so let's talk about how codespaces can be used for onboarding
new employees. So codespaces
users this concept called configuration as
code and what that is is basically config files
dictating how your app should run on the
given environment, whether it's a platform or hardware operating
system, whatever your config files are saying, this is what
should happen. This is what I'm expecting. This is
the environment that I'm in.
And the benefit of this right to have config
files as code is now you can manage them in your repository
with version control. And this allows you to do things like
have them all in a centralized location, have CI CD run
on them, and be able to trace bugs. I'll go on to a little bit
more on this slide. Right, so centralization, you have one single source
of truth for your config files. They're all
in one place. You're not searching everywhere for them because they're in your repository.
You can run like CI CD stuff on them. So if you
want to check out linting or testing or do some
security scanning on them, you can do that all in one go with hours code
and your config files. And then also if you make a mistake,
maybe there's an extra space or a random comma.
You can look back through your commits, your version control,
and be like, oh, that's what changed. I accidentally added a comma.
All right, so let's talk about how we can set this up
for newcomers, right? So you have this thing called
a dev container JSOn. It is responsible for
automatically installing things like extensions, environment variables,
install commands, build commands, your docker
file, post forwarding and post creation commands,
or specifying
your Docker file. So here in this example, right,
this is one for node js. We're saying we're using this Docker file.
We're going to use code JS 16. And here's all the
extensions I want installed automatically. I want es lint, I want prettier,
and I want live share. I could specify the forwarding ports. Like I could
say I want it to run on 3000 when it's open and when
it opens up, when that code space opens up, I want it to run yarn
install da da da da da. Cool stuff,
right? And then we have our Docker file, right?
Docker files are used to automate the installation and containerization
of a container, so it contains a list of commands that the
Docker client calls while creating an image. For this, all I
needed to write was node 16 bullseye, because that's all I
needed. That's all I wanted. It's just node 16, right?
And then we have the Docker compose YaMl file. This is probably
one that's less users, but it is useful if you want to run
multiple containers. So let's say you want to run a database
and a web server in a code space. That's what the Docker
compose yaml file is for,
and you can use it for that. So if we look at
this file right here, we see them setting up the postgres database
and saying even what port they wanted on and putting in all those variables.
So you got it? All right,
let's talk about one use case that I thought of
for code spaces, which is using it if you were a coding
instructor. I don't think many people have thought of this,
but for me, as someone who's taught people to code either
online or in person, for coding workshops or boot
camps, I've been like, yo, code spaces would be so cool for this.
So here is, let me pause this really quickly
and give some consistent here I have a,
I started from the beginning. Give me a
quick second,
give me a quick second. All right,
we were here, so I don't want it to press play, but essentially
pause. What has happened here is I set up
a code space, and this code space, this is for someone teaching
them front end like HTML, CSS and JavaScript if they've never done
it too much before. And what I have is when they open
it up, they get a view of the browser. This gives them a
cloud that I but part of the clock. But I have some
missing pieces here. And essentially one
half is the browser or the preview of the browser,
and then the other half is splitting up their HTML,
CSS and Javascript files for them so they can see it clearly.
And then I have these little prompts created by
an extension, a GitHub extension called code tour. So once they
open it up, they get all of this and the prompt tells them hey,
there's a question mark here. Can you update the h one value
to change it to six? And it does all these things so they can get
a little bit comfortable moving around or navigating
these different files from an HTML file to CSS file
to a JavaScript file. So I'm going to press play so you can see the
experience. So here I'm changing
that question mark to six, and then I say,
oh cool, let's change the color. Let's change
the color. So they're looking at the CSS and the linear gradient and
maybe they want to change it to red. Okay, cool.
And there's one thing that's pretty weird. The hour
hand and the second hand are moving really fast.
So I ask them to update one of the
lines and I say change the seconds to hour.
Yes, cool. So now
that it's updated, the hour hand is going to move on
the hour and the second hand is going to move on
the second and then it says mission complete. So all
the stuff I users here is essentially I'll show you.
First I set up a dev container JSon so that
when they opened it up and all I had in there was just these
extensions, nothing else, because I didn't need anything else.
There's no backend or anything here. Just when they open up this code space,
I wanted it to immediately install eslint for them.
Prettier vs live share an extension I made called deploy
to GitHub pages so that they can deploy this afterwards.
The same vs code theme I had code swing,
code hours, and code spell checker. This helped
me immensely because I find what happens, especially in
a remote environment, is sometimes people get lost,
and especially if there's multiple people and I can't
see that they're lost because I'm not in the same place as them. So having
the code tour extension helps them to stay on track and get guided,
even when they're not too sure what to do. And then
having them have the same theme as me and stuff like that. So they're
not like oh excuse me instructor, why is mine highlighted as
blue but yours is highlighted as pink? Everything the same across
the board for them, same environment, so that it doesn't allow them
to be confused. Then there's can extension called
codeswing. So what I added in there is a file called codeswing
JSon to kind of show the layout of how
I wanted things to go. So I wanted the files, the index
HTML, the CSS and the Javascript to be split on the right,
and then you would see the browser on the left hand side.
Then we had the code tour and this is that extension
that gives you a tour of the code base. I used it to kind of
guide them through stuff. So I have different steps here and
I specify which line and which file and what I
want the code tour to say and they can press next when they've
completed it. I thought that was pretty fun.
Then there's also, I also think code spaces is useful
for those who like experimenting with different programming
languages. There's some people that as soon as a new framework,
Javascript framework comes out, people want to try it out, and I
don't get them wrong, I'm like, it's totally fine. So there
is this idea in code space, or this concept in code space is
called templates. So I'm going to go ahead and
navigate over there. So here
we have GitHub.com codespaces
templates and you have multiple templates. You can either open
up a blank template, a ruby on rails template, a react
Jupyter express, and nextjs and
much more. So we're going to open up the nextjs one.
While this is opening up, I'm going to clear my throat.
And now you all are seeing the login for GitHub.
All righty. And I might zoom in here just a smidge.
So it might take a little bit of time. I pressed reset
right after it did it. It's going to take a little bit of time to
install all the things needed. So it has a couple of extensions
and it should open up a browser view for me.
I'm going to let it do its thing, but we can watch it
happen. Pretty cool that. Here's the browser opening
up on the left hand side for me.
So we can see that in
the browser we have a file that says fast refresh
demo and essentially it has a component with state.
So if I click it, the clicks keep counting.
It can throw an error for me too. Document body is
not a function. So I can go ahead now that everything is essentially
set up and I can find that.
Let me put it on this side so we'll be able to see it.
I can find that index js file and I can say
maybe I want, for whatever reason, the count to increment by
two. So if I save that, it'll automatically change to that.
I think it's
okay.
I decided to go off script and do that. Don't worry.
Let's go back to actually what was on my script. My script was
to actually go ahead and change the file
here. So instead of changing the count,
I expected it to go up by two. That's all right.
What I'm going to do instead. I might not have paid attention to what
the incremental values are. Perhaps this was
for this part and not for this. That's all right.
So I can essentially go ahead and just change
like this. Instead of it saying fast refresh demo, I can
say code spaces takes containerization and
I'll move these files. We don't need this folder so big to
the next level and we can see this automatically
changing. Right? You get that view right there. And this gives you a chance
to be huh? How does next JS work? Let me play around
with some of the features here. It's already set
up for you, or if you already know, next JS, but you just
want to create a quick demo app instead of going through NPM
install or yarn install or whatever for next JS. Here you have
this playground that you can play around in and you can actually
go ahead and just commit it to your repository.
And I think that part of it's so fun. All right, let's go back.
Oh man. All right, now here's
the other thing. I think it's great. If you're prayer programming
similar to Ngrok, you can do port
forwarding here. So if we go to the dev container
JSon, I'm hoping it's going to tell us that it's forwarded. Yes,
forwarded to port 3000 or this is the forward port,
right? And then it forwards it to this
long address that says black girl bytes,
verbospace invention and all these random numbers. So normally
the convention, the naming convention is like the owner's name,
a random word that it's generated, and then a
couple of random numbers, the port number, and then preview
app GitHub dev. Now this is
something that if I click this and I've opened it in my browser,
I can see the same thing, right? Instead of just
seeing it within code spaces, or if I wanted
to share it with someone and prove to them that yes, it does work
on my machine. While we're coding together in live share
on GitHub code spaces, I can change the visibility and
I can say I want this to be public in general or
just public to my containerization. So like anybody who's
part of my organization could be able to see this. So if I but public,
and let's say I copied this copy and
I'm going to open this, but I'm not sure if it
would change anything for you all. But if I was to share this
with somebody, I'll open it in a different browser, they would still be
able to see it as well. It doesn't too much really
show that for you because I'm on the same computer,
but you can change that port visibility.
And it's one of the things that I think is pretty cool on GitHub
codespaces. But wait, there's more.
So after we talk about port forwarding,
you can also manage code spaces from the command line,
which I think is pretty fun, pretty awesome if
you are a command line geek here. In this example,
I show that you can type Gh codespaces list and
see a list of all your GitHub code spaces. You can also create
a GitHub code space from here. So what I'm going to do
in the next slide here is. So I created a GitHub code space by
saying GitHub gh codespaces create that flag
r. Then the owner of this, so I have an organization
called galaxy bytes, and then the repo name, which is pink
moon, and I want it to be the code space to be created
on my main branch. So I'm going to go ahead and do that. I create
it and I choose the machine type. So I want two cores and
I'm going to go ahead and refresh it, and I want it to show up
here. So it did show up. I'm just going to pause
it. It showed up right here. So before we had only one code space
under galaxy bytes, and now we have two. And the second one is
called upgraded potato, and it does come up with these random names that
are hard to remember. So I thought, could you rename
the space to something you can remember? And in fact you can.
So if you do gh code space edit,
and then you put in the old code space name and
put the display name, you can be able to change it.
Now, this won't change the permanent name. This is more like
an aka or a name that you'll be able to remember.
It'll still be called black girl bites upgraded potato. But when
you see it, when you're identifying it, you'll see the name that
you change it to. So I'm going to go ahead and paste in the original
name, the permanent name. I'm going to paste it,
and then in display name, I'm going to call it memorable name.
So for me, when I see it, I'll see
the memorable name, but behind the scenes, it'll still be called that
really long name. So once I refresh it, I should see it say memorable name
rather than upgraded potato.
And you can also delete GitHub code spaces.
So again, because this is the permanent name,
I need to still use that name it gave it. So what
I did is I copied and pasted the name, and I put Gh
codespaces, delete flag c
right before it pasted the name. And once I refresh
my page, I should see that the code space doesn't exist.
And last but not least, GitHub code spaces
is. This is the exciting part. I hope y'all didn't
leave yet. GitHub codespaces allows you to do
stuff for data science, machine learning, and AI. So what
we're going to do next is we're going to use GitHub code spaces to generate
some AI art with stable diffusion,
like so cool. All right, so I
have some gifs here. So that way I'm not doing it live because
the demo gods are never with me. So I was able to generate
this cartoon black girl. So I put in this prompt in GitHub quotespaces
that says a cartoon black girl with cotton candy here and a pink
dress standing in front of a pink sky with cotton candy clouds.
And it gave me this kind of scary looking, to be honest.
And then I did another prompt that says a polar bear looking at
the northern lights, and it gave me this. So let's
see how we can make that happen. First off, you need to
make a GPU powered code space, and you would
do that when you open your code space, you got to open it with
options and you'll choose six core, one GPU
rather than two core, four core. This is in
limited beta right now, like this option. So you will have to
request availability to gpus
or to having a GPU powered code space. Then you
want to sign up for a hugging face account and generate an API
token. Once you have that API token,
each of your repositories have codespaces secrets.
So inside of your codespaces secret, you want to
store your hugging face token and you want to name
it hugging face token because that's what it's looking for.
And once you do that, you can open up a Jupyter notebook
and you're going to run each of these lines. I did
fork a repo that I can show you all at
the end that you can fork from me as well,
so that you don't have to do all this from scratch.
So here at each cell you want to press run to
make sure everything works. So first we're going to install the needed
files for this. So we're installing it or needed dependencies,
and this is literally how long it takes, but I think it's interesting to just
see it. So like on the left side we have these
Jupyter notebooks and we have the dev container and all that going
on. Then we want to go ahead and run this line that
ran pretty quickly. We'll run another line that's
setting up everything for us.
So running, running. And I
think while this is happening we
can just look
at it.
So next is going to be the prompt. So we
can see here we're importing autocast from Torch, and this
is where you'll update the prompt to something you want. So I put a boy
hitting a baseball with a baseball bat. I'm going to go ahead
and run it, and hopefully it's not something super terrifying.
I'll run it right after these are done downloading and
done running this stuff. Come on. Cloud faces
should be done pretty soon. I could have fast forwarded this,
but, you know, it's good to see the real time stuff. So we
already had that cotton can here, one from before. So I'm going to
go ahead and run this.
And even it's specifying the height and width of
the image, and it's probably returning an array of different images and
showing us the first one as we can see here with images.
And then it has the zero if element in the array.
So we're getting there. We're halfway there.
Halfway there. All right.
And it generated a really scary looking image.
It tried, but we're used to stable diffusion doing that.
So I'm going to go ahead and show you all the repo that
I used for this and let
us see. So it should be
called do.
Okay, this is it. So if you all wanted to go to it, it is
GitHub.com galaxyblights stable
diffusion. You can go ahead and fork this repo.
I forked it from my manager, who forked it
from the code spaces product manager,
who forked it from somebody else. So you can keep forking it you all
until just to mess around. And you can create your own
if you wanted to. But remember, this has to work with a hugging face
API token, and you have to have access to
Codespace's GPU, and you can request that because
it right now is in limited beta access.
Let's go back. We're almost done. Like, I showed you all the cool
stuff from GitHub codespaces. So I just want to do
a real quick recap. With containers, you can
standardize your development environments, and with GitHub
codespaces, you can streamline onboarding, you can code from answers,
you can have standardized environments, you can use templates
if you wanted to experiment with a framework
or build a quick demo, and you want to skip
all the boilerplate, you can share your forwarded ports with folks,
and you can perform data science and machine learning tasks
such as generating art,
AI art with stable diffusion. It's really fun to
use GitHub code spaces. Thank you. Thank you so much
for tuning in. Thank you to the
Conf 42 DevOps 2023 and
everyone involved for allowing me to speak or inviting me to
speak. This was so much fun. Please hit me up if you have any questions.
My handle is at black girl bites. Thank you.
Bye.