Imagine in this, it's Monday, the last
print of a project, and you just had a
planning, and you agreed with your team
that the things to do are to fix
two bugs, and you need to finish writing
the good documentation. You feel good. It's Monday,
but it's good Monday. What you agreed on is achievable,
and you're excited for the release.
You're also excited for what comes next. So you
feel good, you feel motivated.
Let's do it on Tuesday.
Engineering manager comes in the room, and she says,
look, it will be great if we can this
through the security. Just before the release.
Have you ever been in this situation? Do you know
this pain? Well, you go to the meeting,
and security team asks you so many
questions. They ask about the documentation
that hasn't been finished yet. And after
the meeting, you end up with this.
Forget about those two bugs. It's a
whole bunch of bugs. And trust me, I also
don't understand what a snail is doing up there.
I've been in this situation way too many times.
And each time, we would have this beautiful
meeting called project, project retrospective,
and we would all agree in the team that,
well, having a security review in the last
sprint just before the release is
too stressful. It's just a horrible idea.
And as much as we would all agree and nod
our heads, the moment we close the door, we would
forget about it, and the situation would hunt us
down with every new project.
My name is Victoria Dalach. You can find me
in the Internet. I've been working tech for
over a decade, mostly as a backend engineer.
But two years ago, I transitioned
to the security team in my company,
and it has been an amazing experience
because I could see the
same organization from completely
different angles. So when I
would go to a meeting with engineers
as an engineer, I would be like, oh, these are my peers. Like,
we share the struggle, we share the problems. We support each other.
But when I went to
another meeting as a security engineer,
all of a sudden, I was a
stakeholder. I was a person who wanted something.
I was a person who had
questions. I used to have questions as can engineer,
but you know what I mean. I would be the one who was blocking
stuff. What?
So I notice quite
a few problems with security, and I
will share something, a piece of security theory
that will completely transform the way you approach security.
Okay, are you ready? Let's go. So,
the problem with security is that,
first of all, there are many problems with security. Let's agree on
that. I will not cover all of them, but in product teams.
The problem I see is that product people, so product designers,
managers, owners, think about
security solely as an engineering problem.
And engineers are so focused on scoping
things right, making it achievable,
defining mvp, that they
label security features as nice
to have and put on a shelf with
other nice to have initiatives. And the problem is
that those features are hardly ever worked
on. But there is
another layer to that. Security is
a huge topic. I like to think about security as
an ocean. So when
I ask you, what do you think security
is? Or how do you know
if your product is secure?
How would you reply?
You can make it an experiment and ask your
peers, fellow engineers,
how do you know your product is secure?
And you will get different answers
from all the people. Security is
a huge topic. There is application security,
cloud security, infrastructure security. It security.
When we think about application security,
only they have vulnerabilities, risk factors,
threats, so many of them,
it's overwhelming. And the lingo.
Oh, my gosh. The lingo security people
use is difficult to understand.
So, before I joined security team, I had
thought that we as developers, have weird
way of talking because we use a lot of different
weird words. But when I joined security,
the first six months, I would Google acronyms
for, like, at least three to ten acronyms
a day. So there are many
layers where security is just overwhelming.
But I bring you
hope, because I
have something very exciting to share.
We can all agree security.
We can all agree that there
is an infinite amount of threats.
Can of threats, you may say.
We cannot identify
all the attack vectors that your
application is vulnerable to.
We cannot do that. There is an infinite amount of threats. And every
week, you got news
about our new vulnerabilities found in libraries that
everyone uses. Infinite amount of threats.
However, this is beautiful.
Wait for it. All of them.
All of those threads can be assigned to one of
three categories. This will be
an acronym, but I think you know it.
Those three categories are confidentiality,
integrity, and availability.
And this is called the CIA triad.
I could make a joke about spice,
but I will not do that, because the only spice I
like to think about are spice girls.
Forgive me. Why is
it so exciting? The CIA triad. Why is it so exciting?
Why is it something that I want to talk about to you,
and I want you to later talk about with
your peers? Why? Because the
CIA triad let us put the
whole ocean into three buckets,
and it's a very impactful thing. But before
I tell you, why is it so impactful?
Let me just define what CIA means.
Confidentiality means that we
want secrets to be secret.
If I send you an email or you
send me an email telling me how did you like this
talk? We only want
us to read it. We don't want anyone
else to interfere in our communication. Right.
Integrity means that we get what
we expect. So when you log into your email,
you want to see all of your emails, right? It would
be very weird if you had all
of your data lost availability.
We can always access the information.
So we expect that you can send me
this email 10:00 p.m.
Or 03:00 a.m. In the morning.
No matter when you can send
email, you can access Instagram.
Your application will work 24/7 right?
This is availability.
Okay, so how is it helpful?
How is it helpful? You see,
it is helpful because it
transform the way you can approach security.
Instead of thinking of oh,
I want my application to be secure,
how do I do that? Oh, this is this vulnerability. Do we have
this vulnerability? Okay, we don't. That's good.
And this vulnerability we don't have.
Okay. And this, oh, we need to fix something.
This is completely overwhelming. How are you
supposed to, as a developer, remember about all
of those things? It's impossible.
So the CIA triad is
very helpful because instead
of going from threats,
vulnerabilities lists,
you take a step back and
you ask the question,
the question, the CIA question,
which is how
can the CIA of this
project be broken?
I don't know if you can fear, but it
excites me every time.
Think about your current project.
Do you have it? Okay, you can
ask the CIA question for it. Let's do it.
How can the CIA of you
say it be broken?
How can the CIA of your project be broken?
It's so powerful because it works
for everything. It works no matter if you are backend,
front end, mobile, if you work in a cloud or
not. If you are junior developer,
meet senior staff,
whatever director. If you are product manager, you also can
ask this question. If you're a designer, you can ask this question.
This will work forever for you.
How can the CIA of the thing I'm working on
be broken? And of course,
if you want to answer this question, you will
need to dig deeper and ask
more questions. And for each category,
confidentiality, integrity and availability. You will
ask questions specific to
your project.
But here let me share some ideas,
some examples of questions you can ask confidentiality
who can see this resource? How do I store
credentials? Do we log sensitive
data for
integrity? Who can create update
remove a resource?
What happens when a malicious data
is sent via form is
the input sanitized? Are we
protected against cross site scripting?
These are examples of integrity questions.
Availability, is this endpoint rate
limited? What happens when external product
is down? How much time does
this database migration
take? These are availability
questions. And let me just stop for a second
with the availability, because I
get this often that when I say availability,
developers stop listening because we
think, ah, availability infrastructure
group, infrastructure team.
But this is not necessarily true.
I mean, it's not true at all, because as developers
we introduce new products, new libraries,
which means dependencies. And you really need to think about
what happens when this great product that
you use for managing feature flags go down.
Does it mean that our whole product is down?
Availability. Don't skip it when
you do this CIA questioning with
your team.
So now the question is when
should you do this? Okay, so you maybe understand
what the CIA triad is now.
We talked about it, I told you about the
questions, but when
should you do this? Like your practice is already full and
booked. So I cannot
answer this question without telling you about shifting security
left. Shift security left is this new way
of thinking about security.
And if you ever meet an application
security engineer, probably in your
company, ask them what shift security left means,
because they will be probably thrilled to tell you more.
But the idea is that when we look at the
software development lifecycle, right, we have five
phases, requirement analysis,
analysis, design. Can I count
on my fingers? Design, implementation, testing and
evolution.
But here's the thing, so I've been doing this way
too long. I don't think we are
working in a lifecycle. It's more like
a timeline. We do analysis,
design, we develop, we test, and then
we release and maintain, right?
And after we release, we just move on to the next project.
So it's never really a lifecycle.
If your experience is different, let me know.
Anywho, we have this timeline and
what happens. Remember the story I told you in the beginning?
We had security review
just before the release. It was on the right side of
this product development timeline.
So shifting security left means shifting
security, thinking about security,
approaching security to the design
phase, right?
So why is it so important?
Because in the design phase,
creating changes is very easy. Because what
you do, you only, I don't know, change a document, change a graph.
You basically work on a piece of paper.
Whereas when you have security review
just before the release, the changes are
extremely expensive.
Not to mention how expensive they get. When you already release a
thing, that's horrible. And it's more stressful,
it takes more time, it's more
expensive, it's terrible.
Shifting security left says hey,
let's talk about security of this thing that we are working on
before we even code.
Let's agree on that so we can have some kind of
confidence that what we are building is secure.
This is shifting security left. So how
do you implement this CIA triad in
your company, in your practice,
you inject it basically what
it means, present it to your peers,
you can send them this small
video, discuss it with your team, discuss approaching
security earlier. Invite your security team
to discussions so they have some
kind of input and they can help you and guide you.
But also make it part of your process
because in order we talk about scaling a
lot. Security cannot
be just an ad hoc action.
It needs to be part of your process. And how do you do that?
The easiest thing except of telling people
about it is to update the
documentation like documentation templates. So if
you have documentation templates like solution
briefs, enhancement proposal, request for
comments, et cetera, add security section there,
add CIA triad show. Hey, how will this
affect confidentiality, integrity, availability?
How can we break it? How can this new feature
break confidentiality, integrity and availability?
And it will help you work
and create more secure solutions.
Important thing, you don't have to do it on your own.
Those can discussions are
meant to be run together in the team and
the more perspectives you bring the better.
So you don't have to focus on back ends only.
Like bring front end engineers in
the room, bring a designer product manager.
How can you create find a solution that
is basically a compromise between business
and security? Compromise, is it a great
word? I think so. Like what we need is some kind of
connection, some kind of understanding.
You can do it to
finish up. Look,
there is no week when we don't hear about
a data breach or vulnerability that is in
this super important library that everyone
uses. We need to
as engineers step up and
we need to understand that things that we are building have
a huge impact on people's life.
We need to take responsibility for that.
The colorless times of moved fast
and break things are over and
it's a good thing actually.
I hope that the CIA triad will
help you create more secure software,
approach security in an easier way,
moved manageable and
I think you will have great fun.
Thank you for joining me today. Thank you for listening me
and please let's stay in touch.
I'm online. Well,
thank you,