My name is Pratik. Thank you. And I'm a principal
software engineer in one of the leading human
capital management companies in the US.
I'm also an active researcher in the field of
artificial intelligence DevOps machine learning and
security. It's great to be here at Conf 42
machine learning conference and to discuss the important
topic of large language model and the
security risk that there is. So let's dive
into my presentation. So today my topic
is the privacy predicament with the
transformative potential of large language models.
So we are living in exciting times. With this advancement in
AI, we find ourselves at a remarkable technological
crossroad which is propelled by this large language models.
This artificial intelligence marvels can engage in dialogue just
like human, generate creative content, and even
write a quote without any issues or error.
With this, immense capabilities are overshadowed by trouble
paradox, which is shielding this data. This model,
which possesses a severe risk to the individual privacy
and the human rights. As useful these models
are, their OPEC training processes raises a significant
privacy risk. And this is a privacy paradox that
we need to grapple with. And one should ask like how we
can take a full advantage of this large language models while
protecting the people's privacy. Let's talk
about the data privacy paradox. The training large
language model involves ingesting a mind boggling
amount of data, and which are randomly scrapped from the
open source or Internet, like from the website, book,
personal communication, you just name it. This unfiltered
data absorption allows the model to inevitably
memorize and spit out verbatim sensitive personal
information, like credit card numbers, private messages, copyright materials
and other defamatory content which
is present in this training datasets. But the
problem just don't stop here at this
data leaks. These models are also absorbing and spreading
the societal biases,
stereotype and misinformation, which present in the
massive amount of online data that they trained on. This private
risk go beyond this individual information, and which
includes discrimination and
allowing misinformation to spread like wildfire across the Internet.
So here is the profound paradox that we face.
The discriminate data driving this model's extraordinary
capabilities is also the very source of
geopolitic, the privacy and the human rights of
the societal human being striking a delicate
balance. So let's find a balance, how we can maintain the
capability of the LLM models and we
can make it secure at the same time. So resolving
this paradox requires like walking a tight rope.
Excessively constraining this training data could undermine
the models broad knowledge and hamper the performance.
Yet unchecked this data ingestion possess unacceptable
privacy risk. Technical approaches like data filtering,
differential privacy and synthetic data can help
to mitigate issues. But implementing this massive scale of
the modern language models is computationally
and logically it's very challenging. We may also need
to accept that some calculated privacy trade offs are
unavoidable, at least with this current method. The key
will be developing a governance framework
to assess and manage the risk appropriately
for the different use cases, and this will be a collaborative
effort. So let's talk about the transparency
and the accountability challenges. Even when the privacy
risk are from this training, data are reduced. The large
language model present another major challenge.
That these are the opaque black boxes, and their
complexity makes it impossible to audit what is specific
data influenced given output just to understand
this machine reasoning process behind it. The lack of
transparency fundamentally undermines the ability to
ensure the safe, unbiased operation of the system
and to hold them accountable when things
go south. So techniques like water modeling,
constant decoding and robust monitoring, this all could provide
more visibility into this behavior. But ultimately,
we must find ways to build transparency and auditability
into the system from the ground up to secure
privacy minded development practices. Let's talk about
this devsecops for the responsibility development devsecops
term is just like a dev operations with
security. So when we are tackling this privacy
paradox surrounding this language models, which demands
a multifaceted, holistic solution with the
principal governance framework on the tech side like
this, continue research into privacy preserving
training methods. The new secure machine learning
techniques will be crucial. Perhaps more particularly,
we must embrace like this
devsecop practices that integrate the security,
privacy and ethical AI principle into each and every
phase of the software development cycle and building this LLM
models. And this can be achieved through cross
functional collaboration in parallel. Comprehensive AI
governance framework align the technological development
with the human values must be cooperatively developed by all stakeholders
like firms, policymakers and
the representative from the impacted communities. Only by
combining this edge cutting solution with the rigorous
governance, we can truly unleash the
large language model's immense potential,
while we are holding the privacy and
this non discrimination and human right.
Now, let's discuss about this governance framework
and ethical principles as we stand.
We understand the capabilities of large language models are
incredible, we have all seen it. But we must maintain, we must
remain constantly committed to confront that
the privacy predicament that they present.
Resolving this paradox is an urgent imperative that
will shape the responsible development of the AI and
for the generations to come through continuous innovation, holistic secure
practices and ethical grounded governance
we can place a trail alignment of transformative
AI with the core human values. This makes no mistake,
like path ahead will be immensely
challenging, but our collective principles and
commitment to prioritizing this humanity webping must
light the way forward. And with the dedication and collaboration
across the sectors, we can unlock the language
large language model potential while maintaining
the security at the same time in this digital
world. In the conclusion, I would say together let's
build a safer digital world.