Thanks for joining me here for my talk leveraging cloud abstractions
to drive generative AI, scalability,
efficiency and diverse applications.
This talk is based on my own personal views and hopefully adds value
to you. In this talk, we'll go over basics
of Chenai cloud abstractions and how
cloud abstractions fuel the Chenai use cases. We'll also
see some of the industry transformative use cases with the advent of
genai running on the shoulders of abstractions.
So the content of this talk is introduction to GenAi
as well as cloud abstraction, cloud abstractions by
examples and then we'll switch over to how genai
deployment occurs, what are the different
strategies behind it, what are the different building blocks around it,
how cloud abstraction benefits, and what is
the cloud adoption in general in our industry? Then we'll
talk about we'll specifically talk about healthcare and
creative content. So direction to Gen AI Genai
is generative artificial intelligence. It is a subset
of deep learning that employs training on
supervised, semi supervised, or even unsupervised
learnings. It differs from the
in the manner it operates. That is, it creates new
content is no more identifying a
cat, but producing a cat out
of the data it was trained on. In simple terms,
Genai is a kind of AI that can produce output
in multiple formats like text,
audio, images, animations, you name it.
This is a huge leap from being able to just pattern,
match, recommend or identify the objects.
Genai has emerged as a transformative technology,
enabling machines to create advanced context aware
outputs across various domains. Some of the
popular examples are Delhi,
Chatgpt, Gemini, Firefly,
next, lithium. In our talk it is really important
to understand do they deploy? So let's
start with foundational models, also known
as FM's. So foundational model
is an AI neural network trained on huge
raw data, generally with unsupervised learning that
can be adapted to accomplish a broad range of tasks.
It is a multimodal in nature, meaning it can interact
from text to text, text to or any other combination.
GPT clip next is LLM.
LLMs are subset of foundational models,
but they are specifically trained on a large neural language data set.
They are specifically designed for generating human
language based use cases.
Train model the train model is the
instance of model which includes learn parameters
and weights. This is a crucial component. This is
the model which generates new content based on different conditions.
The next building block is inference code.
This is typically a bridge between model and your application.
This handles interaction with the train model.
It manages input processing,
encoding, decoding and even managing the
generation process. This component ensures that the user
applications can effectively building block
in GenaI would be data pipelines.
Those pipelines are required for pre
processing input data or formatting the output data. These pipelines
ensure that the input data is correctly formatted.
Next we have to send and receive in
form of web or app layer. This allows application to send request
which would be text prompts or image conditions and receive
generated outputs that would be generated text images or
generated text itself in response. A simple example
would be Delhi where you go and
you prompt and then you get the output back.
So Delhi would have a API running or the UI running
to process your request. Other example could be moving
now to the what is cloud abstractions?
Well, cloud abstractions are the mechanisms to hide the
internal and complex detail of infrastructure
where somehow cloud abstractions empower running of services.
Application bad job. Streaming models consider
the abstraction as a filter to put away the complex detail
asides to be able to see. Now there are different types
of established abstractions which have been in our industry
since few years now. Those are infrastructure
as a service, platform as a service,
software as a service and function as a service.
The last one is the latest entry into the field of extractions.
It is also known as serverless computing. We will talk about
these all entities, but let's talk about them
in a real world analogy. We can relate
to it quickly. I'm pretty sure everybody has gone through
the pain of buying a house or renting a room.
So probably this. Let's start with infrastructure as
a service. Infrastructure as a service is a foundational
abstraction where the tier zero resources
like virtual machines, storage, disk network bandwidth,
etcetera provided to you. You don't
have to build your own data center to get those.
That's the idea behind it. Someone like Amazon or Google
or Oracle will provide these resources to you so that you
ec two Google compute engine Azure.
Compare this to the land you get
from a builder so that you don't have to do all
the work of identifying the land going
through different regulatory in
order to build your home. You just out of the box,
you get the land and you start building your own home on top of it.
That would be example of iis. The next layer
would be PaaS or the platform as a service which offers a managed
platform for deploying applications without the
need to manage the underlying infrastructure. You don't need to
set up your own subnet or routing or
firewalls if you operate on PaaS.
Example would be Heroku. Let's say that you're not
building homes, you don't just want
the land, but you also want a home. And you're thinking to
probably use your expertise in up leveling the rooms,
right? But there could be times where
you don't hide to build the room.
You can customize your room, but you're not interested in building
your room or building a house or getting a land. So that
is something which is known as SAS software as a service.
Shopify HubSpot are common examples of it.
SAS provides capabilities to
companies and developers so that they can focus on their product
and they can build their product on a manage.
You might have heard about function as a service or as I mentioned,
serverless computing. This is the latest entry
in abstractions where you
just get the room, rent a room, and so
it's basically serverless computing where you're in your full application,
you can execute your functionality and
run that functionality on an existing server.
For example Google cloud functions or Amazon Lambda example
could be trigger based counter which when
there is a. When there is a. Okay, now you
have seen some narrative
about cloud abstractions and what are those? Let's move on
to the so what is Genai deployment
story? Like any other distributed system,
Genai system is a combination of different components in
order to ensure the use case is
being served. When you go to chat GPT,
for example, when you enter any text prompt,
it doesn't give you the answer by itself. It actually
has a lot of revolving pieces that is needed
there to empower that. So some
of the, some of the building blocks
we have talked about it would be models, inference code,
data pipelines, web services, and there are few
behind the scene which would be monitoring and alerting some
of the infrastructure pieces like load balancer gateways,
auto scaling groups, some of the integration services,
CICD and some of the regulatory and security gates.
So if you closely see there
are numerous components behind Genai and
we need to deploy that, let's see how those
are being deployed. Various ways or strategies to deploy these
components we talked about in previous slide in order to have
an end to end gen capable system,
there are three major deployment strategies.
First would be in house or private deployment. Second would
be hybrid deployment. The third or the one is
SAS deployment. So the in house deployment
is basically gives you end to end control, but it
also involves managing everything on your own.
And different organizations could choose different ways of deploying
this depending upon the requirement,
regulatory requirement, data privacy requirement and their
resources. But a common theme which
we will try to extract from all three would be that
the cloud based deployments are a common theme across
the industries.
So in house deployments basically means
that, you know, having the foundational models,
the LLMs, everything in house in your own data centers,
running everything in house, including the app,
including the service layer. And that requires a lot
of resources, computational resources as well as
expertise. Example would be generative
AI system in the autonomous driving,
which few car companies
have done on their own. They're using Nvidia system
for training and inference. And that's obviously
even if you go this route of private deployment,
most of the organization which are doing this would have some
kind of orchestration tools to manage the resources and
provide the rights of sections. Maybe they are using Tupperware,
maybe they're using Borg or Kubernetes or just Mesos,
but they have some kind of empower this.
A recent example would be a healthcare provider could
develop a Genai powered medical assistant website in house,
leveraging their own FM's and LLMs to provide personal
patient support. This approach allows for complete control
of sensitive patient data and ensures regulations.
The other use case I confuse defense where there
would be a stricter next is hybrid deployment.
In hybrid deployment, organizations can choose to use
third party or openly available models,
be it foundational models or pre trained models or even pre
trained APIs to bootstrap their applications to use
them. The application code could
still be in house while some of the models may be in the cloud.
Hence the hybrid model libraries such as model
Garden from Google is one of the example where
you actually have the offering to choose whatever model
you would like as per your resource.
There are advanced offerings in this field, for example
vertex, AI or sagemaker where you get not
only the model but end to end platform which
empowers you to get services from
exters. Example would be many
organizations would opt for a hybrid approach using
pre built GenAi services like OpenAI GPT-3
to accelerate development and reduce cost.
This approach allows companies to focus on their core
competencies while benefiting from the so
this hybrid deployment could be applicable to most
of the use cases today where the regulatory running
application in house or managed services like Google or
AWS. In a hybrid model also the organizations
will have to basically use
some of the abstractions with the flexibility they
can actually as needed. Next would
be the SAS deployment. In this deployment
the clients get access to variety of
models, variety of tools, variety of tools
to tune the models and also automated
to production lies. The models can also
be same or different cloud, so no
need of running in house anything. So that would be example
of SAS deployment. A lot of cloud vendors who
are providing these abstractions. They are right now
providing it with right controls, be it GDPR
or any other regulatory.
Google AI studio is one such example.
The low or no code deployment model
is the new entry in this
abstraction field where it is an extension
of SAS deployment where you just don't need to even write the code
and you drag and drop. So you drag and drop your
features and you have the funnel.
There are app builder solutions which are 100% in cloud
which gives the apps without knowing how to
write the code. Chatbots Knowledge systems these are the common
use cases for this type of now
that we have seen different type of deployment strategies, let's see
how cloud abstractions benefit
genai underneath. So in all the different ways
of genai deployment strategies we have seen, there is
a need to manage the resources.
Even if you run on Amazon or your own data center,
you can't burn your resources.
So the cloud abstractions provide
you efficient resources. They focus on
reducing waste and giving you the best ROI.
By leveraging, for example, by leveraging serverless computing and
auto scaling capabilities, organizations or companies
can ensure that their Jennifer system can handle spikes
or varying workloads. So be
it any model you need beat any model or deployment,
there is a clear need to manage the allocation
and utilization, and that cloud abstraction provides it.
The next benefit of cloud abstraction to genai use
cases would be streamlined processes.
So cloud abstractions empower
the standardization of pipelines, be it CI continuous
integration, continuous deployment.
They also provide with the streamline the agility,
the much needed agility in order to move quickly
with a rapid piece scalability.
So the cloud abstractions ensure that the scalability
and the quality of user experience is always there.
Cloud restrictions allow Genai systems to scale seamlessly,
accommodating growing user bases or ensuring a consistent
quality of experience. By leveraging the global
and high speed networks, organizations can deliver
low latency or even a full scale application
or even a viral use case.
Sagemaker was used to scale a Genai
based content recommendation system.
The scale was not less, it was millions of users and
gaining the performance and reliability. There are other numerous
other benefits to the cloud abstraction which
we have not discussed, for example, segregation and
high availability.
The no code model, for example, utilizes the abstraction underneath
to empower a user to safely create an app using
drag and drop. The JNA studio places the right controls to
choose the safe models and mitigate the risk in doing so.
So the existing and established offerings like monitoring,
auto scaling, alerting,
those are the results of already established
abstractions, something that we let's
move forward with the current state option and kubernetes.
So most of the organizations deploy
some piece of cloud native technologies today and
one of them in general. Cloud adoption
is essential for managing and scaling Jennair workloads.
Cloud abstractions play a crucial role in your scalability.
Genai is a transformative technology and
it is definitely inspiring industry
transformations. I am pretty sure we cannot
discuss every industry here,
so we will focus on creative content.
Jennia is also inspiring
new growth opportunities and paving the way.
So healthcare transformation, let's talk about it. Healthcare is
a field where the regulatory concerns would
be very high due to sensitive data.
But this is also one of the fields which
requires innovative the most.
For example, Clara it's a genii tool in healthcare.
It reduces the phone interaction by 50%.
That means that no longer you have to be on the call hourly
call to get some help. This increases the user
experience privacy. This has led to
new and improved outcomes and
it has also helped streamline the healthcare processes.
Overall, Genai has a very positive
transformation. Cloud the
next industry which has seen the most impact
after healthcare is creative content with
AI driven tools like Delhi or Adobe Firefly.
The way you could create an image or audio
has changed. Generation of digital artwork has
improved miles and miles. Now more and
more individuals are exploring these tools,
expressing their artistic creativity.
This has also made the content
creation future potential of Genai
is very positive with cloud technologies. They both
drive innovation and accessibility.
There is a symbiotic relationship and cloud abstractions.
It unlocks new possibilities and increases trees.
We will reiterate that there is a symbiotic relationship between
genai and cloud abstractions. Cloud abstractions
are essential enablers for deploying
managing your geni workloads. They provide necessary
scalability, they ensure efficiency,
they support diverse applications.
Streamlining the processes the
future of Jennia is closely tied to continued evaluation.
With that, thank you.