Jamaica real
time feedback into the behavior of your distributed systems and
observing changes exceptions errors in real time
allows you to not only experiment with confidence, but respond
instantly to get things working again.
Those you hello,
thank you for joining my session. Today we will talk
about machine learning and we will share with you the different strategies on
how to build machine learning mlpowered applications with
JavaScript. So before I start with these
talk, let me quickly introduce myself. I am
Joshua Arvin Lat. People call me arVs. So arVs,
arVs. So from Arvin. So the shortcut
is arBs. I am the chief technology officer
of Newworks Interactive Labs and I'm also an AWS
machine learning hero. So there are maybe
20 to 30 something machine learning heroes all around
the world, and we save the day one day at
a time by sharing our knowledge in
our domain expertise. I'm also the
author of the books Machine Learning with Amazon Sagemaker
Cookbook and machine learning Engineering on AWS.
So if you are interested in learning more about machine learning
experimentation and deployments in the cloud,
then this book may be for you. So let's start by
talking about how machine learning works and what
its applications are. So machine learning is very powerful.
So if we were to solve anomaly detection
problems, if we were to work on product recommendation
requirements and so on, then we may be able to
utilize machine learning by using algorithms and
data to solve our requirements.
So if you are not yet familiar on how machine learning works,
basically what it does is it helps us perform automated
tasks which are usually performed by intelligent
beings like humans. So for example, we have an image
of a cat here. If this were to be processed
by a human, a human would easily be able to
identify if this image is a cat or
not a cat. However, if this were
to be processed by a machine, this may be somewhat hard
to do, especially if you're going to hard code and
you're not going to utilize data to process this,
especially if there are an infinite
number of possible variations for the cat images.
For example, for this one, if you hard code the
implementation of classification for the first image,
how would you be able to process the following images?
One of the possible solutions in order for us to properly
classify if an image is a cat or not a cat is to
utilize machine learning. So there are different strategies,
there are different algorithms available in machine learning,
but in order to solve this type of requirements, we may
be able CTO use, let's say something like this, the machine learning process.
The machine learning process involves utilizing data
to build and train a machine learning model,
which can be used to perform inference or predictions
on new data. So getting
back CTO the cat example,
let's say that we have 100,000 images of cats.
We use those 100,000 images to train a
machine learning model and then that model will
be evaluated and the performance would be checked.
So let's say that it has 90% score.
This would mean that maybe nine out of ten times it would get the answer
correctly. So if you're happy with that model,
then you would be able to deployed it. And then if you,
let's say, have a mobile application, you took a picture of a cat.
If you cases that image to that machine learning model,
then that machine learning model would then give you either a one or a
zero. Maybe zero would be cat and then one would be
not cat. So it depends on how you implemented the inference
part, but more or less that's how it works.
One point that you should know is that this is a simplified
version of the machine learning process. In real life.
The machine learning process is circular and there are a lot of
things we need to take into account, like model training.
We need to make sure that we are able to
refresh the model as well. Because once you have deployed the
model after two weeks to one month, there might be
a chance that your model has degraded already and you need to replace
or refresh it. Now that we have a better idea
on how machine learning works, we can now try
to answer this question, why use
JavaScript for machine learning? For those
data scientists and machine learning practitioners listening to this
talk, maybe you would also ask the
same question, especially if you've used already something like Python
to solve different machine learning experiments and requirements.
So there are different advantages when using machine learning.
But before we go straight into that one, let's answer
this question first. The question that we need to answer
is can we build a machine learning
powered application using JavaScript? Is it
a yes or is it a no? So the correct answer
to this one is it's a yes. So we can build a machine learning mlpowered
application using JavaScript because there are different
libraries and tools available to support these
types of application. So even if there
are different tools and libraries
available for other languages, and even if some languages,
let's say Python and even r, have been customized
more for machine learning, why should we consider using
JavaScript for machine learning in certain use cases?
So there are some scenarios where it might make sense to use JavaScript
for machine learning, especially for a team which
is already using JavaScript heavily. So let's say that you have a
team of, let's say five developers, and they've been using
JavaScript heavily for all of the projects. For a
certain company, if they were to learn a new language, let's say Python,
it might take them a while. And maybe the tools and
the pipelines that the team has already is focusing more on the JavaScript
side of things. So in order for a team to
have to spend less time learning a new language and
focusing on the implementation part using the same language,
which is JavaScript, then types, if they were to implement
and do some machine learning stuff, then they can do it with JavaScript.
The second possible reason why people should
use JavaScript for machine learning is that they can also perform
machine learning references on the browser.
So that's pretty cool because the browser, you can do
some JavaScript stuff there, and instead of the inference
call being made from the browser or the web app
front end to the back end server, it will
all happen in the browser. So we will dive deeper into that
later. And here, as mentioned earlier,
we can avoid the need to learn a new language, because for
this one, maybe you are a front end developer and you're
just starting out and you need to implement and utilize
a machine learning model, then yes, you can
do that using JavaScript. So you may be
able to perform inference in the browser,
and you may also be able to use JavaScript on
the server side. And even if a lot of
tools have already been prepared for, let's say, python,
there are also corresponding set of tools in JavaScript which we will see later.
So let's now dive a bit deeper into why and
how we can perform machine learning experiments and deployed
in the browser using JavaScript.
On the left side we can see a simplified
diagram on how server side inference work.
So what do we mean by inference? When you have a machine
learning model ready, you want to perform predictions,
you want to use that model to perform inference,
meaning you want to perform an intelligent
decision or task.
So in this case, let's say that the problem we're trying to solve is
the identification or classification if the image
is a cat or not a cat. So if you have an
image in the browser, you will need to send
that image to the services through a request.
So that request, which includes the image, will be processed
by the server and the server which has the model.
The model would then be used to process the image
and the output would be either one
or zero. So 1 may represent, let's say not cat
and these zero would represent cat.
So the value, the output value would be returned
back to the browser and then you can basically update
the user interface using
your favorite JavaScript library and you can display these
cat. So if you upload an image of a dog,
then the server would then respond,
not cat. So that's basically how server
side inference work. There's a server behind the scenes.
On the right side we can see the alternative these
we can perform references in the browser directly.
So how would that work? When you load the page,
the model would be loaded as well on
the front end side and here in the second
scenario, no servers are needed,
at least on the processing side.
So when the front end code receives
some sort of event, instead of pushing
the data to a request to a back end server,
the inference will happen in the browser itself
on the client side. So there are advantages CTO
this because for example, if these are network
issues, then the second scenario wouldn't be affected
because it works offline. And if you don't
want your users to pass their data to the
server, then yes, you can do this as well because it helps
with data privacy. So yes, so these are the advantages of
performing machine learning references on the browser. So as mentioned,
you can work offline. So let's say that after loading these page,
you decided CTO disconnect your
Internet connection. Your application
will still be interactive and it will work just fine. So that's
super helpful, especially if you have Internet connection
problems or there's very limited or very slow
Internet connectivity, which of course would affect latency.
So here there's better latency, better performance from a network standpoint
and there no servers are needed. So in some
cases there are cases where you might need to
have a server, but there may be cases, especially for smaller
models where you can deploy it in
the browser. And it also helps with data privacy because
your customers or users data do
not need CTO be sent to the server, to a centralized server
which can be analyzed
and processed by the team who built that server.
So of course these are the advantages. So what may be
some disadvantages to this one? So once you load that
model in the browser, in terms of model
security, that model can already be used
or at least downloaded from these browser.
So that's just the only thing you need to worry about.
However, if you're not worried about model security, then this
may be the solution for you. But again, these are amazing
advantages. And browsers of course support javascript.
Now that we know that we can do some machine learning stuff in the
browser, would this mean that we would
be able CTO use a machine learning library in
JavaScript along with your favorite JavaScript
front end, framework or library? The answer
there is yes. So that's good news for us, because if
you are already using libraries or
frameworks like ReAPP, view and angular or other
new frameworks and libraries,
then it's all about doing some
coding work to use your machine learning library and your
model with it. So in some cases
you will be able to train your machine learning model in
the browser directly and in some cases as well,
you'll be able to perform references in the browser
also. So it really depends on your requirements. In most
cases you may just need to focus on the inference part and
do the training part in the server. So what
are examples of libraries
which can be used to perform machine learning experiments
and inference deployments in the browser,
the browser, the website front end. So here are
some examples like Tensorflow, JS, even onx
runtime for web. So those can be used. And this can
easily be used with existing libraries and frameworks because they're
basically just code. And these frameworks and libraries just help
with processing the data and the different elements
in your web application to make it more interactive and
to help you manage the front end code better. So how about
state management? So if you're not yet familiar
with how state management works, feel free to
watch my presentation from last year
where I talked about how to do pragmatic state management in react,
angular and ujs. So feel free to use
the QR code here or just search in YouTube in
order to watch this video. But you'll definitely learn a lot because
state management is a topic
on its own and it's better if we watch it separately.
But again, if you have a data intensive application
and you want to manage the machine learning stuff
in the browser and do some interactions
and make your applications interactive, these yes,
you may need to learn about state management,
especially when you're doing heavy Javascript work.
All right, now that we have talked about web apps
a bit, let's now talk about mobile apps.
Wow. So we all thought that having
machine learning models deployed in the browser is amazing.
You should know that we can also deploy mobile apps,
deploy machine learning models in the mobile apps
itself. So how would that work?
The more standard or the more common ways to perform machine
learning deployments and even training is to perform all
of these inside servers. So if you
have a mobile application and you have data, these in order for
training to happen, at least in the first scenario, we need
to pass the data to the centralized
system or server. These model gets trained
there and the model will be used.
Similar to an example earlier,
where there's the client, the front end which can be web
or mobile, and then there's the request and
the server would be processing it because the model is in
the services. However, there is a
second option, an alternative where as you
can see on the right side, similar to how
we deploy nodejs in the browser or the client
front end, we can also perform on device machine
learning. This means that the data
of the user which will be used during inference
no longer needs to be sent to a server.
So what happens here is that all the magic is happening inside
the mobile app. So yes, so if the mobile
app contains the model already, then yes, this is possible.
And in terms of advantages, the advantages are the same.
So it helps with data privacy, it works offline,
no servers are needed, and it's faster. So why is
it faster? It's faster because there's no more round trip
from the mobile app to the server and back,
especially when you need to perform inference, it can
all happen in real time. So this is an example of
how you can perform and do and use
machine learning nodejs in your mobile app.
So if you have, let's say something like react native and use
Tensorflow JS, then you can do something like this.
Now let's talk about machine learning in the cloud using
JavaScript. So why use the cloud?
So when using and utilizing
the different cloud capabilities and resources, one of
the advantages when you're using the cloud is that you have full
control over the type and the size of resources
that you're going to use to perform the needed operation.
So in this case, machine learning training
and deployment usually when
you need to work on more complex machine learning models, there will
be a big chance, especially for certain types
of requirements where you will need to deal with bigger data
sets and bigger models. So here
we can see that if we need a stronger computer,
which is significantly bigger and faster and stronger
than what we have in our local machine, then types
we can utilize the cloud for it. Let's say that we have a
1gb data set and it needs to be processed by
a server. The training job and
script running inside that server would be
able to do it properly. However, if you were to process
that large data set and use an
algorithm which is kind of resource intensive,
resource hungry, then a smaller machine would struggle with
it. That's why we can utilize the cloud for these types
of requirements. In addition to
that, if we were to perform automated
hyperparameter optimization HPO,
we can utilize multiple cloud servers all
at the same time to do what we need to do. So in this
case we will perform machine learning experiments and we will
build a model. So in most of
the examples that we know and most of the basic examples
that we've tried and we're aware of, we usually deal
with one machine learning experiment. So one machine learning experiment
may produce one model. However,
in real life we would need to produce multiple models.
We would do a lot of iterations in order to get the
best model possible. So instead of us trying to wait
for, let's say one r for one model,
and if we have 100 tries, 100 different configurations
for different types of training jobs, we would
have to wait a really long time, let's say 100 hours, if we
were to do it one at a time. However, we can do this in
parallel, meaning that if we need
to produce 100 machine learning models and get the best
model from the results of the experiments,
we can do that all at the same time. So machine learning experiment 12345,
all happening at the same time, and you would be able to complete everything in
maybe one to 1.5 hours. So these is amazing.
And these is one of the advantages of using the cloud,
because you're able to spin up and delete resources as
needed. In addition to that, there are a lot of services
and platforms available to help us manage cloud
resources better while performing machine learning experiments
and deployed. So there's something called Sagemaker,
I even wrote a book about it. Right? So Sagemaker is a mature
machine learning platform and
it's a service of AWS. So if you've been using AWS,
then this is something that you can easily use because you have an
account. There are of course alternatives in other cloud providers,
let's say GCP and Azure. So feel free to take a look at it,
especially if your team is already using that cloud platform.
But what I would like to share these is that there
is of course an SDK available
for JavaScript. So you have an API. So the service has
an API. If you need to talk to the API,
maybe perform a machine learning experiment using this algorithm,
you can do that with Python. So a lot of people
know that Python can be used to work with
this service. However, if you do a bit more research, you will
realize that different sdks have been made available in
different languages, and JavaScript is one of them.
So the capabilities available in Python is of course available in
JavaScript, because most of the magic has
been implemented already inside the service itself.
All we need to do is call the right API
call and we'll be able to
have the much needed capability or functionality.
So this is one good example. So let's say that you have a machine
learning model trained and we need to deploy it
instead of us trying to build our references
server from scratch. Let's say something using expressjs and
all the needed libraries to read the model
and use it for inference. Maybe we can do that faster.
Maybe we can have a real time endpoint, or maybe we can have
a serverless endpoint or use other types of inference solutions
by just having these right configuration. Maybe we would need just maybe
five lines to six lines of code just to do all of this.
And this is easily doable in maybe 30 minutes to 1 hour,
especially when you have the code snippets ready to perform machine
learning deployment. So again, if we were to compare this
with building your own inference server, building it yourself
may take three days to five days.
However, if you were to use a mature platform,
then with 30 minutes to 1 hour you will be able to have something which
you can present to your boss already for approval. So those
are some of the things that you should know, because choosing
the right solution starts first by knowing what's possible.
Then you can select later on when to use what.
Take note that some services also
allow us to utilize docker containers. And even without
the container image support, we can already use JavaScript
inside a lambda function. So lambda,
which is a function as a services, allows us
to write code and focus on the code
without worrying about the server. So what
we can do inside a lambda function is that using JavaScript,
we can load the trained model and use it for inference.
So if you use lambda with a serverless API service
like API gateway, then we can deploy the model
in that HTTP API without worrying
about the servers. If we were to use libraries
in JavaScript and we want to build a custom
container image, that's also possible because lambda
has container image support as well. So for simpler JavaScript
projects then yes, we can use lambda with JavaScript
directly. However, if we would need more complex
setups and environments for our JavaScript application utilizing
machine learning models, then we can utilize
container image support of lambda. And lambda can be
used across a variety of services
and architectures. For example, you have a streaming service,
let's say there's one record passing through that service because that's how
the architecture was implemented. So what you can
do is whenever there's new data coming out of that streaming application
or service, you can have a lambda function, process one record
at a time, and perform references in real time. Also,
it's also possible to create graphQL
powered APIs and inside that GraphQL powered
API we have a lambda function, processing the
request and utilizing the machine learning model to
perform inference and returning the response back to the user.
So this is also another powerful implementation
and you can definitely use JavaScript for these types of cloud
applications. So before
we end these talk, let's have a quick discussion on
these best practices. It's about using the right tools for
the job. So right now you are aware that there are different ways to
solve the same thing. However, it is crucial that we
always start first with the business requirements.
And again, a lot of technical professionals always
end up focusing on the technical solutions because wow,
that's cool, right? We can use JavaScript in the browser and
do some references there in the browser directly.
However, you need to be aware that this business requirements
may also include security requirements as well. Because what
if it was possible? However it would affect the
stability of your company, especially if the model has
been obtained from the browser, right? So be
very aware that this is the right process.
CTO follow we start first with business requirements and
then that's the time we focus on the technical solution and we
use a variety of building blocks to solve
our requirements. At the same time,
even if you know the right process, even if you
have a good understanding of the business requirements and the different tools
and solutions possible, take note that everything
that you do will always be a function of time,
meaning that you will not have an infinite
amount of time to do what you need to do.
So, similar to our example earlier where
you have a team of five developers all able
to use JavaScript, then yes, if they
need to utilize JavaScript for machine learning needs, then that's possible.
However, if the team is using something like Python or R
for machine learning already, if you were to use
JavaScript for machine learning, you would have to assess, because the
current team working on the machine learning task
needs to learn how to use JavaScript,
especially if they have no experience using the language in
the screen. We can see the different steps when performing
machine learning training. So here we can define the model,
we compile the model, load the data, use the data to
perform machine learning training so we fit
the model and then once we have the model, we evaluate it and
we save it somewhere. So this process,
this training step can be performed in
the server and it can also be performed maybe
in the browser as well. And it can be performed,
I guess in the mobile apps also. So there are different ways CTO
do this. So the question is where should we train the model
so we can train the model?
Depending on the resources needed for training,
and in a majority of the cases training
may be performed in the server because at least
in the server side it's more manageable, especially when you're
doing it in the cloud. However, there are cases where training may
be performed and it's recommended sometimes to do it in the
browser closer to the user because if the
user's data is stuck
in the browser, meaning it cannot be sent to the centralized server,
then yes, you can perform training in the browser itself
because it helps with data privacy. So let's say that the data
which will be used contains confidential information.
Instead of passing that data to the server,
you can perform training closer to the user in the browser
or even in the mobile app. However, in this
scenario we will focus on training our machine
learning model in the server and we can also deployed
the model in the server and we can do this with JavaScript. So as
long as we use the right set of libraries and tools and frameworks,
then we can do this similar to how we're doing it in let's say Python.
And this is what we talked about earlier. We can train our machine learning model
in the server and then when you load the web page
the model gets downloaded as well in the browser.
So there are maybe one or two steps needed to
convert that model to be usable
by the library or framework in the browser. At the same time,
if you can make the model smaller then better.
Also because this is recommended generally for nodejs
which are of small size because if you were to load
your web application it needs to load as fast as possible.
So if your web app is going to load for five minutes because the model
is too big, too big, then these
model is better off in the services side because the request can
be performed later on. And here this is
also possible. We can train the machine learning model in the server
and then in the mobile app, the model
can be downloaded there directly. So the advantage of this setup
is that there's going to be on device references and
the data of the user which will be used for inference
no longer needs to be passed in the
request to the server. So it helps protect the data and
you can do some cool and interactive offline
inference when using this type of approach.
So there, so if all you have is a hammer,
everything becomes a nail. So in this talk we talked about
the different strategies and solutions on how to use JavaScript
for machine learning. And there are different options,
but feel free to to do a bit more research before trying
to use a solution because once you implement this in production,
it's usually hard to fix or change. So make sure to be
an architect and those the right solution and tool for the job.
So thank you again for listening to my talk. We talked about
a lot of strategies and hope you learned something new.
Bye.