Hi everyone, thank you for deciding my talk about
the managecret across cloud on kubernetes.
That's me. That is Jonathan Hill DevOps
engineer at Appgate. I start
the talk about the unfraze life is
real simple but we insist on making it complicated by
confusion. I love that phrase because when you
try to do something new for your team and generate
new value for your company, it's very hard.
When you implement this with a new technology or
in this case with kubernetes when you try to do
something different where your knowledge
it's very hard generate new tool or generate a
specific tool for with best practice or with
secure it's very hard. It's a learning path
very difficult. But when you learn
this new you can generate new feature to
generate more value for your company. But every
day that you learn something new it's very hard because
implement this in your company, in your job,
in your ecosystem, it's very hard for
you and your team. In this case we learn about how
to use secrets over kubernetes,
how you can use these secrets for your
cloud environments or on prem environments too.
In this case bare metal for kubernetes is more
fashion could be and learning how you can
use these secrets for your Kubernetes cluster
and how do you can get from your cloud provider
and how you can obtain these new secrets for your
cloud environment and how do you can get these secrets
for your cluster ecosystem kubernetes.
That's it. Learning something new okay,
in this talk we're talking about the AWS SSam
Azure keyboard, GCP secret manager Hashicor Bowl
QR Net is a little speckle about QR nets and
the object inside the QR that is called secrets.
How you can use external secret data
operator inside of kubernetes and how to install
could be a little steps for use that and
a little demo about how to use secrets
in kubernetes using bold and how to mix
this ecosystem and how you can use every day
on your QR networks cluster. Talking about
the AWS system manage parameter restore parameter
restore is a capability of AWS system manager
provides secure erational storage for configuration,
data management and secrets management. You can store
data such as password database strings,
MSM machine image ids and Lisa and Scott
ads parameter values. Your secrets area
around the AWS and you store
this in text plane in this case
for row and you can encrypt this
data with your HSM
manage key generated inside
the AWS. You can use that for your deployments
or your ecosystem or your easy
to instance or your virtual machine inside AWS,
right? In this case we're talking show how
do you create parameters inside AWS?
You create parameters inside like a standard that
is generate my poll that is the
bad like that I use. In this case my
secret is called my secret AWS.
In this case the poll for that is
my value, right? You can use
this secret. In this case is client text
for obtain from my deployments or
obtain from my applications
around my ecosystem inside the QR net or
outside of QR net. It could be like a function as
a service in AWS it's called lambda. You can use that
inside of lambda and obtain this information
around the database strings or
could be endpoints from other API that I
can use. You can store this secret in
secure way and you can obtain this secrets
from secure way in EWS you can define
in amy account associate
from a user or from a role from
different ecosystem that you can deploy in there.
You can define that role uses from lambda or uses
from EC two instance or used for virtual machine and
obtain a specific secrets and just can use
for read don't for write just for read and can
update in this case for the ecosystem
the secure team could be updated this secret
for obtain and generate new value for your tools.
And how do you can generate this prospective
for your team, for all your teams and all your company and
how do you can define this process when the applications
can obtain only the secure
secret and how to the secure team can
update this data without the developer team could
be checked this data or it team
just the secure team. That is a big feature for
the cloud and how you can use that in
all Azure keyboard secrets
Azure keyboard is a cloud service for security strongly and
accessing secrets a secret is anything that you can
want to cliently control access to such as API
keys, password, certificates or cryptographic keys key
value therapy support two type of container bowels
and manage hardware security mode HSM pools
poll support storing software and HS back end
keys and certificate manage HSM
pool only support HM backend keys that
could be confused for learning in this part.
But in other words,
how do you can store your data in
security way right in this picture?
Check how can you create new
secrets over the Azure how you can store
secret like AWS, how to dissimilar
for AWS and how you can use in
Azure, right. You generate a bolt
primary in Azure and
secondly you can generate a
secret over the bolt and what is the type of the
secret you can generate inside? How you can
put this secret over the Azure
Azure manage airbag
access control for all ecosystem in your
cloud and how you can put all together how you
can use this like a function as a
service over the Azure. Now how
do you can obtain this secret from
Azure as a function fast or like
virtual machines or from your database
or from your ecosystem around your
deployment inside the cloud and how you can obtain
and how do you can put there all together
inside the azure? In this way you can generate
granularity for your teams or for your
developer teams or IT teams or security team for
obtain this glan reality option from
how you can use for your proposal or how
you can change all your ecosystem around
the company. How do you can
obtain this feature and generate
this process for your company that
isn't very high level because you
can generate could be the security team updated
the secret how to the developer team could be obtained no,
the developer team can update can obtain
this secrets just the application. When this
application is deployment in this way you
can generate this process who
can update these secret and how
to obtain for an application and how to use that for
all ecosystem that you generate inside
around the ecosystem the application right,
okay, checking other cloud GCP Secret
Manager Secret Manager is a secure and companion storage
system for API keys, password, certificates and
other sensitive data. Secret Manager provides central
place and single source truth manage access and outdated
secrets across Google Cloud. That is
definition we've taken about this gets from
GCP around the how to store and how to manage secrets
inside that, right? In this
case we have this picture about how you
can create over the Google Cloud
secrets. You generate a secret like
AWS and Azure generate a path could be or
generate just the name for your secret and
what is the value for your secret in
this case, in GCP you can generate
the granularity for your teams and the application and how
you can use this definition around your
process, how you can put together for the application
and how your security team can be updated and
how your application gets
this updated from your secret for the security
teams and you can change that for your
granular definition in your
matrix could be or your role
associated inside for your company and how to the
secure team just can change and
just generate and just update these secrets.
How the application obtained this secret update it from
your GCP Secret manager how this
application only the application can obtain this secret,
not the IT team or developer team like as well.
In Azure and AWS,
Hashicor Bolt Bolt is a tool for secure
access in secret. A secret is anything that
you want to tightly control access to such an
API key password certificate will provide a unified
interface to any secret while provide tight access
control and recording and detailing. Audited lock secured secret
stores arbitrary key value secret can
be stored in bold bold encrypts these secrets
prior reading them to persist storage or gaining
access to the robot storage. Using no access to your secrets,
bolt can write disk, console and more,
right? In this case, Hashicorpol could
be interface for all your secrets around
your cloud provider or on Prem's infrastructures
too. How do you can manage this secret out
of the box from the cloud providers and
you can generate this interface and
how do you can generate this process? You can define involved
two granularity definition your
matrix for your teams, how to the security
team generate and update these
secrets about your
modify how you can obtain this
secrets only for your application how you can
pull all together that works very nice
for your teams and your
paths for your successful security in
your company, right? In this case, the pictures show
how you can create a keyboard secret.
First you create a bowl, second you create a secret
and third you can create your secret over
the cloud over bolt for present
this secret for your workload
or for your function as a service out of the box for the
cloud provider or on Prem. Could be you can install this
solution on your machines,
on your ecosystem, on your virtualization. Could be
or the hashicorp
could be generate this new tool for
all deployment that you put altogether.
In this case you can deploy these two
in the Qrnet cluster, could be generate a security cluster
only for storage all your bold secrets.
How to your security teams are managed for this cluster
only for the company, right? You can put
all together and generate separately for developer environment
or staging environment or production environment.
How do you can separate these responsibilities
for all environments? How do the
security team can generate this
new feature for the old company? Because you
can generate a new process,
how you can storage and how do you manage all
secrets for the company and how can you
provide these secrets and how you can get these secrets for all application
around your cloud providers or your deployments
that you generate inside the clouds or generate out of
the clouds. Okay, talking about Kubernetes,
it's an interesting technology, could be increased
a lot of the expectation around
the world, how you can use that in all
specification in your company and how to bury
this route for your company and for your team. How you can increase
all values for your company. That is a good
technology that you can use in your ecosystem for
your application or for your IT environments. How do you
can use that with virtualization or increase
the value for all teams and your application.
That's very good.
Let me little definition about
Kubernetes Kubernetes is a portable extensible open
source platform for managing containerized workloads and service
that facilitates both declarative configuration and automutation.
It has a large rapidly growing ecosystem.
Unreal service support and tools are
weirdly available. Yeah, it's a very
explosion for your mind blow up could be.
And how you can uses QRnett and how to increase
your value for your company with that. That is
a good question for you for your company.
How do you can use QR nets for all your ecosystem,
all your apps, all your teams for generating
new value for your company? Let me check about
the little object inside the QR nets is a secret.
Secret is can object that contains a small
amount of sensitive data. Such a password,
a token or a key information myth other
side but put in a bot specification or near
a container image using a secret meet that you don't
need to include confidential data in your application code that
it's a very nice definition because you can
extract the sensitive data for
your application, for your code, for your
repositories. How you can put
this data inside your application
around your Kubernetes ecosystem that
is very nice. In this part of the picture
talking about the master node, how to work secure netties
Kubernetes works with one master node and
worker node. Could be, but depends for your architecture,
depends for your availability zone, depends for your
replication for your application.
How do you can put your
infrastructure, your application,
your business for all your clients and how to
decline your application for all
your needs, right? In this case it's a
single ecosystem for Kubernetes
it's a master node and worker node. And the worker
node deploy a port, a workload, a container
that you can define your application. In this
pod you can inject the secret for your ecosystem,
right? That it could be a small
definition with QR nets and secrets,
but you can use more around that because you can put
in your pod, in your container
application your secret in
two ways, in three ways. Sorry,
this way is environment variable or a
file or a patch with a lot of files but depends
for your architecture for your application and how to the
application gets this configuration or these
passwords or these sensitive data for
yours in that, right? Depends a lot of your application
how to the developer team will be obtained this data
for generate the value for the application. Talking about
the external secrets external secrets
operator it's an operator that integrates
a secret manager system like AWS,
secret manager, hashicorpole, Google secret manager,
Azure keyboard and a lot of other
cloud providers. How to get this information
how you can get this sensitive data for your
cluster, right? These APIs
connect with the operator and
update this data for your bot,
right. But what is an operator? What is
Kubernetes? What is operator by the new
term operator are the software extension for Kubernetes
that make use of custom resources to manage application
and their components. Operators follow Kubernetes
principles, notably the control loop.
In this case when you work
with operator in Kubernetes QR
net is generate new
things for your teams and how you can increase the
value for QR nets could be just for you and
you can use operator for increase this value for QR nets and
how you can use for your company new features.
That cloud be not generated inside of Qrnettis
is just for you and your IT team and how you can generate this
toil task and you can manage
this task with one operator developed
by your or your team and how to reduce the
time that you can use for generate some
task and you can define this task over the
operator, right. You can change everything in QR nets
and how to the QR net how
to the operator could be generated for these
new responsibilities with an operator and
how you can deploy more easily, more fast
that it's a very extensible you can use
this operator for your teams and your clusters
and how to develop that in your company.
That's very nice that works with Kubernetes.
Let me show you little architecture
high level that QR net is an
external secrets use. First you define a secret in your providers
or bare metal in this case with Azure,
with GCP, with AWS or bold
that it's the last slides
you can use any ecosystem that you define
for your application or your security team could be defined for your
company. That covers all needed for your company,
right? Second you can write this definition
for your file for your jammer file. That is the description
how you can obtain this data from the external
provider and how to obtain these values
for the pod, for your warloat for
your application and how to obtain and how to put in there
how to the application weight. This secrets like
can environment variable or file
or path for folder could
be depends everything about
how the application is created for
the developer teams or architecture team and how to define
code can get this information for
the bot or the application, right? And third
you can use this secret in your cluster in this case or
just only for your bot comes to
the demo, right? Okay. In this
demo we show how you can use stern secrets in
your cluster environment and how you can update and
install first the helm chart and
how do you can use this chart and configure the
char for connect for bolt? In this case first
you need to add the external secrets
held to your installation
in the cluster. This case is this command.
We add the helm repo that name external
secrets that it's linked for this
helm char in Internet location.
In this case we can check what other repos
can install in our cluster. In this case,
repo list how we can shake external
secrets it's added for the moment for our external
secrets for our cluster and how you
can use for that. This enable the
hell the chart and you can use this chart
for the configuration. Second, you need to install
external secrets into qrnaries external secrets with
helm enable helm enable
external secrets that invoke external
secrets chart that install and obtain
external secrets value for this case.
In this case we can generate the
external secrets namespace. But in this moment,
if we can check the currently name space is created
actually we have this name space in our cluster
cubectl get
Ms spaces in this case
we can create external secrets mspace
and don't create this
mspace. Let can copy for that
comment and pass in deers and you can
execute this command. In this case,
helm generates all values for your cluster
and the operator can
be enabled for the cluster. In this case we can
execute part of the operator and configure this operator
if you need it. But in this case we can check
how to can use this operator helm
list in this case external
secrets it's enabled for our cluster in the namespace external
secrets is the fear reservation is deployed
in this case. In this case it's
a lot of object generated for external secret cubectl
get pod it's a
new pod for this case.
In this case external secrets or this is the qualification
for minus. If you can use QCTl
get external secrets or
QCTL get
cases. It's the
same way that you can find all objects in the namespace
for the external secrets. In this case,
don't show any resources because you
need first configurate the resource and second use the
resource for to generate new obtain
the information about the bolt, right? In this
case we preparate
secret inside bolt. This secret
is called my secret
and obtained from bolt, right?
First generate the secret bold
we generate in this case on installation about
external secrets. Now we can configure secret
store from one secret poll jaml check
what information have this Jamil this information is
first create a secret that it's
named bold token. This token is the
communication from the username.
In this case for the root name that can you
obtain this authentication for the
bolt in this server and this
part is just the token for
bolt. But in this cases in this part is the configuration
about the server about what
is the path
of the that you can connect
in this case that is the API version.
How you can hold this secrets store in
this case is bold backend and how
to authenticate for the bolt. In this case use
the token authenticate and uses
the bold token that generate in this secret
the secret obtained when the configuration
happens. It's the first part when
you can check the operation teams
could be don't know
what is the secret. In this case I can
separate the files and
this file is the security team and this file
is the operation teams that can generate
the configuration around what is the bold
service or bold survey that I can use
and this configuration it's the common for
the security team and operation teams
or it team that you can use what is
the name of the bowl that you can generate security team
and how to the security team and it team
define this name for generate and establish
some definitions how
the names about the secrets around the QR net is going
to be put in there. Right next
step just apply this file but
after that we can check that what type
of secrets exist in there. Cutectl get
secrets in this case exists
this secret external token external
null secret token secret store
secret but not it's for that and
is the installation about the helm that we generate
in the last step. All right
this isn't secret store.
Kubectl get
secret store that
announce configuration about the secret store around the external
secret right that's it.
Then apply this configuration file and
in this case generate a secret and secret store
in the namespay that we in there
and check what object generated in
this case Kubectl get
secrets and voila.
That's my secret that I generate that it's
vault token that is the name of the token that we
send in this case with this value and
we can check exactly with secret store that
this bowl back end that contains all
configuration around the external secret and
how to connect with the bolt and
my secret for generate this authentication
for the application. Right in this guide
config external secret from both using external
secret is definition on how to you can uses external
secret and how to before this
authentication you can uses external secret for obtain
the secret from world. In this path
we can check my secret ball this
property for secret the secret generate for my store
configuration. In this case is example sync
and generate a secrets store reference for
my secret. That is the back end the bulb
and it's a 60 store, right?
In this case 60 store is boil backend
ball backend this configuration that we generate in this
case. In this definition how to
authenticate before that it's authentication.
You can use this authentication for obtain this
secret right before the authentication
you can obtain the secret in this path
exactly this secret and put in my
new secret definition example
sync and put in their full bar,
right? Let me check
more simply with the example apply
this configuration file.
In this case generate bowl example that
it's our external secret
generation QCtl get
secrets and voila. This example sync
that contains the FUBAR definition
Kubectl describe
secret example sync and
this my fubar my information
about the secret. In any case I
can use this secret that obtained from bowl from
my pod and inject this secret in input
of my pod with environment
variable or can use for
config file or a pack if I
need it. Depends exactly what is the architecture for the application
and how to can use this secrets for
the application and how to can inject in there
for the pod. We're talking about how you
can use the secret generated by external
secret and how to implement in this case for a deployment
over the pod. In this definition we have a deployment
in this case the example that use
image in nginx
80 and use in this case
that is the important part. The secret username,
right? That secret username is belly
from secret key ref. In this case you invoke
the exam pole sync and
obtain the full bar value. That's the definition that
we generate in the previous example that define
the example sync and generate the few bar that
obtained from the bolt. In this case,
right? Just apply
with this comment qctl apply
and in this case generate a deployment qctl
get bot this is
example deployment, right?
Kubectl describe
bot this pot exactly the example
deployment and in this case we
can check something new in
the deployment put in there the pod
the secret environment secret username connect
the secret example sec and obtain full VAR.
In this case if we can check the secrets in these
deployment in these namespace Kubectl
get secrets we
have example sync that contains in
this case get secret describe secret
that obtain the few bar data
that is the complete flow that you can use define for
first the security team how to
define the connectivity
and authorization and authentication over
the bolt and how to in bolt. You can define
this secret that don't know the
developer team or it team just
for the configuration. In this case for it team this
other configuration that will be generated for the it
team they're using secret and third the
development team just use the secret for
the environment and put in environment for the application.
All process around. How do you can define
how you can sensitive data could be secured
in your whole ecosystem in the CLDC
lifecycle could generate new
value for the company because the
secret that could be eject for the database
or could be something other service or
this very sensitive data the IT
team or development team can't access for that
just for the application and the secure team. And it's at the more
powerful tool that you can use for the connect
your cloud and you can connect the
environmental two for the external secrets and
how you can use this external secret for the
Kubernetes and how to these external
secrets generate a new proposal for all your
company and how you can determine this
for your company new process that the IT
team and development team don't know. What is
the sensitive data? Just the secure team
and the application. No more. In this case it's a good
example for the application.
These slides contains the video about how you can check
this offline. Could be,
but you can
explain in this video what is the part of the
secret? What is the part of GML files using
for demo. You can check this video too if you
want. No problem. You if
you have some questions you can send me
pink over the social networks like Twitter
or YouTube or GitHub.
I hope that you can learn something new.
Thank you for your time. See you soon.