Hi everyone, welcome. My talk.
Right, so before I'm drilling down to statistics,
I want to show you what does it mean to
have security in kubernetes at all? Because what weve
end is in the matter of security perspective and not just in general,
of course. So kubernetes is now de facto
what is called the new cloud native
operating system. And that makes it
a lot of companies. We see that 96 of the organizations
are using Kubernetes and we see it's growing
over the years and like in this year, mainly a
lot of adoption of kubernetes. Mainly this is because
it's, I would say, the only orchestrator
available today that
is managed and everyone is fully aware of.
So having said that, the Kubernetes is
the operating system. What do we need to do? We need to secure our
operating system because attackers don't no longer see it
off the radar. They do try to
bridge in the Kubernetes. We haven't seen any major
bridge, but we do see a lot of tries
and we see a lot of documentation on that.
But still it hasn't happened yet. Hopefully it won't happen
at all. But we need to secure SF in that case.
So what we also see in that matter is
that everyone is approaching to
the security Persona in the organization,
to the CSO or security manager. But what
we do see is that he is not responsible anymore
for security when it comes to
Kubernetes. So we do see that
the person who is responsible for security when
it comes to secure your cluster is the DevOps. Right.
We can see it right here. The. Right. So the DevOps is responsible
for the security. DevOps, devsecops,
any Ops Persona is responsible.
And we do see it comes in often
cycles like releasing weekly releases.
And they are using Kubernetes specifically to improve
the scalability. We're using restraiser because we need
to improve the scalability and
also we want to decrease
the development time. So those are the major point
of why even using Kubernetes and who
is basically the Kubernetes security role in your
organization or in any organization. So Gartner
checked that and said, why do
we even need any Kubernetes security at all? Right,
because I'm often hearing that,
okay, oh, I'm on kubernetes then all good, I'm secure.
Great, that's wrong. We do see that
DevOps are telling us that, or telling Gartner
that the security incidents and issues
into their kubernetes cluster are mainly
into detected misconfiguration like they misconfigured
or the YAML are default values sort
of things. And on the other hand,
what they're worried most is cves
in images like vulnerabilities and again misconfiguration
that can expose to let's say outer network
and so on and so forth.
So having said that, we have like two paradigms
of how to protect Kubernetes. So the first one is what weve calling
kubernetes, posture management. The second one is
the runtime protection. So the posture management is
to find known vulnerabilities and mixed configuration. It's something that
we know in advance, but the runtime protection
is like anomaly behavioral analysis and network segmentation.
We don't know it ahead of time. So what do we
focus in on is in one hand like tricking
the attack surface, and we can detect the
posture management early in the CI CD pipeline.
And when coming to runtime protection then
we want to assure and actually
take an action upon detecting in runtime
if attack has happened.
So in order to drill
to the numbers and statistics that we calculate
and got, then we needed Kubescape,
which is armo's open source for Kubernetes
security. The architecture is
pretty simple. Kubescape as a whole
is an open source solution.
It gets from the cluster, the vulnerabilities and
the configuration issues also from
the git repository and container registries. But we won't focus
on that, that time. And eventually it sends all the data to
arm platform. Arm platform is where I can
see all this data in a very
nice way, I mean UI visualizing way,
but also that's where I'm storing the data and I
can analyze that. So I will
talk a bit about Kubescape because that's the tool that
got us all this information and what we've learned
from scanning with Kubescape. So Kubescape
really became like the majority of tools,
most popular tools in security, open source security
tool for Kubernetes. And it
got really high lately.
And what we see here is,
remember saying that we need the posture management and we see
the runtime management. So here is part
of that. We can see the risk analysis and compliance,
we can see the RBAC visualizer, like what are the roles and
responsibility, a visualized graph of
your RBAC in the cluster, and of course the vulnerabilities
coming along the way in your images.
So we're talking mainly about the CI CD pipeline.
So we need to check everything at the early stage of the
CI CD because we don't want to get into the cluster and
realize that we are having some misconfigurations, right? So let's
check things ahead of time in your repositories, in your
registries, across the pipe, before getting into
the cluster. But when weve in the cluster,
we need to verify that we don't have any
misconfigurations there, of course. But we would like to take
the other step of runtime zeros trust.
So it's super easy to install, it's just a help chart.
Just run the command and you can see it all in the GitHub,
very easy. And of course CNCF sandboxing
recently, so you can see it right
away. So after having this
understanding of what we gathered
and how we gathered this data, so now what we're learning
from that. So, as said before,
what is the user title of those people
in the cluster? Like, I think
around 60%, even more like 60,
let's say a bit more, are DevOps.
So DevOps is the security Persona
that we defined in the data we collected from
the clusters. And the region is like
around North America is half, Europe is around third,
and all the rest. And let's
see another overview of what data do we have. The number of
clusters. Most of the users has one clusters,
33% has like between two and four. And the
cluster size, I mean, how many nodes are in this clusters?
34% are less than five and 33%
are between six and ten. There are of course some
beyond 50, but of course it really depends on the environment
they are scanning. So what have we learned
in Kubescape? We are scanning by framework. We're scanning the
NSA framework, the Mitre framework, the armor best, and the
DevOps best framework. And the average score per
framework is around 30%.
And the score that is lower than 30
is an okay score. Okay, beware. You can
check your own score with kubescape and see in
which compliant framework is the score available.
So the top five misconfigurations
are run privileged container, cluster admin bindings,
missing resource policies, immutable container,
fast system, and ingress and egress blocked.
So what we do see here is 100%
had at least one misconfiguration and
65% had at
least one high severity misconfiguration.
And 50 of the cluster has more than 14
failed controls. Controls are the substitute
of the framework I talked before, and those are the
misconfigurations that we are testing and finding.
So let's drill down a bit to what
we see. So, running privilege container
is a big no no. And we can see the basic
of what users are running.
And if you are
putting some data into the
pot spec, then we see it's not privileged,
right? We can see that in the security context if you
run its user that is greater than nine nine nine.
And the runners group also will be greater than
nine nine nine, you're pretty much safe. But you also need to have the
allow privilege escalation as
false. So privilege container will
run in your pod. Okay, that's big bridge
into your cluster. You can check that out
also in a blog that Banda C
armo just wrote. So the
next thing is we talked about 63%
of clusters that have some workloads that are
exposed outside the cluster without any ingress block.
So of course we do need to check those data,
you need to check the ingress. And in
Kubescape we do check that. But look how many cluster
and look at this percentage. That means that
the tunnel out is clear.
And also the 63 again
percentage of the cluster had workloads without proper resource
limitation. So if you don't have resource limitation then each
container can take as much resources as he wants,
right? He can take the entire clusters resources
if he needs. And that is not just
a developing problem but also it's
a security breach. And 37
of the cluster has like application with credential and configuration
file. So it's so easy to say that. But we
do see that going and repeating
all over. We're checking for password word, we are
checking for JW two, we are checking for
private key. All those kinds of phrases are still
available in the configuration files
and 23% of the cluster had like
application running with dangerous Linux capabilities.
And that's like basic because also if weve running on vms
then we need to harden our application. So again
it's not just related to Kubernetes, it's just manual
thinking. Also previously when talking about passwords and all
those other phrases then it's super easy
to check and also to solve.
So 35% of the cluster had workloads
running with insecure capabilities. So we're checking both of those
things and together we see like
it's majority of clusters.
So if we will take a look
now onto the vulnerability part of
the cluster and we checked for vulnerabilities.
It's a good thing to say that has
zero critical vulnerabilities but they do have one or
217 percent critical
vulnerabilities, et cetera.
Again that's a breach. So if you have any critical
vulnerability is mandatory to fix,
especially if it's a remote code execution one,
it's super important one. And the vulnerability by
severity again is just another view of
the critical and high end, medium and low.
So the top five vulnerabilities we found I've
seen here and what is interesting, that 63%
of the container had one or more vulnerabilities across
and 46 of container had one or more critical vulnerabilities
specifically. And we talked about
RCE remote code execution that we see 53%
that container had like one or more
RCE vulnerabilities. All that we learn from scanning
just this ten K clusters.
This is the information about the critical vulnerability.
Glipc of course, and Lib Cre.
There are very well known cves,
you can read about it also in this blog. It's super
detailed about the container scapula and its impact
on Kubernetes. I must say that we will
get into it in next talk. But when
I'm thinking about what we really learn and what are the conclusions
that I'm taking from that talk is that
most of companies already run like Kubernetes clusters
and security is a big pain,
but no one really wants to deal or handle it.
And if you're taking it to the security Persona, he says no go
to the DevOps. And if you're taking it to the DevOps then he said no
go to the security Persona. That's something that we should
combine together and therefore we see a lot of
devsec ops operation now.
And as I said, DevOps are the new security personas.
So Devsecops is the new phrase.
And we are overwhelmed with misconfiguration
and vulnerabilities. We do see
it's a big problem. And here in Armand we are trying
to figure that out with relevant
vulnerabilities specific for the cluster. Whatever runs
in runtime and not just detected in previous
sets, whatever is really, you know,
onto the, onto the memory at a time.
And this will be continued and we will show it
next talk. So thank you very
much for being with me here today. It was a pleasure
and thank you.