Hello everyone. Today we'll cover generalized product management for enterprises.
So if you're a vm looking to incorporate Genai in your
products or at your company, this presentation is a good overview
of the field and what you should consider when building with Genai.
Let's look at the agenda. First, we will cover what is Genai,
what are the factors that led to its popularity? Whether it
is just a hype or is there a long term trend here,
we will also look into the impact of Genai on various industries.
What are the benefits, and talk about some use cases,
how they line up to revenue and cost factors for a company.
Lastly, for product managers, we will understand what the risks are
with Genaii, what you can do to mitigate them,
and when you are building for them. Is there anything that you need
to consider both for internal use cases and for your customers?
So what is Genaida? It is a relatively new
trend in the field of artificial intelligence. It is a system that learns
from existing data and produces realistic versions
of it that mimic the source data, but are not
necessarily a duplicative or exact copies of the
source data. This has huge potential for us, because we
now can save a lot of time and energy when doing repetitive
tasks, or creative tasks like producing images,
music, speech and text.
Genei is even perfect for coding, as it can learn
from the patterns of any programming language, and you
can design new applications and products using that
capability. The most useful aspect,
however, is the one that doesn't require a lot of technical knowledge to
interact with Genai. It simply works by understanding
natural language of a user. And so your user can just talk to
the tool like they would with any other human being. Let's look at some of
the underlying technology that makes Jennair really effective.
Right? So we have gans. These are generative adversarial
neural networks. This is a machine learning framework where you
take a bunch of real images and generate fake ones that are
realistic. And there is this thing called a discriminator, whose job is
to try and catch fake ones. And as time progresses, the generator
gets really good at fooling the discriminator, and the discriminator in turn
gets really good at catching fake ones. And this creates a positive feedback
loop. So over time, this results in being able to create
highly realistic data using an existing dataset.
Next, we have this other technology called variational auto encoders.
This is another type of machine learning tool that can generate
new data samples that are very much like the training dataset.
This helps when we have a very limited data or we need to fill in
gaps in the existing data so that we can train our machine
learning models we have with
enough data that can produce meaningful results. Then we come
to LLMs. Right? This is the hot topic right now. LLMs are where
all of this magic finally comes together in the hands of regular users,
because with LLMs, you can now interact with these machine learning models in a
human language, because the LLMs understand and can generate human
language as well. And this is what has resulted in the trend that we now
see in the form of conversational AI suggest chat GPT.
Now, let's look at the surge in popularity. Why did Jenny
become popular so suddenly in the recent years? Three things.
Firstly, we have better algorithms now that are able to deal
with vast amounts of data efficiently and produce high quality,
realistic data that resembles the original data. And secondly,
we have really great hardware now where GPU makers like Nvidia
have come up with some incredibly powerful AI chips that can now train generative
AI models at very large scale. And lastly, we have an
abundance of data that is from decades of human generated
content that is all available on the Internet now. So AI models can now be
trained with this data. Now, let's look at where is the hype
as predicted by Gartner. Now,
if you looked into what Gartner is predicting, and Gartner is a research
firm that deals with, that has a lot of expertise in
technology and business feed published research about the trends that
happen on time to time. And so, according to Gartner, a generative
AI is in this region called the peak of inflated expectations.
This is where everyone is talking about it.
A lot of startups we are seeing entering in the space, a lot of businesses
are considering using this technology, and there is a lot of promise and
hope. And if you see what Gartner
is predicting, is that Genai will reach this stage
called the plateau of productivity in five to
ten years. When any technology reaches the plateau of productivity,
it means that it is going to be ubiquitous and we will all be interacting
with it in some fashion on a daily basis.
So there's a lot of promise, and this signals that Genei
is here to stay. And let's look at some more predictions
that Gartner has given in terms of what the adoption
of Genei is going to be in the enterprise space.
It is predicted that by the end of 2024, that is, this year,
40% of enterprise applications will have some
form of conversational AI embedded within their systems, whether it is
internal or external, facing towards users.
And in 2025, 30% of enterprises will be implementing
AI, augmented development and testing in their internal processes as they
come up with new applications and products in. By 2026,
60% of enterprises will be incorporating Genai
in their websites and mobile apps as well,
which all companies now have such presence. So 60% is
a very huge adoption figure. And by 2026
it is predicted that at least 100 million people will be interacting with
robo colleagues or Jenny Eye pilot like scenarios as they go
about doing their work. Which means right now we use tools like browsers
and office and Windows and macOS, etcetera. But Genei
is also going to become very popular and everyone's going to start using it as
their go as a work tool. Lastly, by 2027
predicted that around 15% of all newly developed applications
will be automatically generated by AI without any human
involvement, which is a huge deal. Now let's look at some
industries that are impacted by Genei and what potential use
cases and applications that each of these industries will be seeing
first. In the pharmaceutical industry, Genei can be used for
drug discovery, clinical trial design and patient data analysis.
This is a mainstay of the pharmaceutical industry and Genea is going
to help the main core value products within this business
and in the manufacturing sector. Genea can optimize production
processes. It can automate repetitive tasks.
It can help in quality control as well. In the field of
media, Ji can generate articles, it can help
authors and publishers draft content, come up with new ideas,
change the language and tone, come up with personalized recommendations,
and can even be a good brainstorming tool. In the field of
architecture, Chenai can assist in design and
in coming up with planning project planning for buildings, it can help.
It can act as a good brainstorming tool for architects
as they're going about their designs. Similarly, in interior design as well,
right? You can imagine Genei helping interior designers come up with
ideas very quickly for their clients. In the field of
engineering, Chennai can help with product design, any simulations,
the data that is needed for running simulations, it can fill in the gaps,
it can do analysis on those simulations, can optimize various
functions in the engineering disciplines. In the field of automobile and
automotive industry, Chenai can help with vehicle design, can help
with autonomous driving systems. We have Tesla and many other ev manufacturers
now are venturing into this space, so that is a big
adoption there as well. Similarly, for aerospace and defense,
there are lots of flight simulations and optimizations and autonomous
systems that can be benefited from the use of Genei.
And in the field of medicine and being Genei can help assist in imaging
analysis, we have x rays and MRI scans, etcetera. And Genei can help
both patients and healthcare providers predict the progression of
any disease or condition that a patient has. It can also help
the patients get personalized treatment plans on behalf of the
healthcare provider as well. Let's look at some benefits
of Genai that are very relevant for enterprises.
We talked about the applications previously, but what are the specific
sectors within enterprise that can directly benefit?
So first, as we discussed previously, product development can be greatly enhanced
by Genai. It can be accelerated because with the
help of coding assistance or by streamlining the design process
and creating, helping enterprises create new product offerings
within their core product by incorporating Genai to the customers.
And then there's a field of customer experience where a lot of customers interact
with the enterprises for support, and Genei can come
and help with these interactions as well. Where when a customer is
talking to the support team, the support agents
can have a detailed case analysis of what this customer wants.
The customer themselves can deal directly, first with the Genei
assistant and probably be routed to the right pathways that the that
the customer support team can then handle. And then employee productivity
itself, right? Like for enterprises, when they incorporate Genai,
all the employment employees can become much more efficient and
automate their repetitive tasks. And employees can get intelligent insights
reports without having to do a lot of number crunching.
Let's dig deeper into some use
cases. Right. What are the specific capabilities of Genei that we
know today? First, we have this capability of Jennai, that is in writing,
where Jenny, I can produce a draft output and you can
even ask Jenny what business style should it be professional,
should it be casual, what length should it be? Etcetera. And Jenny, I can
get you started with a boilerplate draft, and then as an employee,
you can start building on top of the draft.
It can also help you in discovery if there's a
vast amount of data, for example, internal employee wikis and
knowledge bases. Employees can then directly ask a question,
vision AI, and get the right answers neatly summarized, rather than having
to find very specific article in our traditional search experience,
it can manipulate tone and soften the language as we
spoke about earlier as well. So employees don't have
to spend a lot of time in really crafting
their messages and their documents. Genei can easily
take that load for you. And then next we have the capability of
synthesis, which is where Genei can summarize vast amounts of
data into easily consumable output. So it can shorten
emails, it can shorten any conversations and chats that you're having
internal company forums, any web pages that the company
has. All of them can be neatly summarized and be made available to
you on the fly. It can also simplify any
rules, and if your company has lots of instructions for you as you're
learning and onboarding into the company, it can simplify all of
that and make those was easily digestible to you. So learning becomes much
easier. It can also like classify and sort content right
again, today, all of this is done manually. Somebody's going and adding
these hashtags and sentiments, etcetera. But generally I can easily
do that. And this is useful both for employees. It is useful
for managers and HR who want to understand what the employee
sentiment is around the company. It can help you even do
sentiment analysis on your customer experience,
on your user research. If customers are giving you feedback on reviews
on public forums, you can easily start that now and get a sense of
what the sentiment is. And similarly like
in the support and customer care interactions, Genai can
basically incorporated in the chat experiences now, we all have
this experience where we interact with any company's customer care via
chat experiences now. So with the presence of Genai,
this all becomes much easy. Now, we have some
advanced use cases as well. As we previously talked about,
there's a field of coding, as we talked about. As developers within these companies
are building applications, they can now use Genai as
a copilot and help with the code generation, quickly finding
the right documentation needed to move forward, etcetera. Some of the
other things we don't have to get into, which we spoke about earlier as well.
In the field of medicine and data science as well.
Let's look at what problems Genei is solving. Right what are
the right ways to think about? If you're a product manager, how do you think
about incorporating Genai? These are the few ways
in which you can do it. One, if you're a product manager, first, you can
think about integrating Genai into your core products, which is
you have existing products that your customers are already using,
and you can think about how you can enhance their experience with those
existing products with the help of Genaid.
The other way is to create new product offerings entirely,
whose main value proposition itself is Genai.
So these are in addition to your existing
line of products, and for which you can even charge a premium because customers
get a much more productive and efficient experience. The other
way to think about is employee efficiency. So if you're a product manager,
you can think about how to solve these problems within your company itself
rather than external facing. So you can think about how do you make your
product team more efficient? How are they brainstorming? How are
they, how are the developers, how fast are the developers in coming up with new
products? And can you incorporate Genai in those workflows? That basically
you can think about the first two, which is integrating in core products and integrating
in new core new products as revenue generators
and the employee efficiency. And the next one is process improvements as
cost reduction genai in a revenue stream. Jenny.
And then cost reduction Genii. Right, so as we talked about it,
so what are the, how do we think about the Genii features and
their capabilities? Right. Let's go a little bit deeper
into that. Some of the Genii features which we previously talked about are
automated summarization, for example. Right again,
summarizing content for people being able to create new content.
For example, your marketing team can now very quickly come up
with new assets, new content and copy that can be used
within the product, within your faqs and help centers
and public landing pages. All of this can now be sped up
dramatically. And then you can use the features of synthesis
of information and you can get customer
case summaries, insights and reporting about customers as well.
Very quickly offer search in a natural language to
your customers. Today, your customers might be searching for something and
you're having to invest in a search experience that goes in
indexes, all the search results. But with the help of Genai, you don't have
to do that. You can. Your customers can speak in a natural language or
type in a natural language. They should be able to find any
data that they have with your company. A little fine
tuning is required for this, but automated actions are a very good use
case potentially in the future as well. So if you have products in
the home automation space, or payments and productivity use cases like note
taking apps, or to do lists, etcetera, or any office
productivity applications, you can also think about automated actions
that your customers can do. As I previously said,
you can think about Genai capabilities into two categories. One is top
line. Top line means that these are use
cases where you can integrate Genai into your products,
external facing products, which means you can therefore command
new revenue. They augment your existing revenue streams.
And then you can think about the other category as bottom line, which is integrating
Genai into your internal company processes like
business reporting, internal communications, knowledge management,
feedback processing, customer support, etcetera. And in all
these areas, Genai will reduce costs dramatically.
So those are the two ways to think about it. If you're a product manager
looking to incorporate Genai, in your day to day life,
let's look about, let's look into some risks of Genaii, right?
So if you're a product manager and if you're, whether it is internal or
external, there are a few risks that you must be aware of.
One is Genai need not always be accurate.
The systems sometimes produce fabricated answers which we call
as hallucinations now. So this is a big risk. If you're,
if you're dealing with something very business critical, you need to
be able to consider. You should be able to consider this before releasing your Genai
features. The other aspect is bias. The data
that is used to train the model can also be biased and this can influence
the results in a negative way and impact the business operations significantly.
Lastly, intellectual property, right? Sometimes it's possible
depending on what model that you're using, whether it is in house or
it is a third party LLM solution like OpenAI's solution,
it is possible that the model that they're using can be ingested
on some proprietary and sensitive information.
And this can sometimes leak information. Sensitive information,
or even the information that you are using or the customers
are using to interact with Genei can
inadvertently be used to train the model and therefore be
available to others outside the company as well. So this has to be considered
now with the risks in mind. Imagine you're a PM
now and you're looking to integrate Chennai into your
product and you want, and you're doing this with a goal to
improve the customer experience or to reduce costs and make your
internal processes more efficient. And you have identified
a suitable LLM to power this experience.
I would advise these as the next steps that you should take. First, I think
you should thoroughly evaluate the LLM model
that you have selected and you have to understand its capabilities and
its limitations. As we talked about previously, some LLMs have
different accuracies. They may be biased towards certain data
sets, etcetera. So it's good to always assess the performance with
respect to what your product needs to do. So you can think
you can grade your LLM based on these aspects, right?
How good is it at natural language processing? How good is
it at content generation? How good is it with automation, for example,
if that is your use case? Always good to think about accuracy and bias,
as I said previously. Next, you have to define the use cases and
user journeys very clearly. And it's good to document these use cases and
share it with your team so that they're all aware and they're able to map
out the user journey and the touch points where Genei can be seamlessly integrated,
and again, this can be in the field of content creation,
customer support, task automation, synthesis,
summarization, or what have you.
Next, you need to think about developing an AI strategy.
I will go into this in detail
sharply, but the idea here is to deploy Genei
in a responsible fashion in a way that ensures transparency,
accountability and user control. And we have to provide some mechanisms
for customers to deal with inaccuracy or bias,
etcetera. And we also have to ensure that the whole experience is
private and no accidental leaks of confidential information happens
when customers are entering their sensitive data in these prompts and
when they're interacting with any. You also need to implement some governance
and monitoring mechanisms where you should be overseeing the integration
and the ongoing operation of GenaI within your product. This could
be setting up dashboards to monitor continuously the model's performance,
to continuously monitor what users are saying in their
feedback when they're interacting with Genai, and always
having a process to continuously improve those experiences.
As we talked about it, when we say responsible AI,
the goal here is to establish trust, because a lot of the
times customers, customers have this distrust with anything that is AI,
because again, they're scared that the results can
be inaccurate, they're scared that it can be biased,
or their sensitive content may be used to train the AI model and
therefore some secret business secrets can be leaked
externally. So what you should do is think about the
following. First, make sure you add disclaimers
in your products when you're using Genaid. These disclaimers
should clearly communicate that AI generated content can be inaccurate
and so that customers can manage their expectations and
exercise some caution. Before using these results,
you must implement some reporting tools so
that when Jenny comes out with some result which the user
finds harmful or violates their community
policies or any other policies that
may have, that they may have, they should be able to immediately report it and
give you a reason why they think it is bad, for example.
And you should be continuously monitoring these reports as well. You should also
give fallback options to customers so that they are not completely
reliant on AI powered experiences in order to get value from your product.
There should be some fallback where a user can say, I don't want to use
AI, but I still want to complete this job that I have for which I
am paying you as a customer. Next criteria is transparency.
You should provide clear messaging to users indicating when
they're interacting with an AI system that, yeah, they are interacting with AI
should not be behind the scenes. And invisible to the user. So it
should be very clear that if they're, if a genai is
being used, or an LLM is being used to provide an experience to the users,
they should clearly know that in the UI, wherever possible
and applicable, you should use citations and explanations. So if Jenny
is giving a customer, your customers some results, or your
employees some results, it is
good to have a source from where this has come from,
so that customers have that added layer of trust that
this is coming from a known source, and it's not a mere hallucination
by Genai. There are some deployment models
that you should know about before you go about actually using an
LL. The first one is off the shelf. This is where
you're considering an LLM that is directly available in the market today,
like for example, OpenAI or any other product.
These models are already pre trained and they're not really aware
of your business context or the customer's data. They're just off the
shelf. Basically, the good thing with this is it provides a quick and easy
way to integrate genai immediately and deliver value for your
products or for your internal processes. Then we have
fine tuned or bespoke models. In this case,
the LLM is fine tuned with the data from the enterprise, and this significantly
increases the output quality, because any
prompts or any questions you have for AI, the answers will
be highly relevant to you, because that AI knows the context about
your company or your customers data,
etcetera. And then we have instance based LLMs.
Now, the instance based LLMs are a version of fine tuned bespoke
models, but they have the added benefit of being
run entirely in house. And therefore there is no risk of any
sensitive data making to a competitor. Or in the case of off the
shelf, you still have that risk. If you are giving some sensitive information
in the, in the prompt itself, then that can be
used to train the ALM and you have no control over it. But in the
instance based model, you control all of these boundaries
and therefore the data never leaves your instance.
So these are the enterprise policies when Jennai should
be adopted, right? When Jenny is being adopted. So if you're
integrating internally within your company, or if you
are a PM for an enterprise, for a b two b in a b two
B space, you are. Customers will also expect these
policies to be supported. One is to protect
privacy, right? So in case of, if your product
allows for users to upload images, and that is being processed
by Genai, you have to ensure that if there are any faces,
they are blurred and there's no potential to for the
LLM to ingest these faces and then later output
some other images using those faces. You should avoid sensitive
data. Make sure that you again give disclaimers to your employees or
your customers that hey, do not enter any sensitive data here, or being
able to detect sensitive data and not even allowing Genai to
actually get trained on that data. The other way to do this is
also to secure data. You can even turn off logging at the LLM side
so that if I enter a query or if I enter a prompt,
the LLM merely processes the prompt and gives me an output, but will
not store that prompt and therefore will not train the LLM.
You can consider implementing your solution in that
way also, and the next policy is to protect PII
which is personally identifiable information. So when using Genei
in your experiences, you have to make sure that you're not actually
logging the user's sensitive information, like their name
or their gender, where they are, their IP address. All of this
should not be going to the NLM. You should also
provide controls for the admins of your
customers so that if they don't want to use Genai they should
be able to turn it off. Or if they don't want to deploy Genai for
all of the company, they should be able to control
and configure who should be able to use it, what is the level of
interactions that they can have, what is allowed and what is not allowed
to be shared with this genei. So this is all good to
have as a configurable admin control settings.
That's it guys. This has been a discussion about.
This has been a high level introduction about product management in the Genai space.
Thank you for listening and I hope this was very useful to.