Hi everyone, thank you so much for joining me. Writing code is
something that we learn, right? But managing a project end to end,
probably not that much. In this talk I'll show my journey of migrating
an entire R D code base from BitBucket Cloud to
self hosted GitLab on my own. But with help of people
along the way, of course, planning, implementation and handoffs. I'll share
best practices for managing a technical project with a lot of takeaways
that you could adopt so your project will be handled smoothly and successfully.
So first of all, hi, my name is Hila Fish. I'm a senior DevOps engineer
and I work for weeks. I have 15 years of experience in the tech industry,
which really allowed me to ee that. The DevOps culture is
what helps companies achieve great things.
I also help organize conferences in Israel, DevOps days Tel
Aviv, and Statscraft monitoring conference.
I'm a mentor in courses and communities for women in
tech and other communities. And I'm a lead singer in a
cover band. As you can see this picture, which is a lot of fun.
Okay, so this project took in total from planning
to implementation and handoffs and the whole works. It took one month
and a half to complete. Is it a lot? Yeah, no, you tell
me after seeing this presentation. So the project structure
looks like that. First, I started out with planning what
to think about things to consider, foresee bottlenecks
and tackle them upfront as much as possible, of course,
deadlines, et cetera. Then the implementation phase,
making sure that GitLab is up and running, and also integrations
for doing stuff with GitLab,
Jenkins and Jira, and other aspects like
security aspects, backup and restores, handling expected blockers,
and also leave room for the unexpected, which is very, very important.
Next up, I continued to the training for the R D department because
this tool was completely new to them. So I needed to make sure
that they get familiarized with
working with GitLab because I wanted to make sure that I
don't spring it up on them and they can really be
sure they know what they're doing before the actual
migration. So this step was pretty important to
make sure that they are feeling comfortable with it.
And then documentation and handoffs. I always leave
documentation behind with anything that I do,
but in this case it was extra crucial
because fun fact, I left the company that I
did this project for shortly after finishing the project,
of course I raised the flag that before even the project started,
I raised the flag that I'm planning to live. And then they said
that they want me to do it anyway. So that's why
I knew that I have to make sure that the documentation
is flawless in my opinion. Of course I can't really tell,
but I really wanted to make sure that I leave everything behind
in a way that they can handle GitLab and not
feel hopeless, right? Because I don't want them to feel like oh,
Hila left now what are we going to do, right? So this
phase was very important. I'm going to drill
down to every aspect in this structure during
this presentation, so we will talk about it a little bit later.
And hovering above everything was the project ongoing statuses.
Because I have managers and the managers want to see
what are the deadlines and really follow up on
what's going on. So throughout the project I
push the notifications about anything that happens and blockers
and stuff like that. We will speak about it also later on.
Okay, so I mentioned planning, but actually there
was a pre planning phase. So when
I got the task, I first started asking questions to understand the scope
of the project. So what is my deadline? If I know the deadline, I can
organize my time and make priorities accordingly.
Why are we doing this? Migrating? Because there are several
reasons why. Doing a migration, we want to move from on
premise to cloud. We want to move from SaaS solution to
a self hosted one or any other internal reason.
So this question is very important because I want to make sure the
project process and outcome is according to the managing needs and
requirements. And if I don't know why we're doing it, I wouldn't know if
what I'm trying to achieve and the way I'm achieving it
really works. So that's why I asked this question
and then I planned accordingly. And any
limitations do we need to do things in a certain way?
For example, GitLab has two offerings,
omnibus, which is the VM installation and helm release
for the Kubernetes deployment. So if I knew that,
for example, my company didn't utilize kubernetes at all,
then I assume I would go with VM installation because I
wouldn't want to introduce entirely new
technology along with new tool for SCM.
Right? Two changes at once.
So I had some not really concerns,
but I really wanted to make sure that if we have any limitations,
I need to know about them upfront so I can plan accordingly.
And speaking of plan accordingly, a goal without a plan is
just a wish, right? So we really need to make sure that we plan ahead
so we can know what we are going to execute.
So once I felt like I have enough information to go on.
Then I created a high level plan.
So this was the plan and it's nice, right?
But a plan is great for me, the executor of the plan,
but the management wants milestones and due dates.
This is how they can measure progress and convey status in a clear
manner. So that's why I've taken the plan that you can see here and
converted it to be actionable and measurable with setting up milestones
and due dates. So let's go over each one telephone code.
This was the step and the first step because this was the, let's say prerequisite
for anything else telephone call to create the project for
GitLab, I say project. We had two
because we had Dev and production. I've deployed
GitLab on the production environment for the actual source control management
and also deployed on dev environment for two purposes.
One to try out upgrades on Dev first to
see if nothing breaks, but also let dev personnel
play with it whenever they want to be familiar with the tool,
but also to work on their own mini dev projects before taking them to
the production instance. So also for the migration phase to play
out with the tool and be familiar with it. But also if I upgrade
it to version X and this version brought some
new features with it, they can play with the new features on dev and then
come knowledgeable to the pod instance.
So everything that was related to the GitLab deployment
was done in this phase. Terraform was
utilized to create the projects and also the GitLab deployment
and everything just covered in that phase because
this was the prerequisite. Next up we had the
networking troubleshooting. So since networking
was handled by a different team, I automatically added a
slot, dedicated slot for troubleshooting, since it involves other
people, aka potential bottlenecks.
Right? So it doesn't mean that the network troubleshooting
was restricted only to this phase. I had to troubleshoot issues throughout
the project, but I tried to map every source destination I could and
have it all checked on this phase. Then the next milestone
is GitLab up and running. We want to make
sure that everything is up and running and we can use GitLab.
This phase included a DNS name certificate
and SAML integration. Then the
next milestone was first a bear repo migration.
I used the GitLab migration feature that allowed me to import
repositories from BitBucket to GitLab. I had
some issues with it, open ticket photosupport and stuff like that.
So it took some time. Not that a lot, but still.
And this milestone really talks about getting to the point
where the repo is migrated to GitLab and
I can pull it, push to it and the whole thing related
to repository management.
The next milestone is the peripheral info backups and
monitoring. So I made sure that I can backup everything.
And when I say everything, I really mean everything. Full system repo
backup and branch backup and also not only backups.
I tested out the restores full system
repo and branch because I wanted to make sure that if
something happens, they know what to do. At that time the
restores wasn't really covered as well as
it could be in the GitLab documentation. So I created a procedure
of how to do the restores step by step,
because when something bad happens we
want to know exactly what to do because it's stressful as
it is. So I created part of the documentation that I created
later on included also the restore procedure.
And also I dealt with the monitoring here. So system
monitoring and application monitoring, the GitLab metrics.
And in this phase I tried to close any loose ends regarding
networking issues that I had until now. SSH and HTTPs
tested throughout from several sources and stuff like that.
The next milestone was a second repo migration and pipeline.
So we had repositories that just you need to
work with them as is. But we had repositories that Jenkins did
stuff on them, right, pause it and then created
or built docker images from files there, right. So I
want to make sure that this whole ordeal
works. So in this phase I set up the Jenkins
integration and the configurations needed on Jenkins
side and GitLab side. I can talk about
it alone in a separate talk because
there were several settings that needed to be done.
So in this phase I really just wanted to make sure that the pipeline
works and tested fully against GitLab repository.
The next milestone was continuous migration,
because in parallel to everything that I'm going to
say here is that migration continued. So I divided
the repositories to teams, so it was coordinated with each team
when their repositories will get migrating. But in parallel
I did also other things like training for my team
that needed to maintain GitLab, but also for the R D
that needs to use it. So I gave them initial intro
on make features and stuff like that, and the gradual login.
So GitLab used, the implementation
that we used was some integration that when a user performs
an initial login, then the user entity gets created on
GitLab. So that was another way to
tell them on the training for everyone that was on the
call and on the meeting to hey please log into
the system, play with it and stuff like that so your user will get created.
And then once the user got created then I could set up the permissions
based on the folder structure. I will mention it also later on.
So everything that was really progressing towards the
actual usage of GitLab was done in this phase.
And the last milestone is that migration is
fully done. I finished walking and
doing the documentation and handoffs and the whole walks and I can
tell you under the migration done section that the back
end repo was the most big one
and the import took time because I tested out on the dev
instance and I saw that their import took several
hours. So I knew that I
don't want to disrupt the R and D in that way
and let them paralyze them for
several hours because whenever I did the migration of
each repository I told them
that hey, in order to avoid sync issues you can't push to BitBucket
while I'm doing the migration. So since this repository
took several hours then I knew that I want to
make sure that they can work flawlessly. So that's why I did this
migration on a weekend, and weekend on
Israel is Friday and Saturday,
so it was a happy Sunday after.
Yeah, that's basically about that. And again finishing
documentation and handles and all this stuff. So this was the
entire plan. I also added some stuff that I knew later
on after the fact, but this was the plan and
this was what detailed and explained and what
I showcased to my managers before
I actually started to work on this project.
So for everything regarding related
to the planning, I created a planning doc that consists of the milestones
that I just showed you and extra sections.
I decided to put them all on this planning doc
because I want to have one place that have all aspects referenced.
So first steps, a mapping of needed steps both on my
side or on other teams so I can lay it all
out and see what can be done in parallel and what should be done Asap
to reduce bottlenecks later on. To do
section was out of scope, high level tasks, things to
do and remember after this project is finished.
Read more so I read a lot of documentation of GitLab and
I saw some stuff that we should dwell on it later on
and we should get back to it because it's not important
right now, but it is important in general. So these kind of things I wrote
under the Read more section and things
to think about. So considerations for annual audits and stuff
like that and some more things to add for the planning doc
because why not? Some addendums that I added were
report issues that I've encountered both on GitLab side
and internal issues. I of course listed them on separate
Jira tickets, but again, it's a centralized place to see any issues
that we have that could potentially endanger the project's timeline.
So that's why I put it here for my managing to view it
here. And I also added some more appendices so access
mapping inbound and outbound accessibility to the current
BitBucket hosting so we can make sure they are open for
the self hosted GitLab offering as well. I marked what
was open, so it was both a place to check for status and have
audit for what is needed. I added those in the GitHub documentation
that I created later on, but during the project it was
a good thing to have that, especially for keeping track of
what is still needed to be done. The LDAP groups defined
in the SAML offering to allow access to the self hosted GitLab was also mentioned
here, and main repositories and CI pipelines to track progress of
what I already migrated and whatnot.
This was something that was added by my manager. He felt
the need to add it, so conf 42 ease his mind. I went along and
marked completed on those that were migrated.
Okay, so we talked about the planning, right, which is
extensive as it is. But I think that we really need to take
a minute to talk about another important
aspect of managing a project, which is communication.
So as you can see here, the most important thing
in communication is hearing what isn't said. Since I worked
on this project alone, it was crucial to update my managers on
the status so they can report back to their managers and to
show them that I'm progressing according to the needed timelines.
So I had weekly meetings to update my managing
on the progress, but also I created ad hoc meetings
with updates on blockers. So either issues that I needed their
attention and help to escalate, or just an FYI,
this is how I'm handling it, if you're okay with it. Cool. This is just
an FYI. Me and my managers created zero tickets for
really everything, and I've written detailed updates and current
stats on each one. I created more tickets if
there were more things to code along the way, and also tickets for other teams
to do things that I need, like set up
networking and provide us signed certificates and stuff like that so they can
run with it in parallel, and then we can reduce bottlenecks.
The other thing that I'm saying here is basically to convey the
message that information is power, right?
And information, when delivered properly without overbearing
the recipient with details, which is important, can help
ease the decision managing process and deliver a feeling of stability
and allow your ongoing independence. Running the project, which is
very very important, especially when you are working on a project
alone and ongoing project takes
patience, and patience when planning things go wrong and when you
wait for other teams to do their work. So we
need this patience, but we also need to think about
hey, this takes too much, maybe we need to escalate.
So this is also another aspect of
communication that I want to tell here.
And last but not least, I had
a meeting with the R D team leaders to prepare them for the migrating
and explain what is going to happen. Plus involve
them in the folder structure decision because how I divided the
repositories, I created a folder structure and each
folder had the repositories related
to that team and then the permissions were set up in the folder level.
So since the R D team leaders are
the code owners, I wanted to involve them in the folder structure
decision as I wanted their inputs, but also which is
something that is very important. I wanted to get them on
board because I didn't want to code from the outside, from external way
and say hey, this is what I'm going to do and that's
that. No, I want them to feel
that they are with me on this, right? So that's why
I involve them in the decision and basically want them to be on
board and feel that they have a say, which is very
important as well. Okay, so let's talk a bit about
the implementation. So we decided to go with
the Kubernetes GitLab deployment and I used
their helm chart which you can see here, we use terraform for everything,
for the infrastructure and deployment. So I had to
incorporate Dell Helm chart in our terraform code base
and GitLab was totally new to me. I didn't know
GitLab at all before that project, so I really had to
rely on documentation a lot since my
tight schedule didn't really allowed me enough time to
play with the system and do some trial and error. So documentation
was very important in this aspect.
But also since I had a tight schedule,
I knew that I had to exercise some
judgment and say okay, this is a must read right now,
but this could wait. And that's why I put it in the section of
read more in the planning doc. So documentation is
very important and the documentation was what allowed me to
choose some aspects of implementation as well.
So only because of the implementation of the documentation,
sorry, I decided to use DB version X which was
not a DB version that was default in the chart to prevent
later maintenance because they were that using that version will
a allow me to upgrade to
version 14 which we used. And it also
supports backward compatibility which is awesome for me. So only
because I read the documentation I knew that this is possible. So that's why I
did it. Another aspect is that I haven't implemented the
high availability feature because it wasn't Ga yet, it wasn't
in a general availability state.
So I toggled in this telephone code. I set it
up to false, but I wrote a comment saying that please check it
later on because as sres we know that high availability
is very important, especially for something crucial like
managing code base. So I just added a comment
saying that please check it out later on and once it is g eight
please enable this feature. And why I didn't enable
it before because I don't want to rock the boat too much and introduce
instability to the environment about monitoring.
So monitoring wasn't really baked for their kubernetes offering.
So I basically did it myself. I went through the metrics documentation
and added dashboard according to what I thought was important
and alerts based on those metrics. And also fun
fact, GitHub changed their official documentation due to
an issue we raised during the implementation.
So they said on the documentation that
set up limits, ABC and stuff like that, and that's that.
And then I set up the limits and we had some
issues. So that's why they changed the documentation and wrote
something like for your own discretion and you
need to test it out first and stuff like that. So it was nice
to know that we had an impact on the GitLab official
documentation. Okay, let's talk a bit about
the training for the R D. Right? So GitLab was
a new tool for the R D department. They didn't know GitLab
at all. Also the glossary is different. They are used to pull requests
and now they need to think about merge request because it was actually a category
in GitLab. In the UI it was
called merge request. So if you're not used to it, you could just
overlook it when you're working with the UI.
So they need to really be familiar with
the tool. And basically I didn't want
to spring it up on them and expect them to feel comfortable using
GitLab from day one. So that's why I had
a training session to go over the basics of
GitLab. So the GitLab usage and main features and basically have
them be familiar with the tool before they actually need to start using it.
I also encourage them to play with GitLab itself on the dev environment
and that way they can really feel safe that
once on the doomsday they know what
to do. I also created a GitLab onboarding doc
with explanations how to change their local repocopy to work with
the remote repo URL of GitLab. So yeah,
you can find it online. But I really wanted to give
them the sense of support, especially since they
used to be each time something happened
with BitBucket we said yeah BitBucket,
our hands have died, we can't do anything about it.
But since now we are using self hosted GitLab,
everything is on us, right? So I wanted to give them the sense of support
and know that anything that they need, we are here for
them. So this document helped me do it because even I
instructed them how to change the report. This was the first step
towards this sense of support. And also in spirit
of sense of support, I created a dedicated slack channel for the R
D to ask questions and raise bugs and get support
for all GitLab related issues. And I also put
the GitLab issues that I've opened or found during the
implementation that are relevant for them as a pinned message
in the channel so they could follow up or escalate if
needed and upvote the issues and stuff like that. So that's
about the planning for the R D. So we talked
about the R D. Let's talk a bit about my team, right? Because I
am leaving the company. But even if I didn't left the company, I don't
want to let them feel or
think that hey, this is GitLab stuff. So only Heli is managing me.
No, I wanted to make sure that they are not hopeless
and they know that they can manage it as much as me. So the competition
was really I think that I covered everything that I could possibly
think of, from how to deploy a new version of GitLab to how
to manage and replace certificates and the summer integration
and what information to provide to GitLab support when you
open a ticket for them. So you would avoid the ping pong
and get the fast resolution as fast
as possible. So everything that I could I covered in this
documentation and I did the handoff with training
to go over documentation and answer the questions because I
really want to make sure that they feel at ease and they know what to
do once I leave the company and they can take it
from there. Okay, so I talked
about a lot of things, right? Planning and implementation and
things specific to GitLab, things not specific to
GitLab and stuff like that. So let's see
what in general we can learn from this whole ordeal
that really for me it was hectic, one month and a half for everything
was pretty tight and I had a lot of things to consider.
So let's see what I learned from it. And maybe it's stuff
that you can take from it for your project as well.
So planning is a must, especially for long term project.
You have to plan ahead, understand the company's needs and why
this project is important and use this information to try and foresee
any bottlenecks and plan how you are going to tackle them upfront.
Derive deadlines based on all information that
you gathered and then execute accordingly. Because if you structure your
plan, then it will help you achieve things in a timely manner and
literally progress according to plan updates.
And collaboration matters. It doesn't matter if you're working on a project
alone or with others, you should always involve and bring the stakeholders
up to speed. Other managing or team leaders that are
affected by this project and stuff like that, including regular updates and
raising flags on issues and
brainstorming and collaboration matters .2 so
it's always best to showcase the technical implementation you're planning to your
team members and manager, first of all to
make them familiarize themselves with the project or
with the system because they need to support it later on,
but also to see if they have remarks and brave aspects
that you might have not thought of. So we want
to make sure that the implementation that we have will be as best
and suitable for your use case as possible. So that's why brainstorming
and collaboration really matters.
Trade offs are a given. You will always have a lot of things to consider
and take into account. I really had a lot of things to
think about and juggle and decide.
This is important. Right now this is not important. So deadlines
and mandatory and nice to have implementations and a lot of things
you need to make sure you execute based on that because
yeah, it's fun to play with the cool features that the
UI offers, but if you're under a tight schedule, you should focus on
what matters. Right now,
documentation really is key, both documentation
that you read while implementing technical and logical aspects of the projects.
So it will help you take the right decisions and also defend those
decisions whenever needed, but also the documentation that you leave behind
because you want to make sure you share your knowledge and preserve the knowledge
because you don't want to be single point of failure, right?
You want to be able to go to a vacation and not have a call
saying, hey, we have an issue with GitLab, please help. Right?
So the quotation is very important,
and that's why I think that it should be given
the priority that it deserves. And finally, last but really
not least, change is hard when people are used
to working in a certain way. You need to take that into consideration
when you plan your project, especially if it's a migration project.
So you need to make sure you leave time for training and familiarization
with the tool. So thank you. I know that
I spoke at times fast, and I covered a lot of things because
I really believe in giving value. So if you have any
other questions about managing a technical project or specific
questions about GitLab implementation, you're more than welcome
to reach out by mail, LinkedIn, or Twitter, and I'll be more than
happy to help you. Thank you.