Hi, my name is Gregoruk and I would like to welcome you
on my talk on the Conf 42 Chaos engineering.
And I would like to talk to you about the test estimation.
Before we jump straight into the topic, I would like also
to introduce myself a little. But so I have over twelve
years of experience in the test or the quality assurance
area. I did manual testing in my life, I did the
test automation, I designed the frameworks for test automation,
I tested the software on the real hardware, I tested it in the simulated
environment, I've designed the processes, I've managed the testing teams,
I connected the testing process to the other software delivery lifecycle
activities and stuff like this. So if you think about the quality
assurance activities, I probably did them in
my life, in my career many, many times. And on top
of that, I've started to work with the project management
activities recently and much bigger teams.
So bringing my experience together, I would like to talk to you about
the test estimation. And second title
to this presentation is how did I become a fortune teller? But before
we start, I have to admit
that I had a little bit of the dilemma. I was wondering
if I should tell to you about
the methods of the test estimation, or maybe I should
show you how I approach this subject so give you
more insights in my approach to the
problem of the test estimation. And I think that you can find in
Google all the test estimation methods, like how
you can estimate the test. What's more important to us,
to the QA people is how to approach this problem,
actually. So let's start to this
topic from a couple of the data which I collected.
So, in Poland, the country where I came from, we have
34 million of people. Among those, we have 75,000
of fortune tellers, bionerg, therapists and seers.
56% of citizens of Poland actually uses
their service. And the price per single service is in range
starting from $1, ending up on even $250
per one single service. And why
I'm telling all of this to you? Well, look at that.
There is like almost 60% of people believing
or trying to believe or wanting to believe in
the activities or services provided by the fortune tellers.
But when I read through all of the
job descriptions on the job markets
about the quality assurance engineers, I did not found any
mention about the test estimation in
the activities performed by the qas.
That's pretty much started for me. I started
to wonder why it's happening like that. And I started
in this business in times when testing was perceived as
some sort of negative activity, which has only focused on finding
the issues and pretty much interrupt the entire process.
And I thought about this like, hey,
why project managers, why people who are responsible
for delivery chain, they want to know the estimation date
or the estimation time of the development activities,
but they don't ask the same questions to
the QA engineers, why is it like so,
and maybe we should look at this problem from the other
side of the coin. So why QA engineers are not
giving the test estimation? Well, my theory
is pretty simple about that. Probably nobody
cared about the test estimation in the previous
projects, in the previous deliveries, in the previous timeframes. So that's
why the QA engineers doesn't or do not
provide the test estimation anymore. And I
think that we should change that, because the test estimation is one of the
core activities. If you think about the testing itself,
if you think about delivering the software,
it's pretty much as much important has the
estimation of the development activities.
So let's think about the test estimation.
If you think about this, what the estimation itself, what is
it? So, as Master Yoda said, it's difficult to see,
because always in motion is the future. And if you
think about the test estimation, well, it can be hard because we're trying to
predict the future. And if you think about estimation,
the people who are doing the estimation, even developers itself,
they are often referring to the estimation as guesstimation,
because estimation is pretty much a guessing if you
try to make it very simple. But for
me, it's more than guessing, because there are certain
rules, there are certain things which you can rely on, which makes the
guessing much core, much more
reliable activity, I would say. So let's think
about this. Why it is worth a while to even
estimate the testing effort? Well,
I think that there are like four key things that
make the test estimation worth a while. First of
all, it helps the resource management. So for everybody
who are like managing the testing process or the delivery cycle,
you can manage the resources. If you know that in project a,
you have still a little bit of the capacity of the
testing team and you can use it to support the project b,
it also can work in the other
site. So if you know already that in
the project a, the deadline is really tight and you do not
have the resources there, you can use the other team to
support these testing activities in project a.
So that helps us, the estimation
itself helps QA manager their resources effectively.
Second of all, it gives us safety. We all know that a
good business is a happy business. So if you will give
the test estimation to the business or to your insight
clients, po, PM, whatever, you will
give them a safety, because they will know that you will not sit there and
they will not scratch their heads asking themselves,
our testing team, what they are actually doing and when they will
finish. So they will know when they
can expect you to finish the testing phase.
Third of all, it is professional.
So there is a lot of rumors
in the QA environment that, hey, if you
are estimating the test, probably you cares very professional in what
you do, because only the best can do a proper test estimation.
Because the test estimation, or the estimation itself, the very accurate
estimation is based on the experience. So it also
helps to build your own professionalism as a person who knows
what they're doing. And the fourth thing, which is supporting
the thesis that it is worth a while to estimate
the testing effort, is that you will gain a knowledge. Because to
provide the better estimation, the more accurate estimation you need
to gain a knowledge, you need to understand in a better
way what you're doing. What are your core
activities, what are the core things which you need to check
while doing the testing itself. So those four things
altogether will make a test estimation worth a while.
So, if you want to think about the test estimation,
we should focus on three main factors.
What we should estimate, when we should estimate
it, and who should estimate it.
Let's start from the first thing, what we should estimate. So the
horse as it is, everyone can see, but what to estimate.
And the thing that I was struggling
the most while I was trying to estimate the test was the
fact that if somebody saw my estimation
of a single testing task, they thought like, okay,
so you need to execute this test like 20 times. So if you
need a 1 hour to execute this test, 20 times, one, it gives you
20 hours. So 20 hours done, right?
Well, not really. Let's think about this. I will
give you a simple example. If you will have a room
where there is 100 of people, and you
will need to take a photo with your phone of
a one person. How much time do you need for
that? Like 5 seconds. Take the phone out of your
pocket, unlock it, select the camera
up, point the camera, take the
photo. Done. Right? Let's say 10 seconds.
Okay, but if you would have to
make a photo of every single person in this room. So make 100 of
photos, it starts to become more complicated,
right? Because even if the steps
are the same, the preconditions or something, which we call
the environment or the setup is different and
the tear down is different, right? So you cannot say that if
you would have to take a photo of hundreds
of people. It will take you like thousands of seconds,
right? It is much more to that. So you need to
know or while trying to estimate, or while you will give
the estimate to someone, you need to underline that,
hey, it's not that simple that I will just do
this activity a couple of times and you can just multiply the time
needed for a single task. Times.
How many times I need to do it? So the first thing,
when you do the estimation, you need to think about what
you will estimate in the sense that the sum of
estimation of single testing task is not a
total estimation. Also you need to include
the supporting activities. So we know that actually the
quality assurance activities can be divided on the
quality check and quality control. So quality check
is actually the moment when we execute the tests. But quality control
is everything what we do around the test
execution. So you need to include the time for supporting
activities like writing down your test cases,
connected them with the test base, with the subject of testing,
with the requirements itself. So provide the two way tracking of
testing and the things which you will test.
Then you need to think about, okay, how much time do I
need to report the bugs, to report the testing activities,
to report the results, to create a testing report, to communicate
this, to discuss this. So all of these activities should
be included also in the test estimate. And on
top of that, we should also contain or include
a buffer in our test estimation.
Why to do that, for the reasons which
I already said. So there is not only like the testing itself,
you need to prepare the environment and stuff like that, but also
there are things which you cannot predict.
So for example, the environment will be not available,
there will be other activities. Maybe you will need to think
about something. Maybe you will need to discuss whether the requirement
is actually correct. Maybe you will need to get some more knowledge.
So everything which cannot be predicted straight ahead,
you need to think about this as a buffer, and you need to provide a
buffer in your test estimation.
Okay, that leads us to the second point when we
should do the test estimation, because there's never enough time
to do all the nothing you want. So by
saying when or asking when we should
estimate the testing effort, I'm not asking you about whether
you should estimate this before, during or after testing,
or maybe at the beginning of the project, or maybe during. But you should
think about this question more about what is the
place in time when I'm trying to do the test estimation,
what is happening around what is like my environment,
when I am estimating the test effort.
And you need to think about many, many factors
here. First of all, obviously the stability of their environments.
So whether my testing environments are stable,
maybe there's a time of a year, like in the summer when
there's super hot and we need to shut down the AC.
And as a part of that, our machines
in the server room, they are pretty much slowed down, or they are shut down,
so they are not operating at the full speed. And that
obviously will impact my testing. And also how
stable is our application? Maybe we recently
had or observed issues with the performance of the application,
or maybe it crashes while we have some certain
circumstances, like exceeded the number of the users.
So that should be also included in the test
estimation or taken into consideration. There are other
circumstances, like Covid-19 it
had a very big impact on all the
activities around different companies, in different industries,
because when you're performing your own activities, there might be a
necessity to jump to the other project and support
someone because he went sick and stuff like that. So as
you can see, when you're asking yourself when you should estimate the tests,
you should think about all the factors which are happening around you,
and that's pretty much, obviously will influence the test
estimation. Jumping to the third factor we
have, who should estimate the tests? Well,
obviously, if it is about the testing effort,
obviously the answer to this question is the QA, right?
The QA engineers. But if you think about this,
is it easy for everyone to estimate the testing? We already
said that the test estimation is activity which is
perceived as something which is done only by the experienced
personnel, experienced QA engineers. Because if
you have a lot of experience in the project, you can give a more accurate
test estimate, right? So obviously you can
bring someone who is like just starting in the QA or
even the IT industry, and he will also be able
to give you the estimation. But it won't be such accurate
as someone who already worked in the project, work with
our application, work within our environment,
in our organization, in our company, and already
have some background in testing, and already did the estimation
in the past. So obviously the more experienced person,
the better. But obviously you can discuss the estimation,
you can perform the test estimation even if you are not experienced
or experienced tester also,
who is doing the test estimation. The people who are engaged,
the people who do care about the testing activities,
who do care about the quality in our project.
So in other words, if you actually do care about
what you do, and you perceived the quality not only as
your job, like, yeah, I need to do is like starting from
eight till 08:00 a.m.. Till 04:00 p.m.
But you perceived this as something more, as an important activity,
entire delivery chain, then you are probably
the right person to estimate the tests.
Sorry about that.
And also while thinking about
who is doing the test estimation, you should also think about
the company itself because you should consider the
structure in the company, the organizational culture, everything which
influenced the testing.
Sorry. So you should think about
while doing the test estimation, how the company actually
approached the problem of test estimation,
or maybe approach the problem or the process of
quality assurance, because it is very important sometimes,
as I already said, and this is very sad to me,
maybe somebody or even anybody or even no one
is wondering how much time
do you need for testing? Or maybe nobody is asking this question
when nobody is asking. Then you should be the person who actually
start this movement from the bottom of
the organization and said, yeah, well, this is important for me to
let you know that I need the time to actually perform
my tests. And it will also give you a comfort that you will have
a test estimation and people will know that you need to spend time
over the testing. Okay, so what's next?
If we know what to estimate, when to
estimate and who should do this, what's next?
Well, the biggest sin about the test estimation or about
the activities which we actually perform as a QA is the fact that we
are not talking about this or we not communicate this.
And even if you think about the testing, you will see that
if something is happening, the sooner
person who is supervising our project,
like PM, Po, test manager, whoever,
the sooner he knows about the issues, the better. Right? So it
is the same with test estimation and the estimate itself.
First of all, you need to communicate this. Even if nobody cares, you need to
say it up and loud like, hey,
I need one week for my testing. I need like full 40 hours.
That's the first thing to do with your test estimation. The second
thing, it's not only about being proud from your test estimation
that, hey, I actually did it, I'm experienced, I did the test estimation.
Yes, I have the estimate. It's not about stopping
there. You need to monitor it. So even if you think about the
ISTQB certification and the foundation level knowledge,
you will notice that there's a mention, but this, that it's not
only to setting up the plan for testing, it's also to
monitor this, whether we are going according to the plan.
And obviously, if we are not going according to the plan,
just update the test estimation. So if you think about
the estimation and actually the safe methodology tells a lot
about this. And there's one rule in safe, which directly
calls this a cone of uncertainty.
So let's think about the cone, which is wide
at this entrance and it gets narrow at the exit. So if you
think about this as a timeline and at the start of the project, you get
very wide end of the cone. So if
you estimate there and if you are inside the core,
you can make a mistake by a lot. So your estimation have
a very big margin. But if you go with
time to the narrow end of the core,
you will probably get more knowledge. You will probably execute
some tests already. You will see how you cares progressing
through your test plan and also burning down your test estimate, and you will
be able to update the estimate with the bigger
knowledge, with the bigger experience, with knowledge about the progress you
are making through the testing phase. And probably this estimate
will be more accurate and will be way
better than the estimate from the very beginning. Is it
bad that you gave an estimate which contained
a big margin? No, because you
did not have a knowledge and experience, which you have right now.
So that's why I'm telling this to you, that you need to monitor
it and update it. And those three things are equally important.
You need to communicate the test estimate, you need to tell about this,
you need to monitor, you need to update it, because think about the situation
when you monitor the test estimation or the execution
of the test plan and updating it. You can
tell to your supervisor, like anybody who's
monitoring or having an eye on the testing process,
you can tell this to him, like, hey, we are not progressing
according to the plan. And at this moment, I can already tell
you that I will need additional two days to fulfill the testing
activities. And if you say it like two weeks before deadline, it is
a way better communicate that,
a way better message that if you tell this one day before the release,
like, hey, I need additional two days, right? That's like way
worse situation. Okay, so if
you have the test estimation, we know what to do with it,
then we will probably meet with one of the most common
issue with the test estimation, which you can
find or which can be provided by our PMS Po, our test
manager, our scrum masters, you name it.
Can you do it faster? So they will try to do
their job, they will try to manage the process, they will try to manage
the deadlines, they will try to provide the best outcome in the
shortest possible time. So they will ask you, can you do it faster?
Aka, can you cut down your estimate? So how we
should approach to this issue, to this problem, how we should protect
our estimate from being but down.
So as I already said, I did a very deep research of a fortune
tellers before I started to prepare
this presentation. And as you can already see,
this might be a little bit funny that you will see this sentence
that your dog is not a cat, but that's what fortune tellers do,
actually. And the first advice from
my side is, when we are thinking
about protecting your estimate from being reduced, is to tell to
the people who cares trying to do this something that they already know,
like, okay, but think about this. I know that you want
me to do this faster, but this is like a new project. We need the
time. We need to prepare everything. We need to
check the critical functionalities, we need to execute those tests. We have a
test plan which you already agreed on. And that's like pretty much it
takes time. I cannot make it faster. I need to do it
good. I need to do it in a proper way. I cannot make it shorter.
I cannot just speed the processing of the data
or my inputs and stuff like that. So tell them
something that they already know. Refer to the
size of the project, refer to the risks of the
project, refer to the impact of the project on
the existing system, refer to the importance of the
clients and stuff like that. There's a second thing
which you can do. You can add additional buffer which can be
cut down, and then it will lead to the situation when the person who is
managing the process will be happy because he was able to cut down the
estimate a little bit. But this can be a little bit tricky and
pretty much it's not a very elegant way. The third thing
which you can do when you try to protect your estimate from
being reduced is ask for priorities.
So if someone will come to you and say, hey, we need
to make it faster, we need to finish testing faster because the deadline is there.
You can ask for priorities. You can say, okay, I can make
it in a shorter time, but I won't be able to test everything which
I planned. So can you tell me what should be like the main focus
for me to meet this deadline? And I will try to do my best
and I will show you this in the testing report, that, well, based on
your decision, I focused on this or that parts of the system
and just do very basic checks on the other parts
of the system. So that's very good practice to do. So not
only accept the decision that the test should last
a little bit shorter than original estimate,
but also ask for priorities. What should be my main goal
right now? If you are telling me so, which parts of my test plan
I can just have only in the basics and which
parts of my plan I should do in a normal way.
And the fourth thing which you can do is use your own authority.
So if you previously
tested through a lot of deliveries for the project,
for the product which you are working on, you can use it as
your own authority and say, yeah, I know that this might seems
a little bit long, but think about this, I did this many of times,
I did a lot of projects for you, I did a lot of deliveries for
you, I tested a lot of deliveries and I never was off
with my estimate. So I know that it will
just take that much time. I cannot make it shorter.
It's simple as that. It's just as it is.
And I know because I did it many, many times. So you can always use
your own authority for that. And I will
highly recommend this method because it will also
build your own image as a person who
knows what he's doing. So it's very important as
well. So to sum up everything
which we set up to this point, well, if you think about the test estimation,
it has two key factors. First of all, there are activities
which are focused on the estimation itself. So you need
to have an answer for the question, how much
time do I need for testing? How much time do I need to perform all
the activities, obviously including everything
which I already said, like the supporting activities, the things
which you cannot predict, the organization approach,
the testing, the stuff like all the things
which are happening around, whether there are vacations, whether there are like
c 19 or any other things which will influence
the estimation itself. So that's the first thing. But the
second thing, as much as important as
the test estimate, is to communicate the estimate.
You should answer yourself to the question who should know about it,
who should be notified about this and how to
monitor, how to update it, what to do with the estimation
when I already have it. So if you connect those
two things, I believe that this is the perfect recipe
for bringing the test estimation back into one
of the agenda of our activities, to make it,
again, a very important and to be perceived
as a very important activity in the QA
field. So in other words, if you
want other people to know what you are actually dont
and how you cares going to do it and
what is like the key activities, what you are performing and to
have the better understanding of your work as a QA, you should do
the test estimation because it is one of the key activities
which will influence the entire process. Itself. So remember
about the test estimation, remember about the communicated and
joining those two together will give you a way better
life in a QA area. And that's
pretty much my approach on the test estimation.
So I would like to thank you for listening to my talk.
If you will have any additional questions, feel free to reach me out
on my personal email. You can find me
on LinkedIn in other social media as well. And I'm also present
on the Discord channel for this conference. So if you
have any additional questions, feel free to ask them. And I would like to
thank you for listening to my talk and enjoy
the rest of the conference. Thank you.