You. Hello everyone, and thanks for having me.
My name is Alex. I'm the co founder and CEO of Stepsize,
where we built a SaaS product to help engineering teams manage
technical deb debt. So last year alone, I interviewed over
300 top software development people about technical
debt, and I've been working on products to help engineering teams ship
better software faster for over five years now and raised millions
of pounds to finance that. In my talk on how to manage technical Deb debt,
I'll share with you all the lessons I learned from these people so
that you can apply them too. First of all, what is tech debt,
and why does it matter? I assume all of you know the metaphor based
on financial debt. There are many definitions for tech debt,
most of which work very well, and this is my attempt at simplifying them.
I say that tech debt is code that you've decided is a liability.
It's all that extra unnecessary work that you need to do to
get your software out the door. And I love this comic by monkey
user, which does a great job at illustrating what tech debt is.
The team is digging that tunnel so fast, but forgot
to get rid of all the rubble they dug out. A bug's causing water to
leak into their tunnel. They're stuck in there because a technical deb these
won't be able to do anything about the bug, and they might even die in
there. That's technical Deb and what it can do to a business.
But let's talk about why tech debt is even a thing.
Why can we never seem to avoid it no matter what we try?
Well, it's because software exists in a world of uncertainty. This quote
by Martin Fowler, who in my opinion wrote the best blog posts
about technical debdet. I encourage you to go read them.
Essentially, tech debt exists because the code that we write to solve
a problem is based on our current understanding of that problem. Now,
it sounds obvious, but let's unpack this a little bit. Even if
the perfect engineers found the perfect solution to a problem and
coded it perfectly, their understanding of the problem will evolve, and quickly.
But left unattended, their code will not evolve. And this
means that our code will soon no longer be appropriate. It happens
all the time and much faster than you might think, especially in a high growth
environment. Now, something else to consider is that it's often the
case that it can take a year of programming on a project before you understand
what these best design approach should have been. That's another
quote by Martin Fowler from his piece on the technical debt quadrant.
However, I've learnt that the best teams in the business do
know how to handle such high uncertainty. Despite all of this,
they use the right tools and processes continuously refactor code that
has accumulated too much cruft and they won't accept Messi code
as technical debt. I want to unpack this last bit a little bit too,
so that we're all on the same page. You may have seen this quadrant before,
and when I say that the best engineers in the business won't accept messy Curtis
technical debt, I mean that they aim for this corner of the quadrant.
Technical debt is not an inherently evil and bad thing, just like
financial debt. It's a tool that we can use to gain leverage and test ideas
faster. Just like financial debt. If we take it on without
being prudent, deliberate and managing it carefully,
it will screw us over and we will go technically bankrupt.
We should never get sloppy and accept any kind of incompetence as acceptable
technical deb debt. We should be aware of the current best practices and
use them. We should write clean, readable code, and we should
know that code left unattended will turn into technical debt.
The best engineers teams in the business have ways to handle the uncertainty
inherent to building software and end up in the top right quadrant.
Now, let's debunk a few myths to summarize the key ideas here.
There's this myth that tech debt is bad and no one should ever take any
on wrong. If you're sending people to
Mars, sure, if you're building software where the cost of failure
isn't high, you can use tech debt as a way to gain extra leverage,
just like financial debt. And just as we discussed, taking on
tech debt prudently and deliberately is fine. And if you have zero tech debt,
you should truly ask yourselves if you're going fast enough.
Also, it's not realistic to have zero tech debt because of
entropy in your code base. That's how Ron parages, who's a vp of
engineering at Carter, told me that he looks at technical deb debt.
He looks at it as entropy in the code base. It never ends and it's
a constant struggle. So adjust your expectations accordingly.
The next myth is about how tech debt is only engineering's
problem. Nope. We'll talk about how
tech debt impacts the whole companys and talk some more about how company
culture, particularly how product managers and engineers work
together, impact a company's approach. These technical debt.
And finally, a lot of people wrongly believe that managing tech
debt properly will slow them down. That's super
duper wrong. If you're managing tech debt successfully, you'll see your
number of bugs go down and velocity go up, and I'll show you how it's
done. At this stage, you might be asking yourself,
but why even bother managing tech debt? Now this is a long
quote, but it basically says that companies who have a strategy for technical debt
will ship 50% faster. And Hugh here doesn't
want to ship 50% faster. That's the stuff of dreams for people building
software. And if you think Gartner don't know what they're talking
about, consider this data point from Stripe, who's arguably the
best company software company out there. They found that
engineers spend 42% of their time fixing
the past rather than building the future. And we
at stepsize decided to carry out our own research and asked several hundred
engineers in our community a simple question. How much faster do
you estimate your company would ship if you had tech debt under control?
The answers will surprise you. Two thirds of respondents said
that they'd ship twice as fast if their companies had tech
debt under control. 15% estimated they'd chip
three times as fast. Now, how the hell can they say that?
Let's unpack this a little bit. Technical deb slows the entire
engineering team down within days or weeks and has
repercussions across the entire business. Check this.
But in software companies, too much tech debt means you'll
get too many bugs, loads of performance issues, and too much downtime.
They'll create more work for QA, more work for the SRE team,
and result in broken slas. All that stuff tallies
up to more customer complaints, which means more work for support,
customer success, and account management. And it all adds
up to unhappy customers. I've heard some version of
this many times. We'd be shipping twice as fast today if we'd handled
tech debt carefully in the past. And I'm sure you've all seen this happen,
too. A feature that you thought would be simple and maybe take a sprint ends
up taking the month or more. Now imagine this at a global
scale. So now hopefully you see why it's imperative to manage
tech debt carefully, and let's talk about how to do just that.
First, it's crucial to understand that technical deb isn't just technical,
it's about people. It's deeply influenced by your company's culture. And I
want to stress that point. So that slide is deliberately blank.
Enjoy it for a few seconds. But to give you an example,
if your engineers are never recognized for paying down
tech debt and it doesn't advance their career. Do you think
they're likely to volunteer to address tech debt? Or if
engineers get reprimanded at these slightest hiccup in the software by people who
don't understand that tech debt can be used for extra leverage?
Do you think they'll take on any tech debt? Clearly no,
they won't. And as we all know, company culture is a
huge topic. But I've gone deep into it and in my opinion, I found the
one cultural characteristic that you should focus on if
you want a healthy code base, and that's ownership.
And I'm not just talking about a hazy concept here.
Microsoft did some great research that we can use to
quantify this and back up our argument. Turns out that
if you analyze your git commit activity to see which percentage of modifications
to each file in your code base were made by the main author
of the code, you'll see that the files with most bugs are the files
where contributors made less than 60% of the edits.
In other words, code ownership is a leading indicator of codebase
health, and you can use it to predict where things will break
and reverse the trend before they do. Now, I want to add a bit of
nuance here so that we can draw these right conclusions. This research does not
suggest that each file in your code base should be owned by one and only
one person, and that they're the only person who can work on it.
That would put your bus factor in the risky zone.
Ownership is a spectrum. It starts with orphan code
all the way on the left, which doesn't have a clear contributor, and therefore
no one is implicitly responsible for its maintenance. This is
a bad spot to be in. All the way to absolute ownership,
where only one person can modify the code in question.
And for each file in your code base, you want to be in the collaborative
ownership zone, where the main contributor made more than 50% of
all edits, but not all of them. And generally
speaking, the code is owned by a specific team, not an individual.
We won't get into it today because we don't have enough time, but think hard
about how you can foster a culture of collaborative ownership in
your development team. It's the best way to maintain a
healthy code base. So you now have a rough idea of the cultural drivers
behind tech debt. Now let's talk about technical debt budgets.
You might have heard about this before. It's the idea that you should
allocate a fixed proportion of your sprint capacity to pay back
technical debt, say 10% to 20% of your
time but how the hell do you come up with that number? Well,
it should change every sprint and it turns, but that it's not important
to explicitly pick out the right number.
Right, but I'll tell you how you can think about
this at step size. We like to think about these technet budgets like SRE
teams think about their site reliability goals. So site reliability
is responsible for keeping software products up and running.
But interestingly, companies like Google don't aim for 100%
uptime. And that's because 99.99% uptime
is enough for their products to appear supremely reliable to real world
humans. And that last 0.1% is
exponentially more difficult to reach and simply isn't worth fighting
for. So consequently, if this allows Google 52
minutes of downtime per year, they'll want to get as close to that number as
possible. Anything less than 52% conf 42 minutes
of downtime is a missed opportunity for taking extra risks and delivering
more ambitious features to their customers faster. So think of your
tech debt budgets like your site reliability budget provided it's
prudent technical debt you're taking on deliberately and you remain
below the maximum amount of tech debt you can tolerate before affecting your customers and
business. You should feel free to take more risks even
if you increase these amount of tech debt, because that's how you'll beat your competitors.
Now this pseudograph summarizes the idea. You want
to hover around the maximum amount of tech debt you'll tolerate. And your
tech debt budget can be in the red. You need to pay some back,
or it can be in the green. You can afford to take on some more.
A simple way to define your tech debt budget is to find the intersection of
things you know you'll work on using your product roadmap and the parts of
your code base that have tech debt, but not outside of it,
right? You pay back the stuff that's inside, not what's outside.
You scope out the work and you'll have your tech debt budget
for your sprint quarter or year if you plan
that prior into the future. And the key idea here is that you
don't need to address all your tech debt right now in one go.
You need to address the debt that's in the way of your key goals for
the quarter of whatever period you've selected. Now let's get
practical and talk about how you can incorporate tech debt management into
your day to day agile development process. And the first question that
you should ask of any tech debt is is it small, medium or
large? I'll define each of them. Small debt is these tech
debt that can be addressed right then and there. When the engineer
spots it in the code and it's understood that it is part of the scope
of the ticket they're working on. It could be refactoring a function,
or a couple of them, or renaming some variables. Whatever it
is, it can be done. Right now, the best way to think about it is
to follow the Boy Scout rule. You always leave the code better than
you found it, and small jobs like these don't require any kind
of planning, and each engineer should feel empowered to fix
this kind of debt without anyone's approval. You see this ownership
coming up again as a key factor. Next we have
the medium pieces of debt. These are the pieces of debt that can
be addressed within a sprint. Usually they should go through the same sprint
planning process as any feature work and be considered just as
rigorously. That's where most engineering and product
development teams fail. I spoke about this with James Rosen,
who's an engineering manager at Everlane, who told me that to
consider how much time PMS spend curating the set of features
to work on, and then to compare this to the amount of time and effort
engineers dedicate to managing these business causes for tech debt. And then
he asked me, is it that surprising that close to zero engineering time
gets allocated to tech debt? Now you
all is good software development people should do that
by asking the right questions and making room for conversations about
technical debt in your agile ceremonies and when planning
right businesses rightly priorities work that delivers value to customers.
And you might think that at first glance, getting rid of tech debt
won't do that. But as we discussed earlier, tech debt
does hinder your capacity to deliver value to the customer in
many ways. So your goal is to identify key tech debt in
the way of key goals. These debt that costs the most engineering
hours and productivity losses, or that causes the most
bugs or other issues that impact your customers. To do
that, you need to document your tech debt and to be clear
about the impact it's having on the business. Only then will you be able to
make a proper business case for any given piece of debt and to prioritize
things properly. And this is where tooling has failed us so far.
As Jake, who's a lead engineer at Uncork, told me,
Jira is a great place to manage projects, but a terrible place to
track and monitor tech debt. Just take a look at your tech debt
epic or backlog, where the 7000 tickets that your engineering team
diligently logged went to die until everyone gave
up on the idea. And code quality tools are helpful
at surfacing one facet of tech debt, but they won't
catch most other types in technical debt. Now,
fortunately, this is the problem that we're solving at step size. We built
an editor first issue tracker that engineers can use to keep track
of tech debt right in the code where it lives.
So you'll want to use these code based
issues that you've tracked to identify this subset of tech debt that's in the way
of your sprint. During sprint planning for each feature, you'll ask,
is there an opportunity to address that debt as part of this feature work?
Or which tech debt could we address to make delivery of this
feature smoother and faster? And then you actually scope out the work.
You import your step size issues into Jira, and you add the relevant
issues to your sprint. You need to have conversations
about tech debt in your usual sprint ceremonies if you want to have a chance
at creating the right culture and managing it properly.
Finally, large debt is the tech debt that cannot be addressed right
then and there, or even in one sprint. The best companies I've interviewed
have quarterly technical planning sessions in which all engineering
and product leadership participate. Engineering managers
are tasked with bringing up large pieces of tech debt that their team leads
have reported to them and to make the business case for the ones they judge
to be the most important ones. To make the business case,
you need to explicitly state which business priorities will be put
at risk by the tech debt in question. So these could be key items
on our feature roadmap security KPIs, like velocity,
much more anything that matters to your business. If the debt
is likely to get worse if left unattended,
you need to explain why, right? So, for example, because many engineers
will ship lots of code in the parts of the code base where the debt
is, and you need to add a guesstimate of how much this
debt will cost to the business, for example, in time, if the main
risk is productivity or bugs, if it's quality or
employee retention, if people just loathe their lives
when they're working on this part of the code base, et cetera, et cetera.
And once leadership has approved each large piece of tech debt,
they can be scheduled onto the roadmap, just like any feature
work would. Now, let's quickly go over the key takeaways
from this session. If you leave with anything, I'd like you to remember
that tech debt is inevitable. It's not that anyone's doing a bad
job. It's due to entropy in the code base, which might as
well be a law of the universe. But importantly, you can
use tech debt to gain extra leverage and beat your competitors.
However, if you manage tech debt carefully,
sorry, if you don't manage it carefully, it will come back to bite you.
And the best way to manage technical deb is to create an engineering
culture of ownership, include tech debt in your agile processes,
and to use step size. So I'll take a few seconds to show
you what step size is about. Companies like Sneak use our editor
first issue tracker to maintain a healthy code base while shipping at
pace. So with step size they can track tank debt directly from the
editor and the issues they create are always linked to the code that they relate
to. So they then use our web app to get an overview of the tank
debt in the code base, prioritize improvements based on what matters to
the business at the moment, and once they've done that, they can
use our dura integration to add them to their sprint and finally fix the
debt that matters. And I'll leave you with these wise words paraphrasing
Arlo Belshi from dig deep tools, who said that ten
x engineers may not exist, but 100 x code causes
certainly do. That's what you're after. By managing tech
debt carefully, you can start using our product for
free on stepsize.com and I encourage you to follow us on Twitter at alexandre
omeyer and at stepsize HQ, where we share the latest and best
content regarding tech debt software maintenance and we like to think these
best memes. Thanks for listening.