Hi and welcome. I'm explaining
quick apps, which is a new concept, a new platform to create
mini or light apps for Android. These mini apps or
light apps can help us to create better user experiences
for our customers without the potential friction
of going into the marketplace looking for the right application,
downloading, installing and all this tedious process that can
cause some reluctance at
the time to use our product or our service, our app.
Starting by explaining what is a light app or a mini app.
Perhaps it's a concept new for you, but it's not so new.
It's very popular indeed in Asia, especially in China.
For instance, the WeChat mini
program was launched five years ago, allowing developers to
use or to create experiences
within the main application, in this case the super app, which is the
WeChat application. These developers can create
games to be played inside the witchat application,
can offer different shops
or marketplaces inside the application,
make payments, doing transactions,
or creating any experience within the same environment,
which is the super app, in this case WeChat.
I have to mention that nowadays WeChat has more than
3.2 million mini programs. So you can imagine
the potential we have with this mini app ecosystem
or light app ecosystem.
Nowadays the ecosystem of light apps are very diverse.
You can see some examples here, most of them from China.
As you can see 360, WeChat, Alipay,
Baidu with different names as I mentioned,
mini program, mini app, et cetera. But also you can see
some familiar faces like Facebook Instant games that are
following a similar process. They are offering casual
games within the same framework, within the same environment, which is Facebook.
And also Uber recently launched similar
approach offering the mini
app. Uber eats inside the main application which
is Uber, so you can buy some food where you are on a ride.
This is the kind of light apps running on top of
another super application. But there is another case, a standard
case, which is the PWA, the progressive web application.
This is the standard of W three C to create light apps
and this might run on top of the browser so the browser can
be considered as well as a super app. There are some other examples like
kios, apps for the specific operating
system and some other proprietary formats
like app clips which is the format
for Apple created specifically for their operating system,
following a similar approach but running directly on the operating
system and being considered similarly
as a native application but running on top of the operating system.
Some other approaches, this case for Android and
also as you can see, very diverse from instant
apps. The apps for Amazon based also on web
technologies, Android Go which is a reduced version of
the native Android applications and some others like the
approach of a web app apk to
pack that web application PWA into an Android
application. And there is another set of mini
apps which is called quick app.
This is another version of light apps
running on top of Android. And this is what I will present to
you today in w three c. We are trying to reduce
the fragmentation of the market so you can see in this big
bubble in the middle that what we are trying
to achieve, we are collecting requirements from all the
potential vendors of the mini apps and we are trying to collect all
the minimum features or the common features from all the
versions of the mini apps, trying to standardize the format,
the delivery and also how to describe
the metadata of miniapp. We are collaborating with some
other groups in WC, like the progressive web application working
group, in order to align both approaches
and having a common understanding and interoperability
among technologies. So you can see that this fragmentation
of the market is trying to be solved, at least with
the maximum number of miniapp vendors
into a common w three c miniapp specification.
I will present quick apps which is a specific implementation
of this standard work in w three c.
The MiniApp standard Quick apps is a framework based
on view js. So following the model view view model
approach to create miniapp for Android.
So like you can see in this picture, we can create
native like applications like the one here.
And the user only needs to scan the query code or tap on
a link and just enjoy in the experience so they
don't see any process of installation.
Here you can see the high level architecture,
quick apps the platform. You can see that quick
apps are running on top of the operating system and quick apps might
run in parallel with native applications and web applications.
So all these three types of applications might coexist in
the system. The developers, sorry, the users
can experience native look and feel features, so they
might experience the same as in a native application,
also with the same performance. Because they are running directly on the
operating system, the end users only need
to scan a quercode, tap a link or clicking
on a banner and just run and enjoy the experience
of the quick app. These are very useful
for creating specific task oriented
services like transactional services. When you are in the
street, when you are in the move, you have to pay for a parking,
checking for some information about real traffic
information, so many different things that
you require direct access to some service and without
the minimum friction to get to
access this service. In terms of developers,
what we can achieve with quick apps, we can have access to
the system APIs, the native APIs, advanced system
APIs like access to the calendar, access to
the list of contacts. We will be able to push
notifications to the user based on the native capabilities of
the device with less code. It is estimated that
we only need the 20% of code lines done
in a native application and we will have
the possibility to use pre builtin user interface
components and also prebuilt services that can
access to these APIs of the device. The quickup
platform also allow us to control the full lifecycle of the
product in terms of marketing and other aspects like the
discoverability of the product or the application,
user acquisition, monetization and user retention.
So we have the possibility to create
more discoverable applications using different capabilities
of our device, using the widgets in our device,
creating search results based on the global
search engine of our device. As you can see on the right
hand side, the right picture where
some of the applications are listed there. But in
the case of the Quick app, you only have to click on the open button
instead of install button. So you also can discover
the quick apps in websites, also in links from
other application native applications or quick
apps. So we have deep links to go
specific to specific parts of the application and
also we can have as the rest of the native application all
the quick apps listed in app marketplaces in the existing ones.
Or we can create some new directories to list these
quick apps. In terms of user acquisition,
we have also some mechanisms. You can see the relation
with the discoverability and this user acquisition. It's very easy
to find a quick app somewhere on the web or on
some banner and just click and start
using the application. So enhancing the
user experience because you are not leaving the environment,
you don't need to go to other places. So you
just click and start enjoying the experience. So there
is the minimum friction in this process
of acquiring new user.
Also we have some possibilities to include specific
services based on the implements of the vendors
for user identification. In case you have some
existing account in your device, only with a click
you can log in into this quick app, reducing as
well the friction of registration and collecting information
about the user in terms of monetizing
your product, your application. This is also straightforward.
We can include miniapp payments. It will depend on the implementation
of the vendor. You can implement your own method or you can rely
on third party payment mechanisms.
And also you can add advertising
in ad adverts and also rewarded ads
videos, the ones that you can use for your casual games.
Well, this is a good way to monetize your
applications very quickly and very indirect in
terms of user retention. Once they are using
the application, you will be able to
offer the possibility of storing
or creating a shortcut in the desktop
in the same way as the rest of the native applications.
So with a simple prompt the user
might agree in registering or
adding this shortcut in the home screen. So at the end
they will be able to repeat the experience and just
experience this application like a normal
application, a native application, traditional one, but just
with this brief step, very straightforward
in terms of user retention as well. We have some possibilities to
engage the user for marketing
purposes. We can send push applications, we can offer
possibilities of crossing data between
different quick apps. We have also putting banners in
the apps native or also
in the web to engage the user
in another experience using the same quick app.
I will explain a little bit about the framework, how to create a quick app,
and some details about the technical implementation that could be interesting
for you. The framework the platform
follows, as I mentioned, the view JS framework.
So it follows a model, view V model approach.
You can find some similarities if you are familiar to this
framework. In this example, the example shows the
typical structure of a page in a quick app.
You see three different parts, templates,
script and style. It's very obvious.
The first part template is about the
declarative rendering of the page, the structure and also
some static information. And you can see some
variables there using the mustache notation
that it's for the data binding. Using the logic
part from the script in the script, you can see how we can declare some
variables that will be used by
the template part, the rendering part, and in this
way we can bind the information between
these two parts, the logic and the templates. We are
following virtual dome manipulation with this,
so the refresh will be very quick and
the experience will be quicker.
And as you can see here, we use also style
sheets based on CSS. But the good part is we
can include natively the preprocessing of
CSS using place and SAS. So you see
this example, I think it's very intuitive, very simple to
understand, but let's see the
basic example of a components in a quick apps page.
Regarding the architecture of the platform of the Quickapp platform.
You can see here a high level diagram.
In the top we can see the front end framework,
the one you can imagine based on the previous example,
we have a domain specific language, something similar to
HTML. It's not the same, but very close to
HTML. The style and the layout based
on CSS, as I mentioned, not only CSS, but we also
have the possibility to preprocess using some
advanced variables and some specific
functions using less and SaaS preprocessors,
and also some possibilities to implement
APIs and services based on the underlying device.
Services and apps with user interface components,
basic ones and also some others we can include by ourselves
and reusing by ourselves and controlling the app
lifecycle and the lifecycle of all pages of
our quick apps. In the center we
can see two main blocks, which is the most important ones
in the Quickap platform, which is the JavaScript engine,
currently implemented on a v eight engine.
So a JavaScript engine, very powerful and separately
a render engine. So you can see two different engines
that can help us to provide more
performance to the quick app at the end using the system
we have in green.
Behind the two engines we have the JavaScript
bridge, which is the link between the platform itself and
the underlying operating system, and all the specific APIs,
native APIs of the system, the operating system and tied
to the device,
the runtime platform. Based on the previous example
of the architecture, we see that the two main engines,
the JavaScript engine and the rendering engine,
are running in separate threads.
So this is why we can have
better performance than some of the,
let's say the other types of applications.
So the JavaScript engine is running all the logic,
the pages and the components of this script part,
and the rendering engine refers.
It's rendering the pages and the components using the
templates. This information about how to model,
structure and offer the information to the user also creating
or based on the style sheets we defined in
the previous example for instance. And these two engines are
communicating one with the events produced
by the user. And the JavaScript engine is sending
back the data to populate,
to populate and to refresh the
information in the pages shown to the user.
And in the bottom you can see also the JavaScript
bridge, which is the bridge that should be created
on top of the operating system that links the
platform with the device.
You can create your user interfaces
very quickly and very intuitively with these prebuilt components,
some of them pretty similar to the existing ones in HTML.
As you can see the a for links or span or tips,
but some other more advanced like rating for instance
if you want to include starbase ratings for reviews
on your products, for instance, and also some other possibilities
like adding tabs with just an element,
or if you want to add the element of pull down and refresh like
in the native applications if you want to refresh your page.
These are the prebuilt components. You can create your
own components, custom components, and you can
export them, import them and reduce them in
a flexible way. Also, you can use the
existing ones in the open source repositories that are available
already. If you
want to enrich the experience of the end user, you can make the most
of the device. They are using these services
and APIs that are very advanced and can make
the most of this experience. You can access to specific
information about the device. You can query information about the application,
about other applications in the system. You can
have direct and intuitive access to databases,
local databases. You can share information with other
applications. You have the possibility to use the native device
to share content with other applications installed
in the device.
You can make the most of the features of the device, accessing to the
contacts, the calendar. You can set alarms
on the device, controlling the volume,
assessing information relevant for
the operation of the quick app. That could be, for instance,
the level of the battery or the type of the connection you have
in every moment if you are connected through WiFi or on
these kind of things, and also the vendors,
the quickup vendors, the specific platforms might implement
specific services for the
capabilities to make the most of the capabilities of their platforms or
their devices, and also their cloud based
services. So there is a full range
of services and APIs we can use to make the most of the
experience delivered through quick apps.
So far, quick apps is only supported by Android devices,
but there are billions of Android
devices out there, so this is a good start. Our objective
is expanding this quick app platform to other platforms,
to any device with the target of having a
universal platform to run these quick apps or mini apps.
Also following the standards in WC, aligning with
the existing standards, and the objective of having this universality
and interoperability between platforms, we know that we
need more documents, more code, more examples
and more engagement from the community. So this
is why we have started the Quick Apps initiative.
We recently launched this interest group. This is an open
source community group hosted by the open source
consortium called ow two, which is vendor
neutral. Anyone is invited to join can contribute
with us. You can be a company, an individual, a developer,
and you can join our task forces in a collaborative
effort to create more documents, more examples,
also to create joint marketing
opportunities and any possible collaboration you
might imagine. So just scan the QR code, subscribe the
mailing list and join the initiative. As I mentioned, it's vendor neutral,
open, transparent, and you are invited to join.
So thank you very much for having with me. I hope you
like Quick apps the mini apps and this light app
ecosystem, and hopefully we can meet
in this interest group in this quick app
initiative, and you will be more than welcome. Thank you.