Hello everybody. Today we'll talk about corning and specify
in my case the corarning by project,
the project called Swap. You have QR code to be able
to retrieve my slides on slides.com.
Before dive into the subject, let me introduce myself and
make my self promotion to you. My name is Steve Combrak.
I'm from really in France. Sorry for my get
accent but I try my best to speak as well as possible. You can
find me on GitHub searching Darkwick and Darkwick underscore dev
or Twitter. I'm creator of a cache system called Swan
Reader in Go, Im Trfik Helper, traffic ambassador
and active open source contributor and
also and freelance too. So after that we
can dive into the beautiful world of
Go and see together. What are the
issues in Go? And I
try to teach you what are the main conflicts
with Go. We will talk about Golang
story because Go is very
young language. It started on 2003
at Google but open sourced on 2009
by Francis McCabe and case Clark.
Google tried his
own language to answer some performances issues.
It's written in c, but you don't have to know
c language to code in Golang. The advantages
of Go is you have one binary
file as output. You can build cross platform for
macOS, Windows and Linux for example.
It's really easy to learn. You can
do multi threading and concurrency really
easily and it's really easy to
learn it because it's not a tricky language.
Here are some software using Go.
The first one is Docker, it's a famous one.
It's the soft to manage
containers for those who doesn't know. And the
second one is Kubernetes for the open
source name and Borg for Google instance.
It's an orchestrator to manage containers.
And you have other software like traffic
or Mercury. But Go is not
really for Ops. And you can do some
web app using Go.
For example Hugo is static
website generator from Markdown and
Yaml configuration file. You can
do fail to ban like using bad
actor and you have
a reverse proxy called Gadi to serve PhP
app or any web app instead of
using Nginx, Apache or any other reverse proxies.
So what is my history with coding? Let me
replace the context. I'm traffic contributor
and traffic user since one four.
I'm also helper and traffic ambassador. So any other names
to describe this? And for those who doesn't know traffic solution
yet, it's a reverse proxy written in go to help
you to manage container architectures. And it's a
container first approach. It's designed to manage containers,
it supports the odd detection deployment,
the scaling, it load balances your request automatically.
Only a specific port for all protocols, then traffic manage
for you the service resolution depending Austin
entry, then it's a pivot point of your infrastructure.
And after months to use this solution, there was
an issue I was facing too. There wasn't any cache
system internally to traffic. Then all
requests would have to resolve the associated service.
Then it took many milliseconds to be done and I searched
after cache system solution but nothing appeared to be as efficient
as I wanted or it was only poc.
So after many nights spent to look after that I decided to create
my first program in go. Because traffic is regional in go two and
it souin good. So this project
called Swan is actually in version one
five two and for the record the release names are
free beer names because I love to drink beers. So we witched
over the 100 stars
and don't forget to leave one because I've got an oversized
ego and I like to view the Stargazers count
growing. So the first thing in go I
have to teach you is that Golang is normalized
through some variable environment
variables like the Gopath.
The Gopath will tell to go, where to
find binaries, where to find your sources,
your dependencies and the normalized
architectures. So under your
Gopath it's normalized architectures.
You have bin folder, PKG folder and
SRC one. And I made a
table to resume what
is the goal of which folder?
So sources contain the readable development
sources with your dependencies.
The PKG contains copackage
objects compiled from SRC directory
and your go source code packages, and your bin
folder contains fully compiled go software based
on PKG objects.
Then after the go path you have your go
route which is the Golang
SDK path. It tells to
go which version it has to use and
you have one of the most
useful environment variable, the goos.
It tells to go which kind of OS
it has to build for. By default it
will use the OST OS.
If you are on macOS it will use Darwin,
on Linux it will use Linux and Windows it
will use Windows. So go OS isn't really
important as standalone environment
variable, but you can combine it with the
goarch to tell Go to build
compile for a specific arch with a specific OS.
With that you can do cross platform
build and build for Windows even
if you are on macOS and Im
64 with an rim laptop.
So you can do some matrix to
build for any os with any possible
architectures, so it will generate over
hundreds binaries, but you'll cover every
system with that. So now we
can go to the next section which is
the live demo. You have QR code and
the plane URL to clone the repository
and practice with us during
this session and learn to develop in Go.
The first thing to do with Go is the
editor. So let's see together how to do
our first Edward. Then we will
deep dive into the language,
complexity and concepts in go.
So let's begin together.
I just cloned the repository.
We have main go file to
tell Go. It is our entry point.
We can run only main packages
with a main function with Go.
So if I try to run my main package,
I can just type go run main go and it
will run my go file. So if I
do that, I'm absolutely doing
nothing in my script. So let's
type simple hello world in the console.
So we have the FMT
package which expose some
methods to be able
to debug our code or print something
in the console. So we
will print with a new line our
hello world. It's a little bit laggy because I'm
recording, so sorry for the
inconvenience. Then if
I save and I run main
go, it prints hello world in the
console. Now we have our first hello world working.
We have hello world in the console, but the
softwares we build with go are not easy
like a simple hello world, and because we want
to make some calculations
or any other operations.
So let's see together an
advanced mode of go. It's go routines.
The Go routines are basically a part of a logical thread.
Then go sits on it to
be as efficient as it is,
because the wall language is built
around the go routines. So let me explain more
precisely, what is it? It's asynchronous,
detached from the main thread. Then if you
kill your main thread, the go routine won't
be able to talk with your terminal or
your instance, the instance
it was called by. So we
have to take care about keeping
the main thread running to be able to get
back the data and be sure the
souin is finished once the
main thread will be closed. So let's see together
how it works. Okay, so now I commented my
hello world print and we can go under
grutins folder and create main go
file. After thats we create a function called
go routines. It will return absolutely nothing.
And we can do a simple loop for
an iterator initialize. Thats zero. We can
tell if it under ten with an
incrementation by one just print
something and it will be
sprintf. Then from the
main thread, the main method iteration
like that and just pass our iteration
and we can tell that we have another
function. This function will be called for example
my detached function like
thats and just copy this.
Or we can tell we will give it
an iterator like thats
and that's it. So to call it
we can tell my detached function,
pass an iterator and we can share our
iterator here between
the detached function and the
main function. But if I do that,
it will be a synchronous was. So the
first will be the detached function. Then after
he finished it will run this part of code,
but we want to run them was a detached
mode and concurrency. So go run main
go we have the main
obviously it,
then we have our detached iterations,
then after that the main iteration.
So to run it as concurrent c just
add the go keyword before our function. Then it
will create a new logical thread and just
run it inside it.
Just run like that. So the main method
iterate ten times, but the
detached one at the time to iterates
only four times because the
go instantiation will take some
microseconds. But during this time as
it in synchronous, our for
loop will be running before the
detached will start. So to
be able to wait this, we could add
a simple time sleep, then tell
okay, you will sleep for 1 second
and I have my iterations,
then it sleep
for 1 second and close the main thread.
So that's why we have our detach method here.
So that's not a really clean way to do
that. If you want to wait for go routines, we have
something from the sync package called weight groups.
And what is a weight group? It's a pool of
go routine and it will tell. Okay,
while all go routines didn't finish,
I will just wait for it. To achieve that
we have to define a variable called wg, for example
for weight group from the sync package and
weight group after thats I
can just tell, okay, my weight group will add
a new asynchronous function and
we can just pass our weight group to
our detached function.
I will group my declarations and
here we want to pass our weight group.
So it will be pointer because we
don't have to copy our weight
group pool. Then we could
do just wg
done. But it's cleaner to
tell before reach the end
of the function. So you can use the keyword
defer to delay the execution
of what we placed after at
the really end of the function. So we
will delay the done, and now
we can pass our reference like that.
And now let's
printf print ln. And that's
it.
But if I do that, it will run and okay,
it won't wait for our detached function
end. And to do that we can do
just wg wait and
just run like that. So we
have the first iteration, the second,
and even if I add some sleeping
here, for example,
millisecond,
and I will do the same thing here.
And here I will sleep for half
second.
And now we have our detached between
main method and everything is running.
And while we don't reach the end of
the function, it won't close the
go routine, so it will wait for it. So now
we've seen the easy was for managing
go routines. But we have another concept
in go called channels. So what is a
channel? A channel is like a pipe between your
main function and your goutins. You can
push and pull data inside it.
You're able to tell okay,
I'm at this step, and if
I send you that, you can do this,
or okay, if I do that, you can close this
or like that. So let's see together
how it works and what are the main
issues. So, now we can
delete our go routines.
I will copy everything except the package
name, thats. And I can
remove this. I will go inside channel folder,
main go and just
pass this. We can
remove references to weight
group,
like that. Like that.
And now I would have to use the channel.
So let's instantiate a channel,
just temporarily channel with make and
it's a channel. And my channel will contain only Internet.
We can pass absolutely anything, the interface
or your type or anything else thats
just for the
behavior. And tell to go, okay, I will send
you that under it, like that.
So in my champ channel I
can push data. So if I try to tell
I want to pursue an
integer, then if I try
to print this,
I can do it like that.
Then it will wait for an incoming value.
So we send it here and it will print
this, and it will print if the channel
is closed or not. And to
block the main thread we can do that.
So while I don't receive value anymore
after this, and after this reading,
I will block the main thread. So we
have to edit our
main function. So that's
not growoutine,
but channel like
that. So if I try to run go, run main
go, it will create a deadlock,
since all go routines are not up
anymore. But to
patch this, I have to use my
channel here it will be an integer
channel and I can defer thats
one will be considered was true.
So I will create a simple function and I
send data in it and I have to pass
my temporarized channel.
I do that I
would be able to read data in it but
it doesn't. But if
I try to read data like that then
I get my one. But here I
don't get any data and all go functions
are stopped.
So we could just move
this and replace the
plane temporal channel.
And to read data in it can get
the value and the open or close
and just debug these values.
And I got true because it's open and
one because I send the
value one in it.
But if I tell okay I will close
my channel here. I don't want to get any
data anymore to be pushed
in it. Im able to do that like
this and I
consider thats this will be longer than
the temporized channel.
When doing that I got zero because
I've got nothing and the default value is
zero for an integer and false because it's not
open anymore. I think
we cover the main part of
the channels now I think we can go
further and go the next step and the
next tips would be the testing
because I came from an environment that
we didn't test really,
we didn't test a lot. So while
I'm discovering Golang, I discovered the
unit testing and go is really well,
it embed the test inside the
language itself. So we could just
comment this. And I
don't have folder containing test,
just create it testing or
just test main go.
So we will have some functions
like two is two,
so it will return a boolean
and here we take an integer
and tell see
if n is equal to two.
And obviously I have to return this
for example Frank,
which will return an integer and return
two plus two. And if
I want to go further I can tell fizz buzz like
so it will take an Internet and
return a string and if n
equal to zero I will return
this n
module.
Here I return unbuzz
and the default
will return buzz for example.
So to test this I have to export
my function. We can create a
go file, your go file underscore
test. And if
we want to create a function to
be tested, generally it's
an exported function and it
will ensure that for
example test frank,
two plus two it will
use testing package and in that we
can have some asserts.
But that's really low level and
you don't have any helpers.
So my function two plus two
will return four. So if Frank
two plus two is
different than four, we will throw an
error,
should return four.
Then if I do that,
it will pass. So just run using an
ide, because I'm a nerd,
not really a nerd. So it will compile and
I'm a noob. That's the good word. Then it's
okay, my tests are green.
And if I enable this and
I say okay, two plus two for me,
should return three,
then it will compile, then the test fail and it
should return four. That's it.
But if you're absolutely sure,
two plus two should return three, so you can
tell to your code, okay, I just return three and
it's okay. So now
we've done this test,
what are the other functions?
Two is two like that.
So it will implement the testing package and
just tell if
hang to these two, three.
So if it returned true here,
it shouldn't, then just show
three is not two.
And I will disable this.
And f for the two,
it will return false,
two should be.
So that's really useless here,
but that's for testing. So it will
test any cases like it's unit
testing. And now we
will test the fizz buzz.
And now we want to run
this, what I've done in Fisburg. So if
I try to return something
like if Fizzburz
from zero, different fizz,
I think if it's different than fizz,
then I can display a narrow
message.
For zero, it should
return fizz. And if
fizz buzz, one return buzz,
no buzz.
Yep. And for two,
it should return buzz.
And for
this, it should return buzz.
And that's it. So if I
run it,
we can see everything, every test path,
and we can run tests like go
test on each
packages and it works. But I
prefer on my ide because it's visual.
And to explain, it's simpler.
So if you want to go further, you have a more
explicit example in the solution.
You will run, what is the word,
a web server, you will send JSon response
and any other things using
what we've seen together, so little
useful tools. For example, for testing, you have gotest
got tool for tooling and for linting and
best practices you have golint.
It will tell you you're so bad,
that's not the right way to do that. And the same
thing for govet, but govet
will under any bad
implementations or not just the
syntax, for example. So here are some
examples using that,
some useful commands, go import,
go FMT, et cetera. But I think you know
already these commands and some
useful links. And thanks to Avelino
for making this repository
exist. It will aggregate the
data related to code language and
if you want to read something you'll find obviously
on this repository. So you have code wars
and coding challenge to change you on catas.
So that's little exercise. It takes around
five or ten minutes to be done and
you can see the other responses when
you find something working and
you can see better comprehensions or
faster script.
And I'm working on other side
projects so im working on Smurf.
That's an open source pen test oriented platform written
in angular for the front end, PHP for the back.
That's a good project to help you to manage your
pen test missions or just pentest.
I created Swan WordPress repository
to be able to manage Swan through WordPress admin
and there is the same thing for Prestashop
created by Luke. So take a look
at this. That's good project especially for
smash and I think I'm done here.
Nah thank you everybody for your attention
and im available to discuss about some
things. So like Gordon Ramsay is saying
thank you so much and thank you to comfort to
organizers team.