Welcome everyone to our presentation on AI integration for developers
with a focus on chat, GPT and copilot. I'm Mihaelaroxana
Ghidersa and I'm excited to discuss with you today some of the ways we
can use AI in our everyday tasks.
A little bit about myself. I'm a software engineer.
Right now I have the role of a technical lead at
Signet Health. Whenever I find that I have something
interesting to say, or maybe if I learn something new
that I find that it would be useful for other developers to
use too. I prepare presentations like
this one today in order to share
the knowledge that I have and also learn from other developers.
So I'd like to take thanks to the organizers for having
me and giving me the opportunity to do something that I like. When I'm
not doing technical tasks of any
kind, I like to just go in nature and lose
myself in that area.
So about today we are going to
delve into how artificial intelligence, particularly with
a focus on chat, GPT and copilot, are transforming the
way we do software development nowadays. This is
a huge subject that needs days to be discussed.
Therefore, in these sessions we are going to just dive the surface by
looking at how these tools precisely can help developers
into their day to day work. We are going to discuss how they
can be integrated in your development workflow and how
they can enhance your productivity. And why not also help you innovate
in the work that you are doing.
Putting a bit of context, if we
think on a general level in
today's software development landscape, AI,
it's just not only a tool,
it's an essential component, that it's reshaping our industry.
And when we are talking about reshaping our industry, we can
think both in a promising
way, but also in the way that we are changing the
way we look at our jobs and the way we look at how
things are happening and how our
day to day work is being transformed by all of this.
I'm talking from tools that help us a lot to the
fear of losing your job and having an AI that it's so much more
faster and that is going to take our jobs and
they are going to replace us. And that AI,
it's flawless and has
no issues. So all of these ways
of looking at this evolution and yeah,
this is also reshaping the way we are thinking about ourselves and
our development. Okay, maybe I should try to learn
about this tool instead of being scared of it.
So AI streamlines developers processes by automating
some repetitive tasks such as code generation, such as
testing, and by doing
this, accelerates project timelines and minimizes human
error. It's not perfect, and we are going to discuss about it and
how we can strive for perfection, let's say,
or for the best version, while interacting
with this tool. But it's not
perfect. At the same time, AI's advanced
algorithms excel at problem solving and data analysis.
They enable us to create sophisticated
and adapted software solutions.
We see AI making our work smarter and more efficient,
and creating all sorts of tools that are showing
us the way to this transformation that
we were discussing before.
So basically, if it is to think
in some simple words, is that the role of AI
in modern development? It's to transform
things, it's to bring evolution. So AI
significantly impacts various aspects of software and technology
development. And this includes promises,
efficiencies, efficiency. AI does
some repetitive tasks and
is helping in this way developers to focus more on
creative and more complex work. Then AI
is helping us reduce mistake, the mistake that we are doing
in our day to day work, just the human error
making software more reliable.
Also, the algorithms that AI is
using are great at solving problems and
determining some patterns in our data.
AI, it's not just this
image of a robot that is just talking very
mechanically, but is
evolving a lot to learn from
human interaction and fulfill very specific needs. It becomes
very personal, the interaction, it becomes very personal. It doesn't feel like you are
talking to a robot, it feels like you're just talking to a
colleague, exchanging ideas and getting
some information.
With the help of AI, we can drive innovation in tech
with things like machine learning and all sorts
of apps and services that
are bringing big changes in this field.
And the area where we are going
to be focused today is the
one where AI is giving us very good developers,
tools like GitHub and Copilot that
offer real time help to developers making work more efficient.
And that feels just like you're
collaborating with someone. It's not just feeling that
you are working alone. So let's see a
bit, discuss a bit about each of them.
Chat GPT it's an advanced AI language
model developed by OpenAI. It uses
natural language processing techniques to help
us understand and generate
humanlike text. This ability to interpret
complex queries and provide detailed, relevant,
context shaped responses makes it uninvaluable
tools for developers. But it's not only for developers.
You can get answers from a wide range of
subjects,
situations, domains and so on. So let's
explore some of the, let's say, top features that make Chat GPT
so powerful.
First would be the fact that it comprehends and produces text that resembles
human communication. It's enabling us to
engage in conversations and create a very natural
feeling around the conversations that we are having with Chat GPT,
creating very high quality text contact.
Then it demonstrates a strong understanding
of context in conversations. It can give
answers, recalling previous parts of conversation,
enhancing the user experience for the one that
is working with it.
It's doing a lot of tasks, from generating code, to assisting
in debugging, to creating engaging stories
to answering complex queries.
It brings a lot of values in a lot of professional and creative
contexts. For us developers, very important,
of course, is the fact that it can understand and generate code snippets in multiple
programming languages, which makes it very helpful
for us to seek assistance in our day
to day work. Explanations for certain
contexts, learning new things, getting answers to
things that maybe we forgot about or we never knew. So is like
having a colleague that you are doing pair programming with and
you are discussing and trying
to understand the context and trying to find solutions to
some problem. And last but not least is
the fact that being able to shape responses based on user input and
the feedback that we are giving him,
it allows Chat GPT to adapt to a wide
range of styles and tones and user
needs, which makes it easy
to use in a large range
of use cases.
Personally, I use this tool beyond coding,
from creating a vacation plan,
to seeing exactly what I can visit in certain areas and
actually asking it to do it for each day,
to helping me create an email in
order to give feedback to someone
or just trying to get the right tone
in a certain situation. So for me at
least, chat GBT, it's a great assistant.
Then we go to copilot. That on the other side is more
focused on the coded part. I'm using it
to play in visual studio.
The cool thing about it is that it was trained on a vast
array of source code.
This makes it able to understand and predict coding patterns
and requirements from a wide range.
What it does behind the scene is analyzing the context of your
existing code and comments, and based on that it offers code suggestions
and solutions in real time. So some
of the features to mention, although I'm sure that you might have a lot of
other situations
where you used it in your day to day work, and I'm open
and happy to learn from you. But some of the
features worth mentioning are the fact that it
understands the context of your code and it provides suggestions to
complete lines or functions and is
easily adapting to your style and needs. So basically, if you correct it at some
point and you are like okay, no, I'm using this kind of property or doing
things this way is going to work with you.
And next time the answers that you are going to
get or the suggestions that you are going to get are more specific,
then has a wide range support for
diverse languages and frameworks.
Next, it suggests improvements for logic
and code readability, aiding in efficient
and maintainable code development.
On another note, is a great learning and exploration tool because
it's very interactive. It's not
only for juniors, although I understand that these kind of tools are being
regarded more like a help for juniors that don't have all
the bases, so they need someone that it's more experimented to give
them suggestions. I personally don't feel this way because it's
offering all sort of insights into coding patterns and
best practices and builds on the complexity alongside
with the development of
our code. So I think that it's a useful
tool for everyone. And you
maybe have noticed that for both chat, GPT and copilot,
we are discussing a lot about user input and
the fact that it interprets human language. Well, as amazing
as these tools might be, they don't read minds.
We have to learn how to talk to them, we have to learn how
to ask things from them, just as we need to do it
also with the people around us. So it's about
learning how to communicate in order to
get the best results. And this communication
with AI tools is called prompting. So as the deal
with prompting is the process of interacting with an AI tool
by giving it some inputs that are also
called commands in order to get a specific response.
This process can be very different depending
on the AI tool that you are using.
But there are some general directions,
let's say, that we can use in any context,
even with people. I was just thinking when I
first started learning about this, the fact that learning
how to prompt is going to help us
a lot in learning how to communicate with people because we have the patience
to shape some very
specific questions in order to get the desired answer
from an AI tool. But we are so
impatient with the people around us and we are
always wondering like why don't you understand what I'm trying to say? Like I was
so explicit, do I have to over explain it to you?
And maybe we are going to learn something also about
human communication, human to human communication.
So going back to
the things that we need to take care of is
clear instructions, use clear and precise
commands so that Di understands what you really
want, provide specific details or criteria to
consider so that you get a specific response
shaped on your needs. Then it's important to know
what the AI tool is capable of doing. For example,
some AI tools are designed for generating text, others for creating
images, and some for processing and
analyzing data. You have to understand exactly what you
need from that tool and to see if it's precisely the tool
for you. Then we have to have
patience, as I already mentioned, and understand that
it's not magic, it's a process that
we need to build upon. The initial response from the AI might
not be perfect, so you might need to refine your prompt based on
the output that you received and making it better and
better, and creating a
communication process with your tool.
And I think that using a tool like this
will teach you more about how to craft effective prompts and
communicate more efficiently based on the responses you get.
So by analyzing a bit the response that you
get from an AI tool, you can see exactly what are
you lacking. Maybe you were not very clear with the format
that you wanted the response to be like you want it
in a specific language, you want it to be more formal,
you want it to be in a JSON format.
Maybe it depends on what you're asking from it,
or maybe you could have
created a Persona for that. So for example, you can say to your AI,
okay, I want you to answer to this question as you
were a highly experimented architect,
software architect, and I want you to give me the answer in
that specific way, in a very informed
and professional way. So you have to
also create a context and
give feedback to the AI in order for it to
answer to your needs. But let's play a bit with it
just to see how this works.
Let's see,
so we have in here Chat
GPT four, and for example,
let's say that I'm first just
going to ask for him, okay,
give me the solid principles so
we can see that it's giving us a very complex,
very explicit answer and with
a lot of details, which is good. But for example, let's say that
I'm just someone that is learning right now about
solid principles. So I want the eye to give
me real world examples.
So I'm just going to ask him a
bit more specific, something like this,
okay, explain to
me the solid principles
with real world
examples. And also because I
don't want to stay and wait a lot and I need very specific answers,
I wanted to keep
it short on the explanations.
Keep in mind that
I am.
Let's see you
giving also the context as you can see?
So it's starting to build
things as you asked, in order to get as
specific answers as possible. So it's going to give
us examples for edge.
Great. Now we are going just
to see how it keeps track of the context. We are going to say,
okay, now give
me,
let it
presentation outline that
I can use for the first principle.
So I don't have to say again for the first solid
principle and so on, because it has the context, it know
exactly on what principle am I referring to.
So it's building up on that.
And right now it's going to give us a
context on the first principle
and creating a presentation outline
for that. And it's amazing also with
real world the examples. Great, great.
So we can use it in order to build and build. And then if
I don't think that this was okay, I can say, for example,
make it shorter.
It is. And this
intended for it,
twelve years old,
classic.
So it's creating it even more specific for our needs.
I'm going to give some resources
to you for both Chat GPT and copilot and how to
install it and how you can use it. More precisely,
we're not going to go very much in details because the time is not
very long, but let's look also a bit on what we can do with copilot.
So for example, let's take it from scratch.
I have a very random project
in here that I used at some point for a training.
So I am connected, I already
have an account connected to
copilot, so I'm just going to go and
activate the GitHub copilot chat. So on one side
we can have it like this, we can discuss with
it as we are discussing
also with Chat GPT. So let's just use
one of the suggested commands and say,
okay, explain this text
that I,
I'm trying to,
I select it and it's explaining exactly what's the deal with
the router provider and with router and what is this supposed to be doing?
Another thing that we can
do with it, let's see,
for example, we can put in here,
let's go to home because it's easier.
Here we have some comments and then we have some links and so
on. But what I wanted to do
is, for example, let's say I can activate
it with create
header component.
So it's,
let's put it outside so it can get a
context.
Let's see,
let's just,
okay, let's try something more.
Let's create function
that calculates the
time between two dates.
Yeah, whatever.
So function,
and it's giving some suggestions to us.
Of course it comes to us
to correct and see if it's what we need and so
on and so forth. Let's see.
Okay, great.
Another thing that we can do is
activating it also from this modify, using copilot, and you can
say to it exactly what you want for
this code snippet to
do.
So basically you can use it as you saw,
as soon as you started writing something,
it began suggesting things to you, giving explanations.
Of course we can use, for example, we can create
another function, let's close this one. We are going
to help
it. For example, we are going to do something
like this. Create a
function that
perfect. Okay.
It sometimes it's
a bit slower. Of course, as I said, we need to be
patient with it. I think I
interrupted it slow. So it's
not giving the answer that quickly. And also I think
that my Internet connection is a bit bad.
Let's see. So it's giving it, but it's
suggesting it. But the format, since I did not specify the format,
it's giving me suggestions,
like comments. We can play
with it, but you got the idea.
It's something that since you know exactly what is the
context that you are trying to use in there, you are going to
be able to be as specific as possible.
Okay, going back to our
presentation. So if it is to think
we went through to the play time,
we can see that we can chat with it,
we can generate by using the comments
you can select and then having
suggestions in there on the selected code that we want to work
with. It can predict and complete what we started,
as we did with. The function that calculates the time
between two dates is matching patterns with regular
expressions. We can also write unit codes,
unit tests, writing commands.
It's generating sample data. So we can play with it
in a lot of ways. And I strongly invite you to work
with it and see what are the strong points and where are the things that
you need to be more precise or to be a bit more specific with
it. So when it comes to the integration
in our software development processes,
first of all we need to understand the capabilities of our AI.
And as you were able to see,
we have to learn exactly how to specify
the context, how to specify the format, so that
we in time can train and get as good
answer as possible. Don't forget
to be as realistic as possible. As you've seen,
it's not always that sharp. So you need to be
patient with it to create a context for example I used especially
to not have the perfect context for it. I used a very
simple but let's
say not with
a lot of things in it. The project that I
played with it just to show you exactly that, if you're
giving less context, it's going to
give you answers more or less generic
because it doesn't know exactly how to shape. So it needs some time. We are
doing this first time in that project, so it needs some time to
adjust to exactly what are the patterns that we are trying to
do in there. Then see exactly how the
AI tool that you are choosing is aligning with the project needs,
that you have the team expertise and see
exactly how easy it is to integrate and what
resources do you need?
My advice is to try to work with tools and in
general, it's not only for AI that you can
configure for your product that
are flexible and you can work with and
have strong compatibility with existing systems for effective implementation
on your side. Also try to keep as up to date as
possible.
Work with it constantly in order to see what are the
capabilities and give feedback in order to
maintain its effectiveness and relevance.
Gradually integrate AI into development workflows. Don't do
it all at once. Get used to it. Play maybe in
small projects before actually putting it into your product and
see how it evolves step by step, like how it's improving its
answer step by step and encourage your team
to use AI. I think that we need to foster a learning environment
and we need to adapt to AI capabilities
for successful integrating. Instead of relying
on all of those needs that we were saying on the beginning, we need to
be prepared and to educate ourselves some
of the best practices for integrating AI tools.
Just to keep in mind that as we
embrace AI tools in our development workflow, it's crucial to follow
some best practices and to understand the tool to ensure
effectiveness and ethical integration.
And these practices not only enhance the benefits we derive
from AI, but also helps us understand
what are the potential risks and challenges and how we can work into
resolving those. So when you are starting
with working with AI, be specific
with your goals. Why are you using AI
and integrate it step by step.
Stay updated with the latest advancements
and implement quality control for all the outputs that
you are using. Use AI ethically.
Focus on data privacy and try to mitigate
bias as much as possible.
Don't try to replace, but rather enhance human
skills by using AI capabilities. Address security
risks and ensure privacy in your AI tools and
the way you are doing the integration.
Try to keep the team as
close as possible and foster collaboration
and communication, even though they are using an AI tool,
and use these tools as a
whole responsibly and try to enhance the
software developers into
an area where it becomes efficient
and of quality, so enhance its
features.
I completely agree that it's important to consider
the long term implication of AI investments and to be
mindful of the environmental
impact of scaling up AI infrastructure.
And every time I hear something about this, I'm like yes,
exactly. We need to take care of this because as we continue to innovate
and evolve with AI, we should also think about what the future holds
and how AI can contribute positively
to the advancement of society.
It's our responsibility to make sure that AI development
and integration aligns with ethical
responsibility. We need to think beyond the immediate application
and consider how AI can shape our world in the long run
and ensure our technologies progress
goes hand in hand with sustainability and these
ethical principles that we need to take care
of. So be mindful of this. When you are
going all in, in a project, in a product,
or in the way you are using AI in your day to day life,
all in, all, in here you can have
some resources that you can use and
where you can learn more or how to activate
these tools and how to work with them. And you can also play
with Samsung. I gave you some resources thank
you once again for joining me in this session. If you have further
questions or need guidance, please feel free to reach out to me.
My contact information is on the screen.
So let's continue to learn and grow together
in this amazing environment
that we have.