Hello everyone and welcome to my talk multiple terraform projects in
a Monorepo and today we will try to answer a question, how to survive that
mess. A couple words about
me. I am a DevOps engineer and I used
to be a software engineer.
I try to automate things
and I fan of clean
code and open source and
infrastructure as a code. Here you can find QR
code and link to my profile on
LinkedIn. So if you have questions about
this terrap compose tool,
or if you want to just talk with me
about some DevOps topics or something else,
you can reach me out there. So let's
start when someone
tell you that it has everything as
an infrastructure, as a code, it might
be something similar to that picture. So it
probably not something that you are expecting out of these
words, right? So you can
see there as a code,
but it may be copy pasted,
or maybe not clean, or maybe not
updated and so on. So it
might be different expectations
out of it. I was in this situation several
times and today I will
try to guide you through
my experience out of managing
such projects. And our agenda
for today is first I will explain
prerequisites that we have. Then we will
have a problem deep dive. Then I
will try to explore existing solutions.
What we have there, I will introduce terracompose
then and a short demo and a couple
final words in the end. So let's
start. We have as a prerequisite a set
of projects in a monorepo. They have
various workspaces, which is mostly equal to environments,
various structures and terraform versions.
And if we look into our
projects, you might have similar
situation that you have some projects
in your folder, whatever name I
select projects. And you
might also have some common stuff like
creating vpcs or something like that
which is shared across these projects. And it might
have a little bit different location here.
In this example it's a common, you can see it on the left picture.
Also you can have environments based
approach of structures. Your projects,
as you can see on the right picture with
modules. When we talk about various
workspaces,
mostly we talk about different
number of workspaces per project
and different naming combinations. So some of
the projects might have staging and production
only, some might have life stage
and so on. Also we have different
structures here because some of
the projects might have components which
add additional level of the file structure.
And in the end we might have different terraform versions
across the projects and also different
versions inside the project between different
workspaces, because you might be in the process
of upgrading terraform and you have on
managing, for example, one version of terraform. And in production still you
can have different version.
Okay, so let's summarize
our complaints.
We have following pain points, different terraform versions,
and it's a pain of switching
terraform versions on local between different projects.
Also you have there a risk of incompatibility of the snippets.
And also here we
have a problem that our workspaces
not visible and not trackable by versions control
system. And that's why
you need to memorize everything.
And it creates a problem
when you involve someone for troubleshooting
or onboard newcomers. Aren't there any solutions
on the market? Let's see.
So we have terraform cloud,
which is famous SaaS solution.
It's a native solution for terraform and
it's really good, but it's a pricey
solution and it's not solve everything
that we need. So it still
for us has a low
visibility for workspaces.
And you still need to memorize your structure
and workspaces and
the price for sure. If we take a
look into other tools,
terraground, terramate, terraspace, they are also
really good and they
cover some pain points,
but not all of them. Instead they create
also some pain points, because with
introducing them, you need to
maintain some files,
they are required, or some file structures
or so on. So they create some
amount of overhead. Sometimes it
does make sense to use it, sometimes not.
But we are trying to talk
about the lightweight solution. So we
do not want to have overhead, almost nothing.
And then three years ago
I thought that. Okay, wait, I already
saw it somewhere and I remember
that we have Docker compose and
docker and Docker compose have
a configuration for the projects in yaml.
It's a very clean approach
with config as a code and it
has high visibility and traceability.
And the idea behind terracompose, exactly that.
Why cannot we do something
like that with the terraform projects?
Okay, and let me show you
this quick wrapper.
So terracompose, use cases,
use cases are actually here
actions that we can run in terracompose,
we can run plan, apply workspaces,
run shell and help more
often. For sure we using plan and
apply. And under the hood these actions are
having terraform commands and
providing output of them. We also can
run command inside the container
with run action. We can list workspaces and
we can run a shell inside
the container and join
it. If we take
a look on collaboration diagram here,
we can see that when we trigger terracompose
action under the hood, Terracompose will
read configuration which is written into the config file
and based on that run terraform
command inside the docker.
Also it will run
this action, wrap it into
some different commands like change directory,
terraform, init, select workspaces and so on.
With this setup we solve our problem with terraform
versions because we use Docker
which allow us to have different terraform
versions on the same machine.
Also we solve problem with different structure
and workspaces and memorizing them because we
can customize our alias
with different path, different workspace and
we don't need to memorize them. Only one
that we need to do is to actually create this config file.
We also improve our validation
approach because we chain terraform commands and
we automatically run validation.
We will not forget about it and
it will also automate some cleanup
things after running action.
So it will also help us in this way when
we will talk about capabilities. So here I would
stress that we don't need to memorize
it and it's
a part of code base so it has same visibility.
You can have merge requests
and you can have a documentation
just at your code base about workspaces.
Also having terraform commands provide
us a guaranteed validated plan and
it will just speed up maintenance and development because
it require less time for double check, for printing,
repeated comments and in the end it
means less validation failures on CI
when you will push your code because it
shift left validations and
it require from you to do
all checks locally. First in the configuration
file you can see two
main blocks. This is default
which contains shared properties
across the aliases and aliases which
is actually our projects
and environments. And here
you can see that this terraform version
that we define in default might
be overwritten in alias.
The required property is only one path
only. This is distinguish aliases between
each other and we
have here also example of the hooks usage.
Hooks will help us to customize our projects
even more so we
are able to run scripts or commands
before some particular activities and
or after. And this way we
will be able to do some workarounds
for some h cases. We will
talk about it later. Here you can see
the output of the help action.
So it lists available actions and also
it lists available aliases.
And now it's time for demo.
First of all I want to emphasize
few points about demo. So first
we will have it in AWS.
Second demo project I
prepare it and it contains for
speed and for readability projects
that creates only vpcs and security groups.
And also we will keep terraform state locally
for simplicity, but please never do it in production.
Here I want to show
how I connect to AWS. So it's
just a simple AWS
profile and I export also profile
name with environment variable. I also created
these commands, this aliases which is
just help us to not print
that long commands during the demo.
So let's check that we have only default VPC and
default security group. Okay,
everything is prepared.
Let's download the tool.
So I'm downloading the terracompose
tool and copied into
the local bin. I also will clone
the terracompose demo project which
is available in GitHub.
And let's start with the first
demo project is a common so as I mentioned,
it will create a vpcs for all our
projects and we can use,
and we can create resources in these
vpcs. So here we have folder
with terraform state. We have two environments,
nonprod and production. And we
have here tf varst files,
one managing with workspace and another
one does not match with
his name with workspace name. So for
this use case we for
staging just define
workspace property. And for production we
define beside workspace property, we define also
tfvars property. So this is a
very simple example when we
can omit some break in naming
combinations and we can use
a random name for tfwars. Just put
this name into the alias
config. Okay, let's build
a plan. So this is just a simple command.
As you can see this is plan and then alias
name. Now you see the
output that we are running,
terraform init. We see the
normal Tf init output.
Also we can see that workspace Nonprod
has been found in config and we will select it
and we see the information about
the main factors
for our plan. This is workspace and this is tfwars
name. Then after
checking plan, you can see that this plan is
actually saved in this file. So we can
even manually check it if you want.
Okay, then we can run workspaces alias.
This is also just
a short link to list the available alias workspaces.
Sorry. And we see that we currently
are in nonprod workspace.
So let's apply. When we run apply,
it's also easy. It's just apply and name workspace.
You don't need to define all details about files and
so on. So it's done already. Under the
hood we see in which directory
we are, we are running terraform in need standard
output of it, selecting workspace.
And now we see that, okay, we want to apply
file with this name, are you sure about that?
And also we can see how
long time ago it was modified.
So now you can decide, is that exactly file
that you want to apply or not?
So if we print, yes, we can proceed.
And our sources were
created. Now let's build a plan for production.
And you remember that there we had an
TfVars named differently
from workspace, but terraform
plan is there and file also
pick it up correctly. Now let's apply.
And now you see that, okay,
I ran the command, but now it contains a suffix.
So with the suffix debug you can enable debug
mode which will run it
without init, without format check
and without validation. So it's very useful
for development process and
debugging process, because you don't need
to wait until everything will be validated
and in its process will finished and
so on. So it's
very useful for development, but I
would not recommend doing that out
of development. So you need to have a
clear understanding for what you are doing
that. Okay,
so we want to apply our
changes, they are applied.
And also let's check how we can run
other commands. So we can just
trigger action, run alias and
then we can put any commands
that we want to run, they will be run in
the container. So here you can see that
we list our state and we see that our
VPC is there. And also
I want to show you that our vpcs
were really created and they are
in place. Okay, now let's check
more complex example. Here we see
project that have two compose,
let's go with the app component.
And here we see that
we have beside our Tf
state folder with two workspaces
integration and live. We have also here
some tf state for experiment.
So for example you are doing some experiment in integration workspace
and you have this TF
state folder just for integration workspace
and you want to apply that. So how can you do it for
that you can use backend config property and
define their workspace deer with
another location for the terraform state.
Or for example, if you are using remote
backend, you can put here some key and
use that. So that
just allow you to run terraform
in it with some custom backend config.
And hooks. Help us here because
when we will jump from one
environment to another environment we
will see error because we
ran terraform init with different
backend configs. So for
work around that issue we can just
run hooks which removing terraform
folder on both of these environments
and it will solve our problem.
This is just an example, you might have different use case
and let's see how it works. So I
going to run a plan on integration.
We see here that we trigger
before df init hook and we
run our terraform init using backend config.
We see config sorry, init output and
selecting workspace. And we
can check that in the end we are in workspace
integration with TFwars integration
tFwars. Okay, we see the plan here,
no errors. So I'm going to
apply it now.
After resource were created,
we see that changes are actually were
recorded into experiment TF
state and TF state with origin was
not modified. So you
can see that this option
really works. And our
security group also in place,
we can see it here. Okay, now let's try
to run interactive shell into container.
And for that we will use
shell action. We also
need to approve it because for the
projects purposes and we are inside the container.
Now let's check our workspace list.
Okay, so now we just check in that we
are in the backend
configuration experimental one,
and for live
we can just run terra
compose action plan. It will
run before Tf init hook
again, run normal Tfe
init without experimental backend config.
And you can see that here we
have plan that has been built
incorrect workspace with correct tfwars
file. Let's apply.
Okay, so the resource was created
and here we also can see them.
Good. I think it's enough
for this demo. I hope
that you saw that with this setup,
terracompose tool is really helpful
when we we can just
run action name and alias and it
will run it with the properties with the arguments
that we defined in the config
file and we don't have to remember
them and double check
validity and so on.
Let's back now to
our presentation. So with that said,
all done now, what do you think?
Let's check our points.
So here we have almost
everything solved switch and terraform versions.
It's now only attribute in YaML thanks
to the running it into Docker snippets
and compatibility visualization.
Workspace traceability of the
workspace automate routines needs to
remember all these were solved chain in
commons still. Well, it's a
solved, but it's hard coded. That's why I market it as
partially solved, because in
the future plans I want to make
them customizable and also allow users
to create a custom action or
override default action
to solve different problems,
or maybe just because to
fix something. And if
we talk about complexity and price.
It's an open source and it's a simple yaml that
you can create for 1 hour. So I tried to
implement it into different projects
and I spent about 1 hour and
the job was done.
Now let's talk about the future. So since
that was just a simple wrapper,
a quick wrapper written three years ago.
So I didn't thought about the proper
interface design and this
is something that I see needs to
be improved. Also, I want
to make actions customizable as I just mentioned.
And who knows, maybe rewriting go how
do you think? So I actually
want to encourage you to contribute to this project.
You can find links to this project in QR code
and in my GitHub account.
Please join. And with that I
want to say thank you for your attention.