You.
Hello everybody. First of all,
thank you for inviting us to present in the
42 Devsecops 2023 event.
So today we are going to explain you a bit
about our case. And to do so, I'm having
here with me Sandeep Panghal, which is managing consultant
within tcs and myself Juan Antonio Conde,
head head head head head of application portfolio
composition. We enter into the
case. So let's provide a brief update on where
we are with who we are. So Zurich is a
little more deliveries insurance that serve its customer
in a global and local market. Funded in 1872
with about 56,000 employees, it provides
a wide range of property and casualty and
life insurance products and services in more than 210 countries
and territories. Sandeep,
I will hand over to you to provide a brief update on Tata and then
we can go into the case. Yeah, Tata Tata Tata
Tata Consultancy Services World renowned Tata Group is a
global it services consulting and business solution provider
who has been building greater futures through innovations and
knowledge for over 50 plus years. So we have
been recommended has a top two most valuable brand in
2022 with a market capitalization of
144 billion with a revenue of 25 plus billion
dollars in FY 2022. So we are
a company of 600,000 plus employees representing
150 plus nationalities with a 35
plus diversity percentage. So we are a company
who has spreaded its wings across all the industries ranging
from BFSI, retail,
manufacturing. So whatever you name it, TCS is
there with BFSI predominantly dominating
in the revenue market. So if I talk about from the geographical
area. So we have spread it across the globe with the major
businesses working, coming from the North America followed
by Europe, continental Europe as well as the Asia.
So we have been ranked as a top 20
future brand in the index 2021 and has been ranked
as a top hundred as a leader by the research
firms. Moving on.
Basically now I will be giving you a walkthrough about our automated Devsecops
maturity assessment, about the background, basically how we came
out talk about this solution. So basically here is our CTO
or CIO of an organization who is thinking that how
do I know about Devsecops adoption of the business unit functions
or the entire organization? How matured am
I organization in Devsecops with respect to industry standards?
How do I compare business units in terms of
future investment? Which business units, applications or
the platforms are less efficient with lower
quality and lower production deliveries and the vice versa?
Where I need to invest more? How can I benchmark
each business unit application or the functions against
each other or with other insurance providers or
moreover with other industries. Can I have
some kind of a point in time?
Dashboards, automated continuous dashboard with
neo human error. So this
was the background. Now, if I talk about the problem statement,
there are no standard setup developed matrices which
can be applied across the business units which have been
globally spreaded across the different countries for
using. And there isn't any harmonization of the Devsecops
adoption view of the organizationbusiness and
the matrices which are being produced with the big manual efforts
due to the multiple data sources,
due to the complexities of the various applications,
diverse landscapes and the tools used across the various business
units. And the teams are focusing on introducing mattresses
and the measurement rather than on the production deliveries.
So in order to resolve this problem, here we have Juan who will be
talking about the solution. So yeah, so Sandeep went
through the problem statement. What were the major headaches
that it brings to our organization?
But I'm pretty sure that that's something
that is common across quite a lot of companies worldwide,
especially if they are big corporations. So after
many different meetings with quite a lot of different stakeholders across
Zurich, but also we engage with many different partners
to confirm the direction to follow. So we have been talking with key
reference partners and consultant firms around the globe.
So it came up on the solution has indeed said that we need to build
something that brings automation on
how we produce metrics that is tool agnostic and
just provide the metrics that we
require, but also providing the flexibility in case
that we need to adjust the metrics. And here it is where data hoop,
which is the product that we have built from scratch,
is coming into the picture. So first of
all we thought, okay, so how we are going to be building something new.
Of course this needs to be cloud based, needs to be scalable,
agnostic of technologies, underlying technologies,
but of course flexible enough to integrate with
the different DevOps tools that we are having in the
market. Also code quality tools,
security testing tools, different testing tools that we
can incorporate into data hook in terms of data points
or metadata retrieve from data hook.
In one side we have the technology, but in the other side we have been
designing data hook with the customer in mind. So of course we have
been applying design thinking and user experience principles.
It has been secured by design. So in the sense that we
protect the business units,
data or group data to don't be shared with others, at least
that we are interested providing benchmarks also from
global organization to the business units to the teams
without compromising that anonymization of data
to be presented from one group to another. It has been
also user friendly error
reports produced in order to make business units
application teams understand why they are not
seeing their data within the dashboard, how they can
improve the way that they are doing things. All right? And this has been
the main purpose of data hook. So create a tool that provides
the application team, the business units it heads,
but also the group leaders information about how we
are doing developed in our corporation. So what
is our development efficiency?
So the benefits that data hoop brings to organization. And you
can see some of them here on
this slide. And I have been referring to some of those already. So faster agile
adoption. So of course, I'm pretty sure that many big corporations
like us can think, hey, how agile is our organization?
How many agile applications do we have? Right? So with Datacoop,
we have been able to not only identify how our teams
are applying those agile behaviors on the different tools that
we are using to do software development, but also to do
project management. We have been also able to incorporate
other disciplines like how automated
processes are, how we are doing testing
across the different applications and teams. Right? So once
you know the data, of course you can improve, which is describe the continuously
improvement behavior. But as I mentioned earlier, so that allow us
really to compare with the different units, the different
teams, and not just with the aim of knowing where
we are, also with the aim of course, always to improve.
And of course last but not least, so we
have been able to produce metric at
a scale almost with no effort or with
a very little effort on the team side. All right.
The outcome up to date about what we have done. So here
you have some figures so we have implemented or we have onboarded within data
hook. I would say that right now it's a
bit more than 200 applications from twelve business units has been
assessed. The monthly onboarding
ratio is about 20% plus 20%.
The onboarding process for new application is automated through
Azure pipeline. So almost an onboarding of an application can be
performed without any manual intervention. Metrics related
to customer value, organizational effectiveness, service quality,
measurement areas continuously from several tool sets.
So we are retrieving data on a regular basis, on a monthly basis and we
are producing those metrics to our different teams,
global business units and department benchmark is available for
test, SEc ops adoption, maturity assessment.
Lead time to market KPIs decreased by 9%
over the last nine months. So we're here becoming faster. So this is
going back to the continuous improvement that we have seen on
the previous slide and then also we have identified up to 10%
month to month increase in technical, therefore 20 plus
business areas over the last year. So those numbers areas
just reflecting the adoption of data who within Zurich.
And this well is more to come within the next
months and years. So hopefully this has been something interesting
for you. Thank you very much for listening us
and if you are interested to know a bit more about data hook.
So here you have our email address. Feel free to reach out.
I will be more than happy to get in contact with you
and to provide more details about how we have implemented
data hook in our corporation. Thank you very much.