Hello everyone. Pandy Knight here, automation panda and developer
advocate at applitools. I'm also a huge Pythons fan,
just like y'all. Have you ever seen those at tags on top of
python functions? Maybe you've seen them on top of methods and classes,
too. Those are decorators, one of Python's
niftiest language features. Decorators are essentially wrappers.
They wrap additional code around existing definitions. When used
right. They can clean up your code better than oxiclean.
Let's learn how to use them. Here's a regular old hello
world function. When we run it,
it prints hello world. Nothing fancy.
Now let's take that function and bam.
Add a decorator using this at sign. We just added
a decorator named Tracer to hello world.
So what is this decorator? Tracer is just
another function, but it's a special function
because it takes in another function as an argument.
Since tracer decorates hello world, the hello world
function is passed into tracer as an argument. Wow.
So what's inside tracer? This decorator has an inner
function named wrapper. Can you even do that with
Python? Yes, you can. The wrapper
function prints entering, calls the function originally passed
into the decorator, and then prints exiting.
When tracer decorates hello world, that means hello world
will be wrapped by entering and exiting print statements.
Finally, the decorator returns the new wrapper function.
Anytime the decorated function is called, it will effectively
be replaced by this new wrapper function. So when we
call hello world, the trace statements are now printed.
Wow, that's amazing. That's how decorators work.
Decorators wrap functions around functions.
Think about them like candy bars. The decorators is like the
foil wrapper. And how how decorators function like the chocolate
inside. But how is those even possible? That decorator code
looks confusing. Decorators are possible because in pythons,
functions are objects. In fancy language,
we say functions arent first order values.
Since functions are just objects, we can pass them into
other functions as arguments define new functions inside existing
functions, and return a function from a function.
Those is all part of a paradigm called functional programming.
Python supports functional programming because functions can be treated like objects.
That's awesome. So using
functions as objects, decorators can change how functions
are called. Decorators create an how
decorators function around an inner decorated
function. Remember, the outer function is
like the foil wrapper and the inner function is like the chocolate.
Creating an outer function lets you add new code around the inner
function. Some people call this advice. You can
add advice before or after the inner function. You could even
skip the inner function. The best part is,
decorators can be applied to any function.
They make sharing code easy so you don't repeat yourself.
Decorators are reminiscent of a paradigm called aspect oriented programming,
in which code can be cleverly inserted before and after points of execution.
Neat. So remember how decorators functions
around functions like candy bars?
Hold on, now we have a problem in that pythons code.
If the wrapper function effectively replaces hello world,
then what identity does hello world report?
Its name is wrapper and its help is also wrapper.
That's not right. Never fear, there's an easy
solution. The functions module provides a decorator named
wraps. Put functions wraps on the wrapper
function and pass in the inner function object,
and decorated functions once again show the right identity.
That's awesome. But wait, there's another problem.
How do decorators work with inputs and outputs?
What if we decorate a function with parameters and a return value?
If we try to use the current tracer,
we get an error. Arguments broke it.
Thankfully, we can fix it. First, add star args
and startup kwargs to the wrapper
function's parameters and then pass them through to the inner function.
This will make sure all arguments go through the decorator into the decorated
function. Then capture the inner function's return
value and return it from the wrapper function.
This makes sure return values also pass through. If the
inner function has no return value. Dont worry,
those decorator will pass through a none value.
When we call the function with the updated tracer, we see
tracing is now successful again. When we check the return
value, it's exactly what we expected. It works.
Wow, that's awesome. But wait,
there's more. You can write a decorator to call a function twice.
Start with the decorator template and call the inner function twice.
Return the final return value for continuity.
Bam. It works.
Oh wait, there's more. You can write a timer decorators
start with the template, call the inner function, and surround
it with timestamps using the time module.
Bam. Now you can time any functions.
But wait, there's more. You can also add
more than one decorator to a function. This is called nesting
order matters. Decorators are executed
in order of closeness to the inner function. So in this
case, call twice is applied first, and then timer
is applied. If these decorators are reversed,
then each inner function call is timed.
Cool. But wait, there's more.
You can scrub and validate function arguments. Check out these
two simple math functions. Create a decorator to scrub
and validate inputs as integers. Add the wrapper
function and make sure it has positional args.
Then cast all args as ints before passing them into
the inner function. Now, when calling those math functions calls,
numbers are integers. Using non numeric inputs
also raises a value error.
But wait, there's more. You can create
decorators with parameters. Here's a decorator that will
repeat a function five times.
The repeat function is a little different. Instead of taking in the
inner function object, it takes in the parameter, which is the
number of times to repeat the inner function.
Inside there's a repeat decorator function that has a parameter for
the inner function. The repeat function returns the repeat
decorator function inside. Repeat decorator
is the wrapper function. It uses functions,
wraps, and passes through all arguments.
Repeat decorator returns wrapper finally,
wrapper contains the logic for calling the inner function multiple times according
to the repeat decorator's parameter value.
Now, hello, could runs five times.
Nifty. But wait,
there's more. Decorators can be used to save
states. Here's a decorator that will count the number
of times a functions is called.
Could calls has the standard decorator structure outside
the wrapper. A could attribute is initialized to zero.
This attribute is added to the wrapper function object inside
the wrapper. The count is incremented before calling the inner function.
The count value will persist across multiple calls.
Initially, the hello world count value is zero.
After two calls, the count value goes up.
Awesome. Oh wait,
there's more. Decorators can be used in classes.
Here those timer decorator is applied to this hello method.
As long as parameters and return values are set up correctly,
decorators can be applied equally to functions and methods.
Decorators can also be applied directly to classes.
When a decorator is applied to a class, it wraps the constructor.
Note that it does not wrap each method in the class.
Since decorators can wrap classes and methods in addition to functions,
it would technically be more correct to say that decorators
wrap callables around callables.
So all that's great. But can decorators be tested? Good code
must arguably be testable code well,
today's your lucky day, because yes, you can
test decorators. Testing decorators can
be a challenge. We should always try to test the code we write, but decorators
can be tricky. Here's some advice.
First, separate tests for decorator functions from how
decorators function. How how how decorators
function intended outcomes try to focus on the wrapper instead
of the inner function. Remember,
decorators can be applied to any callable, so cover the parts
that make the decorators unique. Decorate Ted functions
should have their own separate unit tests. Second,
apply decorators to fake functions used only for testing.
These functions can be simple or mocked.
That way, unit tests won't have dependencies on existing functions
that could change. Tests will also be simpler if they
use how decorators function. Third,
make sure decorators have test coverage for every possible way
it could be used. Cover decorator parameters,
decorated function arguments, and return values.
Make sure the name and help are correct.
Check any side effects like saved state.
Try it on methods and classes as well as functions with
decorators. Most failures happen due to overlooked edge cases.
Let's look at a few short decorator tests. We'll use the
count calls decorator from earlier there are
how how decorators function use for testing. The first one is a no
operation function that does nothing. It has no parameters or returns.
The second one is a function that takes in one argument and returns it.
Both are very simple, but they represent two equivalent classes.
How how how how decorators function will verify
outcomes using the decorator for count calls. That means
tests will focus on the count attribute added to the decorated function.
The first test case verifies that the initial count value for any
function is zero. The second test calls
a function three times and verifies that the count is three.
The third test exercises those same function to make sure
arguments and return values work correctly.
It calls the same function, asserts the return value,
and asserts the count value. This collection
of tests is by no means complete. It simplest shows
how to start writing tests for decorators. It also shows
that you don't need to overthink unit tests for decorators. Simple is
better than complex. Up to this point,
we've covered how to write your own decorators. However, Python has several
decorators available in the language and in various packages that you can use
absolutely free.
Decorators like class method, static method, and projects can apply
to methods in a class. Frameworks like flask and pytest have
even more decorators. Let's take a closer look.
Let's start by comparing the class method and static method decorators.
We'll revisit the greeter class we saw before the
class method decorator will return any method into a class method
instead of an instance method.
That means this hello method here can be called directly from the class
instead of from an object of the class. The decorators
will pass a reference to the class into the method, so the
method will have some context of the class.
Here, the reference is named CLS,
and the method uses it to get the class's name.
The method can be called using greeter hello.
The static method decorator works almost the same as the class
method decorator, except that it does not pass a reference to the class
into the method. Notice how the method parameters are empty.
No class and no self methods
are still called from the class, like here with greeter goodbye.
You could say that static method is just a simpler version of class method.
Next, let's take a look at the property decorator to show
how to use it. We'll create a class called accumulator to
keep count of a tally. Accumulator's init
method initializes a count attribute to zero.
An add method adds an amount to the could. So far,
nothing unusual. Now let's add a property.
The count method has the property decorator on it. This means that
counts will be callable as an attribute instead of a method,
meaning that it won't need parentheses. It is effectively
a getter calls to count in the
init and add methods will actually call this projects. Instead of a
raw variable inside those count property,
the method returns an attribute named underscore count.
The underscore means that this variable should be private.
However, this class hasn't set that variable yet. That variable
is set in the setter method. Setters are optional
for projects. Here, the setter validates that the
value to set is not negative. If the
value is good, then it steps underscore count.
However, if the value is negative, then it raises a
value error. Underscore could is handled internally,
while could is handled publicly as the property.
The getter and setter controls added by the property decorator let
you control how the property is handled. In this
class, the setter protects the property against bad negative
values, so let's use this class.
When an accumulator object is constructed, its initial count is zero.
After adding an amount to the object, the count goes up.
Its count can be directly set to non negative values.
Attempting to set the count directly to a negative value raises that
exception. As expected, protection like that
is great. Python packages also
frequently contain decorators. For example,
Flask is a very popular web micro framework that enables
you to write web APIs with very little Python code.
Here's an example. Hello World Flask app. Taken directly from
the flask Docs online, it imports the flask module,
creates the app, and defines a single endpoint at the
root path that returns the string. Hello World
Flask's app root decorator can turn
any function into a web API endpoint. That's awesome.
Another popular package with decorators is Pytest,
Python's most popular test framework.
One of Pytest's best features is the ability to parameterize test functions
to run from multiple input combinations. Test parameters
empower data driven testing for wider test coverage.
To show how it works, we'll use a simple test for basic arithmetic
test addition. It asserts that a plus
b equals c. The values for
a, b, and c must come from a list of tuples.
For example, one plus two equals three, and so forth.
The Pytest mark parameterized decorator
connects the list of test values to the test function.
It runs the test once for each tuple in the list,
and it injects the tuple values into those test case as function arguments.
The test case will run four times.
Test parameters are a great way to rerun test logic without
repeating test code, so act
now before it's too late. When should you use decorators in
your Python code? Use decorators for
aspects an aspect
is a special crosscutting concern.
There are things that happen in many parts of the code, and they frequently
require repetitive calls. Think about something like logging.
If you want to add logging statements to different parts of the code, then you
need to write multiple logging calls in all those places.
Logging itself is one concern, but it crosscuts the whole
code base. One solution for logging could be to use decorators,
much like we saw earlier with the tracer decorator.
Good use cases for decorators include logging,
profiling, input validation, retries,
and registries. These are things that typically require
lots of extra calls inserted in duplicative ways.
Ask yourself this, could the code wrap something
else? If yes, then you have a good candidate
for a decorator. However, decorators aren't good for all circumstances.
You should avoid decorators for main behaviors because
those should probably be put directly in the body of the decorated function.
Avoid logic that's complicated or has heavy conditionals too,
because simple is better than complex.
You should also try to avoid completely sidestepping the decorated
function that would confuse people.
Ask yourself, this is the code you want to write, the wrapper
or the candy bar itself? Wrappers make
good decorators, but candy bars do not.
I hope you found this infomercial about decorators useful. If you
want to learn more, check out this real Python tutorial named
Primer on Python decorators. It covers everything I
showed here, plus more. Thank you very much
much for listening again. My name is Pandy Knight. I'm the
automation panda and a developer advocate at applitools. If you
like my talk, then please read my blog and follow me on Twitter.