Jamaica real
time feedback into the behavior of your distributed systems
and observing changes exceptions errors in
real time allows you to not only experiment with confidence,
but respond instantly to get things working again.
Code welcome
to my talk. The five developer principles that help me as a
new father. You won't believe number seven.
Let's start with the elephant in the room.
The title the joke here is that I'm a tired father
and forgot how to count. Not that funny, but I'm
a developer, not a comedian.
Let's meet our criminal. This is Gil,
but don't let his cuteness fool you. As we will soon see,
he can make your beautiful designs from elegant to a
mess in a matter of minutes.
But before we dive in further, a little bit about myself
so I'm a developer for years now,
but the most important one is that I'm a new father for
two. And the first year as a father,
you are very, very tired because you need to do
a lot of things. You need to keep working and also be with your
son or daughter. And it's
hard. So I got to a
point where it was so overwhelming and
I had to do something. And I'm a developer, so I
used principles that I used in the everyday
work as a developer to make my life much
easier as a new father.
Right? So let's get started.
So monolith design so this
is not me here, obviously you can see from the picture,
but also because my house looked way worse in
the first month when we came back with Gil about
two years ago. But this is what
our application usually looked like most of the time.
If it didn't happen, it will happen. That's okay
because we want to move fast, but once we reach a
certain level, this mess start to affect
our productivity. The main point as a new
father is that you are tired. You can fix everything
around the house. You need to prioritize.
So these picture is where we will start off our journey with
a set of the five developer principles.
So, spoiler alert, I'm going to tell
you right now. What's the key takeaway
that I want you to take from this talk?
The first one is to fight coupling as hard as you
can. Of course, when it's applicable, that will
greatly help you down the road. The second
one is to keep your code as simple as you can and
also be kind. I don't mean here that you
need to be kind in code reviews, even though you should,
or to say good morning in the
morning when you first ask for something on slack.
Also remember the no hello hashtag
what I mean here is to be kind when you are writing code.
I will explain it further in these talk.
So this is where we are going with this. We will talk
about each of these principles. We will start
with definition, code examples, and then my home example.
Let's get started.
All right, so the first one is these single responsibility principles.
The idea behind the SRP is that every class,
module or function in a program should have one responsibility
or purpose in a program.
Let's start with some code examples to illustrate
it better. This code might look okay,
but let's highlight some potential issues.
First one is these function name. It does
two things. It also gets the user and the location.
You can see from the style that this function does two things. Always remember
if there is an and or an or in the function name.
Something is fishy here.
We can also see that in order to get the location, we must
use the user object with its ip.
But why?
At the end we return two objects that are not necessarily
related. So let's try to fix that function.
First we extract the logic of the query validation
and normalization of the user into its own function, which will be easier
to also use in other places.
Next, let's do the same with the location.
You can see that now we don't need the user in order to
get this normalized or enriched location,
just an ip that will give other developers or yourself
the option to use that function when
you need it outside of this scope and
not needing the user id in order to get it
right. And here we have it, the modified version.
Now we have two function that does one thing
right. So here we can see my living room. It's a typical
end of the day state. There are a lot of things
going on here. The toys are the most
obvious. But why is the trolley here?
Why is the laptop on the sofa? Why are there dishes
here? What's going on? Let's move those
to another place and keep the living room for adults.
Kind of all right.
So we moved like it's neater, right?
It's neater. And the secret here is
to move most of the stuff out of the way at these
first stage. You can still see some toys around
because this is also Guild's house. But they are on the
side. And not all the toys are here. I moved them to
their own place. It's Guild's room. I also moved
these trolley to the storage, the dishes to the
sink. And I just left the computer there because
I work these as well.
Next one is the boy scout rule.
Leave your code better than you found it.
So you are tasked with adding a new function that
should calculate some profit. Well, what do you do?
Well, adding the function obviously with
test is what you are paid to do. But what about the rest of these
code? We can see here that down below
that there's these place to add the function and above it's the
already written code that you need to add to.
So what can we do here?
So there is a grammar issue here. That default
date. Got a typo. How about we fix that?
Cool. Also,
what is ACC? And row? What is
r? If someone just went into this function,
will he know what that means?
So we are changing the ACC into total
income, rho into expensive, and r to expense.
But this is highly improved the readability of this function.
So this is the usual case when I
go camping with my family. So we are set in
our camp and obviously we clean after ourselves.
But if these are some trash around us, even though
it's not ours, we will still clean it because it
doesn't matter that other people left it. We want to keep the
world with less trash
as much as possible. This is the original voice cut
rule, right? So let's continue.
The next principle is keep it simple stupid,
not saying stupid. The more complex
something is, the more ways it fails and the more difficult it
is to explain to someone else who actually needs to understand it.
Let's look at some code example.
So this might look like a good idea.
You have one function that holds all the logic to calculate
a specific section did the invoice,
but in reality it will get very large
and very hard to understand when
we'll add more logic into each section or add new section.
In reality, these function is hard to test as well
because you need to know every piece of logic in this long
function, because you need to run the whole function
every time. So let's try it in another way.
Here we split our calculate per section function to
have a function for each section. The above logic
is responsible to take each section and use it how
it likes. And also we can add test for each section.
And by the way, the added benefit here is we
can actually change the order of each section if you want.
For invoice,
let's talk about our home example.
In my house when the baby can't find its
pacifier, you can buy, and I bought a lot of pacifier,
stash them everywhere, closet, everywhere, in the
bed. Or you can just
put a strap on it. Problem solved,
right? Let's move on to the next one.
You ain't going to need it.
Always implement things when you actually need them,
never when you just foresee that you may need them.
Let's say that we need to add a new feature, a function that
accepts a user id and return the user from the Db.
How should we implement it? Let's give it a shot.
I'll give you a few seconds just to briefly look over it.
All right, so this is even not the
worst case. I call reviews and even admittedly myself,
but I want to have something that will actually fit on these slide.
So unless you already have the infrastructure above because you needed
it, there is no need for it. But what
is actually wrong here? Let's find out.
Why do we need an interface, this base repository,
just for a get method? What do we get here?
Other than the thought that maybe down the road it will
help us?
Right? So now it's simpler and we remove
the code we don't actually need. What else is there?
Why do we need this prisma orm here?
So I actually removed these additional code that we actually
need to implement in order to use the Prisma
right here. Like there's a whole infrastructure code in
order to get prisma to work. Why do we need that?
We can just remove the OrM code and use SQl,
what's wrong with that?
But also, why do we need a class?
Can't we just use a function?
Right? I think it's far enough that we went with this,
but just the before and after we
started with this whole base repository
that the user repository extends from with an
Orm and we got to this.
But how does that relate to me being a new father?
So this is a very short list of stuff these baby should
taste and eat from birth to approximately one
year. So I bought special cups
and created spreadsheets for all these stuff that he ate. So I will
know if he's the only child in the world that is allergic
to salt. He's not and most children
are not, but at the end
they just eat from the floor,
so you ain't going to need it.
All right, our last principle is the tell
dont ask.
So the tell dont ask principles suggests that it
is better to issue a command to perform some
operation or logic rather than query its
state and then take some action as a result.
So let's start with these initial example.
I will also give you a few seconds just to briefly
look at it,
right, so we can see that somewhere
in our code base we are checking if a task
is not started created before January 2022
and there is no subscribers
to this task. If that happens, we should just close the
task. But what is wrong here?
We are asking the task for some information
and then we are closing that same task. Why do we care
about that? That seems to be the task responsibility to handle
that internal logic, not the color itself. Let's see how
we can improve that.
We move the internal logic of the task inside task class.
That way the client who wants to use that task object
will tell him to close the task rather than ask for
more information before doing that.
I will finish with the best tell don't ask person.
I know Gil. He isn't asking
for nothing. He demands my attention. He will not
stop until he gets his way.
But one final advice on that don't
ask on the tell don't ask. If you
should do the dishes, do them. Dont ask
for it. Thank you
for watching and for all you new parents.
We are in this together. You can
find me at Twitter, at hashtag
benitool or just send me a message via email.
Goodbye and thank you.