Hi, my name is Maddie Stratton and I'm a staff developer advocate here
at Pulumi, and I am so excited
to be a part of Devsecops here at
Conf 42. We're going to take a little bit to
talk about the journey from DevOps to cloud
engineering, and I appreciate you
taking a little time to walk down this path and maybe
see how things might have changed over
the years. And with that in mind,
before we talk about anything new, I want to talk a little,
but by looking back, let's take a little
bit of a journey to see how we got to where we
are. And maybe that'll help inform what
we could do differently if we kind of think back
at velocity 2009, Paul Hammond
and John Allspa gave a talk called ten deploys a day
DevOps ops cooperation at Flickr. And this was granted
2009. This was fairly revolutionary and as best
we understand it, from unearthing the Arcana,
this tweet from Andrew Clay Schaefer, who Andrew was watching this talk is
the first known use of the term DevOps. Is that important?
Probably not, except that it kind of came, but of this talk.
And likewise, what also happened in 2009,
2009 was a pretty big year for all this stuff in 2009 was
also when Dave Farley and Judge Humble published the
book continuous Delivery, which is still users today when
we talk about these things. So that was 2009. And then also,
finally, Gary Groover published the practices
approach to large scale agile development. This book also
came out in 2009, and there was a book about DevOps. They just didn't call
it that. And so 2009 was really an inflection point.
Another thing that happened in 2009
at that velocity conference, after seeing Paul
and John's talk about Flickr,
Andrew Schaefer, who tweeted that he proposed a birds of a
feather session to say, like we talk about agile system administration.
And one person came to that birds of a feather session, not including Andrew.
And that person was a guy named Patrick Dubois. And later
on, Patrick and Andrew connected and they created an event in
Ghent in Belgium called DevOps Days. And the
reason that it was called DevOps Days is agile system administration
was too long a name for a conference. So if you want to know why
we call it DevOps, that's really why.
But I think it was kind of exciting when we think about this first DevOps
days, it took place in Ghent. If we take a look at
some of the talks that were given there, those could take place at
this conference today. So weve been talking about the same stuff
for a while. The other thing that when we've
looked at how there's been this growth in the
DevOps community, and so much of it comes from these types of community
events, and DevOps comes from the practitioners, from the people that do that,
one thing I think is really interesting is in 2019,
to celebrate the 10th anniversary of the first DevOps days, we did
a DevOps Days in Ghent. And the day before we had a day Zero was
an organizer day, where people who organized DevOps days all over the world came together
to have a little unconference to learn from each other.
So the reason I bring this up is there weve more people attending that organizer
day than attended the very first DevOps days in 2009.
So the movement has really grown, and we can see that over the years.
And why do I bring this up? Why am I talking about DevOps
days? It's not just because I'm the global chair of DevOps Days, and I think
it's a pretty great conference, but it's about these
communities, right? These ideas that we think about when we think about DevOps,
they came from the practitioners. Now talking
about ideas, we, of course, should talk about definitions,
because that's fun. So Donovan
Brown at Microsoft has defined DevOps as the union of
people, process and products to enable continuous delivery
of value to our end users. And I
kind of am into this definition and this explanation of it.
And again, the reason we're talking about definitions is I want to kind of get
us on the same page. So you know where I'm coming from.
And we're talking in a context when we talk about where everything went terribly,
terribly wrong. But yeah,
DevOps is about the people, the process, and the products. It's a bunch
of, you know, put, put Andrew
in a corner a couple years ago and said, andrew, I need you to give
me a definition of DevOps. Andrew is the one who first tweeted
about it and has done a lot of other things, but under
duress. This was the definition Andrew gave me. And you see that
software and human are equivalent in this, which I think is
really, really key. And of know,
I asked Twitter, what is DevOps? Not because if
we know what something isn't, maybe we can reason about what it is.
Hard to say, hard to say. But one thing that's been fairly
commonly accepted when we talk about DevOps is this idea of
columns. You might have heard of this before, and this is an acronym.
This is simply representing some of the principles
that we think about with DevOps. And it's comms and stands
for culture, automation, lean measurement and sharing.
Now, the order of the letters is not significant
other than it spells a word. So if you want to call it clams,
you could, or smolk. But we all sort of say columns. The reason I say
the order doesn't matter is every one of these things is equally
important. And I'm going to break these apart a little
bit and talk about them in the modern thought
around cloud engineering. So I want to dig into them just for a second so
we know what we're talking about and how we compare these tenants. So when
we think about culture, this is sometimes
maybe shortcut is the squishy people stuff, but really it's about how your organization or
how your team operates and how your humans
interact. And the thing to remember about this is, like Lloyd
Taylor said, is you can't directly change culture, but you can change behavior.
And behavior becomes a culture. Your culture is really an expression
of the behaviors, and those behaviors come from incentives,
among other things. So you can't just sort of sit down as a leader,
as a CIO and say, I'm going to change the culture. This is now our
culture, right? You have to influence the behaviors, and the behaviors
are expressed as the culture. When we think about those things and then automation,
this is the one that everybody knows, right? When we think about DevOps, we think
about automation tools and process automation and configuration
management and all that fun stuff. And the
reason that this matters though, besides that, it's fun for
some, value of the word fun is,
as Jez and David said, in continuous delivery. He said,
if you ask experts to do boring and repetitive but technically demanding tasks,
this is the surest way to get it screwed up,
short of depriving them of sleep.
So what we're trying to do here, again, to move at the velocity that we
need to, we need to be redirecting our focus on
the things that require our creativity and our human
adaptive capacity versus things that can be automated.
But automation isn't all of it. It's one of five things. And then we
talk about lean. This was introduced first when
we talked about in 2010, and John Willis and Damon
Edwards first came up with Cams. And then Jez Humble proposed shortly
thereafter to add l for lean. When we think about kind of lean manufacturing
principles, and understandably, this is
not a one to one match, right? You can't run your software organization the
same way that you run an automotive plant. But there are some ideas
that come from the lean movement that are really interesting to us. And one
especially there's several that come in because lean is about reducing waste,
right? So one of the things that we talk about in lean is this idea
of a value stream map, right? And thinking about the value stream. And so if
we think about that in
a tech standpoint, maybe it's from idea to getting
in front of a user, or as John Willis would say, commit the cycle from
commit to cash. We talk about cycle times. This is all part of that value
stream, but it's all the parts that go into that. And this
is not a whole talk about value stream mapping. Steve Pereira, who's at Steve elsewhere
on Twitter, has great content about value stream mapping,
and I'll be dropping some resource links in
the resources for this presentation at the end too,
if you want to learn more about that. But that's really when we're thinking about
how are we looking at ways that we can reduce waste in the process
and look at the entire gestalt of everything and see where these
things happen. And then we think about measurement.
Measuring is really, really key because if we're talking about continuous improvement,
how do we know that we're improving? And oftentimes when
we think about the measures in this perspective, it's not that there's a certain number.
So this is where we kind of think about things like okrs and v two
moms and KPIs and stuff. That's not necessarily the
be all and end all of measurement. It can also just be, is the needle
moving? And is that interesting? They're not necessarily goals or targets to
hit, but they're just ways for us to get an understanding
both from pure performance of the technology part, but also
how are we actually doing with
stuff? And then finally, the s stands
for sharing. And this has a lot to do with just a matter
of getting both. As far as sharing
information in a lot of kind of pathological
or bureaucratic organizations versus
performant ones, there's a lot of information hoarding, because either it can
be when I have this information and someone else doesn't, then that protects
my value. There's also, at a senior level of management, this common
idea of need to know. The reality is, what needs
to be kept from people from need to know is usually a lot smaller than
you think, but it's kind of a form of risk aversion.
But the reality is that the more information we have, the better
we can do our jobs. But also sharing is not
just about that. Sharing is also sharing practices and information.
One really interesting thing when we think about post incident reviews,
so when J Paul Reed did his thesis on how post
mortems are done in large. Actually, one thing he found that I thought was
really interesting is the larger the organization, the less likely teams
were to share the results of their post incident reviews outside
of their team, which perhaps ironically, the larger the
organization, the more necessary because of interdependencies.
So there's a lot of work we can do on sharing. Okay, so these sound
like some like, okay, you're like, this is cool. This is like a revolution.
This is like a cool way to not be jerks to
each other maybe, and move the needle and really be effective
and drive all this stuff. And these were the
principles that weve been talking about in the DevOps movement since
2010, right? That's calms came out in 2010.
And even if you look in 2009, these ideas were all
there. Weve been talking about this for well nigh twelve
years at this point. Right. But we've been doing a lot of
talking. But what happened, that doesn't sound like what
is happening in the discord is actually going on these days.
Right? So we kind of have this thing where it's like
it's all about automation. When you talk about DevOps or DevOps teams and DevOps
engineers, they're automation engineers. And by the way,
I have long since stopped fighting about and being,
you're not going to get me sitting here saying that, don't call yourself a DevOps
engineer or anything like that, because you know what? I'll tell you two reasons why
I don't fight that fight. Number one,
most of the people who have the title DevOps engineer didn't give
that title themselves. So if I'm out here on Twitter talking crap about people with
the title DevOps engineer, the only person that's hurting is the people with those
titles and not the people who came up with them. So I don't do that.
And number two, the title DevOps engineer gets you 20% to
30% more money. So go get paid. I'm all for it.
But that said, we've gotten into this thing where DevOps means
automation. DevOps is scripting,
DevOps is template DevOps. And remember, the a is just
part of, that's one of five, that's maybe one fifth of DevOps. But it's really
become about automation, right? Or it's about Kubernetes,
right? Someone actually, I saw a tweet the other day that said,
are there any conferences that aren't just talks about kubernetes? And yes,
there are, but DevOps all the things is
not container orchestrating all the things, or Kubernetes all the things.
But you might feel like that's where DevOps
equals kubernetes quite often is where we go,
or thankfully, this is kind of fall off a little bit that
it's not about culture. Years ago, there was a very short lived movement for
enterprise DevOps. And one of the kind of loudest
voices in that movement used to say the culture part of DevOps didn't apply
to the enterprise. That, quote, culture was for yogurt.
We know this to not be true, but there still is this thing where it's
like, well, DevOps is the engineering part. There's no people parts of
this. It's not about how we do the work.
And I kind of have
some bad news for you, right, which is DevOps
is being sold to you. That's where we are right now.
And as someone has
said before, you can buy DevOps,
but I can definitely sell it to you by
that. That was me. I'm the one that said that. But I feel like
I've reached the point that I can quote myself in my own talks. I think
I get some kind of cloud leader badge for that.
I'll check on that later. But that's the
thing. We're trying to do a little better though,
right? So we're like, all right, we had DevOps, we kind of talked
about DevOps, and this is about the wall of confusion,
all this stuff. But then we got devsecops. Now we're talking about, I mean,
this is the Devsecops event. So is that portmanteau
a little better? We got security shoved in there now, but that's not.
We have to be more inclusive. What about the business?
Everybody is part of the business, our business goal.
So do we have biz DevOps? But wait. But then we took security up and,
oh, you know what? We need some serverless DevOps because we do DevOps
differently when serverless is involved. Or maybe let's make
sure we really have a big tent. We've got our devsec DB ops ops
because our DB ops people are different than our other ops people. It's a different
kind of ops thing. I don't know. And then of course, we have to DevOps
our DevOps.
That's the thing. Like what? First of all,
I love DevOps and the name is great, but it's really unfortunate because
we feel like we need to express everything through it.
And what this goes to illustrate, if there's
nothing else, now that we're kind of gone through this history.
What have we learned here is that words are hard because
we're trying to express an idea using a
short amount of time. So nuance gets lost in these words.
But don't worry, I have more words for you because that will certainly help.
And what I want to talk about now for the next little bit is this
idea of cloud engineering and cloud
engineering.
One of the ways to think about this is it's employing standard software
engineering practices across, whether it's your infrastructure, it's your app,
Dev, it's your compliance. And this
sounds familiar, maybe, right? This sound a little bit like DevOps,
like software engineers years from web
ops people and security people learn from software engineers.
And it sounds familiar, right? Weren't we trying to
say this before it became all this other stuff?
Because in this sort of cloud first world,
right, we compose our things out of cloud resources
of some kind, right? And we build infrastructure platforms upon them.
And that's where we throw our applications. Maybe we don't throw them, we deploy them.
That's nicer than throwing things. And then we have
to keep them running with our policies or our uppercase or lowercase compliance,
right? The things that we expect. And this
is looking pretty familiar. So when
we kind of break these things down, when I sort of talk, but these,
from DevOps to cloud engineering, building the deploying and managing are sort
of three ways I like to slice them up, right? So if we think about
build. So build sort of might sound like this is
just the writing code part of all of this, but it's about creating
the services and infrastructure that provide,
well, really what our customers and our constituents and our users need.
And like I said, we use cloud resources to build these applications,
then the services and the infrastructure, maybe that's a shared services platform.
So you have a single consistent experience across multiple teams.
Again, it depends on who you are, right? And sort
of when we think about what these are,
we talked about maybe this is composed of shared services platforms.
When we think about reusable infrastructure components,
especially when we think about where you're
not recreating the whole thing and it's not as simple as just Ruby's dry
thing, don't repeat yourself. But about having something
that's, that's sort of understood by a domain expert and then
that's able to be reused, it's building blocks. Hey, this is like how
software works, right? So why can't we do that with our infrastructure too?
It kind of works. And then we can leverage the
ecosystem around those frameworks and tools.
So that's one of the advantages. If you're thinking about tooling
that's using common programming language, that maybe you're writing
this stuff in typescript instead of a bespoke DSL or something like
that, you have all of the ecosystem of go or python or whatever
language that stuff is in, from ides
to testing tools to just common practices. So a lot
of this is about sharing and stuff, right? Okay. So what I'm
going to do here is kind of take this build id. I'm going to do
this for each of our build and deploy and manage and apply how
each of the tenets of columns might apply to that and see how
we can kind of do the layering, right? Like how do these connect,
use that common language. So if we think about the
culture part around build, this is where we talk about focusing on our
differentiator, right? When we're using reusable
shared things, whether they're shared within our organization
or shared with the ecosystem, our organization,
our company, we have a thing that makes us different,
right? And I got news for you. Unless you are like Circle
CI or GitLab or GitHub or someone, it's not
that you're super good at building pipelines, right?
I used to do some work where I had customers that were in
North America, in the public sector, in the US, and I used to say like,
are you the US department of continuous delivery?
No, that's not what you do. Right. So we want to focus on the differentiator,
right? And then the culture part is a common development experience.
So not only, it doesn't mean that every single team in your whole organization is
using the exact same thing, but it does help with that.
Empathy across when we're having similar experiences drives
the empathy, right? So when an automation perspective, these are things like reusable
components help us automate and rebuild. And this,
again, we're leveraging that ecosystem and
all the automation that already exists within that. We don't have to
build new stuff. And this is helping avoid bespoke implementations,
right? How many times you get somewhere and you're like, well, let me take three
months to figure out how we do things here versus like, oh,
this is common within the existing industry or even
within my organization when we think about the principles
of lean, right? Again, we're focusing on value in this
idea, those differentiators. It does help with efficiency,
as a loaded word. It helps with sort of a waste reduction.
But also when we think about continuous improvement as part of that,
it becomes part of our cycle of how we're building these services
and saying where is this kind of coming in from a
measurement perspective is consistency breeds visibility.
And this is a common theme you're going to see repeated
throughout the rest of this talk is
when we're doing things in a similar way, doesn't mean the same way for everything,
but when we're doing things consistently, we have visibility into where
they might differ, and then what needs to be changed.
And then from the sharing perspective, literally the reusable
components. Right? So if I have libraries, I have things like that can reuse.
And just the ecosystem promotes sharing outside, which is
again, that rising tide raises
all boats. And we can learn from existing practices both within the
larger ecosystem, but also just within other parts of our organization.
Hit the wrong arrow key. Sorry about that. Okay, let's talk about the deploy part,
right? I mean, it doesn't count until it's in production. That's for real,
right? Our code and our infrastructure don't really give any value until they're
in front of our customers and users. But we want to do this quality
constant and highly efficient. If it takes us too long or too many
manual steps, we don't have the velocity to get new features
to our customers or also restore service when this happens. So the
thing is, when we apply software engineering practices to our deployment process,
we can ensure that we ship the same way every time.
And it's pretty common. We talk continuous delivery came
out in 2009.
Continuous integration and continuous delivery practices applied to our application software
is fairly common practices now. But we can use those
same principles with our infrastructure. So that means that new and changed infrastructure
resources, they can meet our quality controls and we can track
and understand, especially when we're sort of chasing down that what changed
problem, right? And the value of automation,
our deployment, it's not just about providing tests that make sure that
we do the steps the same way every time.
Regardless of how experienced you are, every one of us
is capable of missing a step or making an error. It's just possible it can
happen, right? And so then we think about checklists,
and I'm going to talk about checklists a bit. But the great thing about checklists,
when I love checklists, is they're even better when a human defines them and they're
run by software. The power of a checklist is defining the
steps, not they're actually running it. So the automation
can express our checklists in code, code that
can be tested, reviewed and managed.
When we kind of think about these ideas, right? We said
it's the same way every time. I mean, every time.
Here's sort of a clue. Like if you have an emergency brake glass.
Oh my God. We don't follow the process when there's an emergency. There's two things
that tells me. Number one is that your process is too slow.
And number two, it means everything is now an emergency. And we
have quality and security checks. So security is just another aspect of
quality when this comes in.
And again, like I said, let's automate those checklists. So,
if we think about how the deploy pieces apply to
the ideas of columns. So from a culture perspective,
having this idea right, it doesn't count unless it's in prod. Like we want to
ship, and we want to ship frequently, so that we can get information.
And we are looking at this as small batches of changes.
And this iterative development idea,
we are not doing these big bang releases because
it's much, much harder to understand not only what changed if something is going wrong,
but if something is going right, why did that something start going
right? Iteration helps us with that which enables for our continuous
improvement, employment improvement. Cool. All right,
so when we think about the automation side of that, right, we think about these
CI CD pipelines. It means we're putting everything through
some pipeline. It doesn't have to be an elaborate pipeline. Your first pipelines can
be, they run no tests. That's the way it's giving
us kind of our glide path and our muscle memory to, that's how we make
changes. And then we can start layering these automated
checks into there where these come in. And checklists are
great. I love mia checklist. So let's automate them, right?
Don't automate their creation. That requires the human creativity and expertise.
But you don't have to tick all the boxes yourself. The robots
can do that. So these
ideas around deployment, these are enabling that fast. The way we think about it
in cloud engineering, this is enabling fast feedback, which helps us see
what's happening in our value stream, right? And it's giving visibility into that
entire supply chain of where all these
places go. And we can find those bottlenecks. So, if we think
about the idea around theory of constraints, the theory of constraints says that
any optimization we make in a process that is not
the largest bottleneck will actually make things worse. So we need to know where those
bottlenecks are. And again, from a measure,
it's that visibility, right? So we're seeing more things,
more information is exposed to us that we are then capturing.
We can think about that cycle time, that value stream,
and it gives us something to understand. Again, there's no magic
number. Just because the cycle time at this organization is this doesn't
mean that's what's right for you, but you need to know what's right for you
and are you hitting it. And again, it's not just about speed, right? It's about
the effective velocity. And from the sharing perspective,
right, it's information that is being shared. If we have,
weve sharing a common approach to our pipelines. From a
shape perspective, weve doing less duplicate work
and it just makes it so much easier. What changed? Because you never know who
needs to touch a thing, right? Or who might be being involved in an
incident or something like that. So it's giving us that understanding of like
here's what happened here. And finally the final sort of tenant
or phase, or I don't really want to call it a phase. Part of
cloud engineering is manage, right? So we can get our stuff into production
and in front of people. But that's not the end. Our customers are constantly
using our services and applications and we have to manage these
resources when they're in use. And from a managed perspective,
it's just sort of making sure that everything is happening the way we expect it
to or that we require. And as it applies to
our applications and services, the visibility across all of our infrastructure allows
everyone on our team, regardless of their role, to have a common
understanding of what's going on. So I'm sure something
that, I mean, we're here at Devsecops, I'm sure you've all heard security
is everyone's job. Well, it's easy to say what that
means in the world of cloud engineering is that we consider security and compliance.
And I talk about lowercase and uppercase compliance, so uppercase is regulatory
policies and lowercase is your organizational policies. But we
consider security and compliance to be closely integrated into our work.
Said before, security is just another aspect of quality.
So if we treat our policy as code,
just like we treat infrastructure as code, our infrastructure as
software, this is a powerful idea because if we express
them as code rather than prose in a document,
then we can apply these policy checks both before and after we deploy our
services and our infrastructure. This also kind of extends that common
vocabulary for collaboration across the teams,
regardless of where you sit in the chart.
The other thing that I like to think about from a managed perspective is that
we need controls in place to allow who can make changes and what they can
change. I mean, you're like, yeah, maddie, I know, right? But why?
Okay, it's not just playing defense, because we
trust our team members to want to do the right thing,
but we need guardrails and controls to ensure that
they are set up to do so. And this means we need
visibility into all the changes that occur, treating our infrastructure just like
we do our source code in version control. Thinking about
versioning our actual infrastructure, not just versioning the code that
deploys our infrastructure. And the thing about having
capability, intentionality around fine grained access controls actually
helps make our team members more successful because they have
more faith and more trust. Right? So again,
we think about the visibility, security being everyone's job. I love
thinking about a common vocabulary because all of that stuff drives empathy.
And the controls and processes enable and enhance,
not just protect, right? So taking us through the
last run through columns here, from a manage perspective,
using common code, common principles around
this really enables collaboration across your,
whether it's software development, whether it's operations, whether it's compliance,
information security,
devsecops, whoever, we're all collaborating
in a way that gets us consistent. And again,
remember, guardrails actually enable confidence.
And this increases a common understanding across disciplines,
which is really what the empathy part that we talk about so much in culture
of DevOps is. That's really what we mean is just have a common understanding,
see where everyone's coming from and what their context is. Right? Sharing context.
Here's the thing about the automation part of all this. Computers can't lie,
right? Tell me how many audits I've been a part of as a sysadmin
for several decades, where the audit was, they asked me
questions. They're like, maddie, every time you deployed this software, did you do
x, y, and z? I'm like, sure I did. Why not? You're just
trusting me, not saying that I would lie on purpose. I might misremember.
But the other thing, again, the gates
put in place that are automated, can't get it.
Come on, just this one time. Do me a favor. My boss is on my
back, right? And then the
process and checks in there enable that trust. And our
policy goes from vague to understandable, right? Instead of it
just sort of being, well, what did you remember we talked about how words are
hard? Okay. All right, cool. So from a lean
perspective, this helps us determine what improvements we
need to make to help increase our safety.
And then we're expressing these value stream changes in code so
we see what's going on with them. From a measurement perspective,
this gives us visibility into current policy. I've heard that infrastructure is code
is executable documentation policy as code is executable
documentation of your policy. So it's much, much easier.
It's not like, okay, well, this is referenced in subsection five, stroke z
of this PDF on this sharepoint that you don't have access to or whatever.
It's like, it's right there. Cool. And it lets us get an instant view of
our current state of compliance. This is really
important. It helps us see when our policy and value collide.
And it doesn't mean that value always trumps policy or vice versa, but we want
to know when that's happening so we can make an appropriate decision.
And finally, the sharing just comes from that
shared vocabulary and also being able to utilize success
patterns wherever those might lie and then sharing that
learning. Right? So when things happen,
we're going to learn something from it. We want to be able to share that
within our organization for people that might not have been directly involved in the
learning opportunity. So when we think about
what DevOps started as and what maybe still
a lot of people hope and dream that it will continue to be.
But compared to what it is, when we think about that, we think about these
ideas of cloud engineering, this is my ask
to you, which is, let's take DevOps back.
Let's make it what it's always supposed to have been about.
We all are clamoring for this, and maybe we'll call it cloud engineering this time
away. Either way, what I want to make
sure we focus on is getting back to these core principles.
That is my challenge to you.
It's been my real pleasure to be a
part of this event. You can find me on Twitter at Matt
Stratton. All these slides and supporting resources
are available at speaking Matty stratton.com. So I've got some supporting
links, some additional reading if you're interested. I have a
podcast called Arrested DevOps. And if you like kind
of silly online game shows about tech, you might want
to tune into DevOps party games, which is another thing that I have there.
So thank you very much. Go ahead and hit me up on Twitter if you've
got any questions, any thoughts on how we can really keep moving things
forward. Thank you.