Hello everyone, welcome to my talk on mastering cloud security automation
using Terraform and chef as integration tool.
Terraform is one of the best products that I've used for infrastructure as a
code which helped me build a lot of infrastructure
in AWS, Google, Chronicle,
tribble as well as splunk cloud.
Like to talk more of my expertise and my experience in using Terraform
and chef and also how did it help the cloud security
automation and I would like to share like
we have a lineup of topics that I would like to discuss starting
with introduction and what is Terraform and chef benefits
of automating cloud security with Terraform,
integration of strategies for terraform and chef security
best practices with Terraform and a real world case study.
The future trends, challenges and key takeaways introduction
so cloud computing automation is on the rise,
but security remains a critical concern. Manual security
configurations are prone to human error and inconsistencies,
so automation of security infrastructure deployment is
essential for consistent and efficient security practices.
The presentation explores more on integrating terraform and
chef for automating cloud security infrastructure.
Terraform is one of very good product, I can
say a beautiful product for open source infrastructure as a code.
Been using this for almost eight years. And the
best part of Terraform is, you know, you can scale up,
expand, destroy,
deploy configurations, everything in a matter of less than two minutes,
let it be in Toronto or let it be in AWS or data lake or
splunk cloud chef on the other hand is is
a master tool for automation and deployment.
Like conflict management platform for automated infrastructure
configuration and deployment. Both tools enable automation,
vision control and collaboration for infrastructure management.
So benefits of automating cloud security. So first
is consistency security configurations across all
the cloud environments you may have a huge infrastructure globally,
say like Asia Pacific, Europe or
you know in America.
So having automation
tool handle these environments is first enables consistency
and the sanity of all the configurations is up in the
repo and also reduce the risk of human error and misconfigurations.
Improved compliance and other ends to security best practices,
faster deployment and scaling of security infrastructure and
increased efficiency and productivity for IT teams,
especially for cloud security. We have the Cert teams,
we have the sort teams, we have the security compliance, we have the global
compliance teams. So everyone using having
like an access to a global environment is
as crucial as having the cloud security automation
in the best practice. So integration
strategies for terraform and chef. So terraform is
mainly used for provisioning cloud resources. Example like virtual machines,
VPN, VPC, transit gateways,
networks and storage and EBS volumes.
We can define the entire architecture
of an infrastructure of a server in terraform saying that hey, I want
like for example if you take an AWS instance, you can say
that I would like to have, maybe I would like
to have a EC two instance with so and so volume with maybe
two, two gates, three gates and however you want to have the EBS
storage volume also terraform provision set.
Chef on the other hand is for configuring and managing the
provision resources. Like for example installing security
software, configuring firewalls, push in confets,
maybe LDAP roles and also a
lot of infrastructure for you know ad
groups as well. Leveraging terraform provider
ecosystem and chefs could put repositories
and also automating the entire splunt, the security
infrastructure lifestyle that we have.
Security best practices with terraform and chef. So implementing infrastructure
as a core principles for security configurations, enabling version control
for audit trails and security automating, security hardening
and patches for processes and also integrating security scanning and
compliance chains in the automation pipeline.
So say that we have a large enterprise with
a hybrid cloud environment challenge,
ensuring consistent security configuration across multiple providers.
So in this example, let's say that we have a hybrid cloud
environment in US,
in Europe, in Australia, New Zealand and Asia.
So having in
a hybrid infrastructure, what you have is for anything for the servers that are on
Prem chef is enabled. So any configuration that you want to push
to the server based in New Zealand or Europe, chef, you know, we do it
with automation using chef and anyone, anything in cloud
say AWS or chronicle or splunk cloud tribal etcetera.
We use terraform challenge ensuring consistency
security configuration across multiple cloud terraform
for provisional resources where we can provide say that hey in
main TF or in networking
TF TF files are the terraform files where we
describe network security groups or resources
and chef for configuring security controls.
The final results of this is improved security posture,
reduced manual effort and faster time to market new services.
Say if I want to have a service up in New Zealand and if I
have the account ready by the networking team maybe it's
a days work of in building the infrastructure, setting up
the VPC network, the transit gateways and also
scaling and you can destroy the instances using
terraform all within an hour. So that's
the best way of, you know, giving an example on how
terraform can we can use terraform to
steal an environment challenges in consideration,
not, not like, not on a very mine critical
scale. It's just like you know, managing and maintaining infrastructure as code
repositories make sure that all the code is checked in reviewed,
peer reviewed, approved and merged and always work
off on YouTube. New pull or a new repo and
integrating with existing security tools and processes like if you have any security
tools that are on Prem, find a
way like you know how we can integrate using Terraform or
chef and how the apps can be deployed using these and
addressing compliance and regulatory requirements.
So if having the Terraform repo made sure
that you know it is only accessible to the team that
are the owners of it, but not like across the
or across the company for compliance purposes.
Increased adoption of infrastructure as a code and configuration managed tools
light of future trends and developments integration with cloud
security posture management and cloud workload protection platform shift
towards policy as a code and compliance as code approaches advancements
in automated security and testing.
The key takeaways is automating security infrastructure deployment
is crucial for consistent and efficient security practices.
Terraform and chef provide powerful tools for automating cloud security infrastructure
integration. Security strategies and security best practices enable organization
to enhance their cloud security posture. Real world case
studies demonstrate the benefit of implementing terraform
and chef and
integrating terraform and chef for cloud security. Automation is
a powerful approach to ensure consistent, efficient and cloud security infrastructure.
This is my conclusion on it and definitely I would
recommend people using chef and terraform.
By leveraging infrastructure as a code and configuration
management principles, organizations can reduce definitely
human errors and improve compliance and enhance their overall security
posture. By embracing tools like Terraform and chef,
organizations can stay ahead of evolving security challenges and maintain a
robust and resilient cloud environment.
Thank you for thank you for joining and I hope you
all enjoy the Con 42.