Hello, my name is Misuthrukal. I'm a quality assurance automation engineer
and in this session I want to talk about the importance of quality
assurance in DevOps principles. We know that DevOps
is trying to bring development activities and operations together
or close to each other as much as possible. And quality assurance
is an important touchstone in this discipline. I'm starting with a beautiful
breed scene, which is not a coincidence because quality assurance
is trying to find ways or channels between different parties
and make the delivery or the transportation possible
between these parties or the stakeholders. So what
we will talk about in detail is, as we just briefly started,
we will talk about the importance of the role or the
place of quality assurance in DevOps. And then we will start talking
about the problems or the challenges that we want to
cope with, or in other words, the achievements or the targets
that we want to hit and aligned with these problems or challenges or
the achievements or the targets. We will talk about several
metrics or dimensions of
quality and I want to focus at least two
fundamental categories, which are the speed and the
reliability or the health of our quality assurance activities.
And eventually we will talk about monitoring activities and aligned
with this monitoring, how well we can fit ourselves
into the product or the project goals, and how well
we can fit in the bigger picture, right? Because as quality assurance
we want to contribute to the product or the project goals.
So how well we can align in this wider
product or the project goal set and how well
we can fit in the bigger picture. Starting from
the role or the importance of quality assurance, let's first of
all consider what we want to do from a wider perspective.
We try to provide the best solution to our customers,
right? But what is the definition of best solution?
So this is the role of Kuala assurance. We try to
ensure we are developing a set of functionalities which
will meet customer expectancies. So sometimes we
try to communicate directly with the end users or maybe the product
owners or the product managers to understand what the
users or the customers need or what they are expecting
from this product. And sometimes we are trying to communicate with
the development teams to understand in what ways they
implemented these features or the functionalities.
So this is why the communication skills are very important
for quality assurance members, because we communicate with
lots of different parties or stakeholders and sometimes we
try to bring all of them together on the same page.
And thinking from the modern project management methodologies,
we know that we are trying to reduce the delivery time
and increase the frequency of deliveries or the deployments.
Because speed is very important. We are competing in time and
in modern project management ways we try to do
the continuous deliveries or the continuous integration activities.
So in this perspective, quality assurance is very important because
whenever we have a neat release candidate, we have to ensure
the quality, not only the accuracy of the functionalities, but also lots
of different quality aspects. We have to ensure, for example,
performance, usability, maintainability, several abilities
of quality dimensions, right? We have to check so
with a proper and health quality assurance process this
is possible. Otherwise there would be some risks whenever
we do not perform the quality assurance activities. Whenever we have a new release candidate,
there will be some potential risks or vulnerabilities and
this would be possible only with a good, or maybe with
an automated quality assurance process set
and aligned with this perspective. Of course, in a scenario
where the quality assurance teams or members are not involved in
the whole development processes, we can understand that
there would be some risks because all the quality
goals or dimensions would not be covered.
And whenever the new candidate or the features
or the implementation would be merged into the production
environment, there would be some risks which would be
resulting in some critical consequences. In the later stages,
we will discuss why this is important to find the
vulnerabilities or the potential risks as early as possible
in the next slides. But first of all,
let's try to understand what kind of problems or challenges we have,
because doing the problem definition in the first place
is important. In this way we can understand in what ways we can contribute
or bring value by understanding the challenges that we want to cope
with. So nowadays the products that we are testing
are really complex and complicated, right? Because they are deployed
in different platforms or execution environments, which means they
have several integrations and interfaces as well, because they
are communicating to different applications as well. There is a large network
of applications and we want to do our verification and validation
activities in this comprehensive scope with different
constraints and limitations. Because there is the time
constraints, there is limited budget, limited resources, there are
some different constraints as well. So thinking about all
these problems and constraints and limitations, we can derive
some different quality metrics to understand how
well we are proceeding with our achievements or
targets. And of course they should be aligned
with the bigger perspective, the product metrics.
So we can start with think and Dora metrics, which formulates
a good set of product metrics. First of all, we can think
of the speed of delivery and the quality of delivery.
We want to provide a good set of functionalities which will
cover the customer expectancies, but we want to do that with a
good speed, ideally the continuous integration,
right? As fast as possible. On the other hand,
there should be a good quality. We should talk about several quality
aspects, not only the accuracy of the functionalities, but also that the performance,
usability and several quality aspects. So our quality metrics
can be categorized in two fundamental groups, the speed
and the reliability, or the quality of
our features or functionalities. So we will discuss these
two categories in detail. And let's start
with the first one, the speed of our delivery.
So there are several aspects or parameters that will affect the speed
of our deliveries. First of all, the direct parameter, which is
the execution of test cases, right? Because it is directly affecting
our pipelines or delivery time. If the
execution of the test cases are slow, which means they are taking
too much time. Of course, after some time, everyone will
start complaining about the test cases. They will say that whenever we
have a new release candidate, of course we want to execute our test cases.
But if execution is taking too much time, they will say that
they are slowing down the pipelines. So execution of
test cases is directly affecting the delivery time. So what
we can do is we can do a time analysis and try to understand
the slowly running test cases, and we can try to understand
the points where it's slowing down the
execution and trying to get rid of the unnecessary weights
or dummy weights in our test cases. Along with
that, on top of the analysis, what we can do is we can
parallelize our test executions. We can divide our
whole set into some subsets, and we can make our
test cases independent from each other.
In this way, we can enable the parallelization of test cases,
and it will already decrease the total duration of our
test execution. On the other hand, even the reliability
is affecting our test execution time.
Maybe it's not a direct parameter, but eventually
how flaky our test cases will be
affecting our test execution time. Because if we have some
flaky tests, which means one time passing and one times failing,
then eventually it means we will need some retries to
retry the failing test cases to understand if they are still failing or
they will start passing. So this means the retries
will increase the total execution duration and it
will affect the speed of our delivery. So in terms of
reliability, we can discuss different conditions. For example,
if our features are properly implemented,
they are implemented as desired. But if our test
case are failing, then it means it's a false alarm,
right? Because our test case is failing. But normally the feature is
implemented as expected. So this is not a real
bug, this is a false alarm. So in this case,
we have to retry our test case, and we have to get rid
of this flaky test case, the false alarm.
On the other hand, if our test case is just passing
whenever there is an unexpected situation in the
feature, in the implementation of the feature, it means there is a silent horror
in our test cases. There is a potential risk
vulnerability. But our test case is just passing, they are
not capable of finding the issue. This is a silent horror case.
So which means we will maybe just let the
issue go in production and we will have some
extra cost in the later stages. These are the reliability issues
and which we don't want to have in our test
execution environments or the test frameworks. But why
do we have some reliable issues? Why we would
have even the false alarms or the silent horror
cases in our test environments or test frameworks? Because we
might have several test smells, as we
may have several smells in our product code.
We can have different test smells in our test automation
framework as well. There are several kinds of test smells, like some
of them are related to test coverage, or some of them are related
to different maintainability aspects of our test code.
But we can get rid of all these kind of test smells to reduce
the reliable issues in our test automation framework and
to reduce these test smells. Of course we need some
strong quality gates. Whenever we have some new test
implementation, we have to check all the code quality even
in our test code. And if we have some issues,
then we have
to stop that, and we don't want them to let go in production
because otherwise there will be some critical consequences.
Maybe there will be some silent horror cases, or maybe there
will be some false alarms stemming from this kind of testimony.
So if we have some quality gates, which can be either
static code analysis or doing the code
review activities, the peer review activities. But by
enabling these kind of quality gates, we can already
find the vulnerabilities even in the test code and
stop them before merging into our test automation
frameworks. So the execution speed of test cases
is already affecting the delivery, but also the reliability of the test
cases. Because whenever we have a failing test, we have to stop the pipeline
and try to understand if the failure is a real bug or
a false alarm. And even the maintainability of our test
cases is affecting the delivery speed. Because whenever we have
a false alarm, which means whenever we have an issue in the test itself,
we have to fix the issue in our test code. And until
we fix and we make the test passing again,
we have to stop the pipeline. And whenever we make the test pass
again, then we can continue with the delivery. So this means how easily
we can fix the issue in the test or
how easily we can maintain our test is
a parameter that really affects the delivery speed. So how
we can improve the maintainability a very well known example is the
UI automation, right? Whenever the layout of the page is changing,
then of course the selectors or the locators of our
elements on the web page should be updated in the test code.
And if we follow good coding practices or
some patterns that will contribute to maintainability,
then we can easily update, for example by excluding
the locators from the test classes or the spec files, then we can easily
do that. By following these kind of good practices
or different approaches, we can try to improve
the maintainability because otherwise it will be slowing
down our pipelines to fix the issues in our test code.
One more good practice to improve the maintainability is removing the
duplication or avoiding the duplication. Because whenever we
have repeated core or duplicated code in test spec
files, then whenever we need an update or fix,
then we have to go to all relevant piece of code
and we have to fix in all of them. But if we have only one
source of truth, for example a dedicated
class file where the implementation is done, then we can go
to the relevant part and fix the issue in
only one source of truth. These kind of different
approaches or good coding practices will help us to
improve the maintenance. So summing up the first part in
terms of the speed, of course we can improve our
execution speed by enabling or embracing the parallelization
or improving the reliability of test.
By removing the test mass or even improving the maintainability
will contribute the delivery of the speed.
Now let's investigate the second aspect of the quality assurance activities,
which is effective testing. How capable or how good our test
cases are to find the issues in the early stages because we might
have test cases running very fast or we might have 100%
coverage metrics, but still we might have some escape bugs
or escaped issues which were not found in our testing activities
but just reported from the production environments. But what might
we be missing or overlooking? What might be the reasons for having
these escaped bugs? Because normally we try to cover all the test
cases or all the features with test cases,
but still we might have these kind of issues. So we have to
go back to verification and validation distinction. Sometimes we
just talk to the development teams and try to understand what is being implemented,
but this is not the only thing that we have to ensure. Right on top
of that, we have to understand if the implementations
were already aligned with the requirements in the first place. This is
the distinction between verification and validation. What is being
implemented and what was supposed to be implemented. So this
is aligned with the customer perspective and customer focus.
So we have to understand what was expected or required
by the customers and what are we delivering or providing
as a solution to them. So to try to improve
this mindset, we can ensure that we are running the correct
scope. We have to update our test cases whenever we have a new implementation
or whenever even we have a new refactoring on the code
base. Then we can try to check if our test cases are
up to date, or if we are running any or
if we are running any coverage issues. But not only the test steps or
the test context, but also the execution environment is very important
because sometimes, for example, let's suppose we have a
data upload feature. So this might be
running with different data types or data ranges.
So not only running with certain data types like integer
values or string values, but also running with double values
is also important. Or not only with positive values,
but also negative values are also important. So supporting
the test steps with the relevant test data or running
in the correct or supposed potential execution
environments is very important because sometimes different users are running
on different browsers, with different devices, or with
different operating systems. So not only running
the correct test steps on a certain environment,
but also running on different potential execution
environments is also very important. So one
more thing that we might try to follow to improve our
test coverage is trying to embrace different test design
techniques. There are some different techniques like equivalence partitioning
or boundary value analysis,
not to overlook some corner cases or boundary values or
different data ranges.
To avoid these kind of issues, embracing different test
design techniques can be a good approach or a
good test design pattern. But also
there is one more thing that we can adapt in our quality assurance activities,
which is the personnel based testing. By thinking of different
personas or different characteristics, we can come up with different scenarios,
for example, thinking of different users from different regions
or different ages, or with different characteristics,
with different activities or motivations or frustrations,
we can think of different use cases or different
scenarios. So in this case we try to avoid having or
overlooking some different scenarios. For example, aligned with
this, we can come up with, for example,
for different people, maybe the accessibility
or the performance is more important than
other aspects, or for other users maybe the
usability or the user friendliness of the interfaces
is more important. So in this way we can try to cover all
the aspects of the quality, not only the functionality,
but also all the non functional aspects would be covered
by thinking from different perspectives and trying to understand
all kinds of or types of different use flows in
our product or on our feature.
Lets we try to discuss the
quality assurance improvements that we can do to contribute or bring value
to the product perspective. Right? We try to provide
or support the deliveries from two different fundamental
aspects, which is the speed and quality, because we want to have
a fast and high quality delivery and we try
to support it from the quality assurance perspective. But how
can we ensure that we are proceeding in the correct direction? Of course
we can utilize monitoring activities and we can collect several metrics
to understand how well we are proceeding in these dimensions
or the aspects of quality. And we can talk about
several different metrics. But one of the first metrics set
from the quality perspective is the issues or the bugs that
we have because it will directly give an idea about how quality
how level of quality we have in our products
or the feature sets. So we can show different distribution
of bugs across their severity levels or across the component
on which they were found or the module on which
the bugs were found. But apart from those, I want to
highlight the importance of having the post mortems which
is kind of trying to understand or trying to interpret them,
trying to talk to them, because bugs have several meaningful
or valuable information. Understand. And if we try
to understand what they are trying to tell us, then we can collect
some insights and we can try to reveal some weaknesses
in our processes and the product. And we can try to introduce some
new initiatives and improvements for the future activities. Because quality
assurance is not only finding the bugs, this is already good enough,
but also trying to avoid them in the future activities.
If we try to interpret the previously created bugs, then we
can try to understand what kind of weaknesses we had in
our past activities. And by trying to improve them,
trying to create some new initiatives, we can try
to avoid them in the first place in our future activities
as well. So not only the bugs of course, we can call several
other metrics as well. So what we can do is we can transform
them into some visual graphs or charts and monitoring
dashboards. Because sometimes interpreting the raw data is
not easy. But if we have some visuals then we can easily
understand what is going on in our environments and what kind
of trends or charts we have. And we can
try to collect some insights about the health of
our processes and the product and the processes and try to
improve them for the future activities as well.
So to sum up, we tried to discuss the role or the importance
of quality assurance in DevOps practices. We discussed the problems or the
challenges we have and we discussed the ways to contribute
to our product goals from quality assurance perspective. For example,
we discussed how we can support fast delivery
in terms of the execution speed. We try to improve the test
execution duration or test execution time, and we try to
reduce the number of false alarms because whenever we have them we have
to stop the pipelines. Or whenever we stop the pipeline,
we try to fix the issues in the test code. So we discuss the importance
of improving the maintainability of test code because
that would directly affect the time where we stop our
pipelines. On the other hand, we discussed ways to support the
quality of our deliveries whenever we have some reliability issues
or coverage issues. We might have some escape bugs,
but we discussed ways to embrace different test
design techniques, or embracing different Persona based test
techniques or different approaches to improve our
coverage and the reliability of test framework or test environment or test
set to avoid those kind of issues. And eventually,
we discussed importance of continuous monitoring
to continuously get some insights about potential
improvements that we can embrace in our processes and
the quality of our products. So thanks a lot for listening
to me and if you have any questions or feedback, I would be more than
glad to try to answer them.