Hi there, my name is Kevin. I'm Seth from change engineer
in Brazil and I'm here today at Conf 42
DevOps 2024. And and
first of all, happy new year for all of us and I'm
very happy, excited and a little bit nervous because this
is my first international talk and
my first english talk. So ignore this fact.
But I'm grateful to be here talking about web workers
and how we can handle with have processing
on the client side. So let's begin and
just to introduce myself and how I said before,
my name is Kevin Uehara. I'm Stefan Change engineer
at iFut. I will be talking about ifut
in the next slide. I'm from Brazil, Sao Paulo. I'm a
speaker and tech content creator at YouTube. You can find
me there. I'm a community partner at Nodebr,
that is Node Brazil community.
I'm organizer of campiness from change.
Campiness is the city where I live.
One of my hobbies is trying to play cs contrast,
but always I remember that I'm
very bad and I didn't play it CSQ
yet. I'm developer for about nine years and focused
on the front chain for about five years and I'm very,
very typescript somalier. I love it.
So talking about ifuT,
the current company where I work today,
ifood is the most big tech food delivery in Brazil.
I work in the ifood logistics tribal. I work
in two chains, location areas and location
gel. Together these two chains
are called by Maps platform. We work
with gel processing, geolocation, partner delivery areas,
deliver routes and much more. Okay,
so let's begin what I will be talking
in this presentation I want to introduce you
what is web workers? I want to show
some application that I built and
see how we can use webworkers,
the results and if the time allow us.
Let's write some code and let's
finish with my contacts.
So the application overview let's create
application first without using web workers and
then we will implement it and visualize the application performance.
And after that we will refact the
entire application using web workers and compare
the results and the performance. Okay,
so what is web Workers?
Web workers is an API provided by the browser.
By default we know that JavaScript itself,
the vanilla JavaScript is single thread without
going to the merits of node js with Lab UV.
However, we note that we have the image
loop callback query stack and this entire architecture
is provided by engine V eight. And we
can say that JavaScript can handle a synchronous process on
demand. Okay, so the browser
offers a series of API that can be used
by development team like storage for example session
storage, local storage,
indexDB workers, PWe performance
monitoring, lighthouse devtools and a
lot of more of features. And one of
the topics I want to address in this talk is web worker
and how do they live, how do they survive, how do
they reproduce? I'm kidding. But why to use
what is the benefits? So let's see.
Web worker are mechanisms that allow operations,
usually large populations or huge operations
to be executed from the main thread, making sure the main
thread is not blocked.
What I want is for a function to perform certain have processing
that will block integrations with the page,
the UI. So imagine that you
have web app and you are
making large or huge
processing but you don't
want your page is
blocked. So the user can't interact
with your page because you are making
this large operation in the main thread. Okay, so this
is a problem and how we can resolve this
using web workers is one of the
solutions that we can use.
Okay, so I want to introduce you this
API. I wrote this article
where I did dive in the same topic
and this concept that is web workers so
you can search in Dev Chio
by Kevin we had or introducing JavaScript web worker
and how I said I deep dive in this same
concept and the same example that I
will reproduce with you. Okay,
so let's choose the app.
So the shown the code. So for our
demo project we will not use any framework or lib.
We're going to use just vanilla
js to do this we will create our workspace
with the following files, the index HTML,
the index js and some styles for our
application, okay, simple styles,
okay, because I'm from James I'm kidding
but we have the script files, okay and
ignore this code here. But we have this
extension here called live server. That is
extension. If you don't know live
server is extension of this code you can use just
to provide a server. And we
have the hot reload, okay so
to the HTML we have this simple
HTML here. We are importing
the style here and the Javascript
here. Okay, so I'm using async import.
You can use defer or async.
But for this example we need to use async.
Okay important. So we have
three elements here, two buttons.
The first button will start a large operation and
the second button will change the background color
of our page. And this pretext
is where I will print the result
of the large operation. Okay,
so this css I'm resetting the
full styles and adding some
styles for our button the paging
background preserve. So that's
it easy. Okay, so the Javascript
file the index js we have this first
function here, we have three functions. The first function
will simulate the large operation. So we
have the valley starting with zero and
we going to increment this valley
using the loop and start with zero and
using the four until 1
million, I think that is one and
eight zeros, okay, and multiplying
by 30
and I return this value here.
Okay and we have this two
event listeners here. The first we will start the large process
and call this function here just
to simulate a large operation in the main thread.
Okay. And console log here processing
the value. And the second button
will change the background color of our page.
So if it's white I will change to dark and
if it's dark I will change to white. Okay,
so let's see the result of
this application without using web worker. So notice
that I will click in the first button that we
will start the large operation and
I will try to click on the second button that will
change the background color, but I can't click because
the main thread is blocked. So let's see,
I clicked on the first button and I
can't click on the second button because
the main thread is blocked until the
large process is finished and the main thread
is free. Okay,
so to resolve this problem I
will use the web worker, so I will create
this fileworker js.
Okay, so I will change
something here, I will move
that function, handle large operation that
was in the index HTML to here
in the webworkers js.
And we have this function here,
this anonymous function called omessage that
we receive as parameter the event,
and we are comparing the
name of our operation that I
name it as operation. You can give any
name you want, but I give operation
and if I receive operation I
will call the handle large operation function.
And after that I will post message with
the value, okay, so that's
it, this is the file and
let's refact the index js.
Okay, so here I'm instantiating
the worker and
processing the path of our file, okay,
worker js. So I create the worker
and instantiation. And here
I'm just creating this before and after just to bring
the time in seconds. And here I'm
calling the function of web
worker, that is post message processing the name
of the operation
that I give operation. So it's the same name
here,
and after that I call
this o message that will
be listening if the large
process, it will be
created on worker from
Maingrad and after the process
on the worker is finished,
it will call it
callback. And this all message to print
and you can use the data that you process
it. Okay, and I'm getting
the data here and printing in the text
content tag, that is the pre tag.
Okay, so this
is the change that we
have. Okay, so the result,
I click it on the start button, large operation,
but we can change the background color
and the user can interact with your page
without being blocked. So the main
thread is not blocked. Okay, so this is
one of the benefits to use the web worker you can
use without blocking the UI.
So that's it. This is our example.
For large or huge operations you can use
web workers and this is one of millions of
solutions that you can use. Okay,
so that's it in oh
my YouTube channel.
If you want to know me more,
I have the YouTube channel, you can
find me there by Kevin Mujara how
I said before, I'm content creator,
we have a lot of courses but I'm speaking
Portuguese but you can use the captions.
We have courses like Ratchi
state management and lot
of more of content. Okay, so you can find me there.
And remember I have this
article on dev tube that I did
diving in this concept, the same example,
but I explain in more
details. Okay, so here are my
contacts, okay, my linkaging, my Instagram,
my twitter, I don't call x,
so I call twitter,
my GitHub, my dev co where
I post some articles there,
my YouTube channel and the SKR quote that
you be redirect to my
link tree that will have all my social medias here.
So you can scan this QR code, okay,
and let's hands on on the
code, let's write this same example,
okay, so I
will open my terminal, I will create
this directory
and I will open my vs code, okay,
so I will change
my tab here and that's it.
Close something here and
let's create our files. So my index HTML,
the index JS
and the style CSS.
So the HTML we have this autocomplete
here, HTML five. So let's
create the title with web worker example
and let's add our elements,
bottom start large process
and the second button change
background color and
the pretext with IG
output. Okay,
so I will
accelerate my desktop
and using the copy paste just
to be quickly because
it's not so important. Okay, so we have this
import of our style here
and the index js, okay so for
our index js, let's create
our function here.
So this function handle large operation
and with the value starting with zero and increment
this value and return it. Okay so
let's add the elements here.
So let's get the elements by id.
So the BTN large operation and BTN
change color and the output and I forgot,
sorry, I forgot to add the class
and the id for these
elements here. So let's add and
let's add for the second button.
Okay so
just adding the style here.
So we have this body style and
I'm resetting the css and adding
some styles for our button. Okay so
in the index going back to
our index js, let's add the event
listener for the second button.
So if the background color is white I will
change to black to dark, or if it's
white I will change, if it's dark I will
change white and if it white I will change to
dark. Let's add another
event listener here that will start this is
a spoiler. So let's remove
and just print a const
valuable and receive the handle large operation
here and print on
text content the value.
Okay so that's it. Let's start our
application, use the live
server. So I will click here and start
the server and it will open my
application. So there's two buttons,
okay so I can change the background color but
if I click on start sludge process,
you can see that I'm clicking in the change background
color but I can't change
until the process is
finished. So now I can change the
background but if I click again I can click
on the background color.
So let's refact our
application. So I will create the worker
file, I will
get this function here
and move to worker and
we have the
function that call all message that
will receive an event.
And if event data
equals for example, I will
give another name, for example large
and I will get the value
calling the handle large operation and
post calling the function post message
with the value easy busy.
Okay, and we finish our workers
and let's refact our index js.
So now let's remove
this function of here and
let's instantiate worker.
Let's instantiate our web
worker. So let's call worker and pass
the path of our file that is
worker js.
So we are going
call the the post message
function with the same name large
and we are going to
called the all message function that we
will receive I event and
just calling the output text
content with the event data.
So that's it. Okay, let's see
if it's working. I can change
the background color but if I start the large
process we can interact with our page
while our large process is
being executed on the
web worker and the main thread is free to
the user interact with your page.
Okay so guys that's it.
This is our example and how we can
use the webhook worker. It's simple
applications but that's it. It's very simple
to use this API so you
can use for your applications
and again this is one of solutions. Okay so
guys, thank you so much and I say
in every video that I created
so stay well always. Okay?
So thank you so much. I appreciate if
you like it and if you like it give me some
feedback in my social medias okay?
Here in my linkaging, Instagram,
Twitter however and I
hope you like it. Okay can thank you so much and
see you soon.