Hey everyone, welcome to Conf 42. Thank you for tuning in to listen
my talk. Today I'll be presenting on optimizing performance
and security and building a robust API in go.
So we'll look into different ways how we can
make our API much more performant,
fast and secure. So let's do a
quick introduction about myself
yeah, so I'm currently working as a senior SRE at Capsule.
I'm also a docker captain and apart from that my
work revolves around backend container systems and security.
So let's get started. There are one building
an API. There are a couple of things that we wanted our API to be.
One is we want it to be secure, we want it to be fast,
and we want it to be robust. So in this talk we'll look into how
we can, how we can address each
of those using different techniques.
So first let's see how we can make our API
secure. There are a couple of things that need
to be done when you're working with security and
authentication and authorization. First of all, like if you
are using conventional username password, it's best to use token based
authentication as it is more secure and also
know when like what type of token to use. In what kind of scenario
like access token or id token, you could use
something like assigned JWT with strong algorithm and
strong secret. However, we all know that JWT
comes with its own set of issues, mostly regarding
misconfiguration. This is where the newer newer way newer
newer tech like pistol comes in, where it is more opinionated and
leaves less room for errors. If you are using SSO,
using Oauth, it's good. If you like, it's good to choose
like Oauth 2.0 with proper authentication.
Sorry, the overflows like
when you're working with microservices authentication and authorization,
you need to use like you it's good to use access token and
refresh token. So it depends on the
company and the team. The other thing that we can make our API more
secure is use a proper course configuration.
A lot of time we see people using leaving course configuration
as default, which leaves API open to different,
different problems.
And, and most of the time when we store cookie s or so
store token, we store it as a cookie. And in order
to make our cookie robust or secure, there are a couple of things
that we could do. One is enabling secure and
HTTP only flag. Basically what this says is our
cookies can be transmitted only if the connection is using
TL's and means SDP. Only flag
tells that JavaScript cannot interact with the cookie.
We also need to store our cookie. It's good to encrypt it.
There are a couple of different ways, but one of the widely used is
HMAC with salt. People use salt and pepper,
but it's HMAC with strong secrets as
a salt should we should be good enough when we're working
or whenever. When we are developing locally. We use SEM site policy as
a bit relax or lax, but people forget to change the
configuration in production to be more streamlined.
It's good to use principle of list privilege when you're working with authentication
and authorization. And the other thing that I
like to do when working with API is I like to re
authenticate user before any kind of critical change, whether it's the email
change or password or update profile, profile update
basically, even if they are logged in. So any
kind of change they are trying to do should be,
should be checked against. Is the user authenticated to the do the operation
and also is the user are authorized to do it? Again,
this is kind of extra guardrail we can add in
when working with API. The other thing or
the next thing that I wanted I'd like to do is validate inputs.
It's good to validate and sanitize all the inputs coming in so that we protect
ourselves from injection attacks like SQL, NoSQL or XSS.
You could roll your own utility functions to do
this stuff. But there are other better test libraries which you
can leverage like validated and blue Monday. Here's an example which uses
validators. Let's go to
the other one. I like to create
an audit trail of user activity. This is like, this is interesting
because how it works is first we define set of
activity that user is allowed to do and create.
Then, then for users activity we create
audit or log trail. And if user tries
to perform any kind of activity which is outside
its defined baseline, we alert, or,
or basically alert the user.
Like administrator example would be user who
is a customer should not be trying to log into the portal. Like, so basically
this, this like having a trail would
help us in the retrospect of the
things that you as a user was trying to access also, and also helps us
proactively protect us from malicious actors.
The next thing that I, it's good to do is
use appropriate response as part of the, as part of
the API response. Because let's see an
example here. When like if in the above example we can see
if the user doesn't exist, we say user doesn't exist,
right? However, with this error message,
the attacker can enumerate whether the user
actually exists on the system or not based on the response.
However, in order. Like instead of explicitly
saying whether user exists or user doesn't exist,
it's good to have a generic response for everything
so that people cannot run like malicious actor cannot run
enumeration attacks. So password
management is also one of the key thing that you need to be careful when
working with API security. It's good to use one way
hash functions so that while storing the password and
also while comparing them, one of the most widely used is bcrypt.
The other thing that I like to do when working with passwords is I don't,
I don't allow certain consecutive characters from user
email or any of their field in their password. So what
this does is basically eliminates attackers trying to do
brute force based on previous known knowledge of
their like emails or something. And the other thing, interesting thing
that we, we can do is check user's password against
a list of like one hundred k a million probably
common most common password. And if it falls
on one of those range, we just deny it.
It's good to do that. So here is
an example I'm checking a password to in like
checking the request password in if
it falls on the range of common most common use password
and if it's, if it false, then we say password to common and send
a status bad request. Other than that, what we could do
is we could check for complexity. So they're making sure that
user password has consist of certain healthy amount of
alpha numeric characters, a string or and,
and numbers and different like uppercase and lowercase
list. And we make sure like certain length is also fulfilled.
We don't want the password to be too short so that it could, it is
easily breakable using brute force.
And the next thing that we could do to secure IPA is
like using passing secret to config file instead of environment
variables. Personally I don't like using environment
variables, like are using secrets using on like
passing secrets through environment variable. The main reason being
they can be accessed from any part of the program. Like people can just go
like to osgod like get amp and then
fetch the secrets. Instead of that you could just pass
the secret from environment where like config file.
Because now when you load the config file and pass it to each
functions which require it to like direct argument or
dependency injection, like you are basically the single
like single instance of that configuration is being passed around throughout the
program. And also you can lock the like
lock the file with file system permissions as well.
So it's like, I find it much much more like
what you call gated compared to environment variables.
So here's an example of server struct which, which has configuration
as a dependency and you can pass it using like
pointer receiver.
The next thing that we can do to make our API more secured is
secure is masking sensitive data.
Basically we want, we want to mask
any kind of sensitive data which might reveal user information while
either it's in transit or address. So there are different techniques
like just using the masking data masking technique where you
could just like encrypt the data as well or use to organization
depending on the circumstances. So next
thing that we could do to implement is implement rate limiting.
People get confused like how limiting actually
helps in security, but, but it helps us to prevent abuse and
protection using DDoS attack. So basically
we don't want people like malicious actors
slamming our API endpoint and, and like dosing
it, right? So it's good to implement rate limiting
algorithm. There are different algorithm like fixed window account,
leaky bucket and token bucket. However,
implementing rate limiting, we need to consider a couple of things as well.
One is we need to plan for burst. There might be some situation
where certain source of traffic might come, like example
salesbitting problem. Or we
need to make sure like we need
to make sure like each endpoint are different and each
endpoint like traffic on each endpoint come
at different rate. For example,
password reset API endpoint might not receive same
amount of requests, same number of requests per like per
minute or per second compared to get orders or list
items, right. So we need to make sure like each of
them have like specific rate limiting policies applied to it.
And what I like to do is implement like respond
the rate limit as part of the response metadata.
For example, here I am responding the total limit
of the request and the remaining amount of rate
limit. And also like when the next time the like
rate limit window would be re
initiated. Basically this is, this is the next time
the rate limit would be reset.
Next thing that we could do to secure our API is having
us like HTTPs connection between client and the server
or API. And we could also implement
API to support TL's natively.
This is like kind of good practice because not always we
will have some kind of proxy sitting in front of our API
to terminate the TL's. It's good to have
the functionality where you can natively support TL's if need be.
And other thing that we need to be very careful
is we can't build everything on our own, right? There are
instances where we need to use external libraries.
This is where staying on top of your patch management is
a must. And I use tools like a sneak GitHub
dependable and even if it's too noisy, this, it gives,
it gives you at least like helps you stay on top of your patch
management. And, and using tools like CSM,
like CSM, tools like Wiz is like added benefit.
So we talked about how we can make our API secure. Let's see how
we can make it fast. I had
to put it here like there are countless instances
I've seen developers using select asterisk to get
in the data and then perform the conditional queries.
However, the problem with this type of query or this query
is it loads everything into the memory
and then performs the logical operation instead
of that. If you know what are the fields that you are looking after
or looking for, you can explicitly define okay,
I need this column from this database where, where the
details is this. And, and basically what this does is it reduces
the total amount or optimizes your query. And, and basically
the, the load or like resource load on
the database would be much much smaller. And if
you find like multiple column, like same column being requested a lot
of time we could, what we could do is implement indexing
so that it is more efficient and optimized.
The other thing that we could do is minimize redundant queries within our API as
well.
So next thing that we can do to make our API fast is implement
caching. I think this is a no brainer.
If the same thing is being repeated again and again without being changed,
it's good to cache it, right? Because it has a
lot of benefit. One is like it reduces the latency.
The next thing is it maybe like it
puts lesser load on the database as well because
now API doesn't need to actually like talk to the database,
database doesn't need to do the processing and return the value. There are different
ways you can cast one is in memory, or you can use external key value
stories like Redis and I like to
respond, respond with like cache
cache control headers like etag or cache control so that
client can cache certain data for like on
if they have the capacity to do that. And leveraging
CDN for static contents like images binaries is
also a good idea. The next
thing that we can do to improve our API performance is pagination.
Basically, instead of returning all the data and trying to
organize into group, what we say is I only need
this much like this first ten data
and, and then you request the next ten data. What this
does is it reduces the data transfer size and which,
which ultimately makes our query much faster and,
and if it like effectively makes our like reduces the latency as
well. So pagination, like using pagination,
we can make our API like pagination is not
just for what you call you. You don't have to use pagination
just for like making it look nice, but it also actually helps
in making your API much fast.
You can use different techniques like cursor based pagination or offset based.
Here I'm using offset based pagination where I specify
the page number and the total page size I want.
And I think everybody seen this coming. If your application is
too large, it's good to break it into smaller services.
Breaking your application into microservices helps you make it
like make the application independently scalable, maintainable,
update able. Like it will be resilient to failure
if you make it right and future proof as well.
So microservice is good. However,
microservice is also a double edged sword like sword.
A lot of time we see people implementing microservice just because
things like they think it is good. However, like do
not just go about converting your app into micro service just because you
can, right? For personally, I think what I think
is microservice is only required if each business
unit or each domain of your
app is handled by separate teams. An example would be like fulfillment,
order processing or payment. So yeah,
now we talked about how we can make our API secure. We talked
about how we can make it fast. Let's, let's see how
we can make our API robust. The one thing
that I follow is fail early, fail fast approach. Basically what
it says like what this means is we fail immediately
if something, some condition are not satisfied. Like we don't wait until,
until, until the actual like resource is, is required.
This helps to reduce cascading failures and also helps
us quickly identify different issues issues before they
become a major concern. And in general it makes the API
more robust and stable. So here's an example.
Since our server is dependent on configuration
from past configuration like protocol or
TL's passed from the config file, we,
we first check whether config file is present. If it's not,
we just feel like immediately return the error and fail.
So this is a good example of fail fast and fail early.
Let's look at the next slide. Yeah. The other thing
which we can do to make our API more robust is
use appropriate status code based on the situation.
So like, let's see an example here.
Here we have to get responses to API admin.
One returns 401 unauthorized and the other one responds with
403 forbidden. Now suppose,
suppose user logs in the credential are correct,
but the user is not allowed to access the page. Now which,
which response code do you think is the correct
one? This is the like correct
and more more readable one, right? Because you
401 unauthorized means like credential
was correct but user is not authorized to do something. So basically what?
Like basically using appropriate status code, it helps us like add
more clarity and understandability to your API as well.
And also it helps us to easily detect the error.
However, we don't want to, as discussed previously as
well, we don't want to reveal too much information which would be,
which can be used against us to compromise our security.
So we need to find that sweet spot between security and robustness.
And yeah, I think every, like all
the groupers know this, don't just check errors,
handle them gracefully because just returning
nil. Okay, looks like I did a typo over here. It shouldn't be capital like,
please forgive me. However, like don't just return error
like this. They call it naked, naked error
or something like that. It doesn't have any
information. It doesn't give you more idea what actually happened and caused
the error. So adding context to error is a good idea.
So what I, what I personally try to do is I only
panic on the main function and any function outside the
main or any of the modules,
I return the error back to the main function and
return them up the call stack. So basically, suppose if something,
some error occurred, I would return, create an error
and then return it, return it up the call stack so that it
can be printed with a nice, nice context around
it.
So the next thing that we could do to make our API
robust is passing context. Context as in here,
I mean, request id require, like passing request
id on each request helps in tracing and debugging here.
Let's look an example over here. Right? So somebody did a post request
and the request id is this. And let's,
let's assume the request came in and
the request was successful, but the client,
like we sent a response, client was not able to get
the response for some reason, and it tried to retry again with the same request
id. Now if we pass the request id,
we can check whether this id is already seen or not. And if
it's already seen, we can actually ignore
or don't don't take any action on this request.
So it's really good idea to pass id request
id when you are dealing with APIs and there
are other benefits as well, it helps you to correlate between different logs.
Because when we aggregate log all the log into single
location, we know like not
all logs comes at the same time. And it helps like using request id helps
us correlate. And also you can pass it with the
tools like JQ, right? It's your integration
with tools like Sentry, Jaeger and like
in general maintain idem potency.
Let's go next one.
Yeah, so the other thing that we can do to make our API more
robust is make it acid compliant.
What? Acid compliant? I'm like, what I mean by that is
our database transaction from our API should be either
all or nothing. So suppose if you are using, if you are
using a banking, like creating a banking application where user
was charged, the user bought something and
when user buys something, some amount needs to be deducted
from their account, right? But for some reason the account got
like amount got deducted but the checkout
was not successful. There should be some
mechanism where you set up so that if the order fails
the transaction for reducing like deducting the amount should also be rolled back.
So this is where like using context and transaction makes the operation
more asset compliant. And it is more like
making API asset compliance is much really important when you are working
with multicultural collection updates because
updating to one collection might work,
whereas might not work for the other one. So it's good idea.
Let's make it next. Yeah, the next thing that we
could do is use structured log. Like as said
in request id are passing context.
Context request id using structured log helps you
maintain and it helps you to like debug and search search
your logs easier as well. Using structured log you can directly
integrate with tools like low key or other different observability
tools. The next thing that we could
do to make our application more robust is implement health check.
Here's an example of readiness and liveliness.
Uh, health check response. So basically
health checks has a lot of benefit,
mainly be being like, you know, whether your application is
running or not and also whether the application is ready to receive the
workload or not. So this is like,
this concept is like it is already used in
containers or docker containers as well. However,
there's no reason for us to not not use the same in
our APIs as well. It like you can use it for service discovery,
you can use it for auto scaling and load balancing.
So here this is the example of readiness,
sorry, liveliness probe. So liveliness response or health
check where we like see,
check whether the server is running or not with with like commit
id, branch and tag. And here we are checking whether the
services that the API depend on are okay and the connection
is successful or not. This is where like we, we verify whether the
application is ready to receive the workload.
The other thing that we could do to make our API more robust is
handle retries really gracefully.
So let's imagine like some
client got booked and it kept on retrying the
same request again and again. Like we call it retry storm.
Other than like having a bad user experience,
it adds loads to the load to the server because it
like we are effectively trying dosing our server,
our API. The, the way we could resolve
this is using a technique called exponential backup where client like
progressively awaits longer time. Like longer
time is like longer each time like
backup limit is reached. So this makes API
more fault tolerant and also more reliable. And it helps
in resource utilization as well because now API
doesn't need to handle all those like bogus retries.
Why is it going to, yeah,
so yeah, as I mentioned before,
while handling retries as well, you could use appropriate status
code. I like to use 429 and 503 for
scenarios like this. And also I like to respond
with retry after header. So basically now client knows
after like how long to wait before trying again.
The other thing that we could do to make our API more, more robust
is expose metrics. Basically exposing time series metrics
of your application. It helps you like it
helps you, exposing your metrics helps you to set up
a baseline and then compare, compare that baseline with
when the application starts to receive the metrics. And now
that comparison can be used for a lot of different benefits such as
like detecting anomalies. Like if there anything suspicious going
on on the application with the application we can use it for planning,
like capacity planning. We could use it to set up SLA's
with other team or our customers. And also,
yeah, in the identify like use that
as part of the root cause analysis.
And the next thing that we could do to make our API more robust is
version them. I think we all are aware of it. Making versioning
our API makes our like makes it more maintainable,
stable and flexible. And like it makes the
API adaptable as well. Like we have. We want to make our
API to be backward compatible as well because some
provider or some client or some customers of our API might not
be interested in upgrading to a newer version because they have implemented
the solution in such a way that they can't use the newer feature that was
released. So version your API is really good idea for making
it more robust. In conclusion,
building a robust API is trying to like watch a movie in this nineties
tv, right? We twist and turn the norms to find the sweet spot and
where we are happy with brightness, jitter and sound and picture quality.
So it's all about finding that sweet spot.
So thank you for watching. Thank you for
listening to me. You can scan this QR code to reach out to me
directly. Really appreciate you listening
to the talk and enjoy the rest of the conference. Thank you.