Hi, folks. Welcome to flow engineering. I'm going to be taking
you through how to level up your team one map at a time.
So let's jump in with a classic. So we've
got a ton of stuff to do, right? Everybody has this giant
backlog of crap that they love to ship,
and there's a million things in the way, right? We need
to do more with less. We've got staff cuts, people leaving,
reorganizations, demands from leadership.
We have to always be improving value,
getting more out of what we do.
We need higher quality, fewer defects.
We want to stop firefighting, and we need to keep everybody happy,
ideally, make them more happy as time goes on. So the
question becomes, how do we do all this and stay sane? How do we
constantly level up? How do we constantly improve our performance,
not just as individuals, but as teams? So I'm
going to take you through an entire end to end process for doing
this. First of all, begin with the end in mind,
right. We're going to talk about setting a clear target and
heading in a direction together. Then we're going
to look at constraints in the workflow, what's holding us down,
what's really holding us back. Then we'll
connect those constraints, those things holding us back to actual
factors inside of our organization that we can quantify
and understand. And then we're using to connect
those dependencies to capability that we can level
up, that we can improve in order to mitigate or break those
dependencies. And we're going to wrap all that up into what I
call flow roadmap, which is essentially a roadmap for your workflow,
how you're going to improve what you do on a day to day basis.
So let's dive right in. First of all, what we want to do is
understand the current state. We want to get everybody together, and this
is a variety of stakeholders, right? We've got design,
development, leadership,
quality, product, all the folks
involved in the value stream, everyone that it takes to get something out
the door in the same room, and we'll work this
out. So first thing we want to understand is pains,
goals, questions, ideas, context.
What are we dealing with? Right? What are people focused on? What are they concerned
about? What do they want to do? We'll get it all out on
the page onto a surface that we can all look at.
And we use collaboration whiteboarding for this, but we could use postit notes on
a wall or a whiteboard. Then what
we do is we take all these things and we focus on
just a single target. Right? What's one thing that we can agree is
more important than everything else to focus on. So in this case,
we've got all this out on the board, all this context, all this valuable information.
Everybody is on the same page about heading in
this direction towards releasing twice as often.
So we can take that and we can understand, what does that actually mean?
What does that look like? So we place that on the board,
right? Clear ourselves a space and understand,
why is that important? Why is it important to customers? Why is it
important to us? Why is it important to leadership, the business?
And we can look at it through all of those lenses to make sure that
we all understand why this is important and we can all get behind it.
Then we look at obstacles. What are the things that could
get in our way? What are the things that will hold us back from achieving
that target outcome? And let's get all that out so we
can talk about it and see it. And then we want to understand what are
the things that we can learn? What are the things that we can test
to see if we can avoid obstacles or get to that
outcome most effectively. And I have a few of
my favorite investigations and I'm going to take you through them.
But you can really put anything on this board and you can use this in
isolation whenever you want, right? You don't have to go through
the entire end to end process. Sometimes you just want to clear the air
or get on the same page and you can use outcome
mapping to do that. But let's look at
that process again from start to finish. So we want to
explore and survey the landscape, understand what's around us,
right? What are we dealing with? Where are we, where do we want to go?
Then we want to understand what's important to us, why is it important
and who is it important to? For different reasons,
we want to look at obstacles, we want to understand what's ahead of us so
we don't trip over something the moment we get going.
And then we look at investigations as options. What can we do
to make progress? What can we do to learn something,
to figure out how to navigate this landscape
that's going to bring us to workflow? What are we doing right now and what
does that look like? How do we understand our current workflow?
So I use value stream mapping for this. I love
it. It's extremely valuable for looking at workflow. And what
we're doing when we look at a value stream map is laying out
all the activities from start to finish for a given
workflow or process. In this case, we can look
at a release process or a single stories
path through a sprint or whatever you want. It can be
as high level or as low level as you want. Obviously,
you don't want to spend all your time in the weeds, and you don't want
to be so high level that it's not very useful to folks.
But after we lay out everything that's happening,
we want to measure it to understand where should
we focus. So the first thing we measure is how long do each of these
things take? And then we measure how much time is passing
between each of these steps. So we'll look at step
timing and delay timing, and then we can layer all kinds of measurements
in addition to that. But those basics are going to give us
a focal point, right? They're going to tell us that there's one area
or a couple of areas that we could prioritize that
we should focus on because they're taking up most of the time.
And in this case, we've got a hotspot that's taking up way
more time than any other area of the value stream. So all of a sudden,
we've gone from everything we could possibly focus on to one
focal point, and we're all on the same page.
So we can take this super deep, too. We can layer on all kinds of
different information. You can see here there's calculations of totals
represented. We've got multiple hotspots, we've got
roles. These little dots represent different players
in the process. We have tools represented here. You can
really layer on a number of different dimensions to
understand the flow of work at whatever detail level you find
productive. So let's look at this again, start to
finish really quick. We pick a stream, and a great
way to pick a stream. A lot of people struggle with identifying
a value stream. Pick a single customer outcome,
and that customer could be internal or external.
But what is one thing that they need to do? And how
do you deliver that outcome? Right. Looking at working
backwards from that outcome, what makes it happen?
That helps us isolate a single stream, and then we can look at
what's happening most of the time in that workflow.
So we target a stream, we lay out the activities
of what's happening. We look at the measurements for
how long each stage takes and what happens between each stage.
We add any dimensions that are going to help us understand to a
greater level of detail what's going on and where we should focus and
how we should focus our efforts. And then we gather
all that information into hotspots. What are the things that stand out? What do we
notice? Where can we focus our attention?
So the next thing that we do, the third stage here,
is to look at that constraint, that hotspot, and break it down.
Understand what's behind this, what's the reason, right? We might have
good ideas, maybe some of us know exactly what it is,
but there's a good chance that not all of us do. Right?
So this gives us an opportunity to look at that in detail,
break it down and understand it, so that we can all split
up and go tackle different areas or just be on
the same page as we continue through this process of understanding
flow and understanding what to do about it. So in this case,
environment, setup takes forever. Why does it take forever?
Well, we have to go to the data team and we have to ask them
for stuff. We have to go to the DevOps team, we have to ask them
for stuff. They're busy, they're doing other things. So what's
really happening there, right? We can dig even deeper than that.
So if we zoom in and then we zoom in again,
we see that we're getting data refreshed by the data team.
They're cloning some data, maybe from production, maybe from another environment.
The DevOps team is doing their thing, but now we
can take these and dig a little bit deeper. Which one of them is
the most problematic? What's the most time consuming? Which one is the biggest pain
that they don't want to deal with. So they just kick it down the road
and you end up waiting for it to get done. So let's look
at that from start to finish. We're going to look at dependencies,
we're going to map these dependencies. We can look at the timing of
each of these stages, like, how long do each of these take?
Where are the hotspots there? And again, we're zeroing
in. We're understanding, where is the major constraint, what's causing
it, what are the factors involved, so that we can focus and we know what
to do about what we see, and we can plot all
that through various means. We can use wordly mapping,
we can use simple matrix to understand
how close it is to us, how complex it is. There's a number of
different dimensions we can use to measure dependencies, but what
do we do about dependencies? Right? So we
can take those capability that we discovered
in the dependencies, the activities,
the contributions of each of those external teams,
and we can plot them in the context of our team, so we can look
at how would we take these things over? How might
we improve the workflow around these things and
could be that we can't do anything about it, really, but maybe we
can improve something on our end that makes it easier for that other
team to deliver what we need. But the first part
about this that really matters is understanding who's doing
what, who owns it. And that could be just a liaison,
right? The person who always goes out to that team and
gets in touch with them and then waits for whatever to come
back. Right. But in a lot of cases we don't even have
that defined, right? We don't have a single point person. So no wonder
nothing happens. Another big reason nothing happens is
that we often don't have a backup for those people. So if they're away,
if they're on vacation, if they're sick,
everything grinds to a halt or people are just scrambling around,
we can look at the skill level, where are we at with these things?
Are we actually able to take them on? Could we break those dependencies?
Do we have that level of capability?
And maybe it's a challenge
that we don't have sufficient resources. We might not have access to APIs
or documentation or tooling, but we can get all
that out onto the page as well and look at that as a group.
And all of this information can be collected into an aggregate score.
So we can use whatever scoring mechanism we want.
We just recognize that these are not
equal. Some of these might be easier to tackle
than others, and we can use that to prioritize.
Again, we're just focusing, focusing, focusing, focusing from
our target outcome down to what can we actually do to
make a huge impact on that outcome? What can we do to
get there? How can we actually make it
happen? So let's look at capability. First of all,
we identify those capabilities, looking at the dependencies, we find
out who owns it so that we actually have like an identified point person.
Or at least it makes sense that we haven't been able to break the dependency
yet. We can look at skill, and that's skill as a
team. We're not singling out individuals here
because we live or die as a team. And we
look at the support mechanisms that we have, what do we have access to?
Can we actually break this dependency? Can we manage this dependency?
Is this something that we can actually deal with or
is it just going to keep dragging us down? And then all of
this factors into this score. The score that helps us
focus, helps us have really productive conversations about what
to do next. So what do we do next? We take
all this information and we can plot it with whatever prioritization
method you want. But this can be very simple. It can
be very complicated. It's really based on whatever you use to prioritize,
use whatever you're comfortable with. But a simple
two factor matrix for this works really well,
helps you focus on the things that end up in the top. Right.
So again, focusing, focusing, using.
Right. So out of that prioritization,
what we can do is we can understand what do we want to do
now, what do we want to do next and what are we going to do
later? That's, again, focus. Right. What are
we going to do tomorrow to make progress and what can wait
or what has to wait, and then what are we going to put on the
radar, keep on the radar but not worry about for now.
Right. We're going to tell people that we're not worrying about it until we've delivered
some of the outcomes that we can earlier on. So we look at
milestones and actions as a part of this. We look at measures of progress.
How are we going to know that we're headed in the right direction? And then
who's going to own those things? Right? Who's going to drive it forward? And this
is not a case of that person doing all the work,
but someone's got to be able to say, here's where we are,
here's what we're learning, here's what's happening, here's where we're going next.
And so getting that all out on paper onto
this shared workspace where everybody can see and
be in alignment means that coming out of this,
things start to happen. And there's no reason why things shouldn't happen.
So we can lay out these things that we're going to
address and understand how we're going
to measure the success of those actions, those deliverables,
and who's going to own those things. And then we can have varying levels of
detail going forward. Obviously, we don't have to lay out everything for
later because we can tackle that when we get
to later or when we get closer to later. So this is really
kind of high definition in the short term and then off
into the distance. We don't need that detail.
We just need to know we're not going to do it right now. And that
clarifies. Again, this is clarifying and focusing.
So why do we do this?
What's the major benefit here? What are the big ideas?
We want to achieve a level of collective flow.
So the ability for all of us to work together on
these complicated workflows,
complicated features, code bases products in
a way that's productive. And the way that we can
connect that to our daily experiences and what
it's going to be like to work in that context is to have personal
flow as well. We need a combination of both in
order to really make significant progress and to really accelerate
over time without burning people out or slowing down as we scale.
So we balance collective flow with personal flow.
And so we're constantly working at varying
levels to make sure that everything flows with
minimal friction, minimal waste. So,
at the collective level, what does that mean? That means we're minimizing delays.
We're attacking those areas of the value stream where we're waiting or things aren't
happening, we're not moving things forward. And where we
can't move things forward, where things are just stuck in
a tedious process or an unproductive process, we can target
those areas and eliminate them. And then,
in a personal context, what we want to do is maximize engagement.
We want to make sure that everybody is operating at their peak
capacity. And that's not maximum work,
it's maximum engagement. It's that sweet spot between challenge
and skill where we see progress. We're engaged,
we feel like we're growing, we're enjoying ourselves, and we're making the
maximum contribution that we can to the team.
And then we want to, as well, maximize the outcomes
of that engagement. What's actually being delivered? What is the
real progress that we're making? And so, through flow
engineering and bringing all this together, we're able to optimize
both of those dimensions, the collective and the personal.
And you really can't do the personal without the
collective. You really need to have an optimized team workflow
in order for anybody to really be able to optimize
their personal sense of flow. Otherwise, they're constantly being
interrupted, they're constantly firefighting buried under
work. There's a million reasons why the collective really
negatively can affect the personal. So we really have to understand
both. But personal flow, I believe,
starts with collective flow. And this flow engineering
is an excellent method for optimizing collective flow.
So what happens when we do this right? Why should we do this?
Often, what we'll see is we can do more with
less, we can serve
more people when we optimize a workflow. If we look back
at that environment setup stage, we've got
usually shared services managing things like infrastructure,
and they're completely overworked. They're constantly firefighting,
constantly interrupted. If they get a chance to optimize
their workflow, if they can automate. If they
can understand what other teams are constrained by, then all
of a sudden they can do more with less, they can have much greater impact.
We see cycle times go down, lead times go down,
fixed times go down. So anytime there's a bug, if you have an
optimized workflow, it gets fixed faster with
less panic, with less stress, and that can
have a positive outcome on what actually gets delivered,
as that fix could be the difference between duct tape
and an actual solution. We see higher deployment
frequency, so deploying more often, learning more often,
getting things out and getting
hopefully benefits from customers. Feedback rewards,
a sense of progress and definitely learning
and lead time. This is the heartbeat of a
company, right? How often are you actually shipping things out to
customers that they can use, that they pay you for, that they're
happy with you about? So we see this dramatically
reduced when you can minimize waste,
optimize flow, optimize performance, and target your
efforts so you're not just chasing every improvement opportunity.
You focus on what's going to make the biggest difference. So let's
wrap it all up. First of all, clarity your target
by understanding your target outcome. You can use an outcome map for this.
Very simple, very effective. Then understand
your value stream. What's the current workflow?
Where's the constraint? What is being negatively
impacted by the current workflow? And then understanding the
dependencies behind those things. It could be there's zero dependencies, but often
I find the biggest delays are connected to external dependencies.
You've got to wait to go and ask for approval
or wait for somebody else to do something for you that
perhaps you could do self service and then
capabilities. What is it going to take to break those dependencies
or improve our level of performance with the things that we do have control
over? That all comes down to capabilities,
capabilities around automation, around creating
self service, ux, good documentation,
adopting new toolings, stitching things together within integrations,
there's all kinds of capabilities that improve flow,
and so we can use those capabilities to address dependencies
and accelerate. Remove that waste, remove the delays,
and all of this. Everything you learn, all the insights
from, all the mapping, goes into this flow roadmap, which is not
just a roadmap, it's a roadmap for how you
ship your real roadmap, right? The roadmap of features that you need to
deliver. This is the roadmap for how you're going to ship all those
features. So this is the most
neglected map in every organization is how
are we actually going to do the things that we want to do.
Not a map of things that you want to do, but the how of
anything that you want to do. And if you unlock this,
then you can really tackle anything. So bringing
all this insight together, plotting into something that's actionable,
is highly effective.
So why do I love mapping?
And why are people talking about this now?
People are going to start talking about this a lot now because this
just showed up at the very top of the thoughtworks
radar. So the thoughtworks radar has been going on forever,
and this is the first year that they've actually added what they're
calling path to production mapping, because value stream mapping
means different things to different people. But essentially
what we're talking about here is end to end flow
with mapping, and it showed up at the top
of the radar. Now, this is a huge
development. It went from not on the radar to the
very top, and it's because it is cited by
every success story. Everyone who talks about massive
performance improvements talks about looking at the end
to end flow and understanding where the data was
pointing, their efforts, their attention, and making decisions
based on that data. So flow engineering is
really going to ride this wave, and hopefully we hear
a lot more about collaborative mapping and flow
focused mapping in the coming months and years.
So a little bit more about why mapping is so valuable
and so important working together in this
way on a visual medium. And again, if it's a whiteboard
or postit notes or miro or
mural, it really doesn't matter. You could use anything
for this, but it's engaging, right?
It's really valuable to have everybody sort of participating and working together to
build this picture of what everybody sees,
everybody's different perspective together.
As you're building this, you own it. You feel a sense of attachment to
what you've created, what you understand, and most
importantly, the next steps. What are you using to do with this?
Feeling a sense of ownership over that process and the outcome
of the map. The map that you create is really valuable.
A lot of people feel like they're not a part of the planning process,
they're not a part of decision making.
This brings people in. It's extremely inclusive.
It also brings people into alignment. Everybody has
a different perspective, everybody has a different opinion.
So unless you get those out into the open, you're not going to
understand that people are pulling in different directions or
have very different understandings of where they're
headed and how to get there. So this provides
an opportunity for folks to really come together. It's entirely
customized. This is not a prescriptive framework you
will not get the same outcome. You will not make the same maps
twice. It's incredibly customizable
and it's entirely bespoke for whatever context.
You can make the same maps in the
same team two weeks apart and have a totally different outcome that
represents where they are at that moment. So it's incredibly valuable
for representing exactly what you're dealing with,
not trying to copy Spotify or Netflix
or whoever folks think is doing a good job.
This is how you do a good job in your context.
It's also something that you remember. You retain
the things that you learn because you're a part of interactively learning those things
and discovering them yourself along with everybody else. So it
sticks. And again, this is all developed
over the pandemic, so it's incredibly remote friendly. It works
just as well remotely where everyone's
in a different time zone or in a room,
it works for both. I had very
wonderful results with any scenario.
It's very flexible and you can deploy this,
you can use this however you choose in your own environment.
So with that, if you want to learn more, if you're curious
about this, you can shoot that QR code. It's going to take you
to a bunch of links. But there's an ebook
and an email course that is entirely self guided
at flow. Visible is it'll take you through start to finish.
And I've also launched with a good friend of
mine, Andrew Davis, the value stream show, which we're
talking about everything. Value streams,
mapping, management, flow,
organizational dynamics, everything that it takes to
achieve that collective and personal flow.
And with that, I want to say thank you, really appreciate
you taking the time to check this out, and I
hope you reach out to me and let me know what your you're doing
for flow or struggling with flow in your
organizations.