Our name.
Hello and welcome to this talk on how to implement a developer security
operations program. I'm Evan Gertis. I'd love
to start this talk out by just asking everyone, how do you feel today?
I hope you're feeling well. Here are the five things that I want you to
walk away from this talk with. Number one, automated scanning removes the
need for manual labor. Number two, when application security reviews
are executed properly, they increase accountability, but they require a security
champion. Number three, strong vulnerability reports are more
easily accepted when they are supported with easy to read metrics from baracode
dashboards and JFrog XR reports. Number four, penetration tests
fill in the gaps where automated scanning fails to catch vulnerabilities.
Number five, the results of the
penetration tests need to be supported with systematic logging.
So why did the IT team set up their remote office
on the beach? Seems cloudy.
Ask yourself, why are you here?
Prepare your mind for an extreme paradigm shift and let
go of any preconceived notions that you previously held. What I plan to
propose will destroy any of the accepted ideas that you once thought to be
true. Imagine, what if we could give
people a pill to get them to do
their jobs and execute successfully?
How you do anything is how you do everything. Proper leadership comes down to planning,
accountability and commitment. This is what worked for
me. Maybe you have different tooling, but the concept is still
the same. You need to find the right tools to help you succeed.
You do not need to do it this way. By following this process, you will
be able to convey your results such that they will be received like a
seasoned salt hitting your manager's tongue. I'm going to present to
you what worked for me.
We inspire your teams to take accountability. Our process uses the right tools
to get people to take action. Our process is based on research from
the two most referenced papers on devsecops from connected
papers. We think we know culture,
but we live in a world where the norms diet information in silos.
And as Peter F. Drucker once said,
culture a strategy for breakfast.
How many of you have sat in a meeting with a liar?
How many of you sat in a meeting with a micromanager? They can
barely do their jobs, and yet they're going to tell you how to do yours.
There's a reason they say crimes often come back to their teachers. It's easy
to catch a lion tiger by their toes. These types can
barely keep their stories straight from one day to the next. They don't have the
common sense necessary for leading a team.
This process does not make your employees into leaders, it inspires them
to lead. We all know that most people can't do their jobs and
as Benjamin Franklin so eloquently put it, always taking out
of the meal tub, but never putting back into it. And what's worse is that
it's both a technology and a people issue.
So, have you heard of shift left? If you
have, are you doing it the right way?
Right now, there is a high demand for infosec leaders who can
pass the torch. And Devsecops is a new field.
The ground has barely been broken in. There aren't any standards in place that present
a synergistic combination of people in process. So we can go ahead and pause here.
Right configuration management it's been
one of the biggest headaches for security engineers. How many of you have stared at
a vim config file for 3 hours?
Here's how we can address these issues. Provide process, implement structure, and finally
lead our team. So, do you want to win win? Then clap
if you want to win, win. Please stand. If you want to win, win.
And if you're a real firewalker, go ahead and pound your chest.
We make firewalkers. Take a second.
Ask yourself, when was the last time
you felt like your boss showed humility?
Other processes do not care about your feelings. We convert your
security teams into firewalkers to give your business an edge so
that you can land and expand, I. E.
We take you from being interested to
a mature devsecops capability.
Our process cares about your feelings.
At the end of the talk, I'd love to give you a more detailed overview
of the training presented here. I want you all to walk away
from this talk with an understanding of the five key points that we covered at
the beginning of this presentation. And if you want help implementing
this, this is where I come in. As you can see, team members
need to be involved in the early stages of the process. We need the right
tools and the right people working on the right things at the right time,
supported by the right reporting. The details of these reports matter more than
the reports themselves, and they need to show where we are going, how we're going
to get there, what needs to be done, and how we will know when we
have arrived. The distinguishing characteristic between our work
and the two most referenced papers that describe approaches towards implementing
devsecops is that not only did we implement
a pipeline, but our process leverages the human
element. Most organizations miss out on this aspect. The weakest
element in any process is the human, and we provide the appropriate structure
to get individuals to take accountability for their
work. As you can see, you need a
champion. These things are more
than just a technology issue. They're a people and
technology issue. Why are these papers important?
Because they emphasize that we need a bridge.
We need more than just technology. We need firewalkers.
It's simple. A process and a team
make a better dream. How would you like to be
80% more efficient?
A process gets a big dog's attention by bubbling problems up to
the top without having to say anything. I walk through the fire and the
flame. I dealt with difficult individuals, and I humbly
set aside my agenda to hear what they had to say. And the key to
influencing others is to listen. In order for our teams to
be successful, we need to be able to establish common ground.
We have to get team members to work with each
other so that we can influence organizational change.
Once we can show progress, instead of telling everyone what we are
doing, it will become clear that things are moving forward. Too many managers
fail to realize that the best way to influence a team is by showing,
not telling, we have the technology. But the key is to build security champions
so they can go on to lead. Others either get top shelf tooling or
suffer the consequences of trying to cut corners.
Let's face it, what's worth paying for
is worth paying for. End of story.
Our process leverages the best tooling.
It's simple.
Passion, accountability, clear communication,
execution. These are the four
things that make an effective team.
We've got the Neosporin for your security needs.
We're going to cover Veracode, burbsuite compliance,
elasticsim, JFrog X ray, and a custom application security
review. Here is what I'd like you to walk away from this section with.
Our process uses a combined approach of static application
security testing, SAS, dynamic application security testing,
dask and container scanning. Then we use executive dashboards to support
our claims. The combination of the tools and dashboards is one of the best
ways to articulate our results to upper management.
We take you from chaos to clarity. Here you can
see an organization with over 254
Jackson databind vulnerabilities sitting in their repository.
And then, just after six months of
using this program, not only are those vulnerabilities gone, but all the
other ones that you saw there are gone too, and it continues to decrease.
First step adversity is the foundation of strength.
And if you aren't first, you're last. You have to set the
tone for your team. I did this myself, and I made it look easy because
truly nobody wants to lead. We all know that success breeds success.
And if you don't know, now you know, you have to
define your champions. However,
it takes more than just talk. The devil is in the details.
The key to a good security report is being able to show the
details of a security scan. Static application security testing will
allow you to pinpoint the flaws that are plaguing your applications.
The next step is to show developers the flaws so they can take the responsibility
for fixing their vulnerabilities. And when you go into that meeting, you need to show
the results and say nothing.
Let the silence consume the room so they know you are serious.
You want the results to speak for themselves.
Simple. Go to the platform,
select scans, analysis, and static analysis.
Simply just using static analysis isn't enough. We have
to use a combined approach of dynamic application security testing and static
application security testing to convey meaningful results. Combined together, they actually
produce something worthwhile. A simple overview of dynamic
application security testing just shows that you create the dynamic scan,
you configure it, you run the scan, you view the results, and then
your developers fix the flaws.
Now again,
it's simple. Click scans analysis,
dynamic scans, and launch the scan.
The container is a foundational layer in any application.
We have to bake security into applications by implementing container scanning.
With bare code container scanning, your team can catch the third party vulnerabilities
in your application. Then developers just need to click the
fix button in the platform to see the detailed instructions on how to fix the
issue. Here's one line of code. Throw it in a bash
script. Run it. Done. The purpose behind implementing
veracode dashboards is to show upper management the results of the security
program. The dashboards will help executives understand where we
are in the certification process, as well as the vulnerabilities that are plaguing
our applications.
So why are we doing any of this? It's to influence
team accountability, and using this process we can show progress.
Real leaders show they don't tell we're raising
firewalkers. Burp suite is a
sword for security engineers. It is a man in the
middle attack platform, and we can use this tool to analyze
and infiltrate web traffic. The only things you need to know
are the burp proxy, burp scanner, burp repeater, burper intruder.
We can use this custom pen testing workflow to find vulnerabilities that the
SAS and dast miss. The Burp proxy
is an effective way for one to perform reconnaissance on an application.
This is one of the first steps in executing a great penetration test.
The proxy allows us to capture requests being made to
the application. But guess what? You got to
learn how to crawl before you ball. The Burp suite scanner
is an effective tool that will allow us to crawl an application so
that we can define the scope of our penetration test. We can download
a PDF report generated from the Burp suite scanner that will allow us to examine
what is wrong with our application. It will provide us with the specific details that
are necessary for conducting a proper penetration test and then simply just use these
findings and give them topper management to support your claims.
The burp repeater is a tool that can be used for
intercepting requests and then modifying them with a custom payload
so that we can attack. The key
is using the intruder.
The burp intruder can be used for attacking an application.
It allows us to execute an automated attack against websites that we
can rinse and repeat successful attacks against them. And if the attack
doesn't work, then we can always iterate through another set of
attacks again. And as you can see here, I am popping
SQL injection and I'll do it again. And I'll do it again until
the cows come home. Here's an example of a custom payload
being built and running an attack.
So why is this important?
We want to influence team accountability,
and using this process, we can show progress. Real leaders show
they don't tell compliance.
Most organizations don't even have anything in place.
We implemented full scale cloud security coverage for a mid sized
organization, and we used a free compliance framework in terraform infrastructure
as code to achieve this. This exercise is perfect for
a new security engineer. The center for Internet Security
Foundation's Benchmark is a great compliance policy to start out with. It provides specific
instructions on how to audit and secure systems, and it's helpful for entry security
engineers who need to create a security program from scratch.
The instructions are easy to read, and it's free.
As one of my greatest mentors once said, you can build a river
in a desert. So let me take you from this desert to
filebeat pre configured dashboards. Here you can see all of the
instances this organization is running. We have cloud trail as well,
so we're monitoring the API. Oh yeah, that SQL
injection I was popping, that won't happen on my watch because we have systematic
logging to support the penetration tests. You can
try to hide your bugs, hide your flaws, and hide your vulnerabilities, but we're secured
everything up in here. The first step here
is selecting that compliance framework. And as I said, you can't
go wrong with the center for Security Operations Benchmark because
it's free to start out with, why wouldn't you pick it?
We can use the standard AWS resources to manage access control
for an organization. The AWS terraform provider has specific terraform
resources for managing infrastructure associated with AWS
IM. Amazon S three is
also a big part of this. It's a storage management service that
can help us store data, such as Amazon load balancer
ALB access logs, which can be queried either using Amazon
Athena or leveraged as a part of the pre built Filebeat
AWS module that I just showed you. Elasticstack can
be used as a security information event management system,
a SIM for monitoring an organization's cloud resources.
To get started with this, we need to implement logging with cloud trail.
Once we have that configured, we can move into elasticsim.
We can take advantage of the AWS filebeat module along with the center
for Internet Security Operations Benchmark, the CIS Foundation's benchmark, to create
a set of dashboards that allow us to monitor all the cloud resources that an
organization is using. The entire configuration can be implemented using standard
configuration files and deployed with terraform
from the command line interface. Why is this important?
Because we want to influence accountability,
and using this process we can show progress. Real leaders show
they don't tell here's what I'd like you to walk
away from this section with. X ray is a tool that is
used to scan your builds and the specific way that we use x ray reports
influences accountability. Our process leverages x
ray vulnerability reports in a simple way that can be used by any organization.
As one of my mentors always said, you can
build a river in a desert. We can make something out of nothing. Peter Thiel
zero to one, this is an example of
a shift left pipeline. So I
asked you, are you doing it the right way?
You might be, but here is a perfect example.
This code could all go out to production without any proper security.
It could be Uber. The code could go out and get hacked
and then become the next biggest press release. However,
security has been pushed forward in the pipeline. This is
a perfect example of shift left. In this case, we have moved the
security forward in the pipeline, preventing code from going out to
production. Not only that,
here's an example of a vulnerability report that
can be handed to management with the specific
fixes that need to be done. And we can stop these builds
before they go out into production, preventing your company from
becoming the next Uber. When we are communicating with upper management,
we want to provide the proper data to support our progress.
It's all about reporting. We can use an x ray report
to generate vulnerability reports to show third party vulnerabilities
associated with an application, and these reports can be downloaded in a PDF
format so that they can be distributed to the right team members. That's the key
we're showing. We're not telling. So first,
let's be honest. You don't want to do this the hard way,
and if you don't have the appropriate numbers and statistics to support
your claims, no one's going to believe you. Nobody trusts anyone
anymore. And these results are easy to read and
they're easy to fix. It's simple.
JFrog has the best support in the world.
Between JFrog and Veracode, you really can't go wrong.
The first step is initializing x ray. We have
to configure a scan using a standard Jenkins pipeline
script, and this can be done with an x ray plugin. The first step
is ensuring that we've configured the proper build info before we launch
the analysis on the code. So the specific
build info that we want to make sure is set correctly are the arguments for
the RT build info function. These include the server id, the URL,
username and password. After we've successfully
initialized the build, the next step is publishing the build info to the
artifactory repo. We want to make sure that the builds are available for team
members to have access, and each of these builds should be clearly
visible in artifactory repo for a given organization.
Then we want to configure a report. One of the most important
aspects of this process is generating report. The report provides the specific
details on the status of the builds that we're analyzing. They provide
the specific steps for remedying the vulnerabilities associated with the application
so that developers do not have to waste time trying to figure out how to
fix vulnerabilities and management can just look at the report.
This provides the perfect situational awareness and context for having a serious
conversation about what needs to be done. So why
are we doing this? Again, we need to influence team
accountability, and using this process we can show progress.
Real leaders show they don't tell.
We have a strategic application security review that leverages
research, proven leadership techniques, and our methods can be implemented in any
situation to get individuals to take accountability for their work. If we were able to
automate the entire management aspect of these meetings, and we
have the data that shows that they lead to positive outcomes.
You can build a river in a desert, something from
nothing. Here are the results of these questions.
As you can see, we've identified a security champion. We've reached
a new certification level. We're consistently scanning. We implemented docker container
scanning. Let's go down to what's happening next. Vulnerabilities either
need to be addressed by mitigation or they need
to be fixed and guidance on these vulnerabilities would be provided as necessary.
But we're going to stop the new vulnerabilities from being introduced and we
can see what was used to get there, why we're doing it,
and who is going to be helping to get the work done. This is
an example of automated ticketing. It's fully self service. People are taking
responsibility for their work and they're not wasting time in meetings.
How much time are you spending in meetings?
So you have to identify a ticketing system. We need a way to
provide auditing and traceability for work that has been completed and
the work that needs to be done. Selecting a good ticketing system is the
first step in assuring cross team collaboration.
It allows everyone to see what each other is working on so
that projects are completed and deadlines are met. We want to establish
clearly defined goals that show what we are trying to achieve.
What has been done a key aspect of this is documentation.
It's critical. Without an accurate record of what has been done, we won't
know what needs to be changed to improve for the future. And by providing a
consistent record of application security reviews, teams will be able to coordinate
with each other so that work gets done on time. The primary purpose of
application security reviews is to provide a healthy discussion
about the status of an organization's security objectives. It's recommended that
these reviews take place on a weekly basis so that the team
consistently moves forward. They can be scheduled either using Microsoft Teams,
Zoom, Google, hangouts. The important aspect is that they are recorded and
the meeting minutes are distributed before and after the meeting.
When the team meets, everyone should read the previous reviews meeting minutes
and they are prepared to answer the specific questions that each member
of the team is responsible for answering. And when you start that meeting,
you start with a question. Each meeting is recorded,
so we need to provide a way for
automating this ticketing. That means
a fully automated solution for task management. The days of manually going
in and assigning tasks are over. This gives teams the flexibility to work on
their priorities without having to waste precious time in meetings.
Ask yourself, how much time are you spending in meetings?
Wouldn't you prefer to spend your time getting the important
things done? The added benefit of
using automated ticketing is that we still retain the records of
what has been done and what needs to be done in the future.
Have you ever lost a great leader?
There are five key questions that
every member is responsible for answering. These are research
proven questions that come straight from Bob Moore, CMMC MCC
president of effectiveness, Incorporated. The simple program
that we've outlined utilizes these questions to take a midsize organization from
a nonexistent security program to a veracode level three certified
partner with fully automated remediation supported
by full scale security information event management monitoring with
proper infrastructure as code resources to meet the guidelines as set forth in the center
for Internet Security Foundation's benchmark.
If you'd like these questions, please message me after
the presentation. Why?
Why is this important?
We are influencing accountability, and using this process
we can show progress. Real leaders show they don't tell.
All right, let's take a victory lap.
As one of my greatest mentors always said, you can build a river in a
desert. Here we go. We've got our software composition
analysis in Veracode. This platform will allow us to see all the third party vulnerabilities.
And then here we have our full scale devsecops pipeline with all the
pain shifted to the left forward in the pipeline as opposed to after
the pipeline. So that way you don't become the next Uber or equifax
or whatever company is being hacked these days. It's very important that you do not
let your code go out into production with a bunch of vulnerabilities. Otherwise you will
definitely make it into the news. Here is an example of the automated
security ticketing that we have set up for application security reviews. This is
an example of the ticket with all the details. As you can see,
the details here matter because it gives the developer the ability to go fix
the vulnerability without any issue, without having to go to a meeting
or wasting a security engineer's time. Here's an example of
the Veracode score. This Veracode score is an indicator of how
well the security is set up in the Veracode
platform. From a security perspective, they can use these results
to go speak to customers in sales and say we
actually take our security seriously. This organization went from a 58, which means
extremely hackable, to 94. Here we have
an example of the elearning curriculum. As I said, a key aspect
of team management is having the effective learning
component available for developers. And this is a custom curriculum that was designed based
on half a dozen conversations with the development team. Here we
have the pre configured filebeat dashboards. As you can see, you can see all of
the organization's resources in the cloud.
And these dashboards also allow you to monitor the APIs.
Again, nobody's hacking this application. And the security engineer has
the added benefit that they can actually support their penetration tests
with the systematic logging from the security information event
management system. You can see that SQL
injection is being popped right here. Added benefit.
The custom penetration testing workflow utilizes the results from
the static application secured scan to execute successful penetration
tests. As you can see, this developer was naive enough to actually let SQL
injection go into their code. And so the next step here is to take
these results and then go pop them with burp suite.
Those results that we saw at the beginning with over 254 vulnerabilities from Jackson databine,
pretty much gone down to nothing. So use
it or lose it. Here's container
scanning we can see set up in the veracode platform,
right? This is automated. It's scanning all the applications.
The security engineer does not have to go in there. What this does is it
provides all the results in the platform, one centralized location for developers and security
engineers to work together to reach meaningful results and help their organization
reach the level of security maturity that they want to be at.
This trend here shows that with consistent scanning, what we
noticed was the vulnerabilities in
the application went down because the results were so overwhelming.
This is an example of the container scanning portion of the veracode
platform. As you can see, there's over 19 microservices here being monitored.
The ones that have Red X's on them mean that they're actually vulnerable.
All a developer has to do is go into this platform, click on the service
that'll take them to veracode, and then they click on the fix button from
the veracode platform. And then they can see the specific instructions
on how to fix the vulnerability. It's very simple
and it's easy for the developer to
schedule these application security reviews. As I said, you could use whatever you like.
Simple Google Hangout will do. All you have to do is set it up so
it recurs on a weekly basis. This is an example of the Veracode
dashboard. As you can see, there's 1675
vulnerabilities remaining. But over 1547 vulnerabilities were closed.
And in this organization, all of the high severity to high vulnerabilities
were removed immediately.
Now, as I said,
prepare your minds for a paradigm shift.
I'm now going to show you an invisibility cloak for
the Internet.
Now you see it,
now you don't. The icon is spinning here. What you're
seeing here is someone accessing the devsecops pipeline that we
described. What is happening here
is we're taking it off the Internet. So not only does this provide the proper
security for all of your code to be pushed to production in a secure fashion,
it's also guarded from the Internet. It's wrapped up in an invisibility
cloak using a zero trust client.
For more information, please reach out to me.
So do you want the benefits of implementing
this program? Do you want to save time and money? If you want to take
your organization to a mature devsecops capability, then here's my contact
information. I'm happy to offer you a free sample of content. Also,
I'm happy to discuss your specific needs in a separate information session. We will
do everything for you. You don't have to spend time worrying about management.
You can focus on the more important things. There's never
enough time. Thank you for yours.
Scan this QR code to access more information related to
my contact. To show a token of
your gratitude, tweet at Evan Gertis at comp 42.
Hashtag success. Hashtag entrepreneurship.
Hashtag comp 42. Subscribe to me on YouTube for
more content. Again, thank you. I'm humbled by this opportunity.
Wouldn't be here if it wasn't for all these great mentors and
wonderful people who have helped me out in my life. Here are the
references to the research papers that were used. Again, reach out to me.
I'm happy to provide you with the slides and the links to these papers.
These are a combination of the two most referenced papers on
implementing a devsecops pipeline from connected papers. Here are all
the resources. These resources provide the getting started guide so anyone can take
this program and go do it on their own.
This is a continuation of this. So again, please see me after the
session. Message me and I'm happy to share these with you. Thank you.
There are any questions. I appreciate your time.
This has been a wonderful opportunity. My name is Evan Gertis.
I'm a Devsecops engineer. I graduated from the
University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill with a bachelor's in science and physics
and the Allen Paulson College of Engineering at Georgia Southern University with a master's in
computer science. I'm a certified terraform associate developer in
electrical and computer engineer, and I'm a certified security plus
information security professional. Thank you.