I am Sena. I am AWS Security Hero
and senior cloud security engineer at Lirabar Studio.
If you want to connect with me, you can
use my LinkedIn, my Twitter and my medium account.
Today we are going to talk about cloud security,
securing the sky strategies for protecting
against cloud hacking let's get started.
First of all, we can start with why cloud security is
so complicated and a nightmare for developers and DevOps engineers.
First of all, there are lots of cloud providers in the market.
Sometimes we struggle to choose which cloud provider is good and
fit for us. In these providers there are lots of services
that we need to learn and effectively use.
Secondly, there are lots of product requirements
in our company. We need to choose what is the best solution for
us, what is the best solution for us
to integrate the security with them. Product requirements can change
quickly, so sometimes it's hard to detect security requirements
and threat management between these product requirements.
On the other side, actually, we all know there is a
shared responsibility model for the cloud providers.
Securing in the cloud and security of the cloud are
the cloud terms are really important for us.
Sometimes companies want to know what responsibilities they have
and sometimes it can
be complicated, analyze it all and get the best
explanation. In addition to all of
this, there are lots of cloud resources we need
to use right now.
You are going to use and you
have lots of cloud resources in your cloud environment.
You need to analyze all of them like unused resources,
used resources that you need to remediate security
findings. And this is a challenge for us.
Depending on cloud resources, there are lots of attack surfaces
in the cloud. We need to aware all of these.
Like there are lots of endpoints, network environments,
databases, AI services, iot services,
blah blah. Attackers love using different attack
surfaces, even if you don't know. And for the
last one, there are lots of tools. We have lots of different tools and
lack of experience in the cloud security. Sometimes companies
get lots of tools to use, check the cloud security installs
and configure them, and after that forget them. It's not
the best way to protect the cloud. We need to know
and use these tools and protect ourselves from
the attackers. So we love
the cloud, so attackers do. In this slide,
there are some
analytics about cloud security. It's from the Orca security report.
Thanks to them for this. If you
want to read them detail, you can see the
report in their site. So there is a
91% of organizations
have at least one vulnerability older than ten years and
46% of
organizations have a vulnerability more
than 20 years old. So it's
important so what does it mean?
It means we have lots of environment, we have lots of vulnerabilities
and we have lots of old vulnerabilities and new vulnerabilities
that we need to remediate. On the other side, there is analytics
about the cloud malware attacks.
So 38% of the cloud malware
attacks are known the Trojans and for the malware
by asset type we can see container storage bucket
and the virtual machine. And these asset types
are the most usage
of the cloud. So we need to
get a plan for this, for the containers,
for the storage bucket and for the virtual machine,
and the last one for the log for shell. You can see the
numbers from it. Log four shell and the log
4G are
some exploits in the recent years. So I can easily
say it's important to protect the cloud with
these numbers.
For the recommendations and
some points that we need to
share, we can start with do not use
public resources unless you really really need.
What does it mean for your storage resources, for your container
registries, for your publicly accessible databases,
for your AI notebooks like Amazon Sagemaker?
Please do not use public resources,
publicly accessible resources unless you really really need.
What does it mean really need? Like if
you have a static website and if you have some publicly accessible photos
in your website, it's fine to share
in the s three bucket publicly.
There is no issue in here. But if you have some public resources
in the s three and some attacker
can write on it, it's a problem or destroy
on it, it's another problem. Or maybe there is some large
files in the S three that is publicly
accessible. It's also a problem for the denial of
wallet amplification attack. And also if you have
some publicly accessible databases and publicly notebooks,
it's also a problem. They are also a problem because
we don't want to databases can publicly accessible and we
don't want someone use our AI
notebooks, Amazon sagemaker models in
our AWS account. So the publicly accessible
resources we do
not use publicly accessible resources is the number
one recommendation from me for
the two. Be aware of resources. Yes. It's also important
which resources, where and why? We need to answer these
questions, how your architecture
is designed. There are lots of resources and there are
lots of like in the AWS. There are lots of maybe
regions, maybe different AWS accounts. And we
need to know and be aware of our resources
and what are the possible vulnerabilities on it. Like your EC two ECs
AWs environment that I mentioned.
Maybe you have lots of vulnerabilities in
your environment and you need to all of them. You need to know all
of them. So what are the misconfigurations in your cloud resources?
Like unused access keys, like publicly accessible
s, three buckets, like cloud trail
that aren't enabled yet.
All of it are the misconfigurations.
And we need to follow and aware and check
all misconfigurations, maybe daily, weekly or monthly,
I don't know. It depends on your company.
And what are the endpoints? For the endpoints, there are lots of endpoints
like EIB endpoints, like lambda
functions,
like API gateway endpoints. I don't know if
an endpoint is an external, this is an issue for us and this
is an attack surface for the attackers.
So you need to know what the endpoints
are and they are vulnerable or not.
And for the awareness. Actually there are lots
of tools in the CSPM cloud security posture management.
CSPM, it's not enough, but it's a good start for your posture
management. Like you can get your security posture
score, you can get general visibility of your
cloud environment. Like for the CIS benchmark,
what are my paths, what are my fails for
cis Azure benchmark, what are my failed ones
and what should I need to remediate
them? This is a good start, but it's
not enough. We need to do
lots of work to protect our cloud.
So for the other one, please read the documentation. I know
that reading the documentation can be challenging and unwanted stuff
for developers, for sometimes the security engineers,
but it's so important. Following the documentation ensures
that security features are configured and configured correctly.
And sometimes there are some additional security features
in the documentation and if we don't know it,
we cannot enable it. So reading the documentation is
very important in this point. And maximizing protection
against threats, again, maximizing protection against
threats is important for us.
And the cloud engineers are updated on the Neve security features.
Yes, that's why I'm saying and best practices
and maximizing the use of documentation minimizes
reliance of external support, saving time and
for your resources. So please read the documentation
whenever you see an AWS service, Azure service,
whenever see a security service,
maybe compute service, database service,
it's so important. Yes. The other
one get alerted from everything you need. Alerting is most important
in the most important thing in the cloud I think,
because there can be lots of anomalies
in your AWS account, in your Azure environment, whatever you
are going to use. And there are always
some class resource threats.
There are always cloud resources, configurations,
chains, and we need to follow all of it. Like what are your anomalies?
What are your cloud resources threats? What are
your configuration chains? Like if someone,
if an attacker gets in your AWS account
and creates a new IM user for herself
or himself, it's very dangerous
for us and we need to be aware of it. So we need to get
alerts from everything we need. And also getting
alerts is an issue. But after getting
the alerts, we need to have a plan for the alerts is another issue.
Yes, we got lots of alerts. And if we do
not analyze them, it's another
issue because every alert should be
analyzed deep dive. And if someone or
something is bad on your cloud environment,
you need to be aware of it. With these cool
alerts, even if false positive alerts, you need to analyze
all of it. And with the alerts we need
to monitor everything. Yes, I am sure you know
it, but again, I want to say
it, we need to monitor everything because the
constant monitoring enables early detection and suspicious activities or
anomalies in our cloud environment.
And the timely monitoring allows for rapid
response to security incidents like there is some
anomalies in it. And if we monitor it, there is
a fast solution for this security incident.
And also monitoring provides valuable insights
into emerging threats and attack patterns.
And also monitoring some resources
helps control the cost anomalies and prevention
of unnecessary expenses. So it's important to
monitor everything. So the encryption we
know the encryption we need to encrypt everything. We need to
dance like no one is watching. Encrypt like everyone is.
Encryption in transit is number one,
encryption in rest is number one. Following the best practices
in the encryption usage encryption stage like what is the
best encryption key for the asymmetric encryption?
What is the best TLS version for my
HTTPs on the Erb? Like we need
to follow the best practice for it and also follow up the cybersecurity
work for encryption changes like TLS 100 and
zero is not secure anymore. SSL version
two is not secure anymore, something like that.
Follow up cybersecurity word for encryption changes helps
for us and the other stuff be
open to change. I love this phrase. So I
want to add in my presentation the most dangerous phrase
in English languages. We always done it
this way. This is the best dangerous phrase because yes,
you have always done in this web and
it's the most dangerous thing in your cloud environment. So it's
important to be open to change open.
Maybe you need to change all architecture,
maybe you need to change your containers,
maybe you need to change the code, I don't know,
but it's important to be open to change and please
do not use a phrase like, we have always done it this
way and we didn't hack
for ten years, so why do we need to change it?
It's too dangerous. Please do not use and always
be open to change for everything, for your architecture, for your
code, maybe for your team, I don't know.
It's important point for the cloud security and
also for the teams. I believe you shouldn't isolate
teams because everyone needs the security, marketing needs of security.
Cloud security needs to security developer needs the security
and each team brings unique skills and perspectives to
the table. And if we do
not isolate the teams, this improves the visibility across
teams and helps identify and address security risks
more efficiently. Maybe some developer knows about
the architectural, maybe some architects in your team
knows about the security stuff in your EC two.
And if you
don't isolate teams, it can be very helpful to solve
things, to mitigate things, and to
find a solution for the security incident.
And also it avoids the duplication
of efforts and resources, because if
one team looks at a vulnerability, for example,
if different teams isolated different teams,
different teams analyzes the same vulnerability, it's a
duplication. And for the efforts and for the resources, we don't
want that. So please do not isolate teams in your
company. And the last
one, think what if. As a security professionals, we always
think what if, what if I get hacked? What if
someone gets my credentials from
here? Think what if an attacker
gets here and do this and do this after do this and after
do this, what should I do? Considering the
potential scenarios in their impacts on the cloud
security posture and identify the vulnerabilities and weaknesses
before they can be exploited. Always think like
what if scenarios. Dive ongoing security enhancements
and updates with your team. Like do
not isolate teams and think always what if.
And after that, I think with these
recommendations,
with this to do list, I think you can protect
your cloud environments from the attacks and
you can increase your visibility in
your cloud environment. So that's it for
my session. Thank you for joining me today.
Again, this is a recording session,
so I cannot get questions,
but if you want to connect me, you can
search from the LinkedIn, you can search in the twitter and
to my medium, I write
some blog posts on it. You can follow me from
here. Thank you for joining me today and see you soon.