Hello everyone, my name is Otavio Santana. I'm glad to be
here today. Let's talk about cloud, these survival guide
for the Java activate cloud era. Right now we're going to cover why
should a move to cloud and why should I keep it and
how can I increase my interaction with cloud, especially the cloud
native techniques and
tools. A little bit about me my name is
Otavio Santana. Today I am
distinct engineer at Soup innovation.
Besides that I enjoy a lot open source.
That's why I become Java champion Oracle
Ace, member of TSP
as a chief member Apache
Eclipse committer. I enjoy the
Java could. So I'm also working several specifications,
mainly in Jakarta ee microprofile right now a member
of CLCF, Linux foundation and Phenos.
Besides that, when I do have free time, I enjoy
to write book and articles, especially about
cloud, Java and architecture. But today is
not about me, it's about how we can increase
our experience in the cloud, right?
Everything is around cloud. We enjoy cloud. Cloud is
so lovely, why not move to the cloud right now?
Previously we need to understand why we are doing that.
If you take a look at the whole history, we could see that in
2001 we had the agile manifesto
where the main focus was to have
a time integration between developers or engineers
and a user where we know the right
direction doing incremental delivery.
After that we could see in around 2010.
So we don't have the exactly time in DevOps because
we don't have DevOps manifesto. But what do you know,
it is after the agile where we
put also the operation on that future to have
tight integration to deliver fast and fast and fast.
Fast of course with quality. And then
we finally understood as well that okay, we need to think about
security not in the reactive way, but as
prevention. Right now we are able to put
security in a process these to avoid any kind
of SQL protection,
some data leak or any kind of thing that
might impact and security of our organization and our technology.
For sure we know the writer
of cloud and what does cloud mean?
Cloud computing is a model for enabling
builders convenient on demand network. Yes, and blah, blah blah,
blah. It belongs to NIS National Institute
of Standard and Technology. But to
me cloud is basically somebody else's problem.
Where I delegate these issue to somebody else,
you solve to me probably. You know that analogy
between pizza and cloud where we put cloud
and pizza both as service.
We started with on premise where we need to do everything by
our hands like make at home the pizza and
move through, go dine out and have
everything fade
for us right. That is soft in a sense.
On the someone else problem perspective.
The idea is, okay, I want to do everything by my bare hands,
I need to have knowledge, infrastructure, everything.
But I had less time to focus
on my business and I want to increase
the experience on my business. So I delegate the hardware to
somebody else. I pay somebody else to handle the hardware to me.
So it is infrastructure as a service,
but sometimes it is not enough,
right? I want to focus even more on my business perspective.
So I delegate the hardware and the operation
on that. In these case I will
use path or platform as service where
I just need to write a code, I don't need to
do something else, for example platform,
Sage, Heroku and so on. And these last
step is I don't want to handle anything,
I just want to use it. So I
delegate the hardware plus the operation and finally the
software knowledge to create these software. So the
Gmail suites, the G suites, I feel like that. So I delegate
everything to another companies to
make my life easier and several perspectives.
But it doesn't matter. In each scale
we are in abstraction. The whole point about cloud is
why won with that. So we want success.
And to us success is faster innovation without
impacting these stability. Okay, that sounds impossible,
but that's what we are looking for with
cloud. At least that's what we're trying to
achieve. Okay, that's why right now we have
several options of cloud providers and service.
We started with yes, infrastructure as a service,
platform as a service and software as a service.
And right now we have more flavors of service
in the cloud. So you probably have heard
about cas, that is container as a service, where we
provide containers. And also
we have decision process as a service,
database as a service management event,
streaming as a service, back end as a service or serverless and
so on. The main point here is those are
new service and we
try to put a category on that situation where caused
it is between yas and cases.
And these manage application service such as database
as a service and serverless are unspecialization
of cases. Okay,
but these is a new discussion. It's not stuttered.
And every time that we talk about cloud,
we are living in a cloud trained moment where we had cloud,
just cloud was a buzzword around
technology. Right now it is not anymore.
Then we moved to cloud. Ready?
Moved to cloud friend. Finally, right now
we are living in a cloud native era where everybody's talking
about cloud native. But wait, what does
cloud native means?
Unfortunately, I have a bad news. You. That is,
I have no idea what does that mean, and I'm
being to tell you what I guess nobody knows
because cloud native become a kind of hakuna matata
where everybody has your perspective.
These about that definition, okay, if you go to
several articles, several discussions probably
these discussion this article, this book has your own definition about
cloud native. Each company probably has own
definition and you might have your
own definition about cloud native. Let's go on
some samples here. For example, in the
pivotal website, cloud native is an approach to
building and running application that explode and
take advantage of the cloud computing model.
There is this amazing book here, or learning path
attaching cloud native application. The main goal
here is to focus more infrastructure
where cloud native is more about infrastructure than soft
development. There is this book here,
cloud native development partner and best practice.
It has a similar ideology around
cloud native to the previous book.
Indeed they have
a new word third that means in deployment,
deploy, up and replace and scale. So it's more about
infrastructure than soft development. Then we
have this book that put everything around
soft development in some level of
cloud native. So today cloud native
is more than a tool set, is a complete architecture and
philosophical approach. So everything is
around cloud native. In the past we
had waterfall, right now we are
living in the agile methodology and the
next move to you is move to cloud native where
everything is around cloud.
We also have CNCF that is an organization around cloud
native by Linux foundation that
has your own definition as well. So cloud native technology empower organization
to build run scalable application.
It has several simple approach, okay,
container service, mesh, microservice. But as you can
see it's abstract enough to fit
everything because it's too abstract and
it looks like more a marketing and sales pitch,
they are technical perspective. But anyway we
saw several articles around, okay, if you create
an application that is container based or it's
ready to cloud and it was burned in these cloud, okay, it's a cloud native
application. And be happy with that.
The whole point here is today is to explain to you
that right now we have 1000 of definition
of cloud native. And that is okay,
that if you have no idea, what does that mean? Because right
now the whole market has no idea either. Okay,
so every article might have a different perspective
of cloud native because it's a new trend.
These everybody is looking at.
And yes, I have my own definition as well based on
the previous book that I read and article as well. So to me
cloud native is a set of good practice to optimize an application in
the cloud through three steps, containers,
orchestration and finally automation.
And yes, we talked about what we want to
achieve with cloud. That is innovation
without impact and use
stability in the software development. And that is these expectation,
right? So we want to be like Apollo, closer to
the sun and the highest as possible.
However, the reality is we become Icarus
where you fall as closer we go to the clouds.
That's sad, but unfortunately that's true.
And we have a thousand challenge when talk about soft development
plus cloud.
Besides the political area
discussions and something like that, we also have
technical challenge to us. We have security routes,
Opengrid database and language backups optimization
such as CI cts at a stand for
as software developers,
architecture and senior engineer. We must know
that everything is around trade off, right? We need
to handle with complexity, we handle with risk,
we handle with cost. And also we need to handle with the
knowledge management. These I need to know what
everybody knows. And I need to move these right person to the right team
to the right knowledge. These is this amazing book that is
fundamental of soft architecture. It's an engineering
approach and everything is about trade off.
Okay. When I mentioned the sauce,
probably it might is more expensive,
however it has less risk. When you go to
yas it might be cheaper than a sauce.
However, I need to handle with more stuff. I need to handle with more
details that I usually don't need to handle when I go
as fast. Okay.
And yes, I talked to why we are moving to the
cloud, the history reason, the expectation,
what we want to achieve, the challenge.
And finally let's talk about the survival guide.
How can we handle with cloud Java
and how we can move our application to the cloud.
These survival guide today is a flight
plan. Oh wait, what do
you mean about flight plan? Because a flight
plan is a plan to go to somewhere in
the cloud, right? So it's a plan. So we need to define the routes,
these schedule, these definition,
the external points like weather equipment,
the crew, the internal tails
and of course with security, with safety
to keep our organization moving while
everything is moving on.
That's why we have etops.
And basically the idea and the analogy with the flight
plan is exactly like that. I need to know where am I,
how far I want to go. I need to check the
internal conditions, the external condition, the budget,
and more precisely these safety.
Remember the point I want to achieve a
success is move faster. If doubt impact our
organization.
And that's the question that we want to answer with
the flight plan. Where are
we? These should we go next?
How do I get there? Because in the flight plan
if it's too far. Sometimes you're not able to go directly between
Sao Paul and Brazil to Japan. We need to have stops for example.
Because once it's too far, I need to create scales on
that stops. And that's the idea I need
to understand where am I and where I want to go. It is if
it is too far, maybe do cases
and to understand everything around it.
And every time when we talk about abdominal
framework in the cloud, we need to talk about the
maturity models that we have so far.
Frameworks adoption that we have so far.
Right now I believe every cloud provider has
your own definition or one information about
the framework of cloud adoption to that
cloud providers. Okay.
And that is okay. In the soft development you probably know
the Richard maturity model where
we simply call cloud rest. Where we have application
that wants to go to these perfect state of art of
rest application where we start with none
and go through hype media controls these hate was and
that is exactly what we want to achieve with cloud.
And the flight plan is basically that it's a growing of
cloud for sure. It's not a good name. Yes these
might be impact religion thing, but the idea is to start
with none and then go to most
optimized as possible.
And let's move on to that flight plane idea.
The first level or none. We understood
that there is no cloud adoption. We are not
using cloud yet, but we'd like to use the
first point on that moment is to understand the methodology
to move our application far as possible.
So I need level o, so need to
create MVP or a buck, create a small application,
prepare if everything is okay, expand,
optimize to finally self sustain.
Okay, so a buck put prepare to
production, go to production, create more
steps, optimize these step to using automation
and then finally self sustain.
Once we understood these methodology and want to move to these cloud,
let's move to the initial step.
We have a little bit of automation of observability
or law on existent cloud
adoption.
Also I mentioned before, the idea is to
handle risk and cost and especially the
complexity because the complexity is the main key on
that situation. Okay,
we need to understand that as much risk I have,
I need to think how to decrease that complexity because the risk
is on the part that I have no idea how to handle or
I understand that's hard to maintain or to keep
moving. There is this amazing book, the philosophy
of soft design where the main focus is exactly to
talk about complexity. So take a look on that.
Okay, we went to none, we understood the
methodology, we moved to
initial where, okay, I need to understand and measure
the risk and these complexity around cloud. And let's
put some automation on our application. So let's move application that I have
to the cloud. And right now let's put a little
bit more CI ACD practice to become natural in
the cloud environment. It doesn't matter if
it's Amazon, Google,
Microsoft or Oracle. And the first
advice you in the level three is make it more observable and
modifiable. How? With infrastructure
as a code? With infrastructure as a code we have
more transparency on what you're doing. It's more observable,
more testable, it has more security.
Unfortunately it's a goodbye that, okay, it works
on my machine. You're not able to make this joke anymore because the whole infrastructure
is these code. And if I want you to
do any kind of modification, I need to have my code that's
totally observable and transparent to me.
The next step of infrastructure code
is Gitops where I have a
merge of several amazing approach.
I have infrastructure code plus prs and plus CI
CD where I have git a single source of
truth, a git as a single place
to operate. And all chains are observable
and verifiable in both areas in the development side
and operation side. Again default.
And for example, right now I'm using these application with Java eleven
and I want to move to the next lts that is Java
17. What can I do? I can create a pr
with that modification in the infrastructure.
If everything is okay, I will run these CI.
If everything is okay, I merge this
application to the cloud. Once everything
is amazing, I'm in
the merge, it's automatically deploying application
with the latest version in the kit. If something
goes wrong and only was able to check on production,
that's sad, but sometimes happened you were able to do a kit
revert and these return to previous version of the
code. Okay, so with GitHub,
the integration between infrastructure code, prs and
cis, indeed you make your code more observable,
verifiable and use git as
a single source of true to both to developers and
operations.
The last step. Okay, I understood
these. No, because I had the methodology, I moved
to understand the complexity around cloud.
I started to do automation in my application.
I make it more observable and modifiable to finally go
to optimization through hybrid cloud.
And every time that I talk about cloud automation,
there is several amazing tips. For example, there is this amazing book here,
19 things every college engineer should know that
has and
I'll highlight, I really recommend to you read once and twice
these use managed service please sometimes, okay? If you
are using some past products,
if you don't have nobody in your team that knows that deeply,
okay. Or maybe you don't have budget. So focus on
development and use cases. For example, it is okay
if you are running kubernetes,
okay? That's not an issue.
Keep it simple please. The source
code, the management for soft delivery and
containers are magic. So those are just
a highlight of these book. Please take it and read it.
And the chocolate application right now is so classic.
I don't need to go deep on that. But if you never heard about it,
please Google it to go deep on your
application. Those books are
classics. Could but code especially to
the Java developers. So the effective Java to optimize
your code style and design code where Joshua
Block wrote several tips Joshua Block
was one of the person who wrote a collection API
Ddd domain driven design to make
your code closer to the business. Remember DevOps and Java
methodology, clean architecture and clean code by
Robin Martin, the uncle Bob please
read carefully these books. Read once, read twice.
It's okay to review the book once you read it,
especially to have more information. And every
time that I talk about cloud native these is
a link between microservice. Okay, should I move to microservice
just because everybody else is doing? The answer
to that is a no, right? You don't need to
move to microservice only because everybody else is doing
indeed, there is three amazing books where you should go and read.
Two by Sanjeevan and one by Naga.
And these three books has two things in common.
Those books are talking about microservice and
those books also has.
These books also have a warning about okay,
not everything is around microservice.
Sometimes it's okay to keep the model application.
I put the highlight on ET booking
and okay, just because Netflix and Amazon are using
it does not mean that you are Netflix and Amazon.
Like your problem said, you are not
everybody, you are unique. Your company is unique,
has minimal requirements. Please pay attention that
okay, especially because it matters to us.
And remember the colors law.
If the organization there's no structure, probably the software
will follow these trends to
make our life easier and advice
we have this amazing book, the best practice in soft architecture
in the cloud era. It is in English and it is
for free. Please take a look at this QR code.
Go deep on that where we have several tips about cloud developments.
It is agnostic most of these time.
However, there are several tips to these other developers.
Okay, I want to know more about cloud. How can I use
DevOps with DDD and a cloud integration
with Kubernetes? These are agnostic but
these is also performance training, something like that. So if you want to take
a look, want to learn more,
take and read it. And yes,
that is it. Again,
hopefully you enjoy my application.
Thank you everybody again, please follow
me on Twitter. My name is otas santana. My twitter is
at archapjava and if you have any questions please let me know.
So send me an email, send me a twitter, any kind of thing.
Thank you, bye bye and that is it.
See you soon.