This is the next phase of IoT and information and visualization
with digital twins. Let's get started a little bit about
myself. I am Tati Hikopian, a program manager
working with digital integration in the built environment.
I've been a course author and speaker for topics like
coding and building information modeling. So let's
get started with what are digital twins? Simple explanation
here is a digital twin is a digital representation of
a physical object or system. For example,
you might have a robot arm like this. You would see in many different factories
as the physical object,
and you might be able to copy it as a digital twin
in a digital environment. Like in this example, where we see on
the upper left inset a manipulating a robot arm
in real time, and then this digital representation in the larger
picture, showing the robot arm movements
as it is displaced from the original position.
This is a really good, straightforward example of what a digital twin does.
It just replicates what's going on in real time in the physical
environment. So the ingredients of digital
twins is IoT, cloud,
and data. The IoT is just a device that is able
to be connected to the Internet at large.
The cloud and network infrastructure behind it lets
you send the data over and
store it someplace. And then the data itself is the useful application
we get out of twins, and they work in conjunction together. And let's
talk about the use cases of digital twins in the world today.
There's manufacturing, factory automation, and simulation.
There's vehicles, tracking vehicles, sensors,
healthcare devices for monitoring the human body, which includes something as
simple as an Apple Watch or pippit that could track steps or
your heart rate. And then there's structures and buildings to
monitor your energy use, and equipment and buildings. Also useful things like trying to
track the displacement of a bridge over time to make sure it's
within tolerances. So what are the benefits of digital
twins, and why do people use them with IoT devices?
Well, it's real time. You can see what's happening with your physical
assets without having to send someone out there to check it, or going
through some very intensive process to figure out what's
actually happening in the environment with the monitoring twenty
four seven, you have always a picture at hand
of what's going on with your physical assets.
It also provides historical data on things like maintenance,
operations, and metrics in one
place. That way, if you want to know what's been happening for a day,
a year, many years, it's at your disposal. You don't have to worry about
trying to collect disparate sources of information to understand the
history of your asset. You don't have to go through binders and
paper logs to get information. It's digital, it's in one place,
it's easy to sort through, and it's scalable
from small to large projects, because the fundamentals don't really change
that much, no matter how big you go. And you could predict outcomes
based on historical data and the metrics you're tracking, which is very useful for
things like maintenance and expansion of operations.
And this all leads to shared benefits for owners
of, say, a real estate portfolio.
You can understand where your assets are,
how they're performing, and how to improve
operations for long term return on investments.
Building managers and equipment managers can understand the
activity of the equipment at hand. For example, if you manage a
school as a facility manager, you can figure out with some IoT
connected devices like agarometers,
if there's some kind of leak in the lives. And instead of waiting until you
have a flood in the hallways, you can get an alert,
track it, and get ahead of the fix before there's any problems in school and
equipment manufacturers. If your devices are already enabled and equipped
with IoT devices on the edge, you could support operations remotely.
If there's any kind of issues with the equipment that you sold
to somebody, warranty, upkeep, downtime,
you name it, you can get ahead of it by being able to tap into
the IoT gateway. So with that in mind,
there's a whole world of digital twins and visualization I'd like to
get into, because it's being, as you could see by the prior examples applied
in so many different fields in so many different ways. But of course, I want
to start with something. Our favorite topic, data standards. And data
standards are important. There are many different kind of standards.
Depending on what kind of field of work you do. There's always more than a
few, and usually try to do their best to make it
a straightforward, reliable process. But usually get this
kind of situation where people want to make like the master
data standard or master standard, and you just end
up with more standards. So that's more
or less the kind of going on in data for
IoT in general. For example, these are different
industry bodies that will work on IoT for manufacturing,
industry 4.0,
manufacturing for certain types of devices,
like Internet consortium. So there's a lot of organizing bodies
around the world that will try to provide some kind of standardization.
So it's not for a lack of standards, it's just for a lack of
heuristics between the standards permeating what is the shared
kind of intent and terminology, not necessarily a
technical specification, because that really is sensitive to the field you work in,
how a vehicle manufacturer and how somebody working in
healthcare might have a very different perspective on the technical specifications.
It's more important about the shared language of the ways
you go about getting started and accomplishing tasks.
What's great about that, though, is we now have this
bucket called a digital twin consortium, which brings a lot of different standards,
more than what you see here, and tries to harmonize the language and the
general operations between them. I bring this up because if you
ever wanted to really dive into digital twins, you do have to understand the flows
of data. And with something like a consortium standard, which brings in common
language, that becomes a lot more easy to communicate. For example,
they'll provide you with the input,
operational and output concept here,
simple representation digital twin consortium puts together for
how you would process reference data. So you don't
have to go into the weeds of a given standard. You just agree that there's
a process for taking whatever your x inputs
are, going through a system and getting y outputs.
This might seem simple and elementary, but I granted this myself.
Where we take things for granted,
we come from different places. I come from a construction
and design background. Other people might be coming from a telecom background,
other people might be coming from a cybersecurity background. And our terminology gets
mixed. So we start early and often with the idea of how to communicate
with each other. And even something as simple as a structured
store of information, again, can be very opaque.
If you don't specify that, it could be some kind of SQL
database, GIS CAD being point
clouds, IoT streams, and different log
lives in history, you name it. Just be very clear and specific
and you won't go wrong. Otherwise, all your data is in an excel
database. Typically, I don't start conversations with
data standards first and foremost, but this is something you want to clarify
early and often is what are our standards? How do we communicate? Because again,
up and down that chain of IoT and
digital twins, there is a lot of communication, and not everybody's going to have the
same point of view about what a different term or system
that is viable will be. So just FYI,
this is something that is very pertinent in this world. Okay,
now we've got that out of the way. Let's talk about tech stacks and how
you'd actually get anything done. And the fun
part of IoT and digital twins is you have to convert a lot
of things to a lot of other things, file formats, data stores,
and there's a lot of interoperability going on here. So it's
about as simple as this. Mixed it out to be.
And we can simplify a little better with just this
idea of how IoT components and connections come together. Starting with the
red box here, the smart devices, whether that's streaming
video, a device, vehicles,
equipment, whatever it is, that's your starting point. That's the
real world where all the data comes from. You have to find a way to
make sure that somehow is connected to the Internet in whatever
way, shape or form, whatever wavelength standard,
Bluetooth, Wifi, you name it, whatever it is
IoT needs to connect. Those are the starting points,
which then goes to a gateway, Wifi or, excuse me,
the IoT device on its own typically does not have a gateway.
So you have to have a gateway, like a Wifi router
or cable connection or some device nearby that can act as a hub
to collect all the data and then set it to the Internet.
This might seem like a no brainer, but sometimes your equipment is
in some remote area and the bandwidth is not great or
connections aren't there. So this is actually a bottleneck you have to work through.
Depending where you are. Sometimes your equipment or devices are moving.
Like I mentioned earlier, if you are asking people to use some kind of body
monitoring device, depending on where they are and how frequent you want that data,
you might have some latency issues. Then you want
middleware, whether it's a server rack,
a cloud host, some kind of database that can collect all this data and store
it someplace and potentially perform operations on it as part
of a network stack or platform stack. And then
from there, you can finally use all that great information as your applications.
You're basically the front facing way of
using digital twins. This is what we usually think of digital twins as the application
layer, but it goes all the way back to the hardware and
the real world assets. Otherwise, your applications are
not going to tell you anything very useful. So as long
as you get this chain going well, you can't go wrong. The thing
is, depending on what world you're working in, whether it's built,
environment, medical, industrial space,
it's all over the place. You can see here,
from manufacturing to urban design to point clouds
to surveying, there's so many different solutions out there. There's even three D
engines you can use, like in a real unity to help you create digital twins.
So the point I'm making here is it's a very diverse
world of technology, and don't feel like there's going
to be an out of the box solution. There isn't
anything so far that I would really say you can rely on for
the next couple of years, at least, maybe longer. You really do have to be
sensitive to the different starting points
of your data. The legacy software and the up and coming
startups make it real. So be comfortable learning
and getting used to different kinds of tools,
because you could put it together yourself or use something like
a data science tool to help you analyze the data. But this is just a
smorgasbord of all different kinds of technologies, like Jupyter
notebooks, power, Bi Kafka, you name it, that you can use for that
as well. So good news is you probably do already have a bunch of tools
that can be at your disposal for IoT, edge and neutral
twins. The underwhelming news is you probably
have to learn a bunch more, at least be appreciative of other data sources and
operations to make this work. So keep it simple.
Don't feel overwhelmed. I'm not trying to intimidate people and make them scared.
Start with something simple lives. Sensors. What are the devices at your disposal?
Are these hypothetical devices that have not been installed yet? They're not available.
They're going to be built or deployed later. Are they real?
Pencil that out. Make sure you know what that is. What is the actual sensors
and devices, how they connect to the real world? What kind of
digital representations do you have? Do you have actual 3d models,
point clouds? Is it just charts and graphs? What do you have at your disposal
and hosting solutions? This is actually becoming more and more an
integral part of the digital twins environment, because even
the big cloud hosts are permeating IoT
and digital twins specific workflows.
So if you can figure out these three buckets, you're already way ahead,
because then it's just a matter of making a framework
that's suitable for the solution, because again, it can come from any different
angle. One example I like to throw out here is digital
twins by Azure. I am just showing here as
an example of a company and projects I've worked on have
used Azure, so I thought IoT was a useful reference.
And you can see here the digital twins that zero provides can
be pretty diverse. It's able to draw from many different
IoT devices, from vehicles to industrial equipment to manufacturing
to signals. So this
is an example of an actual product being released for a cloud platform to help
you package all the data and operations of digital twins.
And on top of that, they have an IoT hub. And this is how
you would take the different IoT devices,
event hubs, and just different data streams,
go through an abstraction layer, and then get actual automations
and functions out of them at the other end. I would say if you're trying
to get things going at a more enterprise friendly level,
this is the place to be. Otherwise you might be spending some time experimenting
with different smaller technical solutions.
And what's great about Azure is you can start small and scale up
given the technology. But this is also true of AWS. They have basically
their own version of this, and other cloud providers also
have something like this, and IoT just lives you a sense of what
you can do. This is Cosmos and IoT Azure. The reason I use this diagram
actually is a great representation that I was showing you earlier of the different
connections and hardware, the gateways, the data storage,
and the presentation. This actually does spell it out. Where on the left here
you have the IoT devices at your disposal. Like I
said, streaming devices, vehicles go to the gateway hub
and from there can connect to the different databases, and the
automations provided for those databases give you the
insights. And then from there, the actions, applications,
interface. Individual twins. So this is more what's under the hood
and how the framework applies for just one tech stack. Again, there's many
variations of this, but it's a little more clear of how you would actually go
about executing these kind of architectures and patterns.
But it can get much more interesting. This is an example of using what
they call an ontology model and the
palantir foundry platform to get real time data out of flight patterns.
So this is getting the weeds. It's not just abstracted. This is
really what you can do with these kind of platforms to get understandings
and insights of how complex
systems work. So I would love to go into a
whole talk about this, but this is really just kind of an overview to
give you how it works, many different technologies
and solutions of platforms and providers. But as long as you can figure out
a way to get some kind of data set from the devices in the real
world and represent them. In this case, it's just a chart,
something fancy, just a chart streaming the data connections from
point a to b to c to z, and then be able
to host them and spread that information. You pretty much have a
digital twin at that point. So talk real quick about
hardware so you get a sense of what's under the hood. I'll keep this one
pretty short and sweet. Let's say you have a built asset and you want
to show off some cool charts of what's going on,
I would recommend going with the
view. There's lots of great information available if you just
connect the devices with some kind of spatial recognition.
I work a lot with buildings, industrial spaces,
so something of a specialty topic. For example,
just a given house or apartment has multiple digitally
connected Internet connect devices, thermometers, security cameras,
door cameras,
your own phone. I actually have most of these things in my apartment right
now. And most people can have basically everything they need
for a setup to represent the different comfort
levels and activity of their own home.
So all you do is map it out. This is an important part of the
process, mapping out what you got. If you don't know what you got, you can't
use it. And usually a lot of the hardware we see
is little chips on these devices. But it could be as simple as
an Arduino board or something like an Arduino board. You can hook these up and
make your own little custom IoT edge devices. And you could
do something like this, slap it on the back of a wall or some equipment,
nothing fancy, just make sure the wiring is good and you could already
have something that can report the information. Good for temperature
sensing, equipment diagnostics. I mentioned earlier
about the plumbing of the school. There's a serious issue with a lot
of buildings where they leak and they cause us a lot of damage in the
hundreds of thousands of dollars. And they're starting to use hygrometers that are small
and compact and retrofitting buildings with them. So if there
is a water alert, a humidity alert, it can go to a central database.
And it's as simple as something like this where you can quickly wire it up
or use wireless methods of reporting it, so that
with a modest investment, you can avoid serious cost overruns.
So it doesn't have to be a huge, challenging project, but it
can be. This is an example of the Dearborn vehicle production
plant by Ford in michigan. They basically not only
connected all their major mechanical equipment in
the plant that runs the operations to IoT,
to have their facility units check status, their equipment,
so their really expensive capital expenditures aren't downtime,
which stops the whole line of production, but they also mapped it out in 3D.
So the next part here, we'll talk about the actual visualization of the
digital twin environment. And what you want to do is make sure that
what you have is useful to the end user. Not for yourself or specialist,
but just an end user that would be able to interact with
it and not disappoint them. You don't want to give them a blue screen of
death or some kind of glitch that would prevent the access. Remember,
we talked about all these examples of the hardware, the technology
stacks, and even the standardization issues. You want to keep these pretty straightforward
and effective and not over constraint what you're doing. Otherwise you might have
some glitches. But we'll talk about the visualizations look like,
and typically the categories that fall into IoT is a 3d model, some geometric representation.
Charts, charts are great, different kinds of charts showing you bar graphs,
if that's something that's very useful for diagnostic information, VRA for
immersion, so that you can really clearly see what's going on
in a given space. And even simple maps and floor plans are very useful
for the average person, which can be done in multiple ways. Two D at three
d projection. So talk about 3d models. Here's an
example that came from the company Autodesk,
and they're showing how you can go through different time of
the day. This is just a time series data explaining temperature
and lighting in a building. You can see on the right there the numbers changing
from different rooms and different settings they have in each room.
What's great about 3d models is they're very intuitive. People like
models. They like straightforward models. They can represent a space and
orient them very quickly and tell them something
useful very quickly. In this case, you're pairing up a model with some sensors
or giving you room information, and you could take a little further and
even make an interactive 3d model. People love playing with interactive
3D Models. They love going around and looking. And in this case,
we're seeing very nuanced data of the environmental
settings in heat maps from room to room. That way
people understand it's not just one size fits all reading,
but there is a little bit of variation in the kind of information they're
reading. And again, time series data,
hourly reporting in this case.
So what's really good about this day
and age is most building projects, and most projects in general, even for equipment,
they have 3d models. So it's not like you have to go and build
a new one necessarily. You just maybe find one for an engineer
or architect and repurpose it.
This will make the client happy, because they might already have this asset. And if
you don't have an actual 3d model, you can use point clouds, you can use
a scanner system. Matterport has something like this. You can even start doing some basic
things with your phones. So 3d models are a great way to show up an
area space that requires area spatial data.
But you can go a little deeper and talk about virtual reality.
In this example, there is a training going on for
industrial equipment using digital twins.
What's useful about this, what's really beneficial,
is you can do remote training and get
a really good sense of how equipment works. It's an example of industrial IoT
being used to help workers understand the equipment they're using without having to necessarily
send them all into the same factory floor. This is a much more efficient
use of time. If you're just trying to get them used to the ins and
outs of something, then we talk about plans. In this
case, this plan here is just a floor plan of office, and you can
talk about occupancy, utilization, temperature,
equipment, adjacency. This is really useful for just the average office
monitor, average office manager in the average
office building. This could be for schools, medical facilities, you name
it. People just want to understand what's going on their space. If you ever been
in a situation where you wonder why one corner of a building is so cold,
this is a great way to figure out what's the highs and lows of the
temperature. So this is nothing fancy, nothing hard to
do, but it's a great way of visualizing very quickly to somebody what's happening
in their environment and help them manage work
environments. But beyond that, you can also start cataloging things.
In this example, the visualization just showing you
clusters of similar types of equipment. This is
from a hospital in the middle, you can see those blue gurneys. Hospitals have lots
of gurneys, but they need to know where they are so they can have them
available for the patients. And in a given facility where you have to
make sure your equipment is in good order,
inventory, maintenance,
and expansions and replacements are known. This is a
great way to figure out what is in your model, or, excuse me, what is
in your inventory and project and your building.
And it's actually a serious problem for many, many different industries,
because they kind of know, they may have an idea, but it's a very human
thing. So if Gus in facility management is
unavailable that day, you may not have no idea where anything is. But if you
have a database like this that represents everything very quickly, and it's been tagged
and verified in the field, you don't have to worry about that. You can leave
Gus alone and you can really quickly pull up all the different assets and the
serial numbers and the product data sheets. Last but IoT least,
game engines. This is an example of a data flow on
the left side. All these different 3d file formats, which there are a lot.
Going back to the whole digital twin consortium of putting the data
together is actually more challenging. They think in this
case they're bringing in different 3d data assets with different kind of meshes and parametric
components into a layer
called datasmith that then goes into unreal, but it can then be hosted through
API connections on your cloud of choice. In that case,
in this example of an industrial facility, you might get lots of different engineering
model formats from lots of different providers, and they may
not be playing nice with each other, they may not be mutually compatible,
I've been there. But if you bring it into a game engine which
handles that kind of exchange,
you can quickly put the industrial and
building and gis and topography together, and then
provide the insights from the sensors as well from the cloud hosts.
And before you know it, you have a whole dashboard explaining a very sophisticated
large industrial facility like this to clients and
operations who want to know what's going on in their spaces, which is actually
a serious problem. You'd be surprised how often it's not clear on a given day
how much energy a facility uses or how much of the facility
is operational, how much of it is vacant.
It really depends on the facility. So this is a great way to
make it easy for somebody at the top level of c suite or
a customer to understand what's going on. And this is a little more customized but
totally doable for most built environments and
their equipment. And last but not least, the urban scale.
This is Helsinki, Finland. They used a layer called city GML
as an information model to help organize their city assets into
a base layer for them to then host different other objects,
like the building information point clouds,
operational data. This is going to help the city understand what's going
on in the city, the flows of people, the kinds
of places where activities at help will understand and better service the
city in different utility expansions
in need of road work you need because again, it's usually just done manually
based on feedback from people, but you could literally just make it an urban level
digital twin, just like twins. In a sense, Google Maps, with their 3d immersion
view is a type of digital twin, but there's no real time reporting besides
traffic. So you could take this further and using the kind of
architecture you see on left there, make your own digital twin. Keep scaling it to
a regional level, including topography, satellite data
and hydrology, which is what they're trying to account for here. So the
scale is pretty much the
sky is the limit. And from here we'll talk about planning if
this got your attention, what would IoT take to plan for digital twins?
Well, the cornerstone here is owners,
because owners do have to pay for all this.
Usually, whoever's managing the end product, whether it's device or
facility, they're the ones paying for it. So you have to get their ear and
you have to build a business case of what is in the proposal.
What are you trying to actually, an RFP, a request for proposal. What is it
they're trying to get across? Potentially do a pilot program,
because this might be capital intensive or long term. So maybe you do have to
get their approval to work. Everybody's happy with
the proof of concept. Describe the ROA
based on the pilot and the RFP to make
sure everybody's happy, including the accountants, and look
for opportunities to roll these out,
because they may not happen all the time. They may be happening one offs,
but once they are, there may get upkeep and
pro tip. You want to be on the leading edge of the adoption curve.
Even if things aren't perfect, this environment around IoT digital twins
and the visualization constantly changes. So the sooner you get started,
the easier it is to change. Because if you go on
the laggard edge, not the leading edge of the laggard
edge, you'll be in a rush to try to catch up with the
business need and use cases of digital twins, and then you'll end up with
a Klude. And I worked on many of Kluge, and you don't want to be
there. And your project team just needs to be set up so
that you assess, plan,
document, train, create a common data environment
type of digital twin, an early release, a cloud hosting solution,
analyze the data, study the trends of that data,
create, update for your operations that are relevant from the
data, and then repeat. It's a cycle. And yes,
there are many handoffs, and yes, there are many steps that yes, you do have
to be aware of them, because it's not one guy, it's not one app,
it's many apps, many people, some who are not technically savvy,
but are very knowledgeable, and you just have to be mindful of the human lives
of exchange here. So to get started,
I have a couple of easy steps to help you. It's not as complicated as
we have here on this chart. Know what you want, what do you want to
do? What do you care about? What is it you want to get tracked in
digital twins? Any simple thing. What are the
opportunities to apply that we talked about? Pilot project, perhaps maybe a
simple test. It doesn't have to be anything fancy, just look for opportunities to apply
it, plan it out, chart the critical path and
what it takes to get there and adjust as you go. It's a very much
touch and go operation in many cases, until you get the final result and then
you can dial them in. So don't be afraid to modify Iot as you proceed.
Achieve you want building performance? Well, you need lots of sensors and analytics.
You want user feedback. Will you need a human facing element to get some
kind of survey data or some kind of human appreciation
out? If that's what your concern is. If you want people to make sure
they're happy with it. If it's not simply a machine spitting out data, you need
to make sure humans are giving you some kind of useful feedback and automation if
you want to just automate the whole thing. If it's already a solved problem on
the performance and evaluation, then maybe you need better
technology automation to get the data fast, because sometimes you have to report
thousands of operations a second in industrial equipment to make sure
that the data there is useful for maintenance
operations. Bringing Iot all together. So from
the beginning end, create connections to the physical environment, get live
updates from the environment and make sure that reliable have a place to
store the data that is nice and secure. Analyze the
data for notifications and usage. Upgrade your
equipment and digital assets over time. Repeat forever.
Because just like the real world that we live in,
nothing stays in one place for too long. Everything changes.
The work keeps going, the ride never ends.
Twins is quite the adventure I've been on over the years from some very
static kinds of data that rarely gets
updated to super frequent data updates and all the
different changes in the digital environment over the years.
So it is quite a fun
place to be. You never get bored. There's always something you can work on,
so just appreciate that you can't go wrong.
Takeaways digital twins are virtual representation of
physical assets. They are not in and of themselves an
operation independent of the physical world. They all exist
in a schema of connected devices. It's not one stream or
one flow, but very much a schema of different devices communicating
with each other to a digital environment. Use common ground
for planning with standardizing bodies and terminology to avoid confusion.
There are many modes of visualization for digital twins. Pick one that suits what
you're trying to achieve. Experiment a little bit. Create a
business plan of roadmaps, because these can take a while and they can have
many twists and turns. So make sure you chart out a course that can last
for at least a few months, if not a year or two. Find opportunities
to use digital twins. Sometimes they're kind of handed to
you, outlined to you by other people. Sometimes you can get clever and create
different ways to help people understand the assets and environments they're
trying to evaluate. Here's some additional resources reading
about digital twins,
standards, enterprises, productivity, you name it.
There's lots of material out here. That's a good starting point for you all.
That's it. Wrapping it up. Thanks so much for joining me in my
talk today. I hope you had as much fun listening
as I had talking about it. If there's any
questions or any outreach, please reach out to me, Tadehhakopian,
LinkedIn, GitHub, anywhere. I'm search engine optimized,
so you can't go wrong with those letters in that combination.
And thank you all again for attending my talk.