So hello all. Good morning, good evening and good afternoon in wherever time zone
you are. So, my name is Archit Srivastava and today I'll
be taking you through my talk. And the topic of the talk is in ignotis.
And the talk is basically an introduction about how quantum computers
can be helpful in the fields of astrophysics. And the meaning
of the word in ignotis is into the unknown.
So it is actually an area which is very unknown to
us, like how can quantum computers
be used utilized in the area of astrophysics?
So let us move forward with the topic. So, a basic
introduction about me. So who I am, where I work, and what all
things I have done in the past. So I am
one of the founders of a quantum hardware community called as Akim.
And at AKM we basically try to spread
awareness about what the quantum hardware architecture is.
And we basically research about different quantum hardware
architectures like photonics, iron trap,
superconducting. And we basically dive deep into
how these different quantum architectures
work especially. I graduated with a bachelor's
of engineering degree in electronics and instrumentation engineering from
RV College of Engineering, Bangalore. And me,
along with one of my colleagues, we started off a quantum research club,
and its name was circuit. So circuit is an abbreviation for
center for interdisciplinary research in quantum information and
technology. And over there, we had different verticals which focus more
on different areas of quantum computing, to be specific, like quantum machine learning,
quantum optimization, quantum algorithms and all.
And I got associated in my final years of
college with a community called as quantum Computing India.
And over there, along with a few of
my colleagues, we started off the quantum hardware learning circle, where we focused more
about the growth and what all things
are going on in the quantum hardware domains. And in
my final years of college, also, I was one of the first quantum computing
interns at the Boon QSI Private Limited, which is one of the leading
quantum computing firms in the computing fluid dynamics
area. And the vision, the mission, the aim that they have and they
are trying to achieve is fabulous, and they are
doing great in this field right now. And the research that they
do at their firm is one of the best in the industry,
which is basically collaborating the research field,
research domain and the industry together.
And the problem statements that they're tackling is
going to help the humanity
and the industry and the research area in general in the
coming future. Currently, I work as full stack data engineer
at Hewlett Beckert Enterprise in the Silicon Valley of India,
Bangalore, in the state of Karnataka. And my
day two day work basically deals with anywhere from developing
dashboards and performing data analytics work,
to developing machine learning models and trying to predict
some certain trends, and parallel developing data
engineering pipelines so that to perform specific ETL tasks.
My personal interest lies in the area of the
field where we can integrate quantum computing with the field of gravitational
wave astronomy. So these two are very vast fields,
and a lot of scientists in these past have tried to integrate these two
fields together to basically get to a one
unison field so that we can explore
what the limits of physics are and how we can break
them so that we can explore the unknown.
Hence the title of the topic. So, moving forward with the topic,
basically. So, the motivation behind this talk was basically
to reduce the lack of knowledge that
is there, that is out there with the quantum ecosystem in general and the need
for the growth in the domain. Like, we get to hear that if
we combine quantum with artificial intelligence or even
general artificial intelligence, we basically can
develop certain systems which will take over humanity, and a lot
of stuff and misinformation going around. And my
personal opinion is we are years behind this
particular years behind actually getting to
leverage the actual advantages what a quantum computer
can provide to us, and then coming
more to specifics of the topics. So there is can increase in the need
to spread awareness about the various topics related to quantum computing
and astrophysics. So in the industry currently, we get to see a lot of
use cases of quantum computing being placed in the fields
of, say, finance, supply chain optimization, or various
fields like pharma, getting to
know about the protein folding examples, and various places
quantum computers are being used currently. But there is
a very niche area where quantum computers can become a
big asset, is the area of astrophysics and gravitational wave astronomy,
where, if the research is done in the right
way, with the correct motivation, then I personally believe
that we can develop certain tools,
certain experiments, or certain methods which can experimentally verify
certain theories of physics, like the quantum gravity, or even
the theory of everything. That is sort
of a hypothesis that people are yet
to prove and yet to achieve. So, moving on
with the topic, what we have in the
topic today is. So if I give you a brief about what the contents
will be. So, basically, I'll be giving a brief introduction
about what the whole talk will be about. Then we'll
dive a bit deep in what quantum computers
are, and I'm sure that my fellow
colleagues, in different talks have talked about quantum
a lot. So in the third segment of the talk, I'll be focusing a
bit more on where quantum computers can work
and what this term ligo
or Ligo means and why astrophysics at
all? And the methods in which quantum computing
can be included in astrophysics.
And what are the final conclusions with the talk that we has today?
Moving on with the topic, so, basically giving a brief introduction
about the talk today. So,
quantum computing and astrophysics. So, astrophysics is
basically the science which deals with the
mathematics related two celestial bodies and everything related
to them. Even the mathematical analysis of,
say, black holes or even relativity
or it is a very vast area, and it is
basically on a scale. If we try to look,
it is at a totally right hand
side. And if we look at quantum computing or quantum physics
in general, the quantum physics lies on the extreme left. So these
two fields are basically at the extremes of these
physics that we have today. And what scientists
believe that if we are able
to combine and unify these two extreme fields, then we'll
be able to get to explore
the unknown that is out there in the field of science and
explain a lot of unknown phenomenon that happen
in nature. Currently,
we have heard about a lot of developments in past
while going through the noble price
distributions that happen. So we might have heard about the
terms lIgo, or gravitational wave detectors, and along with
quantum computers. So these are different
terms that have been floating around from the past couple
of years. And these are very
complex and complicated devices to perform totally
different and very difficult tasks. Like LIgo are
very big detectors out there, which basically
help us to detect the gravitational waves that Einstein predicted
in his theories. And quantum computers are basically
an ensemble of various equipments, chips and
cutting edge technology, engineering science, physics to
basically leverage out the advantages being
provided by quantum physics to perform quantum operations
and give us the advantages that it can provide
to us, so that we can use them for daily use cases
like predictions
in the area of quantum machine learning and encryption,
which is a very niche area in quantum computing right now.
There are different architectures of quantum computers also. And what
is quantum gravity? So, quantum gravity is a hypothetical theory that scientists
have developed, which basically is at
the intersection of quantum physics and astrophysics,
or specifically gravity. So they try to
predict that there can be the existence of a particle
for gravity and called as graviton. And if
that exists, then it basically will complete the theory
and combine the two vast theories of
general and special relativity along with quantum computing.
So, basically, there is a need to investigate the realm of the unknown,
hence the topic of the talk. And it is a very
niche area of research, which has infinite
possibilities. So,
moving on with the topic, these talk so giving
a brief introduction of what the quantum is.
So this is a quantum computer.
Well, actually not, because this is a part of quantum computer.
And right beside, right at the below,
we have the chip. And this actually is a picture which
shows us the inside of what a quantum computer looks like inside the.
So basically, this is called as the golden chandelier, because majority
of the components are created out of gold. And right
there below sits
the quantum child, and the temperature
decreases as we move down the
chandelier, and below it is nearly
absolute zero. So this is a part of quantum
computer, and there will be a lot of casings out of it,
and it will be connected to various various
control system equipments, and then to the output and input signaling devices,
the measurement devices and all. So when
I say, well, it is not actually a quantum computer because
there are a lot of devices attached to it
which is not there right there in the picture. So all
those components, the measurement components, the input components, the output components,
along with the cloud systems, the software, the hardware
and different architectures, they comprise of what we collectively
call as a single word or a quantum computer. So this device is
able to perform and leverage all the advantages being provided by
quantum physics. And it provides the
output so that we can use, a normal user
can use the advantages of
quantum physics like superposition,
superposition and all, and sitting
remotely via a cloud. So companies like IBM,
Google, Microsoft, Amazon, along with several
other companies, they are providing the access
to these quantum computers via cloud, via cloud services,
and via different sdks that they have, via different libraries that
they have created, like Kiskit, Penny Lane,
Bracket, et cetera. So a lot of
buzz and hype is going on around quantum computing and the industry.
And there are companies which are sort of investigating
and diving deep into this niche technology
and leveraging it,
the complete advantage of it, for their own development.
Like in the area of finance, Goldman Sachs, Standard Chartered
and other companies are using quantum computers to basically work
on problem statements like portfolio optimization, stock price prediction,
et cetera. In the area of supply
chain, companies like ExxonMobil, et cetera.
Are working on optimizing the shipment
paths being provided for
the ships, for shipments, to optimize the overall supply
chain paths or routes that they have, so that there is a
cost cutting advantage. And there are other
firms working in different areas like
battery optimization, so that we can develop
more batteries, which are optimized.
And a lot of research is going on in and around industry with the
sdks and the
libraries that these companies are providing. So has
we talk there is constant development going on
around the quantum computers and the structure that we
have in front of us is being constantly updated, upgraded and
improved, so that the companies
that the problem statements that they are targeting, they can be
more optimized, more viable
to the customers and the end users. So,
as I was talking about various quantum computers,
so various quantum computers are out
there. And different companies work on different kind
of architectures also.
So we have superconducting trap diamonds,
photonics, and there are a lot of diamond centers and
a lot more architectures out there, like the
anilos available, being made available by D Wave.
So, all in all, a lot of quantum computers
are being developed with various kinds of architectures. And different
kinds of architectures are optimized for different kinds of.
To work on different kinds of problem statements.
And like the annealous that are being used, they are
more specifically optimized for the optimization problems.
And thus they are being used in supply chain optimization, portfolio optimization
problems by the companies in various domains.
So this, along with the
information being provided in the other talks at the conference
by my colleagues, will basically give you a generic
and overall picture of how the quantum realm
is currently and what the scenario of quantum computing is.
So now, moving on to the focus part of the talk
is basically the astrophysics part, and my personal favorite.
So, talking ABout astrophysics. So, basically,
specifically talking will
be the gravitational waves. So, gravitational waves
are basically ripples in the spacetime fabric,
which was predicted by Einstein's general theory
of relativity. And the pictures
that you are seeing here are different observatories built across the globe.
And the first Two to come up Were in
LIVINgStON AnD HaNford. And these are long
tubes, long vacuum chambers, long vacuum tubes which
carry lasers. And they basically
are like, if I give a number to the length
of these arms that you see over here, so they are 4 length.
And if someone asks, why 4 length?
So it is because if
the arm lengths are more than 4, curvature of earth
comes into picture and the arms BasicallY starts to bend around the
curvature of curves. So it is difficult to keep the laser
straight BeyoND 4
overcome Those kind of disadvantages.
Scientists are currently working on different projects.
Two basically reduce
the arm length disadvantage. So they
are setting up satellites and coming
up with projects in space,
basically. So that like one, two name is LISA. So LISA
is being developed to basically have the
arm length problem solved. And the observatory
will be set up in space using satellites. And you have
various observatories in and around the world. So KAgRA
is one of the observatories in JApaN. It is underground,
and underground observatories have different advantages and disadvantages.
And we have Virgo in Europe. We have geo 600 in
Germany. So 600 is, this specific observatory is
sort of an experimental observatory. The arm lengths over here for
the detectors is only 600 meters. And the
one coming up right now in India, in the state of Maharashtra,
is the Indigo project that recently the government of India
has signed up for, and the budgets have been released.
So these are the overall pictures of how the
detectors or the gravitational wave detectors look like.
So, now moving forward with the talk, so how
these detectors work, actually. So the lasers
that I was talking about. So there is a source of laser light. And if
I play the video again. So the video basically says that there's
a beam splitter, which splits the light, and it
gets reflected by these mirrors at the end.
And these mirrors basically sends the light again to the beam splitter. And the beam
splitter basically domains the light and to a
detector. So the vibrations that you see,
the mirrors that you see are moving. So these mirrors are moving
because of the phenomenon happening below. So somewhere
far in the galaxy,
there can be two black holes or two
massive celestial bodies or any binary black hole merger
or a neutron star neutron star merger or a neutron
black hole merger happening. So once these
mergers, mergers start, so these massive bodies,
they start to revolve around each other. And as
you can see, what happens is they start to form
ripples in the spacetime fabric. And they walk the
spacetime fabric around each other so much that they basically
sort of create was in and around the spacetime. And if
you see, once they merge,
the merger happens. They become
a single body, a single massive body,
and the ripples basically
die out. And these ripples are the ripples that
cross the entire universe.
And it basically reaches the observatories. And once they
reach the observatories, they move these mirrors
back and forth. And these mirrors, once they are moved
back and forth, they basically change the
intensity of light that is falling upon these detectors
here. And the intensity variation that we get at
these detectors are being converted into
how much the earth was basically warped
around. So, if in very crude words,
I have to say. So these gravitational waves that are being sent
because of these black hole mergers that are happening,
they cross us almost every time.
And this is not just true with the black holes,
any body, when it moves. So even if I
am moving my hand, it is creating gravitational wave ripples in
the spacetime fabric. But because my hand
or my body is not massive enough to warp the spacetime fabric that
much. So these ripples are very feeble.
And the black hole mergers,
the ripples that it sends. So once these ripples
basically move across the whole
complete earth or the complete spacetime fabric which contains the
earth and other planets and galaxies. So it basically stretches
and compresses the whole space and
whole space, meaning the earth and people,
me, you, everybody. So once these was
crosses, they basically are. We are
stretched and compressed. And these
stretching and compression basically happen in the order of
ten to the power -34 to ten to the power -35 meters.
It is very small, so we are not able to detect them.
And because the differences are very small,
this small. So these massive detectors are used to
detect the small slightest of the variation in the intensity of
the laser light that is there. And then we basically
get to know what was like. Were there
any gravitational wave being crossing,
crossing the earth? And the reason you ask
why so many detectors in and around the globe is because
these detectors are so sensitive, so much sensitive that even if there is
a car crossing across, like near any detector
or there is someone walking around the detectors,
they detect those noises also. And they
are also trapped in the output
noise. So to separate
all the noise sources, there are
seismic noises, there are quantum noises. There are
various types of noises that can cause
certain kinds of waves. So one type
of signal will be common across all these detectors that you see
here. And that will be the gravitational wave that has crossed. And all
these detectors and various other detectors across the globe are being
developed because we want to just be confirmed that,
okay, there was a gravitational wave that has crossed.
Moving on with the topic. So this was just a very brief introduction
about what gravitational wave detectors are, how they work,
and what gravitational waves are in general. So now
moving to the specific topics. So there's a type of noise.
The types of noise that I was talking to you about were
these different kinds of noises. The seismic noises,
gravity gradient noises, suspension noises, coating brownian noises,
quantum noises, computing thermodynamics. So all these noises are there,
like the mirrors are suspended. So they cause
certain types of noises. The coating on the mirrors, they cause a
certain type of noise in the output. These mirrors are hefty. The mirrors
are two to three story building high, and they
weigh in tons and they
cause a noise. The lasers are so much powerful that once
the lasers are like, they hit the mirrors.
So even though the mirrors are super cool, they still heat
up so much that the mirrors may expand or contract.
And that can basically add
up to the noises, the gases that are there
around the tube. These curvature of earth
also might vary the seismic
variations, the seismic activity that is there in these earth
that is happening. So all these things can actually
add up to various types of noises. And the
picture that you are seeing here is something called as advanced lego.
So it is very simplistic plot diagram
of how insides of those detectors look.
So there is a laser, it is being split into different modes. There is a
mode cleaning happening. And the lasers are basically
bouncing back to and forth in the four kilometer arm length.
And there is a
multiplication happening of the detectors in the 615
kilowatts. And finally, the output is mapped
here. So the major contribution that happens
is one happening by the
quantum short noise. So if you see these graph here of the noise,
this purple line that you see is basically the quantum
shot noise. And these noises come into
picture because we are dealing with lasers. And lasers are basically
quantum particles which can behave in various ways.
So now if we move on with explanation.
So these noises are significant when the gravitational wave
detections are being made, because it happens due to quantum vacuum
fluctuations and quantum vacuum fluctuations.
And these topics are very hefty topics and
very advanced topics. So it can be covered in some other
talk way. So just now giving you a brief introduction and
keeping it open for you to explore is the quantum wave fluctuations, which you
can explore. And to overcome these quantum wave vacuum fluctuations,
the squeeze state of lights are used to reduce these short noises. And in general
increasing the signal to noise ratio. It helps in
detecting the faint gravitational waves, wave signatures and
various machine learning problem statement. Machine learning algorithms are
being used to basically identify the specific
gravitational waves that we want and remove
all these kind of noises that is already there.
So, talking about now we
have talked about quantum. Now we have talked about gravitational waves or
astrophysics in general and what are the methods
that we can implement or propose so
that we can leverage the use of quantum computers in the area of
astrophysics. So, talking about
the areas where this can come, so we can have
something like a quantum signal preprocessing. Then there is a measurement
happening, and then there is a quantum signal post processing happening.
Okay, so this sort of can be a setup of
the quantum signal preprocessing. We have the detection
happening and the post processing can be done. So we're
talking more about that. So the signal preprocessing is basically
the quantum information that is hidden in the potential gravitational
wave. So this method is basically tries to perform a
preprocessing step on the signal before it is measured. So the measurement
step that we talked about that. So if I just quickly show
these slide so the measurement is happening over here,
the output mode clean, there is an output mode cleaner, and there is a
measurement happening. So the measurement that is happening
here, before that, we can have a quantum preprocessing
happening, so that it basically takes
out the important quantum information that we have.
And it might provide a wider spectrum of data collection
by the opportunities, by using the Hilbert spaces that is
available. So, this sort of experiment
is actually going on, and the research is going on in the GEo
600 observatory in Germany, and they
are focusing more on how to extract the quantum information which is
hidden in the gravitational waves, and give more information
about the granularity of what the quantum information actually
provides us to. So, moving on to the
next step, which is the quantum signal post processing.
So, the present signal post processing that we
have is classical, and a quantum equivalent
of the selina post processing steps could be developed.
Like there are many post processing
happening, which include machine learning algorithms. So, instead of the machine learning algorithms,
we can use more accurate and more efficient quantum machine learning algorithms.
And these quantum machine learning algorithms at larger
scale, with hefty data, they are proven to be more
accurate and provide more insights about how and
what the things are, and give better predictions, and separate out things better.
And quantum machine learning is a topic which one
of my colleagues is talking about
at this conference. And it is a very niche area
where things can develop a lot.
And the advantages that quantum machine learning can provide
us can be used as one of the steps of the quantum signal post processing.
And the post processing, basically may increase the processing speed,
and thus increase the accuracy of the signal isolation. So,
increasing the processing speed and basically will
help in increasing the signal isolation,
and the signal basically that we are wanting. So if
there is a binary black hole merger, the signals that we get across
the different detectors,
we can isolate it better and get more
accuracy along with it. And the errors can
also be isolated more efficiently. And the errors that we are
getting along with the
gravitational waves, basically can be isolated more
by the quantum signal post processing that can happen.
So we move on further with the slide.
So this is basically the picture that you see is basically
a frequency dependent squeezing for advanced Lego.
And this is basically a setup that is
being tested out at these Geo 600,
by the GeO 600 team, along with the advanced lIgo. And it
is basically a 16 meters setup. And this
is the basic foundation of the idea. And the 16 m experiment
that you see up bottom right
is basically what I was trying to talk about.
Like, we can have certain post processing
steps, either in the form of optical setups
or software setups, which can help in
isolating the setup.
And we can think it as a modular
setup, like say if there is a gravitational
wave that is coming and we isolate
it. And so we can make the setup more modular
and we can have different types of optical setups,
specifically targeting a particular type of quantum algorithm
or quantum, or a quantum optic setup that we are looking into.
So this is an area where we can dive deep
into and come up with setups which can help
in, ah, not only improving
the quantum in the
gravitational wave detection step, but also developing
on these areas will basically help us move closer
to the overall goal that we have in
the development of an experimental setup for quantum
gravity. So the researches that
the team at the GEO 600 is doing may
lead into the development of an experimental setup
to prove the quantum
gravity and the existence of gravitons. And maybe these
developments will lead to advantages in various
fields also. So, moving on with the
topic. So the conclusions that we can drive out of
the talk will be so these methods
and researchers can help us explore the unknown
area of the quantum gravity. And they have potential
to hypothesize a method to experimentally prove the existence of gravitons.
And the explorations may help in the development in the field of gravitational wave detection,
which will help the ever growing community of quantum computing enthusiasts.
Talking in general, the things that we
have developed in various areas previously,
like in these things that the cutting
edge engineering feats that we developed
in the CERN colliders and
in the LIgo gravitational wave detectors. So a lot of
things are being used in various places in and around
world in various medical applications specifically.
So these things that we
develop while researching in this field will
help improve the growing community of quantum enthusiasts. And also
maybe in future, if we develop more
on this topic, we'll be able to see how
we can hypothesize, can experimental
setup to prove the existence of gravitons and
research more on the area of quantum gravity. And with
that being said, I would like to conclude
the presentation, the talk, and thank
each and every member of the panel and the organizing team
for giving me the chance to present this talk in front
of the audience of the conference and
hope to see you again. And a very much thank you to all.