Chester Santos, the international man of Memory here.
My goal is to make this a very entertaining
and educational webinar.
Memory is a fundamental part of learning
and the acquisition of knowledge. So improving your
memory skills is going to have a positive impact on
multiple areas of your life. In case you
might not be too familiar with myself and my background,
a two minute short video is going to play with some of my presentation
clips, media clips, and also my theme song.
Check it out. And then I'll be back with the webinar that
works. We just did some mental athletic training with Chester
Santos, who has the best memory in the United States, with ease.
Joining us right now is memory expert and winner of the 2008 USA national
Memory Championship, Chester Santos. If you have trouble remembering
names, faces, where you put your coffee task, well, if you do Chester Santos,
he can help. He's a 2008 national memory champion.
He is here to help us. Certainly knows he does. Chester Santos is the United
States memory champion. He captured the title this past weekend in
New York City. There he is accepting the prize. He's not. You can count or
see. He got the names of every conference.
You get it? Every sunny in a national. Who's the
twelveth district New Jersey conference? Rush Holton.
Okay. Rush holter
wrapped up. Ten of hearts, three to go. Two of
clubs. Yes. Jack of diamonds. You got it. And three
of diamonds. Unbelievable. That's incredible. First of all,
we have Carol, Rick,
Pedro, Jack, Andy.
We're dizzying ass every single time. He's got the power to
educate, the power to thrill and memorize,
all wrapped up in invitation for mine.
He's your man.
Some of his techniques stretch all the way back to the ancient Greeks, but what's
amazing is it's standing in front of you as a modern human being. I can
still feel those techniques reprogramming my brain to remember things better.
All right, we're back. You just saw my introductory video.
We're going to get started with the webinar. Now, I want you
to keep in mind that I might ask you to do some things
that can at certain times, seem a bit silly or unusual.
But please bear with me because I promise you that everything
that I ask you to do over the next hour or so,
it's really going to help you to dramatically improve your
ability to remember almost anything at all.
I'd like for you all to close your eyes at this
point. Close your eyes and just visualize
what I describe to you with your eyes closed.
I want for you to imagine yourself in your current residence.
You are in the living room area of your residence.
And you see there in the middle of your living room,
standing behind podiums, looking as if they're about to
engage in a debate. You see Donald Trump and Vladimir
Putin. Just see that in your mind. I know
it seems kind of out there unusual, but picture them
now actually debating in the middle of your living room.
Just see the debate unfold. It's becoming more and more heated
between the two politicians, Trump and Putin.
At one point, you see Donald Trump become visibly upset at
something that Putin says. So he reaches behind his podium to
pull out a pie. He takes it, throws it at Putin, hits him square
in the face. You can see the pie dripping off of
Putin's face. Picture that he's not happy about
it at all. So believe it or not, he now reaches behind his
podium to also pull out a pie, takes it, throws it at
Trump. Splat. You can see the pie dripping
off Trump's face. Now, what started
off as a debate, turns out,
has now turned into a full blown pie fight. The politicians
are continuously throwing pies at each other. Pie is splattering
all over the place. You can worry about who's going to clean up the
living room later. Just see this happening in
your mind to the best of your ability.
You are primarily experiencing at
this point, images running through your head, imagery.
I'd like you now to attempt to involve even more
senses as you experience this scenario happening.
Imagine that you can not only see it happening, you can hear it happening
as well. So you can hear the pie as it splatters
on the politicians. Imagine now
that you can smell the pie, stretch your imagination,
really imagine what that pie might
smell like. So at this point, you can see
the pie fight happening. You can hear it. You can
smell it as well. Let's take it a step further.
I want for you to imagine that you walk up to one of the politicians,
you take some of the pie off of their face, feel it in
your hands, maybe it feels sort of sticky. Go ahead
now even put some of the pie in your mouth.
Go ahead and taste that pie.
Hopefully it's tasting pretty good to you there. Although a lot of people
tell me that it tastes like politician at this point.
All right, go ahead and open up your eyes.
Hopefully you enjoyed that exercise. A lot of people
find it to be a fun exercise. Usually pretty easy
for most people to complete that. But what in the world does
that have to do with improving your ability to
remember things? In fact, it has a lot to do with it. If you
were able to complete that simple exercise,
then you have the ability to remember anything at
all that you would ever want to remember quickly,
easily, and also with tremendous accuracy.
Here are some reasons why. Reason number one, I had you there.
Exercise your visualization ability,
and your visual memory is incredibly powerful.
An example that I like to cite in my presentations
around the world is a situation that we can all relate to.
We might see someone that we could have met
years ago. We may have met that person years in the past.
Oftentimes right away, as soon as we see their face,
we remember their face. We know that we've met them somewhere before,
but we can't seem to remember their name.
Right. Pretty common experience. Something else
that we can relate to. Let's say you go to a party. You go to
a party, you're meeting a lot of new people.
Two weeks after that party is over, you're talking with
one of your friends that was at the party with you,
and your friend describes someone to you that you had both
met. Your friend says, hey, do you remember that attorney that we
met at the party a couple of weeks ago? He's also a member
of the tennis club. As your friend is going
through the description of the person from the party, a lot of times
you can picture who they're describing in your mind.
You might even be able to remember what that person was wearing
that night when you met them. But a lot of times, you can't seem
to remember the name, and it's very frustrating.
A third and final example related to this.
How many times have you been describing to a friend or
family member an actor from a tv show or movie?
As you're going through this description, crystal clear in your mind,
you can picture the actor that you're describing. Your friend
or family member can also picture who you're describing, but neither one of
you can come up with the name at that moment, and it's really frustrating
to both of you. Those three examples that I just
went over all illustrate pretty well that when it comes to
dealing with people, we tend to be pretty good
at remembering faces, but we are not
nearly as good at remembering names. When you think
about it, this makes a lot of sense, because when we are interacting with people
in various ways, we always see the face,
right? We see their face. The face is recorded into our visual
memory, but at no point do we see their name. The name is
something much more abstract to your brain.
So one way that you can get better at remembering names is
to turn the name somehow into a visual,
something that you can picture in your mind.
For instance, Mike might become a microphone
for the name Alice. Sometimes I picture a white rabbit
because that reminds me of Alice in Wonderland.
That's how I open presentations around the world. I've given
presentations in more than 30 different countries at this point. A lot of times I'll
open with naming hundreds of people in the audience
after just hearing each name one time.
It's because I'm turning those names into powerful visuals.
I'm going to get into remembering names in much more detail
toward the end of this webinar, so look
out for that. But for now, what I want for you to note is
the power of your visual memory. When you can take information
that you want to remember and turn it into something that you can picture
in your mind, it's going to make that information so much easier
to remember it later on when you need it.
The second principle to take away from the simple
exercise with Trump and Putin is that after
I had you visualize, I then had you start to get
more and more senses involved from there. As you activate
more and more senses in the encoding process, when trying
to get information into your memory, what's happening is you are activating
more and more areas of your brain, and you are building more and more connections
in your mind to the information, making it
easier to retrieve it later. So I starred in an episode
of PBS's Nova Science. The episode
that I starred in was entitled how smart
can we get? Or it might be easier to just Google Chester Santos,
that's me, and PBS. And you'll probably find
the clip. Anyone can watch the entire episode for free
on the PBS website. Maybe take a look at it at some point.
If you do, you'll see me on the show performing what at first
seemed like pretty crazy memory feats. And then they had me train David
Pogue, who was the host of the show. You might also know him from the
New York Times and CBS News. He's a correspondent for the technology industry.
I trained him on the show, and after just a little bit
of training, he was then able to perform some pretty cool memory
feats. After that, they had some neuroscientists,
brain scientists, come on the show and explain,
okay, how in the world did Chester pull that off?
How did David Pogue do it? With just a little bit of training, and these
brain scientists confirmed that it's because with these memory techniques
that I've mastered over the years and that you're going to learn
about during the short webinar today, what's happening is we're recruiting extra
areas of the brain, areas of the brain that most people worlds
never involve when trying to commit things to memory. With these
techniques, we're activating more and more areas of the brain to help us,
so it becomes so much easier to remember things. Part of
this is learning to utilize additional senses.
The more senses you involve, again, the more of the brain is
activated, the easier it is to remember.
Keep that in mind. Third and final principle is
that in addition to seeing all of this and experiencing
it with additional senses, I made the entire scenario
with Trump and Putin very strange, right? Unusual.
You would never expect to see that happening in the middle
of your living room. I had you do that because I'd like for you to
learn to take advantage of the psychological aspect
to human memory that is all of us. With putting forth little to
no effort, we tend to remember things that catch us by surprise,
that are strange, extraordinary in some way, right?
If this were to actually happen right now
at this moment, wherever you are watching this
webinar, if an elephant crashed into
the room right now at this moment and started to spray water all
over you with its trunk, if that actually happened at this moment,
you would probably remember that for the rest of your
life and always tell that story.
It might be stuck there forever without you even putting forth any
effort to commit that to memory. To this day,
it still isn't fully understood how that works in the
brain. How sometimes in one instant, something will go
straight into long term memory and stay there forever.
Whereas other times, when we have really important
things that we need to get into long term memory, we have a lot of
difficulty doing it. We can spend weeks, months,
trying to get things in the long term memory. Although this
isn't fully understood, we do realize that
there is this psychological aspect to human memory.
Realizing that we can harness that power and apply
it to things that would be very useful for
us to remember names and faces, to get more out of
business networking, and to build better relationships with people
in general. Presentations,
important business related facts and figures,
foreign language, vocabulary, exam material,
and so on. There are so many practical applications for
an improved ability to remember things. When you combine the three
principles that we just went over, visualization,
utilizing additional senses from there, and you
also use your creativity and imagination to make
what you are seeing and experiencing crazy, unusual,
extraordinary. When you put that together right away,
it becomes easier to remember just about anything
at all. We're going to put this into practice now, all right? Without training
anything down, without using any sort of electronic
device to help you, you'll be using nothing but your brain and memory.
Here. I know people aren't used to doing this nowadays. I'm going to have
you attempt to commit to memory the following random list of
words. It's going to be monkey,
iron, rope,
kite, house, paper,
shoe, worm,
envelope, pencil,
river, rock, tree,
cheese, and dollar. All right?
Now, when I recite that list of words to live audiences,
I get people in the audience looking at me as if, come on, man,
there's no way I'm going to be able to remember that. Not unless
you give me a lot of time to do it. But in fact, all of
you watching this webinar, you're all going to have it committed to
memory perfectly, forwards and backwards.
With just about three minutes of study time and with no further
review necessary. Even weeks from now, you will skills know
those words forwards and backwards. They will be locked into
your memory. How you're going to pull this off. Just listen to
what I described to you. See and experience it happening in your mind,
just as you did in the opening exercise with Trump
and Putin. Same approach. The whole key to this,
and probably one of the most important things to get out of the short
webinar today, is to hopefully shift your approach just a
little bit when it comes to any sort of memory task.
Remembering names, giving a presentation, whatever it might be,
rather than coming at it, as we usually do, as a
difficult and boring exercise in memory.
Try to come at it more as just a fun opportunity to use
your creativity and your imagination. That small shift
in your approach will make a huge difference in your ability
to remember things you saw in the intro video, the two minute video
with some of my tv clips. You saw one of my CNN clips there.
I had to memorize during the commercial break, all right? Only had about two
minutes to do it. Then they came back live on the air.
I had to recite that, all of those cards from memory, if you
pay attention, you'll see that while I'm memorizing the cards,
I'm smiling, I'm giggling. I think they thought
that I was a little bit crazy or nutty when I was on that show.
But really, that's the key. If you all are smiling and
giggling while you're going through this exercise, it's a good
sign that you're going to remember all the words. So just have fun with
it. It'll be very easy. Let's do it.
Now, visualize what I described to you. The first word was monkey.
So I want for you to just see a monkey in your mind,
all right? This monkey is dancing around, making monkey
noises. Whatever a monkey would sound like,
I'm working on my monkey impression. Okay, the point here is
to see and hear the monkey. The monkey now
picks up a gigantic iron, because that was
the next word. So just see this like a movie or cartoon
playing in your head. However you can best visualize it. You've got a monkey
dancing around with a giant iron. At this point,
the iron starts to fall. But a rope attaches
itself to the iron. Maybe even feel the
rope. Maybe it feels sort of rough. Really interact with it.
You look up the rope, and you see that the other end of the rope
is attached to a kite. That kite is flying around in the
air. Maybe you reach up and try and touch it. It might just be
right just out of your reach. That kite. The kite now
crashes into the side of a house. Really see it
smash into that house. The house, you notice is completely
covered in paper. For some reason, it's covered in paper.
Picture that. Out of nowhere, a shoe appears,
and it starts to walk all over the paper. Maybe it's messing up
the paper as it's walking on it. That shoe. The shoe
skills pretty badly. So you decide to investigate
and see why. You look inside of the shoe and you find
a little worm crawling around. See that smelly worm crawling
inside the shoe? Worm was the next word. The worm now jumps
out of the shoe and into an envelope.
Maybe it's going to mail itself or something. I don't know.
Envelope was the next word. A pencil
appears out of thin air. It starts to write all over the envelope.
Maybe it's addressing it. The pencil. The pencil
now jumps into a river. And there is a
huge splash when that little pencil hits
the river. River was next. The river, you see is crashing up against a giant
rock. All right, really see it crashing into that rock.
The rock flies out of the river and into a tree.
Picture that tree. This tree is growing cheese.
You probably haven't seen a tree like that before. This tree
is growing cheese. Out of each piece of cheese shoots
a dollar. The last word was dollar.
I'm going to go through this again very quickly, and your
job at this point is to simply replay through this
little story that you've created in your mind. So we started off with
the monkey. What was the monkey dancing around with? It was
dancing around with an iron. What attached itself to the
iron? It was a rope. The other end of the rope was attached to what?
It was a kite. What did the kite crash into?
It was a house. What was the house covered
in? It was covered in paper. What walked on it.
It was a shoe. What was changing in the
shoe? It was a worm. The worm jumped
into what? It was an envelope,
right? What wrote on the envelope? It was a pencil.
The pencil then jumped into what? It was a river.
The river was crashing up against the rock.
That flew into what? It was a tree.
What was it growing?
Cheese. And what shot out?
A dollar. Right? The last word was dollar.
Now, you should be able to recall pretty easily
the entire random list of words by simply
going through that story in your mind. And each
major object that you encounter in the story will give you the
next word if you'd like. At some point,
you can just pause the webinar and see if you can recite
those words forwards and then maybe even attempt to
recite them backwards. If you do that, I'm pretty sure
you're going to get close to 100% correct.
This technique is called the story method.
It is just one of many techniques that memory champions
like myself use to pull off what at first seemed like
extraordinary feats of memory. But really, it's just about the right
techniques, a little bit of training and practice. My brain is not different from
anyone else's. I've just learned powerful
techniques and gone through a little bit of training.
You can do this as well. And again,
this will give you an advantage in just about
any career. This is going to be very useful in various ways
in your personal life and also for the kids
that you have in school. This will cut their study time.
It will improve their retention of information. This provides
them with a much more fun and interesting framework to
use when they have to commit things to memory for school. If you
will stick to this type of training with the story method and
other similar types of techniques, you will notice many
benefits over time. Benefit number one, your memory
is going to improve over time in general, even independent
of using the techniques. But that's only if, after the webinar
today, you force yourself to commit more and more things
to memory and recall them.
Your memory will then improve because your brain is very trainable.
The more you force your brain to perform a particular function over
and over again, the more it signals to your brain that that's something important
that you need to be able to do. So your brain finds a
way to make itself better at
doing it. There was a segment on a science program about a guy who was
in a very unfortunate accident, and a pole
went through a certain area of his brain, and he completely lost the ability to
perform certain functions. What happened, though, is with rehabilitation
and training, the brain rewired
itself, other areas of his brain took over. So areas
of the brain that most people would have nothing to do with
performing those functions, they took over, and he regained the
ability to perform not all, but many of those functions
due to rewiring of his brain.
With training, your brain's incredibly trainable.
The opposite is, however, true. If you
never have your brain perform a particular function,
if you're always writing everything down, if you're always entering
things into electronic devices, what you're saying to your brain
is, you know what, at this point in my life, it's not
important for me to be able to remember things anymore. So it
makes sense that you are going to start to lose that ability
over time. We are living in an age of
perhaps dangerous digital dependency.
People are losing not only their memory ability,
but also other mental functions due to becoming too
dependent on electronic devices.
An example I'll give you. We all used to be able to remember
the phone numbers of so many friends and family members, right?
We could easily dial those from memory. I remember when I was
growing up, my parents would also give me some emergency numbers that they
thought were important for me to know. We could all do that.
But nowadays, you give somebody even one phone
number and they feel paralyzed, they can't do it.
It's getting so bad that there are people out there today that don't
even know their own phone number.
It's a really good example of the use it or lose it principle
as it applies to memory. Another quick example, navigation.
You have people. I'll give Uber and Lyft drivers as
an example. In some cases, they may have been driving in a
city for three, four plus years. But if
something is wrong with the app at that time, if there's
something wrong with the network connection, a lot of
times they can't take you to even very commonly known
landmarks in a city. They will need to pull over,
restart their phone, until hopefully the issue with the app
resolves or the network connection comes back.
Because for those three, four plus years,
they have been 100% dependent on
the gps. They've completely shut off their
brains, so haven't even learned a few simple
streets. The same is happening with taxi drivers. Taxi drivers used
to be world famous for their memory ability. I know New York City
and London taxi drivers. At one point,
universities were even doing research on their brains
because they had just an extraordinary ability to remember
even thousands of streets. But nowadays, I've been in a taxi in
San Francisco, and it just isn't the same anymore due to
dependency on gps. So just be a little bit
aware that we want to be a
bit careful with too much digital dependency.
Try to use your brain, definitely try to use your
memory when you can. I get people in my seminars
all the time that tell me, hey, you know, when I was back in school,
Chester, I was pretty good at remembering things,
but now I'm having really a lot of difficulty remembering
things on the job. They're sending us to new trainings and I don't have that
ability to commit all of this information to memory like I did
back in my schooling years. When you think about it, this makes
sense because then you were using your memory all the time,
right? So when we are in preschool,
elementary school, junior high, high school,
grad school, for some people through that entire block of years,
you're challenged to learn tons of information from a wide
variety of areas. You're tested on your recall of the information,
for quizzes, exams, to write papers. When you first start a
new job, when you do the on the job,
onboarding, right. The onboard training. You have to learn a lot
of new things in order to perform your job functions properly.
But then what happens to a lot of us is we enter this 30,
40 plus year period where things start to become a routine.
We're doing the same types of things day in and day out.
We're not really challenged to use our memory as much on a regular
basis. So when we are suddenly presented with something
new to learn, we feel like our memory capabilities
have been diminished. The positive aspect
of this is if you make it a point to actually exercise your
memory, exercise your brain in general as well,
you can keep your memory strong and really in fact
improve it at any age. Now, some people don't believe
me when I tell them this. A lot of people are stuck on this idea
that someone older in age is going to have a memory worse
than someone younger in age. And that's just the way things are. So I like
to talk about two things. One, I represented the United States
in the World Memory Championship. It was held in the
Middle east when I represented the United States. There was a guy
there from Malaysia in his late sixty s, so more than
thirty years older than me. He destroyed me in this competition.
Okay? He kicked my butt really badly. In the world memory championship.
He actually memorized the entire dictionary, advanced Learners
edition in English and Chinese. He did
a demonstration for people in the audience and for people
from the media that were there watching. They would call out any page number in
the dictionary and give a row column combination. Within a
few seconds, he could tell you the word there and its definition
from memory. He could even do the reverse. If you just called out a random
word like chair, he would say, okay, chair, I think that's on
page 737, row four. And he was
right every single time. He's known as the walking
dictionary. Dr. Yipswei Choi from Malaysia.
These are the types of guys that you get at the world memory championship.
It's pretty intense over there, but it goes to show he was in his late
sixty s. So even later in your years you can have
an extraordinary memory ability. But he is constantly
training his memory with these types of techniques that
we're talking about on today's webinar.
Second example, I've been teaching a one day memory training workshop
in San Francisco for more than twelve years,
and now I have an online equivalent memory school. But I've gotten
people in the San Francisco seminar that from
all over the world and all different age ranges I
have seen in that workshop, people in their sixty s
and seventy s completely outperform working professionals in
their twenty s and thirty s in terms of the memory
tasks in the workshop. And when I talk to those people, it turns
out that they not only sign up for things like memory workshops,
they take language classes. They're always keeping very mentally
active, attending art functions,
museum events, they're really exercising,
challenging their brain at all times. And I think that
is they're really dedicated to lifelong learning. And I
really think that is at least part of the reason how they're staying so razor
sharp even later in their years. So you can improve
your memory, remain razor sharp at any age. If you stick
to the type of training we're going to be talking about today, you will keep
your memory strong, improve it at any age. Also, visualization ability
will improve. You'll create these images in your mind more quickly.
You'll be able to see the imagery more clearly. And visualization
ability has been linked in many studies to more than memory.
It's been linked to overall intelligence. In fact,
if you can take complex information and turn
it into a simple series of images that you can visualize,
see in your mind, it helps to improve your understanding as well.
So visualization, another important thing that you can
develop with this type of training. This is also very good
exercise in creativity and imagination,
coming up with these creative and imaginative stories. In addition,
this is really good exercise for your brain in general.
And everyone is recommending nowadays a brain exercise
program in addition to a physical exercise program.
With the current research, if you're destined to develop Alzheimer's
or another form of dementia. Unfortunately, there is
no doctor, no researcher that can tell you how to prevent
that from happening. But what they do believe is that by engaging
in rigorous brain exercise, you can build up what they're
calling cognitive reserve. If you were to look that up right now,
google it, or otherwise look it up, cognitive reserve is the
terminology that you'll find used in the research. This basically
means building up some extra brain muscle, and they think that
it might help to make you more resistant to some
forms of dementia if you do, unfortunately develop
it down the line. One of the best ways to develop cognitive reserve
research supports learning foreign languages can
really build up some extra brain muscle, extra brain connections.
Of course, learning languages is going to be easier for you
if you master memory skills techniques.
Now, we've covered so far the story method
with random words. I want to make it clear
before we move on to names, which is coming
up, I want to make it clear first that this won't apply to just
random words. This can apply to even very complex
types of information as well. So not just monkey,
iron, rope. I was a speaker at Harvard University.
You can find on my website a testimonial from the Harvard
Graduate Council. So I gave a seminar for
and then one large seminar for hundreds of students over at
Harvard, and then smaller, more in depth training after that.
I had Harvard medical students, law students, business students
in the programs. Even very complex types of information
can be tackled. It's about building mental note cards or
mental cue cards that remind you of something more complex.
You'll have a better idea. As we go through one more short exercise,
I want for you to just visualize what I described to you. See and
experience it happening in your mind as best you can. This will take a minute
or two, really easy. I want for you to visualize some giant
machines. Just see that, picture it. Some giant machines.
These giant machines are smashing up a huge pile of gold
and silver, right? Smashing up a huge pile of gold and
silver. Those machines, out of the gold
and silver vehicles rise up. See these
vehicles? Whatever that looks like to you. And shooting
out of the windows of the vehicles, a bunch of medicine.
Maybe you see pill bottles or syringes or something. Medicine is
shooting out of the windows and exploding out of the
medicine. Oil, maybe black petroleum
oil would be easiest to visualize. Oil explodes out of the
medicine. That was it. This one really is very
quick and easy. I'm going to run through the imagery again, replay through
it in your mind. We had these giant machines were smashing up what they
were smashing up gold and silver. What rose
up vehicles. What shot out of the windows
of the vehicles? It was medicine.
What exploded out of the medicine? It was oil.
What you have just done there, I'm sure you can
recite those items back. You've just memorized the
top five exports of the UK.
So if you were to look up some of the UK's top exports,
you'll find listed machinery,
precious metals,
vehicles,
pharmaceuticals and oil.
So you see there how the images don't need to perfectly
match what you're trying to remember. Those simple
images serve as note cards, mental note cards,
to remind you of something a little bit broader when
you are meeting with clients,
potential clients, or it's a presentation
in front of colleagues, when you have just 510
15 key things that you're able to recite,
demonstrate that. You know that, right? You're demonstrating your expertise,
you're showing that you actually know your stuff. You are so much more impressive.
You are perceived to be more of an expert in your particular
field. People start to have more confidence in you and
your ability when you have a razor sharp memory.
And just a little bit of memory skills training will go
a long way. We talked about it earlier, people are very digitally
dependent. In today's business environment,
people can't remember even a small amount of information. So a little bit
in terms of memory skills training will go a long way towards
setting you apart, making you more impressive and you will be
more memorable in the business world.
Of course, as I mentioned earlier, this is
also huge for kids that you have in
school. This is going to cut study time, improve retention.
Kids find this to be a much more interesting and
fun methodology to use to commit things to memory,
as I mentioned earlier. Let's move on now to one of my
more popular topics. No matter what
type of group I might be talking to around the world,
it's always going to be names. Because names we know is
remembering names is important in just about any career. It's important
in everyone's personal life. I like to
quote the book how to win friends and influence
people. You may have heard of it to this day, it's still one of the
most popular business and personal success books ever written.
In that book, it was written that the sweetest sound to a person in
any language is the sound of their own name,
and also that everyone's favorite subject is themselves.
So in fact, remembering people's names and things about them
helps you to build better business and personal relationships. If you meet
someone at an event and the next time you see them, you can say hey,
John, how are you? How's your wife Nancy? How was your last round of golf?
Automatically what they're feeling is, wow,
they must be pretty important to you if you can remember those things.
About the most important is their name. And then in turn they
become much more interested in getting to know you and what
you're about better. This is really very strengthening
to relationships. Now, on the opposite side,
if you are not remembering people's names, or maybe even worse,
you're calling people by the wrong name, this can be very
detrimental to both business and
personal relationships. I had a guy come up to me
after one of my presentations and he told me he was in sales and
he actually ended up getting fired because he attended
an annual or semiannual conference
and he had accidentally the whole day been calling the
vice president of sales by the wrong name. I think he called him by
a similar name, like it was close to the correct name,
but not exactly right. And the
vice president ended up training to a supervisor and said, look, in a sales
career, this is just not acceptable in
our field. We really need to be good with names. And the guy got fired.
That's maybe, perhaps an extreme example, but I think we all know
that people that are very good with
names are more popular, more likable.
Politicians are clear on this fact. By the way, a lot of politicians go through
memory skills training. They really want to make it a point to get good at
names. And I think we all realize that it can be detrimental to
relationships when you are not remembering names or calling people by
the wrong name. So let me give you some steps that you can put into
practice right away. All right, step number one, to help
you out with names from this day forward, whenever you are introduced
to someone, make it a point to immediately repeat the name and shake their
hand if you can. Or maybe if we're concerned
about germs, you can do that elbow bump with a
pandemic that we have going on recently,
but definitely at least repeat the name. Nice to meet you, John, or pleased
to meet you, John. It might seem pretty obvious there,
but a lot of times when someone is telling us their name, introducing themselves,
our mind is all over the place. We're thinking about all sorts of other things.
We don't even pay attention to the name for even 1 second.
So that first step forces us to pay attention
for at least a second. That's the only way we could repeat
the name right back to the person. Start doing that today.
Eventually it's going to become a habit and second nature to you.
Step number two, early on in your interaction with
the person, ask them a simple question using their name.
So, John, how do you know Chester or John? How long have you been
involved with this organization? Just one question
early on will reinforce the name in your mind.
Prevent it from just going in one ear and out the other. I want to
clarify. I don't mean use the name over and over again
in the conversation to where it starts to seem a little weird. Just use it
once early on. That will be enough to reinforce it. Step number three,
take a few seconds or less to think of a connection between
the name, the person's name, and anything at all that you already know. So John
might make you think of John Lennon. It could be a famous person
like that, or it could be a character from a tv show or movie that
you like. It could be something as simple as you have a friend
or family member that has that same name. Thinking of a
connection between the name and literally anything at
all that you already know is really going to help that name to stick
better in your long term memory. Step number four. Whenever you leave
the party, the meeting, whatever type of function it might be, make it a point
to try to say goodbye to people actually using their
name. That's really going to go a long way toward helping you
to remember more of those names long
term. Those four steps are
going to help you out right away. You will notice an immediate improvement
if you combine them with the visual based technique
that I very briefly hit on earlier. There is no doubt in
my mind that you will be better than you ever have before
remembering names. You might not be 100%. Even I'm not
100%. But if you can remember 80 plus percent of
the people that you're meeting, this is going to pay off big time in your
career. This is going to help you out in your personal life as well.
You're going to find just that this helps you to be more likable
to people. This definitely strengthens relationships.
The visual again that I had mentioned was like a microphone.
You might picture for the name Mike.
There's another step to that. When you come up with the visual
for the name, also connect it to something about the person's
look. So if you're meeting this new person named Mike,
ask yourself what's unique about the look. Maybe to you he's got cool
looking hair. If that's the case, you might imagine the
microphone getting tangled up in his hair. Because how
this works is the next time you see the person, all you have to
do is ask yourself what was noticeable to
me about their look. You're very likely to notice what was
unique to you before. The image that you then stored
there will immediately come back to you. You'll see the mic, the microphone
that will remind you that the name was Mike. It might seem a little strange,
but it's very powerful and effective. Anyone can get
good at doing this with a little bit of training and practice.
If you want some more training and practice with that and to
learn more techniques, check out my online memory
school. So in my online memory school, it's memoryschool.
Net is the URL. I would picture a gigantic
maybe fishing net to remember that it's net is the ending of the URL.
I would simulate introducing you to many people
over and over and teach you a wide variety of visual based techniques
that I wasn't able to cover. On today's webinar. You'll really develop
that skill in remembering names. I'm going to teach you how to remember presentations
without notes or minimize the amount of notes. I'm going to teach you how to
remember foreign language vocabulary presentations,
exam material for the kids in school, or training material for
professionals. More techniques to improve your memory in general.
We're going to tackle remembering information with numbers, facts that
contain figures, formulas, and so forth and so on.
That is only the core training. Then there's an
advanced training program. There's ongoing training every
single month. New videos are uploaded every month so that you
will continue developing your memory skills
through memoryschool. Net.
There's a small enrollment fee of $200,
and then you can continue on as long as you want. At only $40
per month, you can cancel at any time. I do want
to help people out that are watching this webinar that are very motivated
to get started, and the only thing that might be preventing you is the
upfront enrollment. So what I've done as a
special opportunity for people attending the Acupon
code dreams for 100 uses@memoryschool.net.
If you are one of the first 100 people to use code
dreams at the checkout screen, you will see the
enrollment fee go from $200 all the way down
to $0. Yes, I am completely training
the enrollment fee for the first 100 people to
use code dreams@memoryschool.net.
Chester Santos here with a quick summary
of the webinar for you. The three main principles
again to keep in mind for developing a powerful memory are
number one, turn whatever you want to remember into
visuals. Number two, try to involve
additional senses as you can from there.
Three, while you are seeing and experiencing all
of this in your mind. Try to make it unusual,
extraordinary in some way to take advantage of the psychological
aspect to human memory. A quick
review of the steps to keep in mind for remembering names. Step number
one when you are introduced to someone, repeat the name
immediately. Step number two, ask the person a
question using their name early on in the interaction.
Step number three, try to think of a connection between the
name and anything at all that you already know. Step number
four use the name one last time
before you leave, whatever type of event
you may be at and for further training
memoryschool net.