Welcome to this talk. Today I'll be talking to you about every
developer's or administrators or
operator's favorite tool, which is SSH,
the same Ssh that allows us to remotely and
securely connect to Linux securely connect
to Linux remote Linux servers
over an insecure network. Now, at the moment,
the most popular way of authenticating
SSH access is using SSH keys,
and that's what I'm here to talk about. This talk is to
show you or shine
more light on why Ssh keys aren't so good,
how they are doing harm to your infrastructure, and to convince you,
or to show youll how SSH certificates are superior
and why you should adopt them.
Now, SsH keys are actually not
bad. At least they are better than using passwords,
plain passwords. Theyre they are convenient and easy
to set up, and on their own they are actually quite secure
and cannot easily be hacked, thanks to the mathematics
of private keys and public keys, which I'll get into
later.
However,
traditional SSH keys usage has
private keys stored on digs, which means that
they can often be stolen using
malware or red
if a team member's device is compromised and
they have Ssh keys that aren't protected
with passphrase on their device.
Now, even when SSH keys stored on Dix are protected
with encryption passwords, they can also be stolen using
those passwords can also be hijacked
using brute force attacks because people
are susceptible to using insecure or easily guessed passwords.
And when SSH keys are stolen, bad things
happen. In recent
times we've had several
terrifying stories of companies that have suffered severe
data and monetary loss due to one
or two compromised SSH keys. We have companies like
Godaddy, Shapeshift, Capital one, and just
to name a few. Now, I won't go into the details of what
happened with these companies because these stories are available
online and you can read them on your own.
The aim of this talk is to spark discussion
and for us to examine really
the inner workings of how traditional SSH key authentication
works, and consider if there are better
ways to manage SSH access in such
a way that these incidents are less likely
to happen, and in such a way that SSH
access is safer.
The question is, is there a better solution?
And yes, there is, and that's SSH
certificates, and that's what I'll be talking about in this
talk to show you how SSH certificates
are superior to using SSH keys and
how you can start using them. But before I get
into all that, I'll just take a moment to introduce myself and my company
and then we'll proceed.
Yep, that's me. My name is Linda Ikechukwu
and I'm a developer advocate at Smallstep Labs.
Now, small step builds Small Step is a company
that builds toolkits that empowers developers,
operators, DevOps, engineers, it administrators
to be able to easily
and seamlessly adopt PKI and use
digital certificates, 509 certificates, SSH certificates
to encrypt and secure all
their infrastructure, from internal websites to kubernetes
to docker containers to databases
and what have you.
So now
in this talk, I'll be shining the light on how
SSh keys work and reasons why they are
bad for you. And then from that
we'll move to looking at what SSH certificates
are, how they work, and how they
are superior to traditional SSH keys authentication,
why they are great for you. And then after that,
we'll look at how you can start using SSH
certificates. What are some tools that are available out there that you can
start using to deploy SSH certificates into your
infrastructure? And then lastly,
I also shared some links that will help you learn or
set up SSH certificates in your own infrastructure.
So let's get right into it.
Why are SSh keys bad for you?
Now, before I proceed, I'd like to state one thing.
SSh keys are not so bad as I mentioned.
In fact, I would say that when
they are properly secured and managed, they could
be the simplest solution and probably the ideal
or preferred solution for a small of,
say, ten to 20 devices or users
or developers, or a small home lab.
Because right now, with the addition of the SSh
key types, a server can now enforce the use of hardware
bound private keys for SSH.
And this prevents sh
private keys from being stolen from devices.
And that's great.
But as we proceed in this talk and look at
the walkings of Ssh keys and how it works
underneath, youll discover that SSH keys
are just not scalable
or robust for larger organizations who have fifty
s or hundreds or thousands of servers
and users. Do youll hand out
dongles to every single person who needs Ssh access?
That's a bit of an overhead, yeah. So let's
take a look at how
ssh key authentication works.
Ssh key authentication works kudos to the magic
of asymmetric cryptography, as I mentioned, which is the
special correspondence between a public key and a private
key. So if
I send you a big random
data and you sign it with
your private key and send it back to me,
if I'm able to use youll public key that
I know to decrypt the signed
random number that you've sent to me to obtain the original
random number that I sent to you. Then I can be sure that I'm talking
to you because you are the only person who has
your private key and your public key and
your corresponding public keys, which I have, is the only key
that can decrypt the signed random message
that you've sent to me that can correctly decrypt it.
Yeah. So when
you ssh into a server using your public key, the SsH
server challenges your client to sign something with
your private key, and when it does, that signature
or that signed message is checked against the public
key stored on the server. And if it matches, then you can successfully
log in just as this image depicts.
Now this may be an oversimplification, but it's
more or less how SSH public keys authentication works.
SSH certificate authentication works the same way,
but with an important twist that we'll get to in a moment.
Now how so
we get the hang of how SSH authentication works.
Now,
when a developer,
like I mentioned, to ssh into a host using a public
key authentication, the host needs to know youll
public key. Now, by default, youll public keys
have to be added to the
authorized key file of every host or server
that youll like to have access to. So a normal SSh
key onboarding or deployment involves a developer
first generating their own key pair,
which usually involves some baroque incantation of SSH keygen.
Then they'll submit their public key to an administrator or operator
for approval and distribution. Then the operator
will then deploy their public key to a host
where they need access, sometimes to
all hosts or all servers within the infrastructure,
maybe using some workflow into
the authorized key files of all servers. And then once
that's done, the developer now has SSH
access from this,
from this.
From what I've just described, we can already see the
first shortcoming of SSH keys, which is that it
requires laborious and mundane key management activities.
The procedure because
let's face it, the process of onboarding SSH keys
is time consuming and not
scalable for organizations with hundreds to thousands
of servers. Like I mentioned,
you're going to have to maintain and update
keys on the authorized key file of every server, and that can be operationally
challenging and intensely time consuming for operators
and administrators.
So one way organizations try to deal with
this sprawl, or key sprawl is as
they grow, is to use can authorized keys command on
servers. This could be a program or a
bash script that outputs authorized public
key files. So instead of a file, you can have a
dynamic lookup of keys every time someone tries
to log in, or they use something like ansible
to push keys out to all their servers and
keep those files in sync.
But then even all of this
adds very unnecessary overhead. And the
truth is, no matter how thoughtfully executed,
the task of gathering and shipping and
maintaining SSH keys always remains
messy. It's always messy. Always how
do you keep track of all credentials that can open a
door in your infrastructure?
Do you have up to date inventory of all SSH enabled SSH
keys in your organization? Do you even know who is using ssh
in youll.org or which keys belong to which person?
Because SSh keys on their own
do not encourage a strong understanding of which device
or which user owns specific keys.
And there's always ongoing cost
associated with monitoring and maintaining homegrown machinery
for adding, removing, synchronizing, and auditing
static public key files across your
fleet.
Now the second reasons why ssh keys aren't so great
for you is that ssh keys do not expire.
They remain valid forever, whether you intend them to
or not. And the truth is, as long as the public key is in
place of somewhere, the private key would work.
So even after developers leave your company, their SSh keys would
still remain valid. And they or some other
person Ssh keys can be shared,
theyre can be stolen. So they or some other person
or can get a hold of those private
keys and use it to wreck know, just like the
story of shapeshift, godaddy and
other organizations.
And the worrisome thing is that there isn't actually any way to
revoke inactive keys. So to revoke or remove
a key from youll fleet of infrastructure,
you have to update all your host or servers to remove
that public key. Now,
can you easily update all your servers and
then back to the tracking problem of SSH keys?
Still, when a developer leaves, how do
you know the keys, the exact keys that belonged to
them? So then, how do you know which key to remove?
So unless your company builds its
own custom solution, Ssh keys do not support
that level of object trail.
The next reason why SSH keys are really bad for you
is that it encourages unsafe user
behavior and bad security practices.
Have you ever tried using into a remote host for the first time and
encountered the image or
the warning on the screen? Now, the default
behavior here for most of us is to click
yes and just move on with our lives without giving it a second thought,
but that shouldn't be so, because what's happening here is the SSH
client literally screaming at youll that the authenticity
of the server or host you're trying to connect to can be proven
like it's telling you that you can actually be sure that you're connecting to the
right server or that the server that you're connecting to belongs
to your organization or is an infrastructure within your organization.
So what's happening theyre is that your client tries to initiate
an SSH connection to a server, but the server
tries to authenticate the client by checking.
The server first tries to authenticate the client
by checking if the client's public keys is present in its authorized
key file. Now it does that and it
is. Then your client also tries to authenticate
the server by checking if it is a trusted
server or if the server's public key is in its known hosts
file. Now it does that and
it doesn't find it because that's not ingrained.
It's not a process that usually occurs in traditional SSH
keys deployment. At this point, the right thing
to do here would be to verify theyre fingerprints
by using an administrator or an operator or consulting
a database that has fingerprints of all servers
across your fruits. But the truth is that how many
people do that? Yeah, and so when you type, yes, your connection
proceeds without authentication and the server's public key is
permanently added to the known host
file of your client. And this whole
scenario is known as trust on first
use antipattern. That's tofu.
In this scenario, you're basically making assumptions
that you're connecting to the right server. And frankly,
that's a scary assumption to make because it's a cold
world out there. Yeah,
and theyre are top
of mind, three reasons why Ssh keys are just
bad for larger organizations.
And then now you're probably wondering, is there a better way to manage SSH?
Is there a better way to manage SSH
access that makes is there
a better way to manage SSh keys? Can we do something about SSH keys
to rectify these situations?
And quite frankly, I would say that you're asking the wrong
questions. The truth is you can't tame
ssh keys. Yeah,
they just have a rudimentary fundamental
design flaw. And so the answer would
be to just use SSH certificates and here's
why.
So what I have here is what an SSH key
certificate looks like when decoded.
So an SSh key is simply a public
key bound to some meta data and policies
defining who the certificate belongs to and what
the certificates can be used to assess, among other things.
And I will just walk through some important
properties or some properties of the SSH certificate on screen just
to give you an idea of what it enables.
So first we have the type and there are two types of
SSH certificates. We have the user and the host certificates.
What I have here is a user certificate.
So host certificates are used by hosts or servers to
authenticate themselves through SSH clients.
I will talk on that later when I describe
how SSH certificate authentication works.
And for user certificates,
which is what I have here, theyre are used to authenticate SSH
clients to host.
Now, user stats are quite similar to host.
The major difference here is the principles field,
which we'll get to next.
You have the public keys, and this is the same public key
portion of the key that you would have with a traditional SSh
key. The difference with a certificate is that a
certificate authority, which we'll get later, has signed
all of this metadata that you're seeing and satisfying that
the public and private keys pair
is trusted within your infrastructure.
Next we'll have the signing CA, which is
the signature of the
CA that signed, which is the signature of the
certificate authority that signed this certificate.
Then we have the key id and this property is usually
outputted in SSH logs so you can put any
important identifying information here.
Then we have valid which
defines the lifetime of an SSH certificate,
because SSH certificates do not live forever.
Next we have the principles. And principles are an
arbitrary string that allow access to a specific host
or a specific user
on a specific host.
And then we have the extensions property which allows for
privileged SSH features like agent and
port forwarding, or even to force configuration directives.
Now let's look at how SSH certificate
authentication works. Now to get started using
SSH certificates based authentication,
the only additional element you need to introduce to your infrastructure is
an SSH authority. Now I make the distinction of
calling it an SSH certificate authority because you cannot
use a certificates authority configured to issue
S 509 or TLS certificates to issue
SSH certificates. And that's because
OpenSSh uses a custom and simpler
certificate format. Now as
I mentioned in the beginning, SSH certificate authentication works
almost the same way as using SSH keys.
Now in this case you would configure
clients and hosts to trust certificates issued by your CA.
And to do this it would involve
something like editing the SSHD config file
on each host to specify the CA's public key so
that that can be used to verify user certificates
and then youll can also add. It would also involve you
adding your CS public keys to each client's
known host file to
be used to verify host certificates.
I won't go into the technical details of how
this is set up because that's not what this talk is all about and
different tools have different ways to do it. And some tools
make this process automated. Yeah,
I'll link to resources at the end. My duty theyre is to convince youll
to consider using SSH certificates in your
infrastructure, show you why they are great, and so you can
consider using them in your infrastructure if you're not already.
So as you can see in the image, when an SSH client
tries to connect to a remote host, it first obtains
a valid certificate from the CA and the
host will typically get this host certificate when it is first
deployed and then be renewed regularly from
the CA, maybe each
month on a timer,
then also once. Then the user
will also ask for a certificate and signed
by the CA. Then when
the client tries to connect to a host, the host asks for certificates from
the client and confirms that it has been signed with the private
key of the CA that it has been configured to trust using
the CA's known public key. And then the client will also do the same
and ask for a certificate from the host and verify that the
host certificate has also been signed by the public
key of the CA that it has been configured to trust.
And then once certificates have been exchanged,
the protocol would then proceed as it would with
public key authentication. Now this brings me
to the first reason why SSH certificates or
using SSH certificate authentication is far superior
to traditional SSH key authentication. And that's because
the way SSH certificate authentication
works immediately eliminates the trust
on first use anti behavior that we talked about.
So youll can have both clients and hosts can be
sure that they are connecting to infrastructure that actually belongs
to their organization. It creates a walled
garden, which is great for organization.
Another great thing about using SSH certificates is that they are easier
to maintain and manage. That's after the initial
setup. Static keys in authorized key files
are no longer needed, and so you don't
need to have scattered keys across your infrastructure.
Instead, peers, clients,
host, and clients learn one another's public keys on
demand when connections are established. By exchanging
certificates. Now, eliminating key approval
and distribution processes has immediate
operational benefits for organizations because
you're no longer wasting up cycles on mundane key management
tax, and you eliminate any ongoing cost associated
with monitoring and maintaining homegrown machinery for
adding, removing, synchronizing, or auditing
static public key files across youll hosts.
Now, also, because certificates allow for inclusion of
metadata, you know exactly who
a certificate belongs to. And then you
can implement more fine granting access controls
and you can have youll visibility. And when you have visibility,
visibility makes way for things like governance,
compliance and reporting.
Now, the third and probably the most important reason to use SSH
certificates is that SSH certificates expire and they
can be revoked. You can define a validity period
using the valid property that I talked about.
That I talked about. So this little detail
is so crucial because it encourages safe security practices
and reduces companies risks, exposure and surface
attack. Because unlike traditional public key authentication
where key management oversight and that's like forgetting
to remove an S employee's public key from a host
results in SSH failing open and
allowing unauthorized access without end.
You can set up SSH certificates to be valid for say
16 hours or longer or even shorter,
depending on the exposure risks of the
host that they will be used to
assess. So even in an incident of a mistake
or TEF or misuse or key filtration
of any form, compromised SSH
credentials or certificates will expire
automatically without intervention.
So before the attackers would
have time to make sense of what they are
doing, their assets would aspire.
And that's what's so great about SSH
certificates. Now,
with all of this that I've shared, I hope that you're starting to
see how SSH certificates can make your
workflow secure,
easier to operate, easier to manage,
easier to automate.
Now the next thing is to get into tooling.
How can you start using SSH certificates? Because I
do hope that from the little I've shared of how SSH certificates
are superior to traditional SSH keys, that you're
convinced to give SSH certificates a
second thought and a deeper look, and try to discover
how you can start adopting them in your infrastructure.
Now there are a couple of open source tools that you can use.
We have SSH keygen, which can
generate root certificates and
sign host certificates. There's also Netflix bless
which is Netflix SSH certificate authority
that runs in AWS Lambda and uses IAM.
Then we have n Sheridan cashier,
which is intercom's SSH. Can you have
Uber palm SSh which lets you
use SSh to authorize pseudo use?
And then we have our very own smallstep labs
step can. Now, I talked
about SSH certificates being short lived.
And in addition to that, I'm not very familiar
with how other tools on dislikes works,
but with small step can
the private key and certificates always go into
the SSH agent and nothing is
stored on Dix. And so once the key and certificates is
in the SSH agent, they can now be used for connections
but theyre cannot be exported easily so it makes
it difficult to steal SSH certificates.
So in addition to SSH keys being easy to manage,
having inclusion inclusivity
for metadata which encourages more visibility and
better audit trail, and not
being short lived and
using able to be revoked now,
they are also much more resistant
to theft.
Now, I have to mention that the caveat of open
source tools is that you have to do some setup
yourself. You might have to probably build
the foundation is there, the support is there, but then
you now have to build out tooling for dashboard,
for visibility, for auditing and
so on.
And that's why I'm using to mention that small step
has a paid SSH product that offers complete lifecycle
management, audit login and full visibility into all of
your certificates. And you can manage and keep track of everything
from one admin panel out of the boss.
You just plug in and be on youll way. So I'll link to
resources to learn more about it at the end of this talk,
just to show you what SSH certificate authentication
enables, let me just blow your mind for
an instant. I really hope that your mind will be blown.
In addition to all these advantages
that I've talked about today associated with using
SSH certificate authentication, SSH certificates
authentication also allows for extensibility.
Rather, you can issue SSH certificates via a
variety of authentication mechanisms to facilitate
better usability, which makes obtaining SSH
certificates simpler and makes
obtaining SSH certificate a more simpler and elegant experience
for your users. So for instance, you can use,
for instance, so do you know that you can use SSH with SSH?
And that's so awesome because just imagine this,
a developer starts their day and they want to ssh into a host.
They type SSh username into a client and they are taken to a
screen requesting them to sign in via your
company's or your organization's identity provider.
And once the developer completes their SSO sign in,
a better token or can OIDC identity
token is returned to the login utility.
Now using this token, the utility
generates a new key pair and requests a signed certificates from the
CA. So then
the developer is then issued an SSH certificate with an expiry
time, long enough for a workday, say 16
hours or 20 hours, and the certificate is stored
in memory and now they can use it to assess SSH hosts as
usual. How cool is that? You bring youll
IDP and we bring the ssh and mash it together and you
have a seamless SSH experience for your developers
and users.
Now this is what small step SSH does,
and by default, small step SSH means
a 16 hours certificate to cover a workday, and subsequent
SSH sessions won't require reauthenticating
until the certificate expires.
Now, with a seamless OICD sign in flow
like this, it's easy to enforce your existing security
policies like multifactor authentication or
using Fido U twelve security keys.
And the cool thing about this is that removing a
user from your identity provider automatically terminates
their SSH access in seconds. I mean, if you ask me,
that's like the coolest thing. So now when a developer
leaves your company and their IDP access
is revoked, they lose all SSH access.
So you no longer have to worry about having rogue or
unidentified SSh keys lying around in
your infrastructure. That's no longer a threat. Yeah,
no more unused keys using around and needing
to somehow get keys off every host,
that's no longer a threat or a problem.
And still talking about small step,
we also have can
integration with a tool called indent and it lets
users request access to company resources
that they need to do their job of Yaslac. And this is just to show
you what's possible. There is so much more that is possible
with using SSH certificates.
So by adding intense on demand
access control to small step, now approvers can
approve and review requests and
initiate certificate generation process right from
Slack. And this is helpful in cases where external
consultants not in your organization need to get access,
or you want users to just be able to request access
to SSH into hosts on demand instead
of mapping host to users from your identity providers.
It's super awesome. And I
mean, do I need to say more?
Honestly, do I need to say more? I don't know about you,
but at this point, if I were listening to myself, I'll probably be sold.
Yeah, like I mentioned at small step,
we're convinced that SSH certificates are the best way to do SSH,
and they are not hard to understand. The initial
setup might be a little bit involving,
but it's well worth the effort. And I believe that SSH certificates
demand more press and broader use.
And so at this point, I really hope that you
consider using SSH certificates in your infrastructure
and in your organization. So you can either use open
source step ca SSH enabled certificate authority,
you just have to knock out a few things on your own, and we even
have a video tutorial that you can follow to
do that and set that up in your home lab, or to test
it out and then for your organization. Or if you want to get
a lot of futures right off the bat, you can check out SSH
pro and take it for a spin via a free
trial. And as I mentioned, here are some links
that you can check out to learn more about how
to start using SSH certificates in your infrastructure
today. And that brings me to the end of this talk. I hope I
have convinced you and not confused you that SSH certificates
are the right way to do SSH authentication.
Thank you,