Hello everyone, my name is Akanksha. Welcome to today's session.
There are three new trends we are seeing and I'm going to talk about each
one of them in detail. The first trend we are seeing is that there is
an explosion of data from all the connected devices. The growth of
data is coming from devices like mobile phones,
smartwatches, IoT devices and many more connected
devices. Even applications are actually generating data,
the social media, the way we are purchasing things.
So mobile phones generate a lot of
data. By our own estimate, the volume of data is
growing from ten x every five years. To take advantage
of all of this data, you need to be able to partner with
someone who can easily manage this volume of data.
The second trend that we are seeing is microservices.
Now, microservices are now more popular because application
needs have changed. Applications now need to scale quickly
to potentially millions of users. They need to have
global availability, manage petabytes of data
and responses in milliseconds. Now, microservices allow
small groups of developers to build these modern applications
and innovate faster AWS. They can independently
build and grow new products for their businesses without bringing the
whole application or the website down. And the third trend that we are seeing
is there's a transition to DevOps models. Now businesses
are transforming from an IT model to a DevOps model,
which gives developer more power to push code to production faster.
It also uses automated tools like continuous development,
continuous deployment and continuous integration of new code.
So these are like three trends that are driving the new requirement
and need for purpose build databases.
Now let's also transition into topic of self managed databases.
Self managing your database is a tedious, time consuming and
expensive task. And if you guys have worked on
databases or worked as a DBS, and I think you can really correlate
to what I'm saying now, is you have to worry about your operational
efficiency issues such as hardware and software installation.
You need to make sure that your database is fully patched,
all the cpu patches are done, make sure the backups are done
and they're done correctly and accurately as well.
Performance and availability issues are taken care of and
there could be failures, and failures could be very huge ones,
which is like a failure of a primary instance can mean downtime
for your application and lost money for your company. In the worst
case, a faulty backup plan can result in permanent data loss.
Now, many dbas don't even know how the databases will
handle an instance failure until it actually happens.
Now, when using an on premise data center, capacity planning
is regular fact of life. You plan months
in advance, guessing at your growth rate, and then you
overestimate to be on the safer side. And by doing this you're
wasting money on unused infrastructure. And occasionally, if you're
not good in projecting your growth rate or your need, you underestimate
it and then you leave your customers unhappy with unexpected downtime.
Now as a DBA, we really want you to innovate on behalf of
your customers and not manage infrastructure.
This is like a shared model that we have, but we'll start off with the
left hand side. So if you look at the left hand column, this is what
we actually spoke about just now, where you look after the whole stack,
starting from server provisioning, patching, configuration and recovery.
And on the right hand side is shared model by AWS, which is
also like our fully managed database services. By AWS we
handle all the fundamental operation. You get the patching,
minor upgrades without downtime, automated backup failover,
high availability and durability is taken care of and we are able to provide
you all these features through a console with single click because we
are using AWS cloud the AWS cloud is split
into different AWS region. Each region is split into multiple
availability zone which acts like a
separate data centers within the region. When you're using
managed databases on AWS, your database storage is
automatically scaled according to your needs so you will never
have to run out of disk space. Your database instance size
or the cluster size can be increased as needed quickly in
the console. We are based on the
model which is like pay as you go model which is based
on you pay only for the instance and storage
that you use. This results in more flexibility and
obviously less using upfront. As a database administrator,
you provide value by assisting on schema design,
query optimization and access control, building new applications
and making your customers happy, and not by
managing infrastructure for the new modern architecture.
AWS offers 15 purpose built database
engines that support diverse data models that allow you to
build use case driven, highly scalable distributed
applications. By picking the best database to solve the
specific problem, customer can break away from the
concept of one size fits all database and focus
on building applications to meet the needs of their business.
This allows customers to scale faster,
innovate faster, build new features faster. Now let's
look at the fully managed database services that we have.
We provide a wide variety of database types. Now if you're
using a relational database, then Amazon RDS includes
supports for seven different relational database engines. This could
be open source options such as MySQL and postgres.
NoSQL or a commercial option such as Microsoft NoSQL Server
or Oracle database. If you're using a non relational database,
AWS offer multiple options there too.
AWS document DBS is a fully managed MongoDB
compatible document database. Amazon Elastic Cache provides
support for both Redis and Memcache, and Amazon
Keyspace is an Apache Cassandra compatible database
with serverless scaling and pricing characteristics.
Now let's look into the managed database that
we have and how do you move basically to the managed database
services? The most straightforward and simple solution for
customers who are struggling to maintain their own relational databases
at scale is to move to a managed database service like
Amazon RDS or Amazon Aurora. In most cases, the customers
can migrate workloads and application to a managed
service without needing to rearchitect their application,
and their teams can continue to leverage the same database skill
set. Now some of the customers who migrate to self
managed databases are essentially running the databases on
on premises. They would like to reduce database burden,
they do not want to re architect and they would like to have better performance
and availability and scalability. Now the easy way
is customer can lift and shift their self managed databases
like Oracle SQL Server and postgres NoSQL
MariaDB to Amazon RDS. For customer looking
for a better performance and availability, they can move their
lift and shift their NoSQL and postgres databases
to Amazon Aurora and get three to five times better
through output. Now Amazon RDS provides a
couple of very nice features. For example,
it provides you the scale and performance and it automates
the time consuming administrative tasks like provisioning
and database setup and patching, and the backup customers who are
using non relational databases like MongoDB and Redis
as document and in memory databases for use cases
such as content management, personalization,
mobile application catalog, real time gaming.
So the most straightforward and simple solution for these customers
who are struggling to maintain their non relational databases is
to move any of into our fully managed non relational database
services like moving self managed Mongo databases
to Amazon document DB, moving self managed
in memory databases like Redis and elastic cache to Amazon
Elastic cache. And in most cases, these customers can migrate workloads
and applications to a managed service without needing to
re architect their applications and their team can continue to leverage
the databases that they are using now. Customer wants
to move away I think most of you
will also correlate it. You would like to move away from old car databases
because they are expensive, there's a proprietary, there's a lock
in, they offer pumative licensing and comes in
with frequent audits from their vendors, which nobody really
likes. So even if you are not using that feature, but if you
clicked it, then it will be flagged in the audits and you have to pay
for it. So there's a common trend that we're seeing is customers
would like to move away and go into like a license free
model where they don't have to pay for any license to any of the vendors.
And for that we have built Amazon Aurora,
a MySQL PostgreSQL compatible relational
database built for the cloud that combines the performance
and availability of commercial databases while providing
the cost effectiveness of open source databases.
Now there are no annual licenses you pay for
the capacity you use. This turns your capital expenditure
into operational expenditure and better matches your
cost with your revenue. Now some of the Aurora key features are
it is highly durable Amazon Aurora database volumes are
up to ten gb in segments and each segment is replicated
six ways across availability zone. It's highly fault
tolerance because it handles the loss of up to two out of
six data copies without losing write availability or
three out of six copies without losing read availability.
It monitors your disk and nodes for failure
and automatically replaces or repairs them if
it finds out anything is not working fine. There's a continuous
backup, incremental continuous backup with no impact on database
performance. It is obviously designed to be compatible with MySQL and PostgreSQL.
So if you are on any of the commercial database
engines and if you would like to go into microservices,
this is also the right time to think about going completely
license free and move to any of the cloud native databases
that we have. And Amazon Aurora is actually one of them.
Now let's look into how is the application landscape
changing right now. Back in 1670s,
mainframe was prominent way of building application.
This lasted until 80s where the client server was introduced
and then that also significantly changed the way applications were
built. And then the Internet arrived in ninety s and as
a result the underlying data model also changed
predominantly and database still remained monolithic.
But now this has changed. Now we fast forward it again to today.
Then you see that microservice architectures are how applications are
built in the cloud. Microservices has finally reached
the database and this allows developers to do
what they do best. They break large applications into
smaller services and pick the right tool for the right job.
They want to avoid a single overburdened
database with one storage engine and one compute engine
trying to handle every single excess pattern.
Now there are other things that we have also seen that latency
requirements are much lower and they are expected to be able to
handle millions of transactions per second. So in general,
the application landscape is changing. And if you look into this,
the change requirement of applications, the user growth is also
changing, right? So the applications are going global,
right? Businesses are capturing more data. As I said earlier,
there's a huge data growth happening, there's a huge
emphasis on performance. Businesses don't want to
dilute the user experience these days, right?
And if you talk about scalability, then a lot of businesses
are embarking their digital transformation. And these measures of
scales are component by number of devices that access
their application. There are billion of smartphones in the world
and mobile is bare minimum expectations in 2021.
So all of these requirements are actually changing the
application landscape, the user expectations and the requirements
around it. And to tackle this, we have provided 15
purpose build database engines that support diverse data models
that allow you to build use case driven applications
by picking the best database to solve specific problem
and customer can break free from one size fits all.
And if you go from here, then you can see we have
relational databases and we have document DB.
We have in memory cache databases.
Let's look at the variety of purposeful databases that
we have. We have key value database DynamoDb
which stores database as a collection of key value pairs and
it is idly used for ecommerce shopping cart product catalog.
The next one we have is document DBS that stores data in
a JSON or JSON live document. And it's ideal for mobile applications
and cataloging in memory databases. Store databases
in memory for low latency access and they're ideal
for caching and gaming. We have craft databases
that represents relationship directly and are ideally used for
social networking or fraud detection. Then we have time series databases
that stores data in time order and append only,
which is ideal for DevOps and application monitoring.
And last, we have ledger databases that stores in immutable or transmittable
cryptographic logs. And it is ideal for finance,
manufacturing, HR, payroll,
retail invoices that I can think of. So we have
a huge broad spectrum of all these purpose build
databases. Now in the next step, I really want to dive
deep into DynamoDB. It is a key value and document database
that delivers single digit, multi second performance at any
scale. It's a fully managed, multi region, multi master
database that is built in with security, backup and restore.
And some of the key features or some of the highlights are DynamoDB
can handle more than 10 trillion requests per
day and can support peaks of more than 20 million requests
per second. Okay, so DynamoDB
actually automatically scales tables to adjust for capacity
and maintains performance with zero administration.
Availability and fault tolerance are built in eliminating
the need to architect your application for these availabilities.
It encrypts all the data at rest. By default.
We have point in time recovery feature that helps you
protect your tables from accidental delete or
write operations. DynamoDB is serverless. Also it integrates
with lambda AWS lambda to provide triggers,
and using triggers you can automatically execute
a custom function when item level changes
are done in the DynamoDB table. So hundreds of
thousands of AWS customers have chosen DynamoDB as their key
value document database for mobile, web,
gaming, IoT and all applications that need
low latency data access at any scale. The next database
I would like to talk about is documentDB. A large variety of
applications, drivers and tools that customers
already use today with their MongoDB non relational
databases can be used with Amazon document
DBS with little or no change. It is compatible with MongoDB
3640 drivers and tools and
latest support can be found on our website. But with the launch of the support
of MongoDB 40 compatibility, Amazon document
DB supports the ability to perform asset transaction across
customers. Customers can easily migrate their MongoDB
databases on premises or from on premises to
either EC two or to document DB.
Document DB is also very much integrated with our
Amazon Cloud Watch which provides you metrics
for your database instances and it provides you some very key
operational metrics. For example, how does your cluster
look like compute memory storage through output.
So since it is integrated you can get alerts. You can see the
current status of these metrics here and as well.
And lastly, it supports 15 database read
replicas as well. Now database Freedom is
an AWS database and analytics modernization
incentive focused on accelerating enterprise
migrations from Oracle and SQL server,
Netiza, Teradata Cassandra or MongoDB platform
to AWS cloud native database services.
It is an incentive program, but it not only provides you an expert
advice, it provides you workshop partners migration
assistant to help you with your migrations
and guide you through your migrations. Now we have a
series of migration workbooks or playbooks that we call them. They are
freely available for download on our website and provides a
step by step guide outlining how migrating your
databases or what you should look out for. These are extraordinarily
detailed and can help anyone who's looking to migrate themselves
with common technological hurdles or
things to watch out for. I also would like to talk about
DMS which is data migration service that we have
and it is used to migrate between homogeneous database
types, such as going from one MySQL instance
to a new MySQL instance. Or you can use DMs to migrate
between heterogeneous databases, such as
moving from a commercial databases like cloud to a
cloud, native relational databases like Aurora.
There's another great tool that we have which is schema
conversion tool, and it helps you to migrate your database schema between
heterogeneous data types. It attempts to convert all
the schema and code objects of the target database engines,
including the stored procedures and functions. It also scans
and converts your embedded SQL statement in
application code. So in combination of playbook dms,
it is very easy to migrate your databases to AWS
let's look into partners we have quite a range
of partners with us, but the question that I get asked
is why do we need partners? We really recommend
looking into our partners that can help you to do
any proof of concept or actually can do migrations for you
as well. They help you reduce your operational cost so
that you can focus on innovation as well. So here is
quite a few of our partners. We have migration partners.
We also have license advisory partner here as well.
So if you would like any help on your licenses or you would like
to know more about them, then you can refer any of our partners
here to help you with that. And lastly, we have
lot of resources. We have also launched our database certification.
So if you guys would like to know more about databases,
you can visit the website mentioned here, or you can
take the database certification as well.
More information, contact us and then
once again, thank you for joining today's session.