Are you an SRE,
a developer,
a quality engineer who wants to tackle the challenge of improving
reliability in your DevOps? You can enable your DevOps for
reliability with chaos native. Create your
free account at Chaos native Litmus Cloud hello
and welcome to the conference site Reliability Engineering Conference presentation
on system state clustering using EBPF data. What is our
agenda for today? We will be looking at what is EBPF? What is clustering,
how EBPF and clustering can work together, how EBPF
and SRE work together, what are potential use cases? And we'll be
wrapping up with some question and answers. What is EBPF?
EBPF programs are event driven and are run when kernel or application passes a
certain hook points. Now, what are hook points? Hook points include
system calls, function entry exits, kernel trace points,
network events, and several others. Once your execution passes
that hook point, from there on you can run some of your
own programs, nothing but the EBPF programs. And those EBPF programs can pass
data back to the use space via some data structures called maps.
Just to give you an example, let's say you want to know
how many times a file is being opened. So that is nothing but a file
open system call, right? So you can have an EVPF program defined that
actually doors on to this particular system call, which will be
triggered when your file is opened. And once that program is triggered,
you actually get control into that, and then you can pass
data in and out of the map, which will actually. In which you
can maintain account of how many times a particular file is opened or not.
So that's the basic fundamental of how EBPF works right
now here, explaining the same thing which I was talking about earlier.
So here we have two diagrams
here. Like one is a storage hook EBPF, and the other one is a network
hook, EBPF. So whenever I issue a syscall,
which is going to do a write or read on a particular file,
that syscall actually reads the file descriptor, and then via
the block device, it actually reads and writes to the storage.
Right. And that's where you can actually hook the EBPF program,
and you can trigger that program to understand which
file is opened or how many times a particular file is opened. On the right
hand side, if you see the same kind of behavior
you can get for, let's say you want some program
to be triggered in case of network activity,
like some sort of traffic you have received, or some sort of.
Whenever you want to get information of receiving a
request over a network, you can actually hook an EVPF program into that
and then pass the data about that program back
to the user space via map. So this is how essentially
it works together, delving into it a little bit more.
So how it happens is actually you write code. You write
the EBPF code and then you compile it into a bytecode, and then that bytecode.
Actually there is an EBPF verifier that actually verifies whether your
code doesn't go out of the bounds that
has been set of an EBPF program. So if
it is going out, then the verifier will not execute the EBPF program, because basically
your program is going to execute in the kernel, right? So we can't afford
unsafe programs being executed there. So once your
program satisfies all the verifier and jit bounds, it can be
attached to many hook points, right?
We talked about hook points. So one of those points could be like a class
ingress or any sockets. So you can have socket filters, or you
can have TC ingress or TC ingress. So you
can attach your program in these kind of places, and then whenever you
see any traffic coming or any particular network event
happening, your program will get triggered. That is
essentially how one of the software that I'm going to discuss later,
cilium, that's how essentially it works. Right. Here we look
at an example of an EBPF program, right? In this one.
This is actually an example of how many times a kernel function is entered.
Now our function here that we're trying to trace is exec v Cecv,
right? So you see on top that there is a map, right?
That's a k probe map, which basically says that how many times in
this map you are going to maintain the number of times this particular function was
entered, right? And that is the map.
And in the program section in the functions,
you see the k probe execv function. In that one, you actually
have a map lookup element. So this is basically going to look up into the
map and see how many times already it's there. And it's
just using to update the map. It's going to fetch
and aided one and using to update the map so this
program can be attached. And then once the program is
triggered, it will automatically implement or increment the
number of entries, which basically means the number of times this particular function has
been triggered. Good. So now we
talked about EBPF, right? So EBPF helped us understand
how at a certain execution points we can
actually understand the way the
program is getting triggered. Right. Now, how can that be used with
machine learning? So we are going to talk about a simple use case of machine
learning called clustering, right? So what is clustering? So, clustering is nothing,
but if you have a lot of data and
you want to make sense of what group each data belongs. So, for example,
in this particular figure, right, you have lot of data points,
and the color of the data points basically is telling us the
type of data point. And if you want to actually maintain a fine line between
all these three different types of clusters. So this lining,
or the grouping up of different clusters, different data points
into clusters, is called clustering, right? So it's an algorithm that can help cluster different
data points into classes, right? And the data
points that are similar will be closer to each other.
Right. And when you represent them dimensionally,
ideally it should be closer to each other. And the algorithm that helps
us to understand or to do that, clustering, there are many algorithms
can do that. So the methodology is clustering, and there are many
algorithms to do that. Right? Now, here we
look at an example. It's a very famous example. Whenever any person starts machine learning,
the first thing I believe that I had done was
the iris example to actually understand how clustering works,
right? So iris is nothing but a data set of flowers,
right? There is this particular flower which has the data that
is provided is length, length of the sepal, width of the sepal height,
and those kind of things. So, petal width, sepal length, petal length are provided.
And these are three dimensions that are provided. And when you
actually group them, you can actually see that
the similar flowers or the similar flowers actually tend to light
together. And that's what we are seeing. The green, yellow and the purple, they are
actually similar data points and they are tending to light together. Right?
Next, so we looked at what EBPF was and
what clustering is, how both of them can work together.
So what is the basic use case of? Why would we want them to
work together? So EBPF can help us understand the basic characteristics of a system
behaving right now. So how many network calls are coming,
how many times this particular file is getting opened? Right? So these are data points.
So these data points are generated by EBPF. Right? Now, once you have
the data points, we can use clustering to actually cluster those data points
and understand and basically create some
sort of domain in which we say, okay, this behavior, this system behavior is
good. This system behavior is not good. And that differentiation
in domain can be done by our machine learning logic. Which is the clustering
logic, right? So we have EVPF that generates the data points.
Clustering can actually clustering the data points, right? So initially,
to help us, so every machine learning problem is essentially a
label problem, right? So initially
we can label some data, right? We could actually label them positive,
or we could label them negative. And then in a production
scenario, we can use the model that is created to actually read
whatever EBPF generates the data we can actually subject to the model. And then the
model will tell us whether in the real time whether that is a good
system behavior data point or bad system behavior data point. So that's
how we can use the function together,
to take an example. So we have something called express data path.
In EBPF, express data path is actually the earliest.
So whenever you get a network traffic incoming,
there are a location of sockets to it, socket buffers are located to it,
and then that socket buffer location happens in the kernel,
and then the traffic moves up. But even before that,
we have an express data path functionality in which even before the
socket buffers are located, we can actually understand some characteristics of
the incoming network request, right?
And along with XTP, we can add our filter programs,
right? So we can attach EBPF program to the XDP, and that
EBPF program can actually help us understand the data about the received packets
of the network, right? So there is a EBPF program that
you have attached to an XDP filter, right? And once the network packets
keep on coming, your program writes data
about all these received packets into a map and
user space. Program then reads the map and pushes,
let us say it, to any data store,
and then from that data store, your clustering algorithm can actually understand whether
this incoming network request is normal or not. Right?
If now there are a lot of requests coming in, right? It doesn't
make sense to actually predict each and
every data because there is an infinite number of data requests
that are going to keep on coming. So you can apply some
sort of a time series algorithm on top of all these to understand, okay,
is it gradually building up into a series of not normal requests? And if
so, that means there is something wrong that is happening. You could actually
be facing a DDoS attack, or you could actually be facing a
denial attack. So these kind of things can be estimated
or predicted prior to that event already happening. So here we
see how EBPF can actually help in understanding
whether a system behaving is in the right
domain or is in the wrong domain. Right?
Next we'll talk about some
of the existing open source software
that actually use EBPF.
And they are also be very
good at. Very good software at providing
full system view related to system reliability engineering or site reliable engineering,
right? So you can actually install these software on your cluster,
and you can actually have a single view of how
your entire cluster is behaving and how do they
do that. So we are going to discuss cilium and pixie.
Both of these software actually use EBPF as their fundamental
base to hook on to
many system or kernel points. Like for
example, network events or file events.
They hook onto these system points and then they generate data.
And then there is an API that actually captures all this data and then shows
it as a UI to the user saying that, okay, this is what is happening
in your cluster right now. And that is what essentially site reliability engineering.
Site reliability depends on observability,
right? And observability is enabled by software like cilium and
Pixie. Not only observability, there are a lot of other things that are also enabled.
For example, network traffic control. So cilium
actually does a lot of load balancing. There is a lot of network policy management,
bandwidth management and all that. And finally, you can also have operations
and security metrics also available via the Hubble
framework. So, Hubble framework is the one which actually
reads all the data which is generated by cilium and provides it
as a UI. So what does cilium do? Cilium actually provides the
right level of information for troubleshooting application and connectivity issues. Right? Now,
if you look at this diagram on the right hand side,
right? So you see that there is a NIC card, right? There is a network
card, the kernel, there is a EVPF program that is hooked onto
this network card, right? And in user space,
you have installed cilium, which is actually connected to
the CNI. And there are pods that
are running. So what happens is anytime your pod issues a traffic,
or receives a traffic, cilium can track it, right? Cilium tracks it using EBPF doors
and then sends it to data spaces, those databases, nothing but maps.
And then those maps, those maps are like. Or ring
buffers. Ring buffer is a map, right? So those ring buffers keep on getting
populated, and then once they're getting populated, it automatically keeps on
refreshing the data on your framework, on your hubble framework. So that
is the UI. So essentially how it works is
EBPF is doing the high volume work of
understanding the requests and those requests. The data about the request is
passing onto the map. Cilium reads those maps,
provides it as a UI. So that's how this whole cilium
can hook into the observability factor of SRE.
The next one that we are going to discuss is Pixie. Now, pixie is similar
to cilium. It's very, very similar to cilium. What it
basically does is it adds EBPF probes to provide access to metrics,
event stresses and logs. There are pixie scripts, right? So Pixie has
scripts that you can run, so you can execute PX script commands and
you can get data out, and you can actually get data out in JSON format,
and it's very user friendly, right? Just like
cilium, Pixie also has a CLA and a live UI. So if you
look at this diagram, right? So pixie actually
works on something called pems. Pems are nothing but pixie edge modules.
They are nothing but daemons that run on all the nodes. So those demons are
actually hooked on. So those daemon processes are nothing but EBPF modules that
are hooked on to some certain system events. So anytime the system event gets
triggered, your PEM or your edge module actually transfer
data to the process that is running on the
cluster, and that is actually going to collate everything and
provide it as data on the
CLI or UI. Or that is a place where the pixie API runs. And then
pixie scripts can actually read off that API and then provide you
good results. So if you look at both of these software, what essentially
they do is at the lowest level of the system,
at the lowest level of the system, which is nothing but the network card,
or at the kernel level,
they run EBPF programs. And those EBPF programs actually collect
data, and then they collate that data and they send it,
or they help in the observability part, just by collecting the
data from the base, like at the earliest, that system
can get a request. That's where it collects the data from.
So these two softwares are very common.
In fact, we are using many components of these software to actually help
in the observability aspect. We have many verticals in
our SRE system, and one of the verticals being observability.
So we use both of these software and the fundamentals involved
in these software very rigorously to understand the observability aspect
of the site reliability engineering.
So we looked at these two software. Right now,
what are the potential use cases? So like I said,
how we can understand the system behaving system behavior
can be understood by the data that the EBPF doors
are generating, right? So there is system performance degradation. Check whether
your system, whether you are so for example, system performance can be measured
by the number of database reads. Let's say there is a database read. Every time
there is a database read, you expect some
minimum level of database reads. If that is not happening, that means your system
performance might be going down. Network traffic check
how can you actually understand whether
the optimum amount of network traffic is being handled or whether there is lot of
network traffic which is malicious is coming into your system?
So that also can be tracked by EBPF hooks,
right? Preventive maintenance. Preventive maintenance is nothing. But let's say you have an API
that is not behaving properly as it is. So now that API can,
API aware modules of cilium can actually understand
whether the API is behaving properly or not. How many get calls are issued,
how many put calls are getting issued. So those kind of things can be
understand by these software. And then if
the API behavior is not consistent with what is expected, then we
can actually run sort of preventive maintenance, as in we can actually upgrade the
versions or upgrade the backend or something like that to actually
help us cover the multiple aspects
of SRE. So these are some of the use cases. Now we look at one
use case in particular. So let's take a network traffic use
case, right? So like I said earlier, so we have
XDP. XDP is nothing but express data path, right? Express data path
is the earliest in the
system that actually an interception of a network packet can happen.
So even before socket buffer, even before SKB, you have XDP.
So XDP is the earliest. So basically if you are able to filter out
something at XTP range itself, your system will not actually
waste much resources in allocating socket
buffers and doing all the processing up the kernel. So if you are able to
filter it under, which is basically the entry
point, which is XTP. If you're able to filter your traffic at that point itself,
that means you are going to save a lot of load on your system later
in allocating socket power. So how does it work? Right? So there is a receive
queue, it receives incoming requests, right? But at the
traffic class ingress, we have actually hooked a BPF
program. Right? Now, our BPF program,
let's say we have a BPF program which says that, okay, from a particular IP,
if there is a packet, I need to drop it. Why? I say that because
I believe that that IP is a malicious IP,
right? And that IP is maintained in the map. So the BPF map actually maintains
that IP, right? So you have a packet that
is coming from a received queue your BPF program checks the receive
frame, right? That's the XTP receive frame it,
check it, look at the IP address, and if the IP address matches the one
on the BPF map, then it actually does the XTP underscore drop, which basically nothing
but drop it. On the other hand, if I have to redirect
it or send it somewhere else,
so I don't need the packet to go up the kernel and
then come back, I can actually send the XTP underscore
TX itself. And at that point it's when the packet can
go out to some other interface. So that's how we can do XDP
redirect or HTTP transmit these kind of things. And if
everything is passed, if you feel that everything is green, then you issue an XDP
understand pass, which basically says that, okay, now you can go up the network stack,
you can get the buffers allocated, and all those cases.
If you look at this, right, your single EPPF program has done
a lot of, has saved you a lot of effort in
this particular use case. Why? Because let us say you
are maintaining a list of ips, right?
Every program or every organization maintains a list of ips
that are considered malicious, right? So you maintain a list of these ips, right?
And you pass them onto a BPF map. All that you have to do is
you actually update these maps, you actually update this map to just update
the malicious IPS, and your EBPF program actually dynamically
keeps on rejecting traffic if it's from those ips. So this is an excellent
example of an interrupt traffic use case in which you
actually use EBPF to control your
resources, your resource allocation, and to
stop any malicious actor from obtaining access
to your system. So yeah, this is one of those use cases that
we are actually trying to explore a lot more in
almost all our systems, right? So that
brings us to the end of this particular session. I hope
it has informative, hope it triggered some sort of thinking as
to how EPPF machine learning and SRE can work
together. Now I'm open for questions. Thank you
once again for listening, and all the best using
EPPF. Thank you.