Safe
for joining me for this session on what the cloud threat landscape looks
like in 2021. My name is Trickram and I am
a cloud security architect or checkpoint, and I work with customers
and some of our business partners in the UK and Ireland,
mostly discussing our cloud security technology and how
that helps to address our customers'needs and requirements when it
comes to cloud deployments. Now, I promise I'm not going to talk about any technology
or pitch any of our solutions in this session.
It's more general talk about the types of interactions I have with customers
and the sort of concerns that real customers are seeing that can be quite different
to what we see from the different analysts
and some of the bigger headline threats that people talk about when
it comes to cloud security. So I'm going to be running through a very
quick summary of what the cloud threat landscape looks like
to us and to our customers, what they're concerned about,
but more importantly, what the different types of customer conversations I
have are, and what the different sort of customers expect
from their type of usage in the public cloud.
So a little bit about checkpoint, and again, this is not a pitch. I promise
I'm not going to be talking about our solutions or anything. Checkpoint were one
of the first vendors to market with a commercial firewall offering back in
1993, and we've been going since then. We've come up with
a lot of new technology to address different needs. We've had ips,
antivirus, endpoint and other solutions, and now, and this
is where I work, I work in the cloud area of the
business. I should say that cloud isn't a particularly new technology for
us. We've been with cloud pretty much from the start. It's been running for about
eight years or so now with checkpoint as a vendor. So what are
the biggest threats? And unfortunately, I'll start with a vague answer, which is,
it depends. It varies very much depending on the type,
the size and the maturity of the customer that we're talking to. Different businesses
have very different priorities, and I can't emphasize the
very, quite enough here. Some customers are very new to
public cloud, some of them are very experienced, and we've
got a lot of customers that fall in the middle as well. So for some,
cloud might be, hey look, I've got an ECT running in AWS, I'm a big
cloud customer. For others, it's huge deployment, multiple platforms,
multiple different asset types, compute, database,
machine learning, pretty much everything the cloud can offer. They will have an
element of that in their deployment. So it is very broad and
we speak to very different types of customers, and so much so that one day
I'll be talking to one at the entry level public cloud,
the next day it might be a cloud expert, and I'm really on my toes
trying to keep up with them, more or less. Everyone faces the same risks,
though. So in public cloud, in a data center,
with a server that sits on a desk in an office, people are
exposed to the same types of threats, and it's
just maybe in a different order. So again, depending on your maturity in
the public cloud and where you are with your level of service adoption in public
cloud, you're just going to face different things slightly differently, and maybe to
a more or less a degree as well. So I'm going to
stereotype some of the customers that I speak to on a daily basis
to give you an idea of what sort of interactions I have and
how the different types of threats that the analysts talk about affect
the customers that we speak to. And I say real businesses or typical
businesses. These are the requests that I get from some of my customers, some of
the partners that I work with, and hopefully it'll give you an idea of how
different they are and where they sit on that maturity scale and as such,
where their priorities lie when it comes to addressing these types of threats.
So, customer number one, this is what we would call a
more traditional customer that's got some servers and a data center,
and they don't have a lot of exposure to cloud. So it
might be the business they work for, or it could be a public services
organization. And traditionally speaking, they don't have any
care or desire to move to cloud. But someone somewhere has said,
we've had a mandate given to us where we are now going to move to
cloud, and you have to start moving into cloud.
They don't have the education, they don't know what they want to do in cloud,
but they've been told, go off and do cloud. So they'll do just that.
They'll go to AWS is your GCP, and they'll start
looking at services and think, oh, compute, I've got a web server that might be
useful. Databases. Yeah, I've heard of that. We've got one of those in a rack
somewhere gathering dust. Let's go with this. So they
will almost be forced into public cloud adoption, and it
might not be something they want to put a lot of effort into. It might
not be something they've got a lot of skill and expertise or even budget to
put that level of effort into. So they will go into it,
reluctant from the outset. And this type of customer,
they will typically face very different problems
than someone who is experienced or willing to move into public cloud.
They will see a lot of misconfiguration type problems. I'll cover
some of the highlight headline problems toward the end of the slides,
but this is one type of customer scenario that we see fairly regularly.
Then you've got the second customer who has some sort of demand or
requirement to be in public cloud, be it a technical demand
or a commercial demand. They want to reduce cost potentially, or be more cost effective.
The usual type of arguments for why businesses want to move to cloud, and you
look at the first or second slide and a typical pitch and
cloud is more cost effective. It can be, I wouldn't say cheaper. That's a bit
of a misconception, but anyway, not going to talk about that. They have a
need and a driver that's pushing them into public cloud, and something about
it fixes a particular problem they've got. The reason I've got here,
the square peg round hole stock photo,
is a lot of people see cloud as the fix all solution.
They take what they're doing now and they think if I do it in cloud,
it's going to make everything better. They don't necessarily know why, but they've
heard lots of success stories about going to cloud. So they take what they're doing
or what they have been doing in the data center, in an office hosted
solution, wherever it might be. A non cloud scenario,
they'll take exactly that and they will dump it into cloud, the lift and shift
scenario, if you will. So for these customers, they are going to typically see problems
around functionality in the architecture not working
in the same way that they wanted. So again, probably misconfiguration,
but taking non cloud workloads and putting them into cloud
can lead to other problems, like scale, or maybe some
of the security mechanisms that they've got in a traditional
environment aren't present in cloud, and they've looked over them and maybe thought,
yeah, we'll fix that later, let's get it working now, and then we'll worry
about security later. Something else that comes up quite frequently for me,
then we've got the far end of the scale. We've got customers
who have only ever used public cloud and only ever want to use public cloud.
For them, data centers are not a thing, and they've missed out on the experience
of being in a data center, racking up servers, plugging cables in
power, networking, worrying about airflow, making sure the server is
cooled, and all the fun things that you have when you have to ferret around
in the data center for hours on end, you can tell I'm a little bit
jaded about that. But anyway, let's not get bogged down with that. These types of
customers have very different demands, and it's all about the native tools.
It's all about agility, elasticity, and ultimately speed.
Not just speed of the service and how quickly a user can access it,
but how quickly they can get the next change pushed out to production. So the
points I've got here, if it's not using native tools, if you're kind of shoehorning
something in, they don't typically care about that. If I've got a logger request
or a firewall rule modification or some other, what they
see is archaic control to get an update
actioned in public cloud, that's a blocker for them. That's not something
that lends itself to the overall experience of being in cloud, which does work
well with speed and agility and the ability to get
to value more quickly. And there are less barriers there to that app
as well. This is something that we come across a lot. People are increasingly more
interested in consuming APIs to automate deployment into cloud.
So to summarize that, the first type of customer that we have
is, I don't want to generalize too much and say that they're slow,
but they are more used to a slow moving environment.
Somewhere in the middle, you've got people who are wanting to move to cloud and
want to take advantage of these things, but are held back by something.
So they'll do the best they can and they will cut
corners and kind of crowbar things into public cloud where it doesn't
necessarily fit there entirely. Then you've got the ones who understand cloud. They know what
they're doing, and they just want to go fast, get everything deployed, and make changes
rapidly, regularly, and deliver the next feature or the next update or the next thing.
And they want to do that without being held back by,
dare I say, security. Something to bear in mind, and this is something I have
to remind myself of quite regularly, is that cloud is a lot of things to
a lot of people, and to some people it is still nothing. So within
checkpoint, as an organization, we've got the team that I work in, which is the
cloud team, where we predominantly speak to cloud customers. But there are
still a large number of people out there who don't know cloud. They're not experienced
with cloud. And while a lot of people watching this session are probably thinking
this seems quite basic, and I know what cloud is for. I know what I
should be doing in cloud. There might be people out there who are new to
cloud, same way that there are the types of customers we speak to. They have
very little idea about what to do in cloud. They think that it's where
technology is going and they want to move what they've got from data center into
cloud, but they have no way to kind of get up to speed very quickly.
So for them, that is a risk in itself. Moving to cloud, moving to an
unknown environment, and being faced with all of these services,
all of the controls and all of the ways of setting up these services,
that is scary and a risk in itself.
So this quite nicely summarizes the type of journey
that we see when customers are starting out with cloud or very
experienced with cloud. You've got the data center on the left, and then you've
got the more cloud focused technologies on the right hand side.
So with serverless lambda functions, azure functions, whatever your platform of choice is,
you've got serverless in some form or another. Then you've got the
different points in the middle. So starting off on the left, one of the first
barriers and threats when it comes to cloud is
the speed of changes. The first type of customer that I spoke about would
maybe see one or two change requests a week to open up a port or
to provision a new server, deploy an application onto it.
When you're in cloud, one or two times a week just isn't something
that most customers will encounter. There will be dozens of changes
daily, if not hundreds a day. If you look at the extreme example of Amazon,
they have a vast number of changes per day, which would just make a traditional
legacy network admin cry and hide in a corner of a
data center. Then you've got the shift in focus of who's in control in
these environments. So typically you had the system admin,
the firewall guy, the network guy, the security guys, they were all the kings in
their domains. Now that we've moved to cloud or are moving to
cloud, depending on where you are in that sort of customer scale,
the developer, the engineer, they're the ones in control, they're the ones
that are using this service and pushing this technology out to
its new home, which is the cloud you don't have the natural
flow of information and infrastructure from.
Here is something I've built on my laptop. I'm going to put it on a
USB drive or an FTP server, then send an email to the
admin team and say, please make this live, please check it for security, please check
it for network visibility, et cetera. They do
everything. They write the application, they write the code, they are responsible for deployment
and hopefully they've considered security when it gets into production.
So what ports are open? How am I going to scan the dependencies, the modules,
the packages that I use? All of this is basically down to
one role, which is the developer. So admittedly, depending on the
size of the team, the size of the business, there will be lots of developers
with a slightly different focus. But that's probably a topic
for another session in itself. Generally speaking, in the larger scale
of things, when you're looking at customers who aren't in
the cloud, to customers who are very mature in the cloud, the developer
is the new person who is responsible overall for these
types of things. Now moving on to the next step, each of
the newer types of services in cloud. So whether you're using containers
or one of the microservices based architectures, sort of beyond
containers, kubernetes, for example, you are then faced
with a vast number of perimeters that you now have to secure. So again,
going back to the traditional days, the traditional teams, you have a very
well defined perimeter and that's your data center. Beyond that you've got your firewall
and that is the ingress and egress point for all of the traffic and all
of the consumption of your application and all of the data that leads.
Now if you're using something like serverless and you say to the network
guy or the firewall guy, where does the firewall go? Well, it doesn't, it has
no place in serverless. You've got to look at other technologies to be able to
secure that. So the traditional points of control have
gone, they're not gone completely. There are now new points of
control that you have to consider, but this is very far removed from
what teams are traditionally used to. So again, that is another
threat to any workload that's running in the cloud.
If you think you're protected by your traditional tools, your firewall,
for example, your endpoint solution, your insert
other security vendor type here that might not be relevant or
even possible to deploy in a cloud scenario.
So that's another consideration. And then there's code as well. So we've said already
that the developer is the new king in this realm and
they're the ones who have a vast amount of control over the deployments,
the level of security associated with that deployment as well.
Now there are some excellent developers out there who have got a lot
of security focus and they know about secure coding and secure software development,
lifecycle management. There are some people who have no idea why input validation
is important and they just won't do it. So one small
example, but generally speaking, a lot of what happens in cloud
and cloud architectures and cloud deployments is purely code based now. So you
don't have the team that builds the server for you, that puts the security software
on it, that patches it, that maintains it. Again, it's down to one
person or maybe a handful of people that write the application and then stick it
out in production. Not saying that's the case in every scenario by any means.
There are some very thorough approaches to security when it comes to cloud
deployments. But generally speaking, this is something which is quite
lacking and leaving everything up to the development
teams who have a very focused level of experience
on development and producing code. They don't necessarily know
about all of the risks that you face at the network level, at the perimeter
level, at the host level, at the operating system. There's a lot to consider and
they have a hard enough time thinking about how to make the application work,
let alone securing it with many tools
and many different techniques. So all of that said, hopefully setting the
context a little bit with our take on what the
threats are to use and adoption of public
cloud for businesses. Again, businesses being a quite varied term in itself.
Small business, large business, will approach it differently and face different problems. But the
biggest one that I think most people would agree with is misconfiguration.
It's probably the biggest one because it covers so much, and it's a very
vague and broad term, and I would be here for hours to
talk about all of the different types of misconfigurations that I've come across and I
talk about with customers. But generally speaking, there are some more
commonly misconfigured assets that I see when talking to people.
These focus mostly on storage. So s three,
storage accounts in azure networks and databases,
the most common things that people couple with the different types of workloads
and public clouds. S three is something which gets used and possibly misused
a lot, not just by users and engineers and architects in
the cloud, but also by the media. When it comes to saying cloud is insecure,
there's this s three bucket that's been leaking files. It's caused this many problems
across so many organizations. Yes, it has.
Personally, I think it's a little bit unfair because there was a
problem back in the day when you deploy s three that it wasn't secure
by default. Now security is the default option, and users
have to tick a number of boxes to say, yes, I know what I'm doing.
I want to make it insecure. I want to make it accessible to everyone
on the Internet. But then users tend to favor functionality over jumping
through hoops to get access to something. So that's a problem in itself,
and that falls under misconfiguration. So Gartner
have said a number of times that most of the failures in public cloud
are going to be down to the users. And it was, I think, last year,
about 95% of cloud security problems being the user's fault.
They've increased that. Now, through 2025, up to 99%
of cloud security failures will be on the user, which I can completely see.
Cloud contains a number of brilliant services and tools
to secure those services, but they're quite complex. And as such,
I can see, and we do see customers misconfiguring a lot of
things a lot of the time. Then we've got
IAM an authorization. This is a really difficult error,
and one which we're often asked by customers, do you have
a magic thing to fix it and not here to pitch at all?
It's not something which we have. A magical solution
to controlling what your users do and what they have
access to and what they should have access to is a time consuming and
difficult task. We've seen some customers with
some very unique approaches to it. We've seen some customers with
no approach to it, and they will go for the, let's just leave it open.
Nothing bad will happen, I'm sure, and we'll secure it later on. That is not
something I would advocate by any stretch. It's a terrible idea,
although it's complicated. You at least have to get the basics down. If you don't,
you're in for a fairly horrible experience. I could almost guarantee that I've
got here that it played an important role in a recent incident. It played a
very unfortunate role in a number of instances recently where an attacker
has got in through maybe a security vulnerability in something
that's hosted in public cloud. But they've managed to use IAM to move
laterally in the environment and pivot onto other systems until they can
eventually get data out. And there have been some large financial institutions
and some other software vendors who have fallen foul to this recently. So it's
definitely out there. It's definitely happening, and it's definitely being abused. Things like the
mitreattack framework can help you address what areas
you need to focus on. So with IAM and authorization being
such a broad topic, tools like that can help you focus your efforts
on the different vectors that you have in your environment and what
types of security you need to put in place around those tools and
services to at least cover the basics off. The last part I'll
put as a threat, and it's kind of something that you can do to combat
the other threats as well. And this is agility and visibility.
So one of the biggest problems that we see with customers isn't
they're not necessarily worried immediately about zero days
and advanced threats and apts and other people getting in and pillaging
the cloud accounts to find very niche vulnerabilities and abusing
IAM to get from service to service. At this point, a lot
of customers are concerned about what they've got in cloud from a
c level or an executive perspective. They don't know what cloud is
to them, so they have no visibility of what workloads they're
using, where the workloads are, whether they're compliant with any particular
frameworks. GDPR, California Consumer Privacy Act,
CCPA, that's the one. I remember the acronym. Finally, any of
these frameworks are a huge concern to CSOC levels
and execs. So for them, they just want to know what they're doing in public
cloud. They're not worried about the misconfigurations.
They are, but not directly to the level of do I have the right ACL
on my file storage thing? They want to know,
does somebody have a handle on everything that's going on in public cloud?
And you can get some of this from the cloud platforms, but it's
not laid out for you in a nice, easily consumable manner.
You quite often have to dig around, find all these different details, and put the
pieces together yourself to give you a really complete picture of what
your cloud presence, and therefore attack surface means. You have to
look at different panels, different tabs, different views, different windows,
sometimes even different platforms altogether. If you're a large enough
company that you consume multiple cloud platforms, then you're just multiplying
the problem. So you've got now two platforms where you don't know
where to look for the different assets, to see what you've got deployed in what
regions and what state they're in. So visibility, I think, is fundamental
to getting control of what you've got in your cloud platforms,
and then agility as well. And this is something that I touched on a little
with the cloud maturity diagram. So as
your cloud level of experience and maturity gets stronger and you get
more experience in cloud, you start to do things more quickly with
that. The business gets used to that agility and wants to keep
up that cadence of releasing things very quickly and very rapidly,
that eventually there might be a slight tilt towards let's get things
out there and then we'll worry about security later.
More often than not, that later never happens until somebody else
finds your deployment in a somewhat secure, maybe insecure
state and they will be able to take advantage of it. And the whole argument
of oh well, we were planning on securing it today, tomorrow, later is
irrelevant. Your data is gone. There's someone in there, somebody has damaged
your reputation, they've got your ip. You need to do this as
soon as you can. Security needs to be a primary consideration when you're moving
to cloud. It shouldn't be an afterthought. And with the agility,
the roles and the responsibilities have changed when it comes to securing what you've
got in public cloud. The security team that the traditional heads,
they're no longer the ones that are in control. It's now with the developers.
We mentioned this again on the cloud security maturity
diagram. Even if there is a relationship between
those teams, they might not have overlaps. It might be that
the legacy teams are far too legacy and they don't know how to
talk to the cloud developers, the engineers, the architects, the people who
are pushing out these services for consumption by customers. There's no common
ground if you've got the technology team who are still talking about firewalls,
and you've got the DevOps team, the cloud architects,
whoever it might be talking about, pushing out serverless functions
to cater for services to be used by customers.
The firewall team can't put a firewall in front of that in a traditional sense.
So the teams just operate in isolation, hoping for the best.
Agility in that sense is a threat. It's one of these weird ones that
you turn around to be a strength as well later on, provided that you
bake security into your agility. But that's again
a slightly different topic for consideration. So what
do we see as solutions to this? I've mentioned commercial offerings in here,
again, not here to pitch. Commercial offerings are available on the visibility side of
things. I think this is a really important thing to get started
with when it comes to cloud deployments. If you don't know what you've deployed in
public cloud, you have pretty much no hope of securing it. So make sure
you're making the best use of what native tools you've got available.
Anything that lets you set up monitoring on logs,
whether it's network logs, API logs, user interaction logs,
you need to make sure you've got that turned on. Quite often in the
cloud platforms, logging isn't on by default because that
consumes storage space, which costs money. Some of the analytics
services associated with looking at the logs, they're not free either. They will cost
a fairly nominal fee in some situations. Some of them are horrendously
expensive, so obviously take that into consideration, but try and get some
visibility of everything. Don't have any service which is available
to users or even developers and internal teams that doesn't have some level
of logging on it to see what's going on. If the worst happens and someone
does manage to get into your environment, into the cloud environment, the lambda function,
the container environment, whatever it might be. If you've got some logs, you can start
somewhere, you can see how they got in, you can hopefully fix it and prevent
it happening in the future. If you haven't got any visibility of what's going on,
things are going to be rough. Then misconfiguration. Again, this is a
very broad topic to cover, so I won't be able to cover everything here,
but I think automation is the key. And again, couple that with visibility.
There are some fairly decent tools out there in the native platforms
that you can use for some are free, some of them are not
free, but they're not extortionate either. And again, commercial offerings are available,
but where they're available, and especially where they're free, make sure you're turning them on.
Things like AWS, trusted advisor, they can help out as well. They can give
you recommendations on some real easy to fix things like
your s three bucket there that's got world writable permissions.
That's a very bad thing. Don't do that, turn it off. There are more complex
recommendations as well. That's just a common one that tends to come up when talking
to customers who are new to cloud environments. But misconfiguration is
such an obvious thing to happen, especially when you consider
how many services there are and how many of those services have got such diverse
configurations about them. Again, if you're using more than one cloud platform,
that's multiplied by the amount of cloud platforms you've got, because the service that
you're using in one is almost certainly not going to be the same in another
platform. So you've got to learn one way to do it in this platform one
way to do it in another, and it's very little consistency between platform
a and platform b. It might be completely different,
completely worlds apart when you're configuring these different things.
So trying to automate it where you can can help you achieve
a level of consistency across those platforms. But make sure you're
testing that automation I have seen some fairly awful situations
where something has been automated, not particularly well tested,
and that automation has just led to mass deployments of
badly configured things. So in one example,
fortunately, I didn't make it out of testing. It was automating permission application
for a storage facility in a cloud platform. But they got the
permissions wrong. So it wasn't just one poorly configured storage
service, it was hundreds if not thousands of poorly
configured services. Fortunately, it was noticed fairly early on and
they managed to update it via automation, via the templating engine they
were using, and fix it at scale. So if you can automate,
brilliant. But make sure you're paying that attention as well, because that can be a
whole different rabbit hole to fall into if you've got poor automation practices in place.
Native tools I've mentioned this, some are good, some are better than nothing,
some are free and some are not free. So make sure at
least to get the bare minimum covered and then on to IAM. So this is
probably the hardest area to give any really easy
suggestions for. There's so much to cover. There are numerous
tools in the platforms, each of them are very diverse and very different.
It's unfortunately something you just have to spend some time on. It's worth it though.
It is a worthwhile investment to get these right,
because they can save you a lot of pain and suffering in the future.
If, for example, I mentioned one of the larger, more media focused and
highlighted breaches in the last couple of years that did rely
heavily on poorly configured permissions in the
cloud account. So when the attacker was in, they managed to basically
knock on the doors to see which ones were open and abuse
the high reveals of privileges on certain services,
then get onto that one and escalate those throughout the environment to ultimately
get data out. Now, if you take the time from the outset and make sure
that you're using IAM, you're using security groups rather than
assigning privileges directly to users, following the best practices.
At least that will help a lot when it comes to
securing what you've got in your public cloud environments and making sure
that if the worst happens and somebody does manage to exploit a vulnerability
in a software package, or manage to find something that is poorly configured,
you're limiting the blast radius and the
area of effect of what they can do from that service that they have managed
to get a foothold on. If they've managed to get onto, let's say an EC
two instance that doesn't have fully open permissions to everything in not
just that account, but any of the adjacent accounts to it as well, you're limiting
what they can do. Yes, it's bad, but it's far easier to fix than a
multiple account affecting breach. Where they've got in, they've got a foothold.
Maybe they've even got access to the account. Difficult to say.
Attackers are very persistent, and if there is a weakness, they will pursue it until
they get what they want, which is ultimately data or resources,
be it a crypto mining resource or something else. If they don't want
your data, they will be in there for something they won't leave empty handed.
So take your time. Get this bit right. There are some tools out there,
not necessarily tools, in saying yes, your IAM solution is configured perfectly
well done, but tools to make sure you're not giving your users too many permissions.
Something like permissions boundaries if you're using AWS,
this is a really useful tool, and a fairly simple tool as well, to make
sure that no matter what the scenario is, a user in a particular area
can't get more permissions than their boundary gives them. That's a
really powerful tool to make sure that your user in one
situation they don't have read and list permissions for something,
but accidentally you've given them root permissions somewhere else. A permission boundary
can be a really powerful tool for making sure they don't cross
over from a read owner user into a readroot
user, which is a fairly bad example, but you get the picture.
Use what you've got. It is a time consuming area.
If you're not familiar with it, read the documentation. Look at the best practice
guides. There are some fairly lengthy documents out
there, and they're quite difficult and painful to read. If you've been through any of
the certifications, I'm sure you've had the pleasure of looking at the different IAM options
available, but it is useful and it's a worthwhile
investment in terms of brain space and time invested when it
comes to cloud security. So some quick takeaways
from this session. Not everyone is a cloud expert. Businesses are very different
levels when it comes to cloud adoption. So what might be
normal day to day operation for you as you're managing a huge container
architecture with lots of microservices scattered across multiple cloud platforms.
The person who is considering cloud next might be very new to cloud,
and they might be looking at deploying their first instance into the cloud.
So for them, their interest in security and the threats that they're interested
in might be very different to you. There's no right or wrong. Everybody wants to
secure their workloads and their presence in cloud environments just don't
look too unkindly on people who are new to cloud.
You were new to it at one point, so you didn't get to the level
of cloud expertise you're at today without making the same mistakes that people that are
new to cloud make. So be kind to people. It's a fairly
intimidating place, is cloud, and there's a lot to take in in
a fairly short amount of time, especially if you want to make the most of
it and not find yourself falling foul of misconfiguration and some of the
other nasty things we've spoken about. And businesses still see cloud
as new technology in some parts. Not everyone, most people are aware
of cloud now, but when I first started out sort of talking about cloud and
working with cloud, with customers, there were some people who had no idea about cloud.
I think it's fairly safe to assume that most people have at least heard of
it now and know some of the benefits and some of the threats that might
face them if they were to move into cloud. So that's a very
brief summary of some of the customer types that I speak to on a day
to day basis, some of the threats they face,
and some of the general solutions on how aim to
fix them. And thank you to conf 42 for allowing us to
present.