Hello and welcome to unlocking LLM potential
a journey with APIs. My name is Ricardo Covo
and I'm a principal consultant on the app dev and
modernization practice at Centralogic.
My LinkedIn is my main forum of social
media, so please feel free to reach
out if you want to connect.
Today we're gonna be following this agenda.
I'm gonna do first an environment overview. I'm gonna show
you what I'm going to be using during the presentation.
There's going to be a lot of demos, we're going to come and
cover the basics just so we have
common terminology and understanding.
We're going to follow that with a demo, then we're going to go
into the meat of it, which is chat completion with tools.
So tools, APIs, functions are
tools that you can augment the chat with.
And then there is a new feature, at least on the
Azure OpenAI, which is the assistance,
and I'll cover a little bit, I'll do a small overview,
but a lot of the concepts will translate into that.
So environment, we're going to be using OpenAI
as our AI service.
I have some sample web APIs that I'm going
to use and then there is a
visual studio project that we're going to be working with
to develop this project.
So let's check that out.
So from,
from the Azure perspective. So I
am using an OpenAI service.
Once you go into it,
it's gonna ask you to go to the
Azure AI studio to actually do your
work. So I'm gonna click on that. A brand
new browser is going to open.
It's kind of like a different tool. So we're going
to give it a little second for it to load.
And one of the things that you can start looking
in here is if I go into resource
management keys and endpoints,
this is pretty much the service, the endpoint
of the service and the keys that I'm going to have
to feed my client on the code to actually
have access to this functionality on OpenAI
Studio. Here's where you have your
shad, your completions, the assistance that we're going to, so the different
services that are available from OpenAI,
but also important is the models,
so you can deploy different type of models. So I have
deployed only a GPT 35
turbo is more than enough for the
demo that we're going to be doing. So this name
is important because from the code I will also reference.
So that's what you need to know here from the Azure part,
from the web API, the sample web API
that I created is in a container app. And we're
going to simulate creating timesheets for
a project or projects. So I've
called the timesheets API and here in postman you
can see how I can get the different projects,
or I could add hours to a project. So getting
the project is a simple get. It's taking a little bit
because it's probably a cold in
the container app. I have it set up that it can go up to zero
instances. So it takes a little bit to come up, but you
can see here that it returned an
array of projects in adding hours to
a project involved doing a
post with a certain payload
and a certain specific URL.
So this is where we're going to eventually going to be using.
And those are the three things that you, the two things that
you need to know. Like in Azure,
it's where you have your endpoint, your keys and your deployment.
And from postman I've been,
this is how I can test the APIs.
Let's go now and show you
visual studio. So I have an application
running that it looks like this. It's like the
simplest shot you're ever seeing. And then we're
gonna be playing with some code here. It's a blazor application
that is already running, but that's what we're going to be using for
the demo. All right, so let's continue
here. So some
basics. So the service is whatever service is providing
dialm, you could be, it could have been deployed
locally or it could be,
in this case I'm going to be using Azure OpenAI, but it could go
on the chat on OpenAI itself.
And then when you create,
to use that service, you kind of create a client on your code
and initiate it with some options. The chat is
kind of the conversation that is happening.
Roles are who is participating on that
conversation. It could be the system is kind of like
the assistant setup and then whoever
is. So the end user is a user, the assistant is that
reply coming from the service.
And then tool and functions is another type
of role that you can have and we
will get into. So when you
are having a conversation with the chat, you send a request
message that includes the role, the content
in the history, and then the service is
going to send you back a response message
and it has the response content and some
other indicators, for example, whether you need to
call functions.
So this is how typically a chat conversation will
start. A user will say something to the
application and the first thing this application
is going to say is, I'm going to set up
my system and the system is
context that you're giving to this chat conversation.
And in this case you're setting up the system to be a helpful
assistant. And then what is the actual message
that the user is sending is hi there.
Now the service is going to respond
to you with some answer.
In this case. How can I help? Now on
your next step, you want to say, hey, I want ideas
for a talk on Genai.
Well, you have to send all the conversation back
into the service because remember the service,
if you don't provide them a context,
then they're not really, they're not
really smart. They respond based on a context
that you're providing. So you have to send all the
conversation if you want the conversation to evolve
in a natural way.
All right, so let's look at
a demo. And the demo is going to look like this.
So the code that we're going to look actually generates
to this. So there is a space
for the conversation, an input and a submit and a reset.
Let's look at the code.
I'm going to collapse some of these things. You can see
here. The conversation is going to loop through messages and
display them. And then down
here is where you have your prompt and you either send
a prompt or reset the chat right away.
I can tell you that reset the chat is basically eliminating
all the history of the messages that you have. And that basically
means a new conversation.
But let's see what happens when the page is
started. I'm going to read the endpoint and
the key from the configuration file and I'm
going to initiate my client. Now. When I
send the prompt,
I'm going to do some state management here.
I'm going to actually display the message.
But here is where I say, hey,
from my API client,
get a chat completions async.
Now chat completions is a very specific
terminology. If I go back to here,
you can say here completion, right? So that's kind of
what you're initiating over there.
So I'm going to go back and see that.
To initiate that, I'm building a track completion option.
This is important because this is where you actually set up
your assistant for your conversation. You're going to say the
deployment name is GPT 35.
Remember in azure AI studio I
had that deployment name and I'm setting
the system message. And here I went
a little funny with it and say, you are a helpful assistant
that is obsessed with cookies.
It's very simple setup, but I'm also here
if there is any messages on that conversation, I'm going to
actually set them as messages on
the options. So I am sending that context
back. So that is
basically the base use case. So I can say hello
there right
now. I. Oh, there he goes.
How can I assist you today? Are you in need some cookie related?
So it's showing the cookie thing right on my face, even though I had
no context for it. Why are you
talking about cookies?
Submit that. And it's just
gonna, it's just gonna respond
in some, in some ways. I'm just gonna reset that. It's gonna clear it.
Clear the chat.
All right, let's go back to the, to the presentation.
So we introduce the concept of tools,
and it basically gives the chat the assistance that you're
creating, access to tool like coding,
interpreter or knowledge retrieval. But it also
is, and more importantly for the context of this
presentation, is allowing me to build tools
using my function calling in
here. What would happen is I'm
still going to send a system configuration,
the message from the user,
but in addition, I'm going to send it some tools
and those tools are going to define the functions
that I am providing to the assistant.
The assistant is smart to know that you need to call some
functions. So it's going to say, hey, you need to call functions
and it's going to give you an id that you can use for,
that you will use for reference. Now you
know that you need to call functions. So you do call the functions.
So the service is not going to call your APIs or your functions
on its own. It's going to tell you to call it,
and then you perform the actual function calling and
give them a response. So when
you respond to it,
you're gonna say, hey, I did call this function with this id
and this is the response.
And then it's, and then it's gonna generate a natural
language response. So in this case, you're asking,
what projects do I have? So imagine if you're
doing your timesheets, you first need to know, hey, what projects are
available to me? And then you add hours to it.
So that's the first thing that we're going to do is going to ask,
what projects do I have? And then
it's going to tell me, hey, you need to call a function for that.
And I'm going to call the function and I'm going to tell the system
what the response was and then I'm gonna,
and then it's gonna send me a nice natural
language response for it. Right?
So let's look at the demo for that,
it's very similar to the previous one that I have.
You can see the same kind of chat.
But in here, when I defining
my completion now, I went a little more serious
like standard with it. You're a helpful assistant. You will help employees
fill their timesheets. But when it's time
to define the tools, I'm going to say, hey, there is
a gets projects function in a definition kind
of looks like this. It has its own type. And then
you give it the name of the project, give it
a nice description. That's kind of like the prompt that does.
It's kind of like the hint that
we're giving the assistant of when to use
this particular function. So you
here will define. In this case, there are
no properties that are required for this particular function.
So I have configured
my chat
to know that there is a gets project functions.
The rest gonna remain the same. I'll show you this when we
call it.
The other difference, when I'm processing the chat completely
completion, I'm going to look for
the finish recent on the response.
And if it's two calls, that means that
the assistants have determined that you need to make some
calls. And then you actually have
to go ahead and do that call yourself.
So what I'm going to do is put a stop sign around
here, and I'm just gonna
go and say hello.
You can see here the finish reason.
If I go into here,
hopefully let's do this here.
If you go up, sorry, that didn't work very well.
But if you go into here, you can say that
we have a finish recent stop. That means
you have nothing to do. Just continue running and
yeah, how can I assist you today? And I'm just gonna ask
it, can you show me my project,
please? All right,
so now if I do the same thing, the finished
reason is, hey, you have some tools to call.
So he's going to go in here, it's going to do
some management of the state, and then you can have multiple
tool calls. So I put them on a for each.
And this function right here is going to
process that call. So I think I'm
going to put a stop sign right
here now.
And I can see here that the
function that I need to call,
I'm going to say, hey, it is if projects
function get project functions. And it is.
And here we have successfully called a
function. So it's just that right now I have it hard coded
just to show you the different stages.
When you set up functions, it's up to you how the function
gets executed. It could be executed in
line like in here, or it could be a DLl call,
or it could be some,
a web API call, which is what we eventually want to do.
So in here, I'm just saying, I'm just simulating
that this is going to be my response and
I have to send back that tool call
id because that's how the assistant is
going to reconcile. It's going to say, hey, I asked you to do something,
did you do it or not? So when I go back,
you say it
went back again and this time it was stopped.
So it was project blue, green and yellow.
So it is exactly what I have here.
Right? So that is
basically our first iteration
in calling a function call.
Alright, so let's continue here. So I have changed,
so I've been doing this, I paused the recording and
doing so it's faster, but I have changed
to my branch of API function call. And in
here, what I want to show you is that the get projects,
it kind of remains the same. There's no change here
that is going to do anything.
But I did added a second function,
a second tool definition. And what this
does is add hours to projects.
This is the description. And again,
if you can graph the description in a
way that is very, very descriptive,
with little words, that's going to be best because
you're not going to use as many tokens as required
as otherwise you would. But in here
I do have to define parameters
and it is an object, it has a project
id, a project, a number of hours,
a description in an entry date.
Oh, and here I
want to show you that when I set up my
system, I actually gave him context on
what that they would, that what the current
date is, because I'm going to be saying things like please
add 2 hours for projects x for
today, and it needs to know what today is.
If you don't set this up, the assistant,
I think it gives a weird 2022
kind of date. So make sure
that you set up the right context for that.
And in this, so this is the
required fields are hours, description and
entry date. So pretty much anything,
everything. Project id in truth should
be one. Then the
chat completion.
I am now giving multiple tools for
it to be able to determine what to call.
And let me show you
here what happens when the
function name is equal to get project functions.
What is going to do is going to go and I just have a
very quick get
projects implementation. It's just an HTTP client, it's an API
wrapper HTTP client. It goes into projects
and does a response,
but if it is our add hours to
project name,
it actually goes and sends all the arguments
because get projects didn't have arguments.
But add
hours to projects does have arguments in the
function call, which is something that is coming from the chat completion.
Actually tried to determine what the arguments were
and is good. And I'm just going to send it to my project and what
I'm going to do that because these arguments
are going to come as adjacent. I'm going to, I created a small
add hours model. I'm going to deserialize into that
and I'm just going to make the right
URL and post it. So get
projects is a get and add hours to project is
a post. The rest kind of remain
the same. So let's see how that works. I'm going to go here
and I kind of say web project are
available to me.
So this is kind of the same that we did before.
It's going to say, hey, you need a
function call and
it's going to go and say yes,
you probably need the get projects
results. And this is going to go and hit my API.
It's going to take a little bit, I guess.
And if you see the project results, you can see here
that I'm saying Phoenix, Griffin, Kraken is what
we saw in the
call over here. Phoenix,
Griffin and Kraken. And I'm just gonna
let it go now and see what happens
the next time that it comes. The finished reason is gonna be stopped
because there was a function call and I already did it,
I sent it back. So now
I go here and say, hey, these are the projects that are available for
you. Alright, so I'm gonna
say something like add 2 hours
to Project Phoenix.
There you go. Phoenix for today.
I'm going to submit it and it's
going to say, hey, you have some functions
to call. So I'm going to go inside
of tool called response message
in here is going to say yes,
you need to add hours to the project.
And then here is something very cool that
I want to show. So even
though I said add projects to Phoenix because
I'm sending all the contacts and it has all the information, it knows
that the id for Phoenix is one.
He knows that I'm
saying 2 hours. I didn't put a description. So it just
said working on task and entry
date is today. So I'm just gonna
close this and let it go. And it's gonna go.
Okay, so let me just not stop here.
I'll just go.
It's gonna come back and the finish reason now
is gonna be stopped. So let's see.
Hey, 2 hours have been successfully added to pre phoenix for
today. Let's, let's do another like
add an hour to Kraken
for yesterday.
Description should be working
on weekend. So let's
see what, what that, what that does.
So response is going to say, you have a tool
call. That's fine. I'm just gonna
stop here and let's see
the arguments.
If I view the arguments, project id three.
I said project Kraken it is. Id 3 hours,
one working on weekend. And I said yesterday. So because
the assistant has the context of what day is today,
it knows how to calculate yesterday. So that's
great. So I'm just gonna go and do
that.
And it says, an hour has been successfully added
to Project Kraken for yesterday. Actually gave me like a nice
indication. Now, if I try to
repeat this, my service
has an error that doesn't allow you to add twice for
the same day. So let's see,
it's gonna say again,
two calls, it's fine.
And put this here.
So the hour results was error, error that
request. I'm gonna send that back to
the assistant and see what
the message is now. It says, I apologize,
but there was an error and could not add that. Now,
if I had, if my API
have given a more descriptive error, then I
could have sent it to the assistant to provide more
input. But as it is, it just being
very apologetic and putting some nice wording
around it. So that's it. That's how you
use functions with your LLM
and allow you to call your own APIs.
I hope this was very, very helpful.
When I discovered you could do this. It was
thanks to a colleague of mine that created
this system for us. And for
me, it just opened a world of opportunities.
As I said in the intro, we've been building APIs for
many years for other systems to integrate with
it, but now we can integrate with natural language,
with these APIs. And again, I feel
that it opens a lot of opportunities.
A few lessons learned when I was working on these
demos and this talk. APIs and
SDKs are changing very, very quickly. So be
patient when your
SDK and model versions will make a difference. So if
there are things that are not working and you're wondering why,
just look at that. Optimizing system prompts
and function definition is crucial, and also it
will save you money. And I am a C
sharp guy and I think they've done a nice work with the
API. But to be honest, it does seem like Python
is a first class citizen on
all of this. A lot of the demos sometimes are in Python,
so at the very least learn to read
Python and or use,
or use Shaqpt or copilot to help you with
that. Before I
go though, I did promise to talk about assistant,
so this came into
preview when I was preparing for these demos, and finally
it's available to me. So if you go into assistance,
you can see that it's a little bit like
all the setup that we did, but with
a UI, I could go here and
say, I'm going to open one that I created earlier.
You can see that I'll give it a name and it has his own id.
So when the client in the client,
the new way of doing it would be that you request an instance
of your assistant, aid your assistant by providing
the assistant id, you create the instructions. This is
kind of like the system message that you
did, and then you set up the functions right here.
You can see here that I have get projects and it's very similar
to what I have in the code. I would create one
for add hours to projects and then instead of having
to send it with every call, that instance
of your assistant will have it.
So this is something that I think will be the future
for this kind of implementation.
So it is good to keep an eye on it.
And with that, I hope that you have enjoyed
this set of demos. And again,
if you have any questions, feel free to reach out
and I will make myself available,
have a great conference and enjoy all the other
talks.