Flask is a python framework that allows you to build web application.
But in order to use flask you have to install a lot of libraries and
dependencies in your local system that takes so much time and
space. That's why we are going to use Google Colab.
Google Colab is an online Jupyter notebook where you can write
Python program in these small set else and
execute them. So let's see how we can write.
So web application means HTML code.
So how can we write the HTML code here?
In order to do that, if you want to
display any HTML file using Flask, you have to
create a folder as templates. So how can
we create templates folder here? So for that
we have a command as make directory
in Google Colab MKDI and because I want to create folder
with templates name. So I'm going to write templates
and then minus p.
So after writing the line you can
simply run this code and you can see that here it's
working. So if there is no error, you will get
a green tick. We have already created
templates folder, now it's time to write the HTML code in
this folder. So for that we are going to use
command as write file in Google Colab.
And then because we want to write inside the templates folder,
we are going to put the folder name. And now because I
want to keep the name of my HTML file as index HTML,
I'm going to do that now. Here you can write any HTML code.
So I'm going to write HTML 40
and I'm just going to write one text.
Welcome to PI friends 42.
And you can close your body tag and close your HTML.
So let's add one styling as
well. A very simple styling for this.
I'm just going to put style tag here.
So here you can put any HTML code.
You can also copy and paste from
other sources as well. Okay. Yeah, we have missed
1% sign. So that's why it's giving the error you
it. Yeah. So now it's working.
Now let's see how we are going to write the flask code.
So first we are going to import Os and
then import threading because we are going to execute this flask
code in a separate thread and
then we are going to write from
flask first let's see, let's run this and
as we are going to host this flask code in ngroc server.
Basically Ngroc will just give you a
public URL which you can use and accessible
only for 6 hours. So instead of deploying this code
in a local host. I'm going to deploy this in Ngrok server.
So first let's install that here.
Otherwise it will give you error.
So this is the library API ngroc.
Let's install.
Yeah. And now let's import flask.
I have imported this file render template. In order to
render my HTML file and display it,
we have to import Ngroc as well from this API ngroc
that we have installed before. Now here we are
going to build one environment.
I'll keep this environment name as flask and
as we have to initialize this flask.
So we are going to use this app.
I'll provide the port as well. 5000 so
in order to use Ngrock before it used to
be free but now it requests authentication
token. Authentication token is nothing but a key
that you require to provide it here so
that you can use this Ngrok. So how can you get
this authentication token?
You can just go to Ngrok. You can log in
to the Ngrok website and you will easily
get your authentication token. You can
see it here.
So I'll just copy this.
Sorry. And paste it here.
And now we are going to connect this with public URL.
So we are going to connect our local URL with Ngrog.
So for that there is a function as Ngrog connect
and this port is for my public URL.
So I'm going to connect it with Ngrok.
And here I'll just print whether it's showing me that URL
or not.
I'm going to show that public URL.
Here's now
let's configure this.
So basically flask work on several API
and root. So here we are going to pass the root.
So for by default if you pass
it like this with this dash, that means it will take you
to index HTML by default the
main page. But here if you have lot of HTML files like
home HTML or about HTML, then here you can pass
as about. And then if your
website, if anyone open anyone is root to about
then it will render this code. But for now
this will just take us to our main file.
So here I'm going to use render template function and
you can provide your file name, that is index HTML.
And now it's time to run the flask
in a separate thread.
These are some by default code that you will easily
find in ng doc server start
function in order to start this thread. And now let's
see.
Okay, just comment this lined.
Actually I have already used this authentication token.
So now it's not letting me to use again.
So I have changed this authentication token with
new one. Now let's run this so
you can see here you will get two URL. This one
is our local URL, that is localhost
and this one is the ng doc URL. So if you click on
this link it will give you your HTML
output. So similarly you can also create
your new css file and new
directory for different file and
you can write the flask code and you can relink
and render your template here and you will get one ndroc URL that
will be accessible for 6 hours and
along with one localhost URL. If you don't put ndroc and if
you directly simply run the python code, you will only get this
localhost URL which you cannot share it with anyone.
But if you are creating some application and want to test
whether it's working or not, and if you want to
share that link with anyone. So for
that ngrok is very much useful.
So you can see this is our output.
So that's how you can run this flask code in
google collab.