You. Hi. I'm going
to talk today about postmortems and why I think
we can do more with this technique in the tech community than
we are using today. First, let me introduce myself. My name is
Fabricio and I've been coding since 2002. I've worked with
big corporations and also small startups, and I had my time
in academia as well. Nowadays I'm the CTO at BXBlue
and this is the experience that led me to what I'm trying to show you
when I things about postmortems, I see in the community a grim face
about it. Even though there is this shared knowledge
that it's a powerful learning tool, we are always focused
on the failure part, but I believe there is more for us to
extract from it when we look at what we can celebrate and
what we can improve on it. So let me share about it
first. Looking what is a postmortems? According to the dictionary,
a postmortems is an examination of that body to determine
the cause of death. This definition comes from medicine, but it's pretty
close to what we think about postmortems when you're looking in tech as well.
It's not a surprise when you look for the definition of postmortems,
according to the PMBok, is that it's a process used to identify the
causes of a project failure and how to prevent it. So it's
similar to what medicine defines, with a twist that we're looking here not
only to determine the cause of death, but also to
learn from it and avoid it in the future. The counterpart
of a postmortems is a pre mortem, where instead
of looking to the past, we're looking to the future. And it's
a process used to foresee the possible causes of a project
failure and mitigate it. So it's a risk analysis that we're
trying to improve on what we are doing and avoid those
risks in the future. But when you want to look forward and you
want to try to foresee those risks, you have
to learn from it in the past. So a post mortem
is one of the biggest tools to do a good premortin. And when
you're looking for a post mortem, for me, the best definition
of a postmortems comes from its synonym, autopsy, which comes from the
greek sing for yourself. So it comes from experience,
yourself, your mistakes. And for me, this is a good postmortems.
It's a tool for learning. It's a tool for recording the history of a company,
of a product, the tasks and the moments that were shared.
So what some people experience it, other people
can also experience as well and share this context,
share these learnings. It's a communication tool for all
the teammates in a company. But the types
of postmortems that we are used, CTO, it's very limited. So I'm
going to share some other types, some other techniques that you can
use to improve on your postmortems. So I classified six
different types of postmortems, including the classic ones and
some new ones. So the first one is the classic one.
Those closure is the one defined for the pinbot.
It's not restricted, but usually started for project and it's
focused on reporting what succeeded. So you can double down on
that and what failed, so you can learn from that and
avoid that in the future. The second one is the root
cause. Analysis is the most common one. When you see a tech blog
about a post mortem, usually it's targeted on failures and downtimes,
and it's focused on reporting why it happened and why it
won't happen again. It tries to give the sense of security
that you know how to fix it or that you already fix
it and it won't happen again. A new one that I want to introduce
is the detective. This postmortems tries to
recreate, usually in a first person, a step by step description
of what happened. It's a good way to share with other people
what were your process of thinking when you're handling with a situation.
This will allow other people to look on your process
and learn from it, or even allow you to improve
on your process itself. A different type, and is a very
uncommon one, is the open problem. It reports those findings
of an ongoing issue or a pain point without an implemented
solution yet. So here we are talking about something that is
not fixed or even you don't know the solution on how to fix it.
But it's very useful because you're onboarding what
you learned and inviting other people for either contributing
with the design of the solution or the investigation of
the problem. Or even if it doesn't come CTo be
solved right now when it comes back in the future, you know
where to start from and you don't start from scratch. And those
last one, and not least, is the celebration. I'm pretty sure
that you celebrate your achievements with your team, but usually
these are shared celebrations and they are pretty
much already defined. But each person has a different
learning curve and each person can have a different point of view.
But what is an achievement for them. So celebrating about
why things are important, it's very helpful
on recognizing that each person has a different
perspective on the team. So with those different types of
postmortems, what can you do? CTO keep up and do it in your team.
So first, schedule some time for it. Be it after a big event
or something that you think that you should record that
learning process or that context. Schedule some
time and just write it down. Then agree with other people
where you should start it. So other people know where to
look for context and where to find what happened
and when. Then after you write it down, collect some feedback,
not only to share what you learned with other people, but also to see
what they think about what you're writing. Also, they can share some light about
other things that you didn't notice and you also could learn from your experience.
Then share it, be it right away or afterwards.
When you see something similar happening. Share your postmortems so other people
can also learn from it and get some value from it. And also
the most important, just start doing it when you start doing it. If you
don't have the other parts already figured out, they started fitting CTO
place. So this is it. I hope I shed some light about postmortems
for you, and I hope your interest had
a little push forward about starting yourself trying these
new types of those postmortems. I'm very eager to learn
about how you're doing your postmortems and how they are helpful or not
helpful or your challenges, and I'm very open
to discuss. So till next time.