Hi, I welcome you all to
topic week of unleashing the power of quantum computing from theory
to practical application. My name is Emmanuel Samir Harris,
and it's a pleasure to present my presentation
before you for this conference,
that is conference 42, Quantum Computing 2023.
So let's get started.
Unleashing the power of quantum computing from theory to practical
application quantum computing has the potential to
revolutionarize the world of computations. In this
presentation, we'll explore the basic of quantum computing,
its practical application, and future development. Quantum computing basic
okay, let's start with the basic. As everything has a
basic, so even quantum computing has basics.
Quantum bits, qubits that what we call
quantum bits or qubits, is a fundamental unit of quantum information.
Unlike classical bits, which can only have two
states, zero or one, qubits can exist in a superposition
of both state at once. This gives quantum computations
the potential to perform certain calculations much faster
than classical computers since they can
process many possible inputs simultaneously. Qubits can be
implemented in various physical system such as ions,
superconducting circuits, or even individual photons.
However, qubits are subject to various sources of noise
and error, which can make it difficult to maintain
their delicate quantum states as a
long period of time. As a result, much of quantum
computing research is focused on developing error correction techniques and
improvement the quality of qubits. Unlike classical bits,
qubits can exit in superposition of states,
allowing for multiple calculation to take place simultaneously.
Let's come to the second thing. These second thing is of quantum mechanics.
Quantum computing makes use of principle quantum mechanics,
including entanglement and tunneling. Quantum mechanics
is these branch of physics that studies the behavior of
matter and energy at the smallest scale, such as atoms and subatom
particles. It includes concepts such as wave particle
duality, superposition, and entanglement,
which are fundamental to our understanding of quantum computing.
While quantum computing is still in
its early stage of development, researchers believe that it has the potential
to revolutionarize fields such as cryptography,
material science, and drug discovery. As the technology
continues to improve, we may see more and more application
of quantum computing in coming years. The third
a brief history from the first quantum algorithm
proposed by Richard Feynman in 1982 to
the development of the first quantum computers in the 1990s,
the field of quantum computing has made great stride in recent years.
Let's continue more below. A brief
history of the quantum computing quantum computing has been an
activity area of research since the 1980s,
when the physicist Richard Heyman first proposed the idea of
using quantum systems to stimulate quantum
phenomena more efficiently than classical
computers. In 1994, Peter Shaw develops a quantum algorithm
that could factor large number of exponential faster
than any known classic algorithm, demonstrating the potential of
quantum computers to solve problems that are intracellible for classical
computers. In the year followed, shore algorithm
researcher develop a number of other quantum algorithms
such as a Grover's search algorithm and the quantum simulation
algorithm. The first experimental demonstration of quantum computing
were also carried out in the 1990s using system such
as nuclear magnetic resonance,
NMR and iron traps. Since then,
the field of quantum computing has continued to grow rapidly with
the development of new hardware architectures, programming languages and
quantum algorithms. Notably, milestones include the creation
of the first five qubit and 16 qubit quantum computers
by IBM in 2016 and 2017, respectively, and the
development of fault tolerant quantum error correction codes
by several research groups. Despite the progress
in quantum computing, many challenges remain. One of the
biggest challenges in the development of large scale, fault tolerant quantum
computers, which will require significant improvement
in qubit quality and error correction technique.
Nevertheless, researchers remain optimistic about the potential of
quantum computing to revolutionize fields such as cryptography,
material science, drug discovery in the coming years.
Popular quantum algorithm shows algorithm we
have Grover's algorithm and quantum machine learning.
Let's go through them one by one. Shows algorithm shows algorithm is
a quantum algorithm for integer factorization. It allows
for efficient factorization of large number which has
important applications for cryptography. Many encryption
schemes rely on the fact that factoring large number of computations
difficult for classical computers. However,
Shore's algorithm shows that this problem can be
solved quickly on a quantum computer, which would render
many current encryption method insecure.
Grover's algorithm Grover's algorithm is a quantum algorithm for
searching an unsorted database. It can speed up search problems by
an exponential factor, making it a powerful tool for optimization.
For example, if you had a database of nth items
and you want to find a particular item, a classical computer
would need to search through all n items one by
one, taking O n and a time.
Grover's algorithm, on the other hand, can solve the problem in o
square at n time, which is significant
speed up for large databases. Quantum machine learning
quantum machine learning is an emerging field that combines quantum computing
with artificial intelligence. As you can see that
the future of artificial intelligence is combining it with the
quantum machine learning. It has the potential
to enhance AI by processing data much faster than
classical computers. Some of the application of quantum machine
learning includes image and speech recognition, drug discovery,
and material science. However, quantum machine learning is still
in its early stage of development and much research is
focused on developing new algorithms architecture for quantum computers
cryptography secure communication crypto analysis
secure communication quantum computing could
be used to develop an unbreakable system for securing
communication between two parties. Crypto analysis what is that?
It is quantum computers could also be used for breaking
current cryptographic system with ease, posing a major
threat to security. Okay, in which
area again we can actually use quantum computing. It is the
drug discovery quantum stimulation quantum computing
could all allow for more accurate simulation of molecular
interaction, speeding up drug discovery and reducing these cost of
clinical trial optimization problems.
Efficiently optimizing drug candidates and designing
custom molecules to interact with the specific biological target would
have a significant impact on the pharmaceutical industries.
What are the challenges? Developing precise model for molecules and handling
the complexity of simulating large biological system
are some of the challenges that researchers are currently facing.
Optimization problem how can we actually help with that?
Route optimization quantum computing could help optimizing
delivery route, reducing transportation costs and
improving efficiency. Quantum nel a quantum
optimization approach that could help solve complex optimization
problems across diverse industries from finance
to logistics. Fluid dynamics quantum computing could allow for
more accurate modeling of fluid dynamics and application in aerospace,
energy production, and more manufacturing and robotics.
How quantum computing can help us in this field supply
chain optimization quantum computing could optimize these supply chain
management, reducing cost and improving efficiency.
Robotic control system quantum computing could provide more efficient
control system for robotic, improving their capabilities across
industries from manufacturing to healthcare. Challenges the high
cost and complexity of quantum computing hardware are some of
the challenges facing its adaptation in these industries.
What is the future of quantum computing? Hardware advancement new hardware,
architectural and material such as topological
qubits could help overcome some of the current challenges in quantum computing.
Software. Challenges new software tools and algorithms are needed to make
quantum computing more accessible and solve real world problem impact
on various industries from finance and healthcare to material science and
cryptography, quantum computing has the potential to
transform many aspect of our lives.
Let's move on to quantum computing hardware and software.
Okay, presenting the current state of quantum hardware
including various technologies, superconducting iron traps, et cetera
and their challenges. The slide focus on the existing quantum computing
hardware technology. It highlights key technology like superconducting qubits
and iron trap qubits. We can
actually try to see the superconducting qubits are
based on superconducting circuits and have been
a popular choice due to their scalability, but they face challenges related to the
maintaining qubit stability and reducing noise. Iron traps qubits,
on the other hand, use trap ions to represent qubits and have
the advantage of longer coerced timing mention.
The other technologies that we can actually see are
such as the Topo logical qubits and photon based
quantum computing are also being explored. Let's explore
the quantum software development framework and programming language.
The example will be cusket and cirque. This slide
focuses on the software aspect of quantum computing.
Software plays a crucial role in designing and implementing quantum algorithm,
simulating quantum system and
optimizing quantum computations. Quantum software development
framework and programming language provides a high level interface and
tool sets for developers to work with quantum hardware and
simulate quantum system on classical computers.
Quizkit is one such problem framework that offers a comprehensive suite
of tools, libraries and documentations for
quantum programming. It is an open source framework developed
by IBM Quantum and provides
a user friendly and accessible environment for developing quantum
application quizkits. Allows developers to construct
quantum circuits, execute them on actual quantum hardware or
simulators, and retrieve the results. Circ, on the
other hand, is quantum programming framework developed by Google. It focuses
on providing a flexible and low level interface for quantum algorithm development.
Circ allows developers to
define quantum circuits and computations directly, giving these fine
grained control over the quantum operation and gate level manipulation.
Additionally, these frames works have vibrant
and active communities that provide support, share resources,
and foster collaboration. Developers can access documentation,
tutorials, sample codes, and even participate
in hackathons and programming challenges to enhance these quantum
programming skills. In summary,
exploring quantum software development framework like whisket
and circ empowers developers to work with quantum computers,
design quantum algorithms, simulate quantum
system and optimize quantum computation. These frameworks provide a high level
interface resource and a supportive community to facilitate the development and advancement
of quantum software, highlighting the need for
error correction and quantum error correction code.
Let's move and discuss about this part. Quantum computing qubits
are highly sensitive to noise and external disturbances, which can lead to error
and degrade the performance of quantum computations.
These errors can arise from factors such as environmental
interaction, imperfection in hardware computers, and inherent
fragility of quantum state. As quantum
computers become large and more complex, the occurrence
of error becomes increasingly likely,
hindering the reliable execution of quantum algorithm.
To overcome these challenges, error correction techniques and
quantum error correction code has been developed. Error Correction
is a critical aspect of quantum computing as it allows
for the detection and mitigation of errors, thereby preserving
the integrity of quantum information and enabling reliable
quantum computation. Quantum error correction code are
specialized coding schemes that are designed to detect and correct errors
in quantum states. These cases provide redundancy by
encoding quantum information in such a way that error can be detected
and corrected without directly measuring the fragile quantum state.
The most well known quantum error correction code
is the surface code which is cases on a two dimensional grid of
qubits. By applying a set of carefully designed operations,
the surface code can detect errors that occur during
quantum computation and enable their correction. Other cases
such as the color code and topological codes are also
being explored for their error correcting capabilities.
Quantum error correction codes are essential for achieving fault
tolerant quantum computation where errors can be effectively
managed and suppressed by encoding quantum information redundantly
and use error correction code. Quantum computers
can operate reliably even in the presence of noise and
errors, highlighting the needs for error correction
and quantum error correction code underscores the
significance of developing robust techniques to
handle error in quantum computing. System error correction
course provides a pathway towards scalable and fault oriented quantum computers
and ensure the accuracy and fidelity of quantum computations.
Researchers and scientists are actively exploring various error
correction strategies and code to improve the stability and
reliability of quantum computation. By incorporating error correction technique,
the potential of quantum computing can be fully realized,
enabling complex computations with higher
accuracy and precisions. Let's move on to these quantum
algorithm and its application. In these section, let's delve
into the fascination world of quantum algorithm
and explore these practical applications.
Quantum algorithm harnesses the unique properties
of quantum system to solve certain problems more efficiently
than classical algorithm. Introducing key
quantum algorithms and their
advantages over classical algorithm first, let's discuss some key quantum
algorithm that has revolutionarized the field of computations.
One remarkable example is Shaw's algorithm. It is a
quantum algorithm that efficiently factors large
number of tasks that would take classical
computers an impractically long time shows algorithm cases a
potential threat to classical cryptography system as it
can quickly break the widely used RSA encryption schema.
Another notable algorithm is Grover's algorithm. It provides
a quadratic speed up in
searching an unsorted database compared to classical
algorithm. This has significant applications for data
retrieval and optimizational problem where
finding the best solution from a large search space is essential.
Let's come to the second part that is showcasing the practical application
of the quantum computing. Let's try to understand this as well.
Quantum computing is not just a theoretical concept, it has promising
real world applications as this whole theme of me
presenting is all about that. One such application is cryptography,
which with the advent of quantum computers,
new cryptography algorithm resistant to quantum attacks are
being developed. These algorithms leverage the unique
properties of quantum systems such as quantum key distribution and quantum resistant
encryption. Scheme optimization problems are another
domain where quantum computing excellence many
real world problems such as resource allocation, supply chain
optimization and portfolio optimization involves exploring
vast search space. Quantum algorithm can provide exponential speed
ups, enabling us to find optimum solution more efficiently.
Machine learning is an area where quantum computing hold
immense potential. Quantum machine unleashing algorithm
has the potential to enhance pattern recognition, clustering and optimization
task. Quantum inspiration technique like quantum inspiration,
neural network has shown promising result in solving complex
optimizational problems. Let's come to the third part that
is providing real world example and success stories to illustrate the practical impact
of quantum computing. Let us share some real world example in the field
of quantum chemistry. Quantum computers are
revolutionarizing the simulation of molecular system.
This has profound applications for drug
discovery, material design and understanding chemical reaction
at an unprecedented level of detail. The financial
industry is also exploring quantum computing to tackle complex problems.
Quantum algorithms can be utilized in financial modeling,
risk analysis and portfolio optimization, enabling more
accurate predictions and efficient resource allocation.
Several success stories has emerged from industries embracing
quantum computing. For instance, a leading airline company uses quantum computing to
optimize flight routes and reduce fuel consumption,
resulting in significant cost saving and reducing carbon emission
in health care. Quantum computing is being explored for personalized
medicine, genomics and optimizing
treatment plan, potentially leading to breakthrough
in disease diagnosis and treatment.
By showcasing these application and success stories, we can understand the
transformative potential of quantum computing in its various domains
and its ability to solve problems that were previously intractable.
Let's come to the next slide.
That is visualizing a quantum circuit.
So I have actually done that on
the Jupiter Ide where I actually
imported the quizkit. And as you can see, then I started
drawing a quantum circuit. When building a quantum circuit,
it is often helpful to draw the circuit. This is supportively,
natively by a quantum circuit object.
We can either call print on the circuit or call the draw method on the
object. This will render an ASCII art version
of the circuit diagram. Let's building a
quantum circuit now. Okay. Circuit as
you can see, this is what I have given.
Circuit is equal to quantum circuit three comma
three. And then the command. What I have given is circuit x
one circuit h range. We have taken as three and circuit
cx as zero and one circuit measurement as range of three to range
of three. Then we have printed the circuit and this is the circuit
diagram. Okay. And also we
have given the circuit run. I've sourced this
from the Quizkit visualization of
quantum circuit unleashing the
power of quantum computing. Let's now turn our attention to the challenges that
quantum computing faces and explores the exciting future prospect of
this transformative field. I have given these points
here discussing the current challenges in scaling up quantum computers
and improving qubit stability. One of the primary challenges we
face in quantum computing is scaling up the number of qubits and the building
large quantum computers. Currently, we are working with a relatively
small scale system due to technical constraints and delicate
nature of qubits. Developing robust and scalable hardware
architecture is crucial to realize the full potential of quantum
computing. Another challenge we encounter is
improving qubit stability and reducing noise. Qubits are extremely
sensitive to environmental disturbances, leading to error and
decohers. Advancement in material science
and engineering are needed to enhance qubit coherence
times and reduce error rate, paving the way for more reliable
quantum computations, touching upon the need for
continued research and collaboration in the field.
To overcome these challenges, it is imperative to foster collaboration and
knowledge sharing across academia,
industry and government institutions. Continued research efforts are
required to address the technological barrier and advance the understanding
of quantum systems. Collaboration enables
us to pool resource share expertise and accelerate
the development of quantum computing technologies.
Furthermore, interdisciplinary research is crucial for tackling the multifaceted
challenges of quantum computing. Experts from field like physics,
computer science, mathematics, machine science and engineering must
work together to develop comprehensive solution
and drive progressive in quantum computing.
Sharing thoughts on future prospectives and potential breakthrough
the future of quantum computing is incredibly promising,
incredibly promising. As we overcome the
current challenges, we can expect to witness significant breakthrough and
advancements in the field. Here are few potential futures prospective
to look forward to. First, achieving quantum
advancements where quantum computers
outperform classical computers for practical
problems. In a major milestone, we anticipate that quantum computers will
demonstrate their security in specific domains,
spurning advancement in drug discovery, optimization,
machine learning and more. Secondly, the development of
fault tolerant quantum computers will be
a game changer. Fault tolerance will enable error
correction and ensure the reliability of quantum computers on large
scale system. This will unlock new possibility and acceleration,
the adoption of quantum computing in various industries and
scientific research. Lastly, the discovery and
exploration of novel quantum algorithm and quantum inspired techniques
will continue to drive innovation. These algorithms could revolutionarize
fields such as optimization, cryptography, computations and
data analysis, offering unprecedented computational power and insight.
By highlighting the challenges and discussing the future perspective,
you gain a deeper understanding of the efforts required to overcome the
obstacles and the potential transformative impact of
quantum computing. It is an exciting journey of
exploration, collaboration and innovation that holds immense promise for
the future of computations from theory to practical application.
Welcome everyone. In this section, we explore the transition from the
theoretical concept to the practical application of quantum computing,
showcasing the immense potential in holding for real world problem.
Introducing the power of quantum computing for practical application quantum
computing has these
potential to revolutionize various industries by providing exponential
computations power for solving complex problems. Let's dive into some
practical application. These quantum computing shines secondly
that discussing the application of quantum computing, drug discovery
and material design one of the exciting area where quantum computing
demonstrates its power is in drug discovery and material design.
Quantum computers excel at
simulating the behavior of molecular, allowing us to explore chemical reaction
and interaction more accurately. This capability has the potential
to revolutionarize the development of new drugs, accelerating these
discovery of material a specific property and optimize
chemical process. Highlighting the impact of quantum computing
on optimizational problem optimizational problem are
pervasive in many industries such as logistics, finance and supply chain management.
Quantum computing offers a remarkable advantage in solving such
problems efficiently. By leveraging quantum computers, we can explore
vast search space and find optimal solution much
faster than classical approach. These has these potential to
revolutionarize resource allocation, scheduling and route
optimization, leading significant cost saving and improved
efficiency. Exploring the potential of quantum machine
learning the intersection of quantum computing and
machine learning opens up exciting possibilities. Quantum machine
learning algorithm has a potential to enhance pattern recognition,
clustering and optimization tasks. By harnessing the
unique properties of quantum systems, we can unlock new insights
from complex data set and train more accurate model.
This could have application in areas such as image recognition, natural language
processing, that is NLP and personalized medicines.
Discussing these quantum cryptography and secure communication security and
encryption are paramount in a digital age. As you all know,
with the advent of more
complex algorithm, the security and
encryption will be playing a much bigger role
in our future. Quantum protography offers novel
approaches to secure communications.
Quantum key distribution protocol leverage the principle of quantum mechanics
to ensure secure transmission of encryption keys. Quantum resistance
encryption scheme are also being stories to safeguard data
from future quantum attacks. Quantum computing can play a pivotal
role in enhancing data security and privacy,
emphasizing the potential impact on financial modeling and optimization.
The financial industries heavily rely on
complex mathematical model and optimization algorithms. Quantum computing
has the potential to revolutionarize financial modeling,
risk analysis and portfolio optimization. By leveraging
quantum algorithm, we can perform advanced simulations,
analysis, analyze market trends, optimize investment
strategies more efficiently, leading to more accurate prediction and improving
decision making. These 7th point is summarizing
the transformative power of quantum computers. In summarizing, quantum computing is
poised to unleash its power in various practical applications
from drug discovery and optimization of machine learning and secure
communication. The potential impact is immense. As researchers
and industry professionals, we have an exciting opportunity to harness
this power unlock new insight and solve previously
intracrackable problems.
Let's come to the last part that is these conclusion
and the takeaway. Quantum computing is an exciting and rapidly evolving
field with many potential application. While challenging. While challenges
remain, progress in hardware and software is paving the way
for new breakthroughs. It's important to stay informed
and keep an eye on developments in this fields.
Thank you for joining me on this journey into the world
of quantum computing and its practical application. As we conclude,
let's recap the key takeaway and transforms potential
of this revolutionary field,
highlighting the transformative power of quantum computing
quantum computing represents a paradigm shift in computation,
offering unprecedented computational power and ability to solve
complex problems efficiently. By harnessing the principles of quantum
mechanics, we can unlock new frontiers in science, research,
optimization, cryptography, and more. The practical application of
quantum computing are vast and impactful. From drug
discovery and material design to optimization problems and
machine learning, quantum computing has a potential to revolutionarize
various industries, leading to significant advancement and breakthroughs,
emphasizing the need for continued research and collaboration.
However, realizing the full potential of quantum computing
requires continuous research and collaboration. We must tackle challenges
related to scaling up quantum system, improving qubit stability,
and developing error correction techniques.
Collaboration among researchers, industry experts and policymakers
is vital to address these challenges and drive the field forward.
The interdisciplinary nature of quantum computing necessities
collaboration across multiple disciplines includes
physics, computers, science, mathematics, material science,
and engineering. By working together, we can leverage diverse
expertise and accelerate the development of practical quantum computing technologies.
Encouraging exploration and adaptation of quantum computing
as quantum computing continues to advance, it is essential
for individual and organization to explore its application and embrace its
potentials. This may involve learning quantum programming
languages, experimenting with quantum simulations, or collaborating
with quantum computing companies and research institute.
Quantum computing is an exciting and rapidly evolving field as researchers,
professionals and enthusiasts have
the opportunity to contribute to its growth and shape
its practical applications. Let's stay curious, keep exploring and unlock
the full power of quantum computing for the closing remark.
In conclusion, quantum computing holds tremendous promise for
solving complex problems that were previously intracrackable.
Its practical applications span diverse domain,
including healthcare, finance, optimization, and cryptography.
By embracing collaboration, research and innovation,
we can unleash the transformative power of quantum computing
and pave the way for a future of enhanced computation
and technological breakthrough. Thank you very much
for being with me for this wonderful
presentation. I would like to take the
Q A sessions any question and answer any doubts.
If you have, you can put it across to me
and I will be very happy to answer it. Thank you
very much. Thanks for Emmanuel Samir Harris.
And I would like to thank you, the greater
people who have helped me to present this presentation. Thank you.
Thank you very much.