Welcome everybody. Thanks for being here. I'm so happy you all
come able to join.
Today we're going to discuss a little bit building resilient
application. How you can implementing an exaggerated architecture in serverless
application with Python. My name is Hazel Sainz. I'm a solution
architect and I am an AWS community builder in the serverless
category. Okay, today I
want to share a little bit.
In this session we're going to go deep a little bit about
what is an exagonal architecture, where are the
use case that you can apply to them?
And most of all, what is the story behind how
I learned to design this application
implementing it. This is a story about
how I learned to design resilience application as a rock star.
Yeah, it sounds awesome, but it's actually a fact.
I start developing software for some years now and
in the beginning all that I do was designing
applications, thinking always as a monolith
because that was the technology back then.
So the main focus when I have a problem,
I try to design everything in a specific
server. With the times go by, I changed that and
I started to implement it by using layers.
So I started creating my web server,
my application server, my database server and so on.
And that was a good architecture about
that time. But everything is progressing and
everything. We're moving forward and new technologies all days
come along. So I learned
how to design in a different approach.
Most of all because when I started to building in
cloud, I realized that that approach in
some cases we can still using it, but it's not the
same effective that had before because now
it is a little bit expensive if we do
it that way. So with that said,
I changed my mind and I started to think
differently. And this is what all this session
and this architecture is about. We need to start
things differently. We need to start think not
only at the server level, we need to go deep and
change the way that we design our code.
Through the time we used to have
different type of how to split the code and
we have a lot of patterns out there that we can use.
We have something like MBC and
I already did that too.
And when we have like a microservice,
that is a good approach. But when you come
a little bit more into the serverless world,
you will see that sometimes it's been
a little hard to maintain.
So let's go move forward.
Let's talk about hexagonal architecture.
Okay, let's go move forward. For start,
let's talk about what is an hexagonal architecture.
The concept says that hexagonal architecture
is a pattern that promotes the separation of code logic of an application
from its external interactions. Think about
your application as a signal.
Each side of the hexagon represents a port that interacts
with the outside world to the an adapter.
But let's take a passenger.
The first ectagonal that this architecture represents
is the domain in here.
The main target of this section is
that all the domain logic, that means all the
business logic involved in your application goes.
But we're going to have a new approach.
So after that we're going to have an outside exagonal
that's called ports. And this port we're
going to use it AWS like a communication
between our domain logic,
the adapters and what is the adapters about.
The adapters is all the
different components that application
needs and why this is a good approach and why
we should even consider it when
we have the domain part in this middle and in the center. That means
that you can adapt that device. We call these adapters,
you can adapt different inputs,
you can adapt different inputs and use the
same domain logic. So what
happened? If I need to change one of these inputs, I need
to change this one for example. I just can
add a new one and remove this. But all
the main logic, all the business logic will
be remain stacked. So that's why
Excel and architecture is a good idea. But we have
another concept in here. In the beginning I just
mentioned that in my journey I started with
monolith application, then with a resilient applications, and now we're
moving forward to serverless architecture.
And in serverless architecture we all know about what is the
good to develop in this kind of architecture,
what is that? So we'll forget
about handling the servers because in the past,
every time we develop someone we need to
know that disabled was ready, then every disabled
was patched and everything. So in this scenario, in this architecture,
we forget about that and that's, that's something important.
The other thing that we forget about it is that
we don't have to worry about if our architecture,
we're going to grow as we need it.
We forget about that. Why? Because fabulous architecture
offers that. So that's why
we want to go there. And one use case that
is really common is that I
can have a combination of
a full application in serverless architecture itself.
I can have a front end and I can design all
my back end using a serverless architecture using different
servers and so on. Today we're going to see like
a basic application with serverless.
What is that? I have an API gateway.
I have an API gateway with an
interface. So what are the benefits of
using an external architecture? If you tried this approach,
one of them will be then we enhance the testability.
Why? Because the business logic is the
couple from the external component. So that make
it easy to make your test cases to use only the
business logic. You can use mock adapters
to your port directly from here and
just test specifically that functionality
and you isolate your unit testing.
That's pretty awesome. What else?
Well, you add flexibility into the development
and deployment. What happened if you want to shift
a monolith database to a microservice? Or perhaps you
use user interface change like the
mobile for web, or you
change the way you connect. That can be easily
done by using the adapter. Like I mentioned before,
what is the last benefit of using a stagnant architecture
that is so important? The maintenance and the scalability
as your application grow. Because let's face it, when we start an
application, we think we're going to use it right now. But you
don't think a lot about what's going to happen in the future. But with this
architecture, your code is ready to grow.
So aws your application grow,
maintain and clean. The separation between the color logic,
the external interfaces, easy that
you can scale or you can update the parts of the system. Like I
mentioned before, you can change what is the
adapter that you're going to use. You need to
make a change specifically to the business logic. You know exactly
where you have to head up. So that's why it's so important and
that's one of the benefits that you can have.
But just let's go a little bit more deep into the
future of the application. So let's talk about serverless architecture.
And serverless architecture promotes the idea of building application
as a collection of functions that responds to events.
That is the concept, right? So this model
complements the hexagonal architecture.
Why? Because if you remember the hexagonal architecture,
its main complaint, the main target is to
the separation of concerned. And using
functions like lambda function,
you go in the same direction,
right? So let's talk about a basic
API. In here
I get the diagram of an
API that is connected with a lambda function and this lambda
function. Use dynamodb to storage and
use simple email notification to
send emails to the customer. And in this
session we're going to discuss an example that is
really simple. It's like create a new user.
And when you create that new user sends an email automatically
say, okay, welcome, I'm here.
That's why I print this diagram in this point
of view of this session. But something
that is important, like I said, is that the serverless architecture
is promote the same idea. This completely separate
the functionalities. So that's why hexagonal
architecture with serverless it's a good idea. But let's
talk about why. Why is the perfect mix?
What is that such good idea? So if we
remind the concept an
exciting architecture offers interchangeability,
it help us to separate. Let's talk
about a little bit more about that. Why is a perfect.
The excel in architectures offer us that is denturchability.
That means we have adapters that make easy to change our application
interact with the outside world that
help us to facilitating testing and the evolution
of the support, right? What else? We have simplicity
despite of the complex name around it.
The exam architecture simplified the application development and
maintenance because clearly separate
the responsibilities of each functionality
and we have the separation of concerns.
By keeping the application core logic isolated,
developers can focus on the business rules without getting
struggle with the external dependencies. It's more easy to
think about my business logic without exactly
know what adapters we're going to use.
I can use the adapter, but I actually don't know what is beneath that.
So I can say I'm going to save it in the database, but I don't
care what database is because me as the
business logic responsible, I only say,
okay, this is the record, send it to the database.
About serverless. Serverless is an even driving architecture.
And what is that
is run by Evans.
That means everything's come up with an event. If an event occurs,
something's going to happen. So this
is important because it's treating every interaction with the outside
world through events. And remember that in our exaggerate
architecture we have this adapter. So what
is the main merging
here is that every time you have an event,
you will use an adapter to actually go
and play with your business logic. So that's why
it's important. And we have something else. We have
something that is called decoupling. Just as a serverless function did
decouple from the underlying infrastructure, hexagonal architecture decoupled
the application logic. So serverless we
have the separation and the decoupling between different
functions exaggerate architecture separate
even more inside our function. And what
happened when we have all these benefits
together? Well, we create a resilient and
easy maintained application. I know that sounds awesome,
right? It sounds like magic. Okay, we're going to have everything separate,
all the code is working and do it exactly what we need
to do and everything sounds good. So why
that's that image. So we have to remember something.
With a great power comes a greater responsibility. And that's
why I use Spiderman. When you use an exaggerated architecture
and you use serverless application, the main responsibility
is how you design resilient applications. It is
your responsibility to actually split and
separate the concern in a proper way.
You need to separate in function
in the most effective way and inside the function you
have to think about the defined. So in
the developer world, I saw
some cases in the past that when they
ask you to do some change, you just go directly to the code and
start writing about all what do you need to be done in there?
When you use an exaggerated architecture and you use serverless,
you have the same requirement, but you need to step down
and say, okay, let's design, let's think about
how we're going to split the code, how we're going to split
in each different function and how it's going to
be split it inside the function. So that's
why you have a big responsibility as a
developer. Implementing an external architecture
is not always easy because we have a lot
of developers in our team sometimes and it's hard,
the process to try to maintain that separation
between the requirements
is done and then all that transformed
to the code. So it is difficult,
it's not impossible. You can do it. There are many techniques
that you can use, but as a developer you need to be aware
that the responsibility when you have this kind of design of
these patterns and these architectures is
important that you to follow because if you don't,
you're going to have mass in there. That's why
it's great responsibility. Okay? So after we know
all the benefits, all the things that we need to keep in mind and
the awareness about when we should use
it and when not to use it, let's talk
about how we implementing a machine learning architecture,
let's put it together to start it. We have a
lambda function. Inside the lambda function, we're going to have our
exaggerate architecture, okay, that means only the
first diagram we put inside the lambda
function. But what actually we're going to do. So we're
going to have a new adapter, we're going to have a port and that port
is going to communicate with the adapter and the adapter, we're going
to be in charge of saving the record that
being that inside our lambda function, we're going to have the domain
part separate from the ports in the adapters,
right? We're going to use another adapter
and that is to notified and send an email about okay, welcome to
the system, remember, so that's why we're going to
have a second adapter and
we're going to use another one to just connect
the app gateway through our application.
In some cases in the serverless architecture we're going to have directly
the code access adapter and in other ones like it's serverless,
we're going to have Evans. That is going to be the trigger
for our solution. This is the case for the integration with
Apikate win and lambda. Right. And what else
we mentioned about the benefits they're going to have to using this architecture,
we're going to have the unit testing that the unit testing can be focused
into the domain and we're going to
have the integration testing. So if you see this diagram,
it's really clear what is the separation is happening and why
it's important to keep absolutely everything.
So we have the domain, all the business logic
inside domains part in the first executive
we're going to have the port and we're going to have the adapters. Then here
we're going to have the communication with the other services, in this case
dynamodb and San let's
dive in into code. Let's dive into the code.
So I have lambda function here
and the main difference is that this
is my domain of the core of the
lambda. This is my handler. And in here the only thing
that I have is the business logic. If you see in here,
I don't have any logic specifically that use
the database or anything else. Only I received
the information and then I use this, I implement
the adapter for save a user. This is the adapter
that manage all the data information.
And I have another function here that
is in charge to send the email. So this is implemented
in another adapter. So the code for each
adapter is separate. So I have this one, this is
the first one. And in here it contains all the
logic related the database.
In this case I'm using dynamodb. So I
have the definition, the table name,
the data that I need to insert into the
and I have the return that is returning the
user id. Okay, and this is my adapter.
I have another adapter that is in charge to send
the email and this contains the logic specifically
for the implementation of SES. So I
have the email sent in here, I have the source,
this is an email account that I create just for
this session, the address that I'm
going to send the email and I have the
body message that is going to put in the email to stuff.
So how can I trust it? What is the beauty of this is
that let's say for example in the future I need to change the
database and not use dynamodb and
change it for let's say Aurora. Okay. If I'm
going to change that, the only thing that I need to change is the
adapter and I don't have to change any logic into
the business side. The core logic remain the same.
If I need to add a new logic related to the business,
the only thing that I need to change is the core
of this function. So the
separation of the concerns is
really important because allowed me to grow
in the future without impact each other. And I
don't have this spaghetti code and I used to have
in the other architectures
or patterns that I use them before. So let's test this.
So if you see here, I create a test
case. This is really simple that I have
the name, this is my payload, the email that
I'm going to send it. I'm going to say hi,
I just say Monday night. Okay, I have
the email and I just click send with
this change. I'm going to check Edith is really
receiving it. So give me a minute, I will try
to show you that. Okay. So if
I go my email here, I did receive
the email and I have this thing,
the message. So I say thank you for signing up,
we're excited to have you on board. So this
is great because it is working
and if I need to change in the future then I
don't need an email, I need an sms. I can do
it just to adding a new adapter in here or redefine
my adapter. I can remove this and add a new one that only contains
the main logic of the new step that I'm going to implementing. So it's really
easy and it's not something that is going
to take you a lot of time, but it is important to take the
time to analyze design this
structure in the beginning when you're creating your
functions. Why? Because you're
going to save it to yourself in the future. When you
try to give maintenance into this code, you will be
able to remove some logic easily, you will be
able to add a new adapters and even
you will have
less trouble to try to make
a knowledge transfer to new developers and so on. So your
team will appreciate us.
Okay. If you see it's really simple,
please make a habit to design your function
before turning decoding and let's
try to create the more resilient application
that we can, and Xavier architecture allow us to
do that. Okay. So if you like that little
demo, you can try to do it yourself and play
around it, change a little bit the logic, change the adapters
and you can play with the code. So how you can
do it, you can scan this code and you can go and
read my article about it. So you're going to have a copy of
the code in there so you can put it directly into your console
and play a little bit with it and have fun. And just to
finish here, I would love to share a phrase
with you. This is from Harry Potter. I am a
huge fan of the saga. So this is the sentence,
it is our choices, Hari,
that shows what we truly are, far more than our
abilities. Because in this architecture
and this design, all is about the
choices, all is about your decision and
building a resilient application. It depends
from you. Thank you for joining me. It was a pleasure
to me to be with all of you today.
I leave you here my social media. Please follow me.
I give all around
the world and also write technical content.
So if you're interested about knowing a little bit more about
serverless, a little bit more about AWS and another
things about programming and development
and deployment.
Nice to see you and thank you for watching.