Hello and welcome. Today I want to talk about open source library quickstreams
and how to use it to process streaming data in Python.
I'm Tomas Neubauer, I'm CTO and co founder at
Quicks and I want to give you a short insight into
how I kind of get into stream processing and why
we are doing this. So before Quix, I worked in
McLaren and I was leading a team that was connecting f one cars
to factory, basically connecting
a track site to cloud so people can build real time decision
insight in a factory without traveling around the world.
And it was quite challenging use case because the
amount of data from each car was quite huge, roughly 20
million different numerical values per minute.
And as a result, we quickly find out there is
no way how we're going to be able to persist this and query
at the same time with a database in the middle.
And we were sort of forced to look around
for different technology and we end up using streaming
and Kafka broker and we successfully connected the
data and we thought we have solved the problem. But really
the bigger problem was to teach all different
cross functional streams that mostly use Python
and Maslab to leverage this data that we
had now in the Kafka, because streaming is
traditionally Java based ecosystem and
all the tools and frameworks and engines are built in
Java, and as a result it's quite hostile
to Python engineers. So before
we start, let me talk you through what we're going to cover today.
So we're going to talk about different streams processing architectures,
pros and cons of each. We're going to talk about Quickstream architecture
and then to kind of demonstrate the theory in practice,
I will build a real stream processing pipeline in
visual studio code using quickstreams to kind of show you how it
works. Let's talk about streams processing and why you actually want to use
it, because here you get one kind of a gist what
use case we were solving
in Maclam. So generally you
want to use streams processing if you're either getting
lets of data or you want to
react to that data fast, seconds, not minutes, hours or
days. And if you say yes to
at least one of the questions, well, this is probably why you
want to use stream processing. If you say yes to both,
well, it's perfect. So in
the first case, you might want to preprocess your data before you land it to
a storage that could be normalization of your schema,
joining of data filtering, down sampling and
any sort of data preparation in general,
because dumping the raw data into a storage is
expensive, decreasing the performance of your database,
and it's going to just spread on a disk
lots of data and you can't afford that
if you have lots of data and input. If you have five messages per
day, you probably don't care.
Now second, if you want to react to data
fast, regardless of the velocity of your data,
so imagine you want to react
pretty quickly if the nuclear reactor
core is getting overheated or
if you getting your food delivered in two minutes,
you really want to get that information to the destination pretty
fast. And this is where you want to use streams
processing. Now with the stream processing you
have basically two different architectures to
choose from at the beginning. The one is to use client
libraries from the broker of your choice. If you use
Kafka, there are many different libraries.
For example the confluent maintain library,
which is really up to date,
and you will get all the latest features there. And when
you do that, you're basically combining Kafka with some microservice orchestration
like kubernetes by yourself. The second is
to opt for full fledged stream processing framework like fling
or spark. At that moment you're combining that
plus fling or spark and you're kind of adding a dimension to
your architecture. And let's talk about those two options now.
So the first
is quite elegant
for simple use cases where you're just processing one message at
a time, so you don't really have any
context, any sort of state between the messages.
And at that point you are not dragging any JVM dependency.
You have different languages to choose from, so it's quite great.
But the moment you need staple processing, the moment you need
rely on the value of the previous message and trust me, you will end
up there pretty much all the time.
It's going to be very difficult. It's one of the hardest computer
science problem to solve this reliably
at scale and residently against
any hardware failures.
So this is where you might be tempted to go
to something like Flink or Spark. The problem
is that the moment you do that, you're just getting lots
of problems. So first you're dragging a huge Java dependency
to your architecture. And second,
it's not really typical way
of programming because you actually not using Python or
Java, you're actually using Flink DSL to orchestrate
the engine to manipulate data in a scalable,
resilient fashion, which means that it's a different mindset
really, and it also brings some problems to a
day to day developer's life. Like for example debugging so let's
discuss this in a real example.
So here you have Flink
and Quickstream's code. They will do the same thing.
Get the topic with the data of chat application
where people having a different,
they're chatting about different topics in different rooms and you want to calculate
how many words per hour, per room was done.
And here with fling, you're going to connect to a Kafka topic.
Now you can see here, if you look closely, I'm referring
to these two jar files. Well,
putting apart that it's quite difficult
to found the right jar file, to put it to right place,
and to know that you have to also rely on another
jar file. So it's a dependency chain.
But then you are not connecting your code to Kafka,
you're connecting fling to Kafka.
So that's why here you have the SQL statement
which is basically doing exactly that.
And this is the first problem.
Obviously you're relying on not the official Kafka client,
but you're relying on this Fling connector.
And b then
when you want to do some operation, let's say that you want to
calculate this number of words,
because we need to use a custom logic
here to count the word. We are not really going to do
that in Python. Here we're
going to build a python function that we're going to register in fling,
and then we're going to reference the function in our DSL,
which means that fling would basically communicate between Python
and Java with the sockets. And every time we
receive new message, the data would float both
directions. Now I guess you already
start to feel that this is not ideal.
It's not ideal for performance, for developer experience,
and not for debugging, because you simply can't put a
pain point here in this method.
It's not running in your computer, it's running in
some node in fling. So this
is on the other hand an example of quickstream doing exactly the
same. It fits into one page, which is first
plus, but b, this function is doing
exactly the same thing as the previous one. It's running in the same runtime,
which means I can do this,
I can just put a breakpoint in that method and debug
it, see what's happening. So imagine here, it could be not one line but
hundredth line, it could be a couple of classes, could be quite complex
engineering, and I can debug it in
my iDe. And I don't
have to rely on jar files. There's no Java, which means I will not get
exceptions like this. This is my own exception. I got when
I was having the right flink connector,
but incorrect. Kafka client jar file.
And then obviously this is not the greatest architecture
of how to run your code. So you have the Java environment,
python environment, they're connecting to each other. There's a difference between local
and cluster deployment. My goodness.
So what is our approach to stream processing? What I want to show you today
is different approach. The combination of Python, Kafka and
kubernetes, a library that will work nicely
with Docker Kubernetes, graceful shutdowns and
Kafka concept to deliver highly
abstracted stream processing for Python developers so
they can use the whole ecosystem of Pip at Conda
and really use machine learning,
math, physics, all of that without
the drudgery of Java engines
and use their favorite ide in
building their pipelines. And our goals
really is to build scalable and reliable system
both on the transportation of the data side and compute
side, which is extensible and correct.
Correct means you can rely on the output regardless
of the hardware failures, network outage,
et cetera. So this is the basic architecture
and you basically see that Kafka,
where you have replication of data and horizontal scale
is then being consumed by your compute side, where you have the containers
running in a kubernetes, in a stateful set
underpinned by the PVC, where you have your state backup by changelock
topic. And when you need more compute you add more instances of your
Python microservice. When you need more transportation of your
data, you add more nodes in your broker. All it's
good. And then is
how we're going to access this library,
what is going to be the API? And because
Python is a huge community of
developers and huge portion of them are
using pandas for offline analysis in Jupyter notebooks,
we have decided to create a library which
would have interface like pandas dataframes. So you
using the muscle memory that you learn on batch in
streaming and you don't have to relearn new API.
So today I want to show you this in action.
And actually I want to kind of demonstrate the theory in practice
by programming the crash detection microservice.
So we're going to look at the sensor data from this app and
we're going to create a
threshold detection. If we go over a certain number of
gforces applied to this phone, we're going
to create an event of a crash. So let's get
to it. So now we are in quicks.
When I have my pipeline that I want to show you today. Here we
have a web gateway which exposing an API
which this application on my phone would use to send the telemetry
into the pipeline. So I'm going to start the pipeline here.
And you should see that this is basically getting green.
Amazing. And if I go to Messages, I'm getting messages through
this endpoint to the topic. If I get just
one random one. Now you see that it's a payload
in a JSON, not really that
friendly for processing, but we're going to solve that in the next
service. In this service we're taking this raw data and
we converting it to much more
tabular type of data like this.
Cool. And then we have third service called
features which I have prepared for kind
of build something new here. So I will clone this
local and go to visual studio code to get coding.
So we are now in visual studio code when I'm running my dev container.
So I have exactly the same environment as I would have in quicks when I
deployed this to the pipeline. And now we're going to develop
the code that would read the data from a sensor in a phone and
look at the actual meter readout.
And if we met some threshold we can create alert.
So let's get to it. So I'm just going to do a python free
main API to see what is in a topic.
Great. So we have some data. So let's
stop it. We see here the accelermeter,
the dimension. So let's just make a filter
where we make sure we're only getting rows where
this is present. And then I
see we have a timestamp in epoch from
1970 nanoseconds. That's not really that readable
for the development. So let's convert that
to a string.
It.
So it requires seconds,
this method. So I'm going to just divide it and then
let's print it.
Yeah, it would be probably better if
we make this a string.
Amazing. And a table like view is
probably going to be a bit
nicer.
So you see all three dimensions and
a timestamp which is current time. If I shake
you see it's going that values up and
down. So first thing we're going to do is calculate a new
column which is going to be the
accelerometer,
absolute value from all dimensions. That will give us kind
of a sense regardless of
the rotation of the phone,
how hard the forces are. And let's
just print timestamp and
this new column.
All right, so if I take the phone into my hand. Oh great,
we're getting high numbers. So that is
almost where we want to be, but this will
be susceptible to kind of bumps when you
hit with your bike, a bump or you
just get a random shaking
of your phone, it would not really be a real crash.
So let's look at let's say one or 2 seconds long
window where we accumulate the forces applied.
So if there is a continuous
forces applied to the phone like you are falling from the rock or
something, we're going to create an alert. So for that
we're going to do a hopping window, so we're going to
do extraction
of this parameter first
and then hopping window of at
2 seconds and we're going to emit
the row every 250 milliseconds
and we're going to get a sum and
we only want a final row of each window.
So let's run it.
Cool. Now obviously we
get the start and of the window and the value to make
it a bit nicer to read. Let's do the same transformation here
with the startup.
And now you can see that this data being generated four times per
second. So that's great. And if I start
doing some simulation of the crash, you see that we
accumulate this value. So now we are kind of in a
good position to just output this result
to output topic like that and
we can just deploy this to our pipeline and connect it to
our APIs or front end.
And so this is how you use Quickstream's library to
process real time data in a broker. Now I hope you saw
how simple is that? So give
it a try.
Here are the QR codes for GitHub. So you can try this
library or look at the code of the library,
or if you want to try to build a whole pipeline
in the cloud, you can sign up for a free tier of our
cloud plus form. I hope you enjoyed this talk. And if
you have any questions, we have a community slack when you
can discuss anything with me or my colleagues, and if
you have any problems with our library when you're kicking the tires,
just let us know, we won't block you. Thank you very much for
listening to this presentation and enjoy the whole conference.