All right, so let's go ahead and break into this PowerPoint a little bit.
And it's going to be super straightforward. Really quick theory,
just because like we all know youll need the theory to
understand the hands on piece and you need the hands on piece to understand the
theory, both them go together. So let's just go ahead and
go through it, but I promise it won't be too much PowerPoint hell. All right,
so first things first. What are secrets? Now youll usually hear
that secrets are like passwords or API keys or something
along those lines. But in reality secrets are really anything that
you don't want in plain text. Now this could be a username for
whatever reason, don't know a specific use case, but maybe you
would want a username and a password to be tied together and
not in plain text. Again, for whatever reason you could go ahead
and you can put that into a secrets now out of
the box. Kubernetes does have the ability to create secrets.
In the core API group there is a resource that you can
use to create secrets. However, here's the
problem with Kubernetes secrets. Now, they are unencrypted by
default. And what I mean by that is when you create a Kubernetes secret,
it's stored in ETCD, which is the Kubernetes data store.
And then from in there it's unencrypted.
So there is zero encryption inside of
ETCD for the secrets. They are stored in plain base 64 text.
Which means if you have access to etCD, if a service account has
access to etCD, if any engineer has access to etCD,
if any attacker gets access to etcD because it's not secure
for whatever reason, yes, they can get direct access to
your secrets. So because of that, when I'm in production environments,
I typically say that we should be going with another secrets
provider, another third party. In fact, there is documentation even
in Kubernetes documentation that states all of this. It's like, listen,
everything is unencrypted by default. You should probably go with a third party
if possible. Now from a third party perspective,
there are a lot of different options. However, I typically go
with Hashcorp vault. And the reason why, other than the fact that
you can kind of just deploy it and not pay anything for it, there is
so much documentation and so many getting started guides and
so many different ways to run it in production that you can read about and
watch videos on and even courses and all that good stuff. So when I'm consulting
for customers, I'm always thinking about not what the latest and greatest is,
but what's actually supported heavily. And Kubernetes
and Vault is supported heavily. And I think the fact
that it's supported, number one speaks to how good
it is. But number two, it goes into just how important,
having documentation and having best practices and all of that is.
So with that, let's go ahead and learn about how we can implement hashcore
vault in our Kubernetes environment. All right, so now that we know why
we would want to use vault, let's go ahead and actually figure out how to
get it installed in Kubernetes. So first things first, we're going to
go ahead and we're going to use helm. Helm is the Kubernetes package manager.
And essentially instead of just going to the raw Kubernetes manifest and running Kubectl
apply or Kubectl create, we can version it with helm,
update it, roll it back, et cetera. So first things first, you want to
make sure you have the Hashicorp repo. Now I already
have that because I have it installed already. So next what I can
do is I can use this install command. Now I'm going to be naming my
chart vault. I'm going to be calling upon the vault
helm chart and then I'm going to use two flags. Well actually a few.
So the first is to enable the UI. The second is to
enable the service type as load balancer. And then next what I'm going to do
is I'm going to specify the vault namespace and I'm going to create that namespace
if it's not already created. All right? And as we can
see, this was deployed. So I'm going to clear
that screen and I'm going to run Kubectl getall namespace
vault. Okay, so notice here
how there are a few things going on. I have the services, I have the
deployments and then the pods right here.
So this container is still creating.
Now we want to wait until it's in the running state so I
can just show this to you really quick. All right,
it's still creating. Let's go ahead and give it a few more minutes or a
few moments should only be seconds. All right, so as we can see,
it is running, but it's not officially available yet. It's saying
zero of one. So what we want to do is I'm going to open
up, well rather I'm going to go to this IP address and if
you're wondering, by the way, I'm running on
aks. You could be running in any cloud, any managed Kubernetes service,
doesn't matter. I just so happen to be running in aks.
So really quick, let's just go ahead and show that again. I'm going to
copy the IP address which is the load balancer
for the vault Ui. And then I'm going to head over to the web browser
really quick. All right. And I'm going to pop that in and then I'm going
to put it over 8200. Okay? So we can see the
UI is up, but it's not unsealed.
That's why you see that zero one there that the container is running,
but it's not available. So what I want to do here
is I am going to run this Kubectl
exec command. And essentially what I'm doing is I'm running the vault operator
init command inside of the container or inside of the pod
rather without actually executing into the pod.
So as you can see, we have a few unsealed keys right here. All right?
And then here's the initial root token. So what
I'm going to do is I'm going to have to run this command three times
because we're going to have to unseal it a few times. So let's
go ahead and run that just like this.
And then I'm going to pop in the first key.
And as you can see, it says one of three. So with vaults you always
have to put in at least three unseal keys. So we have to
do the same thing even though it's running in Kubernetes. Same thing.
All right, so now let's put in the second one.
All right, now it says two of three.
And then finally let's put in the
third here. Got to run the command first.
All right, and as you can see, we are now good to go.
So if I go back to the UI here,
we can now see that it's asking me to sign in.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to scroll up again,
I'm going to get that initial root token, I'm going to
pop it in here. And we are now in and
good to go. However, one thing that I do want
to show is remember this pod used to just
show running, but zero out of one was actually ready. So now if
we run Kubectl, get pods namespace
vault, we can see that it is now officially running.
So our UI is up, Vault is deployed in our Kubernetes cluster.
And. And now we're ready to officially start injecting secrets. And that's
how you can get vault up and running in any Kubernetes. Cluster, thank you
so much for watching.