Hey everyone, I'm Roy, team leader at Firefly. And today I'm going to talk to
you about the AWS CDK and what does it mean for the world of infrastructure
as code? So as I said, as a team leader in Firefly,
what we do is basically look at your entire cloud footprint, or kubernetes
clusters. We fetch them into our console and we
show you on the other end your entire infrastructure as code footprint, whether it's
terraform, Pulumi, cloudformation, CDK of course,
and even helm. In the world of kubernetes, we track them
both together and we show your entire cloud footprint in the means of your infrastructure
as code. We can detect drift in real time and we can help you codify
them back to infrastructure as code in any language you can think of.
AWS part of me working at Firefly. As you can see, I'm very enthusiastic
about Yak. And when I was in the last reinvent,
I saw a huge hype about the CDk tool of AWS and
got into it a bit. So basically at reinvent,
all of the guys coming into our boot estate about the AWS CDK
and how can they use it and how do they start even using CDK
instead of cloudformation or even any other infrastructure AWS code you can
think of. I started searching about it and
saw that CDK is basically a very cool tool that AWS
brought us, and we can migrate our cloudformation very
quickly into CDK and even start new projects in CDK
in a heartbeat. So as you can
see, CDK is basically more of a concept than an AWS tool.
It means cloud development kit and this means that each
infrastructure code tool that is written in code,
whether it's Python,
go typescript and even node JS,
and not written in configuration language such as Yaml's,
JSON and etc, is a cloud development kit.
The AWS CDK is an implementation of AWS to
this concept and is going to be the successor of cloud formation
in AWS. They created it originally and native
to the AWS experience. So using the AWS CDK is
a very comfortable experience when you're deployments into AWS resources.
Also, you can use any
coding language you can think of, whether it's typescript, which is originally created
in, or Golden Python node JS and moro
tools are on the way. So how
does AWS CDK works and what is it different from the cloud formation?
So as you can see, CDK is basically written
over the cloud formation and it uses the cloudformation stacks
to deploy your code into the AWS resources.
Basically, you can use any language you can think of, as we already said,
and then you create constructs, you create your AWS resources in code.
You can create any resource of
AWS that you were able to create with cloudformation
through the CDK code. And after creating the
CDK project, let's call it, you can just create CDK,
synth and deploy. And you create your resources
on your AWS cloud through
cloud formation stacks, as you can see in the map over here.
So first of all, you do the CDk sync command.
It's basically planning your code into
state file that is going to be created on your cloud.
And after running the command CDk deploy the
command, will create the resources on your cloud,
will save the state file on s three bucket on your cloud,
and also create the cloudformation stacks that was deploying
your resources on the cloud.
If that's the case, then who should use CDK and when?
So basically, first of all, all cloudformation users should use CDK.
Why? Because it's super easy to migrate into CDK.
It's natively AWS such as cloudformation, and it's
also super comfortable to work in. If you're even working with Stackset
or deploying into multi regions, Cloudformation won't be able to
do it. And you'll need to use Stackset, which is like patch over cloudformation,
to create stacks in multiple regions. In CDK,
it's natively written because it's just code, and you can create models to
deploy in each region out of the stack that you already created
in CDK. Even more than that, AWS oriented
DevOps and SRE teams will be much like to use the CDK,
even if they're not using cloudformation at the moment. Doing it with
any other languages such as terraform or even Pulumi.
Moving to CDK is going to be a native experience for AWS
users, so it's also a good idea to work with.
And lastly, any other enthusiast
of infrastructure AWS code can start working with CDK, create some projects and
see if it's fun to play with. I guarantee a very good experience
out of it when. So if you're
already using any cloudformation projects,
then you should use CDK right away. As I said, super easy migration
and you can just start playing with CDK. Do it much easier than
creating the messy yamls or JSons of Cloudformation,
and you'll see the difference right away.
Another time to start is if you start a
new infrastructure called Project and you think about the
tool to work with, if it's going to be on AWS, then it's sure to
have with CDK. So let's talk
a bit about the pros and cons of AWS CDK. So as
I said, the pros are pretty much straightforward. It supports
multiple languages if it's typescript that it's originally created in
JavaScript, Python, Java Net and even
Golang. Also, it doesn't require any
DSL or config such as JSon or YAMls.
You can create complex yak projects with it. As you know,
cloud formation is super messy code to write, and if
you're going to create a big project, it's going to be a hell. The dependencies
are going to be huge, and if you're creating links between assets,
it's not going to work or it's going to be a hell for you to
maintain and develop. Also, as I said, the multi region operations,
you don't need to use taxit, you can just create any models you wish
and you'll do it on any region you want. And also lastly,
it's AWS oriented. So basically it's going
to be the best experience on AWS cloud if you're going to do infrastructure as
code at all. Also, if you're using any other CDK,
as I said, if the concept is not AWS invention such as CDK
for terraform or CDK for kubernetes, then other
CDK is going to match better for you and not the AWS one.
So let's see some code. As you can see here,
I have two files. One defines a
CDK stack, creates an S three bucket
and an SQS queue out of a new resources that you can see
on your code. And the last resource
is a cloud formation import. I basically already have a
cloud formation as you can see on the others window that defines
an EC two instance. And by migrating all
the AML of the cloud formation into this stack, I will basically
have the CDK in this CDK stack.
And in heartbeat I just imported the entire cloudformation into
CDK and it's just easy as that. You can take huge examples
of yamls or JSON's cloudformation, you can just import them into CDK and
in heartbeat you will be migrated and you can just keep on working
with CDK instead of cloudformation, which is basically amazing.
Also, as you can see here, after clicking
synth and deploy, I deployed my CDK
stack into AWS through a cloud formation stack.
I also have my state files in an S three bucket and these
two stacks were created out of the deploy. The first one, the CDK
toolkit, is code stack that
is creating the necessary resources on your AWS,
such as the bucket the state file is going to be saved in. And the
other stack here is my CDK deploy
that I ran and as you can see, I created a
bucket, an SQS, and also the migrated cloud
formation which is now supported in my new CDK stack
and AWS. You can see it's defining an EC two instance straight out of
my CDK call, even though it was created on Cloudformation,
which is amazing.
So this was my lecture, and now I want to talk to you about two
important key takeaways that I wish to pass on.
So the first one, CDK, is a rising technology.
It's still in its few first steps,
and it's probably going to get much bigger in the next few months.
I absolutely recommend you to use the CDK now
instead of later on. Migrate your project and make your
life much better when using AWS, CDK and the
other one. If you're a cloudformation user, then you're even more
recommended to go into CDK and start working with it
and you'll see the magic happens in few
minor steps. Thank you everyone
with Roy. I'd like to keep in touch for any
questions you have. You can see my mail here. So thank you so much and
have an amazing day.