Hello and thank you for joining me today at Conf 42,
Cloud native. Today I'm going to give a talk on something that
I feel very passionately about and I think is absolutely one
of the most exciting new trends in cloud native, even though it has been around
for longer than, longer than might meet the eye.
Initially, my talk is on ephemeral environments,
and it's called redefining preproduction, because with these environments,
we're are seeing pre production environments
catching up to the advancements that have been made in production
application deployment. My name is Natalie Lunbeck and I work
at Shipyard, and I'm also the primary author of Ephemeralinvironments
IO, which is an open source community resource guide.
You can go there right now. You can also check out our GitHub open a
PR if you have anything you'd like to contribute. Always looking for
new stuff there. All right, so let's get started.
So I wanted to give a quick overview of what we're talking about today.
I wanted to start off with how teams are using ephemeral environments,
but most of all, how teams are using static environments, because many of them
are stuck there not necessarily by choice, but by
habit. I wanted to introduce the concept of ephemeral environments,
and then I wanted to kind of go into how ephemeral environments
exactly simplify the SDLC software development lifecycle.
All right, so this slide, depending on
how well you know it, this might be something that
gives you a lot of stress and anxiety. And hopefully it doesn't. Hopefully,
your environment workflow does not look like this. But if it
does, you can very much see why we
do not like this. Well, first off, this is not
reduced or abstracted. You probably might
only have four static environments total for your whole team,
which is absolutely crazy. When you think about the volume of PRs that you
have opened every day, how are you possibly supposed to
test those one by one in this,
which you really can't? That's where bottlenecks come in.
And then one of the things about this image that gives me the most anxiety
is you can see how these environments are actually just coupled
together, and they share a lot of dependencies. And if you know
how easy it is to break staging, you also know
how staging can then in turn take down all your other
environments. And you never want to be that person on your team.
So fingers crossed, this isn't what you're doing. But if you are
doing that, you've probably thought about a
more modern solution, because this has been done
for a very long time. And I think modern application
workflows, like, we've had so many advancements in production,
but why is pre productionlike stuck in the past the way that it is?
And that's something that I want to talk about, because if you do
have a static environments workflow
set up, you've probably thought about how you can change that, but you
know that it isn't exactly anything trivial.
So I wanted to define what exactly is an
ephemeral environment. And this is courtesy of ephemeralinvironments
IO. It is a short lived, encapsulated deployment of an application,
automatically leveraged on every code change through Gitops.
Sounds pretty great, right? Let's go a little further into that.
They are robust on demand copies of your application for running
tests, previewing features, and collaborating async across teams.
So this is honestly instantly an improvement,
because before, if you had queues
of PRs going into staging and maybe you
had another testing environment, but you really didn't
get to do the type of comprehensive and frequent testing that
you would desire. Ephemeral environments would mean that in
theory you really could just open a PR, which would trigger
a workflow to spin up an ephemeral environment, and it would
automatically trigger the rest of your CI workflow that might not even be
run till production. So it would be running your end to end tests,
your integration tests, and of course unit tests, even though those are
a little easier to do. Although end to
end tests and integration tests obviously need to interact with your database,
so you are going to need some full stack application there.
So this is already a game changer, but I think
that you know that. And hopefully,
again, hopefully this is not your SDLC, but this is what it tends to
look like with long lived environments, environments that never turn off.
You're developing to the point where you're ready to open a pull request and
then queue in one of your colleagues for code review, merge it
to main, deploy it to staging, along with everything
else that might get deployed to staging in a day,
and against all like 15 of those PRS
branch that are merged into staging, your end to end tests are going to run.
And without doubt, I think it's pretty fair
to say that this might break something. This might take down
your staging environment, which is not necessarily bad.
I think it's always great to uncover bugs. It's always a learning experience,
but that's not great, because maybe your staging environment is
coupled to your other static environments, so everything's taken down
and oh well, nobody else's features have been able to be
tested. So that's a pretty major concern. So then
you're going to go back, you're going to hope that you're fixing
the correct bug, but I guess you won't know for a few days because you'll
open that PR, you'll loop in someone again for a code review, merge it
to main, deploy it to staging, and really hope that you fixed
your bug there. But at that point it's been days and days in between,
and you might keep repeating this depending on how
complex your fix is. And you really want to
see those results which you can't necessarily see on your local
environment because of all the dependencies that
you might not have access to until later on in the pipeline.
And then of course at a certain point it passes and
along with a bunch of other things, it's deployed to production, which is
great, but that's a pretty slow release process and
I don't think that that's at all ideal and it's something
that you could be doing a lot faster with.
Of course, now that environments have caught up to
application infrastructure. So I wanted
to just show you a visual of what this looks like when you're using ephemeral
environments. And this is really nice because now we can visualize multiple
things at once, multiple branch being worked on. This is
when you're developing a feature to these point where it's ready
to be opened as a pull request. And then you just
click open pull request and immediately
your CI workflow, probably the same one that you're using much later
in your pipeline, gets triggered and it takes that URL
from your ephemeral environment, points it to your end to end tests, points your
end to end tests to it, and they run against the environment and
then that way they'll uncover bugs within 15
minutes or however long they take to run after you've opened that PR.
So instead of context switching, you can just kind of sit back,
relax, wait for your test to fail and then go right
back. And you can take a lot more risks here, get a lot done
faster just because you're aware that you have this opportunity
to correct them kind of on the spot instead of several days
later. So this is really nice, so everyone can
merge their PR with confidence, merge it to main, deploy it to
staging, and of course your end to end tests will run
again on your staging environment. But this time it's really nice because
they're running against branches that have already been tested.
So anything that they're looking for are just conflicts between the
branches being interacting together instead of
bugs, and the standalone branches themselves. And then you can deploy,
and we tend to see people deploying around 50% faster,
50% more features, which is absolutely great.
Why wouldn't you do it this way? So I wanted to
introduce to you a project. I mentioned this at the beginning,
but this is my open source community site,
maintained with a few other excellent contributors. It's called ephemeralinvironments
IO. And back in 2021, when I was
starting working with shipyard, I was trying to learn about
ephemeral environments. This was a new concept to me, and I
really realized pretty quickly that there are no online resources
on ephemeral environments. So I talked to my team and I
talked to some other professionals in the cloud native community,
and they gave me some great best practices that ephemeral environments
should have in an ideal world. And I wanted to talk to you about them,
because if you're building or looking for an ephemeral environment
solution, it really should check all these boxes in
order for you to get these most value out of such a solution.
Wanted to go into the six pillars of things that we deemed most
important to ephemeral environments, and the first one
of those is the dev workflow. So really in
a perfect world, ephemeral environments should integrate into your dev workflow
pretty seamlessly with no overhead. I mean, you usually
would configure them with your git provider, and then
you should just be able to develop normally, press all the buttons
you normally do, use the same exact git workflow
and they will just pop up. And generally
what this looks like is when you open a PR that triggers your
CI workflow and your ephemeral environment management platform
is listening for changes, and it will spin up ephemeral environments,
it will spin up one based on your PR and it will give
you a link which you can access it, and then every commit you make
thereafter on that PR will also be reflected in the same environment.
And this is honestly really great for development, because as
you're working on a branch, you can keep making changes and then seeing them live,
interacting with them in ways that they would behave in
production, which honestly, you don't normally get that until you're
actually in production. And this is really great for
QA. It simplifies it, it allows QA to happen
much earlier on in the pipeline, and then also on an individual per
branch basis instead of multiple features
being tested in tandem. And then it should be to
the point where you have the confidence, where once you merge a branch,
you feel like it's tested, it passes
all these cases, even your end to end tests are able to
be run against it. So you can kind of almost skip
that staging step and just deploy it with confidence, which feels
really good to do. And then another
feature is that ephemeral environments should promote collaboration,
especially across teams that don't normally get to work
together this easily. So for example, developers working with
developers, a nice thing about this is code review can happen
much earlier, and it can happen in addition to
traditional code review. They can interact with a production like environment
and see those changes, and they can contribute to the
branch and see their changes spun up in that same environment.
So it's honestly an excellent place for collaboration.
Also wonderful place for product to work with developers,
because product can give developers a plan
for a feature, developers can make that happen, share the
link and product can interact with it instead of just seeing a
screen share or screenshots or just
any type of non thorough interaction that wouldn't really
give them the idea of how a feature should be becoming.
So it's really great because they're able to interact with it as much as
they might need in an as realistic environment as possible.
And then of course, as we talked about a little earlier, this is much
easier for QA as well to collaborate, just because they can check
out a branch much earlier on in the process and both user
test it and run automated tests, which does bring us to
our next point, which is testing. So ephemeral environments,
one of their biggest use cases is for testing,
and that's both user and automated testing because
they are very solid environments
for both. The type of testing that you don't normally get to do
sometimes until production even.
And what makes this so easy is they use your CI
CD pipeline and generally what you can do, since they're so easily
shareable and accessible, you can just point your
CI CD pipeline at the ephemeral environments and it
can use that link and that bypass to run the tests
against it. And this, I'm going to say this word a lot, but it
promotes more user authenticated testing and QA,
more testing more often. You're able to do it as
soon as a feature is ready and more and more times.
And because you're doing it at the feature level and then also on every subsequent
merge you are testing, sometimes we see 40
times more often, which sounds fake, but no
people have done it, which is really absolutely
crazy, but it can never be a bad thing.
More and more and more testing is absolutely what you want.
It's never a bad thing to catch bugs earlier. And your
team is often very thankful because nobody likes
to delay a release. And one of the
virtues of ephemeral environments is they're on demand. So you should
absolutely go all in with this, and you
should make them Gitops first. They should really spin up when a
branch is ready. I know I keep saying this, but it's absolutely
essential to them. There really shouldn't be any manual intervention
that prevents people from using them. So if they are Gitops
enabled, they should be there on significant code
changes, and then they should go away on their own to not incur additional
cloud costs. And because of this, there's no
time limit, really. You can have async collab, let's say
you're working in the morning and you want to collaborate with someone who
has later hours than you. You can just spin it down,
wait a few hours, and then your coworker can spin it up and work
on it then. And nobody's getting blocked because everyone's on their
own schedule and you're not worried about incurring additional
costs because this is so much cheaper than your current static
solution. And it's really nice because you will have more of these.
So everyone can have as many
environments as they want. You could really even have one per branch and
have them just whenever you need them, which is
huge virtue. And this is a very important
section. It's something that you absolutely can't overlook. But I would
like to say, I mean, I'd like to say that because they're isolated,
ephemeral environments tend to be more secure.
They should be entirely decoupled from any dependencies or other
environments. And this isn't just for security reasons, but also
just so in case something breaks, they don't take down your entire
environment pipeline. But you still should be sure to take a few
measures into account. One of those is sanitizing your data. You should remove
any PIi just because you shouldn't be testing
with it anyway. So not exclusive to ephemeral environments,
of course, but still very important. And then you should
enable SSO. You really shouldn't be doing any of
the authentication logic on your own. That's just
one more thing to worry about, one more vulnerability. And when you use an SSO
provider, maybe you're using GitHub, maybe Google,
then you don't really need to worry about any
breaches because that's on them.
But you are also able to have introduced granularity
and make sure that you're only allowing people from your
organization or people who might be stakeholders. And then
the last, but certainly not the least, probably one
of the most important considerations for ephemeral environments is
cost control. And this is really nice because since they
are ephemeral by nature, they're short lived, they are really
cost efficient by nature, which is not just great for your
organization's wallet, but also great for the environment, because you're
not using electricity that you don't need to be using.
If you're using the cloud in an elastic way, you're really only using
the resources that you need. And this takes
us into another great benefit, is you don't really tend
to encounter the same resource constraints that your team might have had previously.
And a big part of this is because
when you have just a few static environments going 24/7
that's just a lot of time that you're not using them. So of course you
can only afford a few of them to really be cost effective.
But if you have environments that only last for a few hours, if even
that each, you can really have as many environments as you want at
a given time and still come out ahead with your savings.
I wanted to thank you very much for joining me today as I talked
about ephemeral environments. I certainly hope you found
something useful from this presentation and if you have any more questions
or would like to talk more or find out how you can contribute to
ephemeralinvironments IO, you can email me.
Natalie at Shipyard build always happy to talk about this and
I thoroughly enjoy giving this presentation. I love talking about
ephemeral environments and I think that they're just such a fun and interesting
topic, and I'm very glad that they've picked up the pace in recent years
and I'm looking forward to see seeing what the environment landscape looks
like in a few years. Well, thank you again and I hope you enjoy the
rest of comp 42 cloud native. There are some great talks coming up
and I know you won't be disappointed. All right, have a wonderful
rest of your day. Thank you.