You.
Good morning. Good afternoon everyone. Welcome in this session
of Conf 42. Today, I'm excited to delve
with you into increasingly important aspects of our digital world,
container security. As we integrate more with
sophisticated technology into our workflow, understanding and
securing our containers environment has never been more crucial
than today. So join me in this session of cracking the
code of cloud security. We will focus today on protecting containers,
infrastructure and workloads. Let me share with you
a couple of striking statistics
based on Aqua Security report. In 2021,
about 40% of containers images are pulled from public
resources. This fact alone underscores
the far reliance and publicly available
resources in our container ecosystems.
There's a lot of resources out there, but what does it mean for security?
While public resources offers a wealth of
useful tools and efficiency, they can also bring inherent
risk, such as potential vulnerabilities and unvetted content.
Compounding these numbers with
an issue of having 12% of containers
were running as a non root user, which is a
best practice in container security. So we can see that
this is a notable point because running containers as a non root
is a recommended best practice in container security. It significantly
reduced the risk of privileged escalation attacks which can led to unauthorized
access and control over containerized application.
So as we progress today through our presentation,
we'll explore what these statistics mean for
your security posture, the challenges that they present and
the strategies that we can implement to safeguard our containerized application.
So let's dive in and start to unveil the complexity
of container security.
I'm today with you. I'm Fouadmulla. I'm a seasoned cloud security architect
and the lead consultant. I worked with many multinational companies to
secure their workloads and infrastructure, specifically focusing on the cloud
and multi cloud administration. I'm CISM and CISP and
SAS plus certified. Feel free to connect with me
on LinkedIn. I'm happy to share with you thoughts and perspectives
regarding security. Good,
let's start with the agenda. So there will have a couple of main
topics. First of all, introduction,
the background of this presentation and the container security challenges
that we might face that we face inherited from the container
security nature. Cloud containers,
vulnerabilities and container security in the terms of devsecops,
enhancing security and going beyond the defaults.
Also some kind of tools for automated vulnerability management that
we can use and configuration management and network segmentation. A few
points also best practices in container security.
Let's get started first.
Essentially, you don't really need containers to ensure
security of your application. There's plenty of technologies and tools
that you can use. However, by using containers
wisely and many lines under wisely, you can
really enhance your application security.
Containers are not really prerequisites to say for securing
application, but if you use it in a
good manner, you can offer a runtime separation
of your app. On host you can only deploy what you
need. So there is
a smaller attack surface, it's easier
to set up, which means it's easier to patch.
There is a predefined setup, so which can increase also consistency,
which all the security personnel loves as overall
improved security through their isolated nature,
which can help in containing breaches, for example minimizing the
impacts. However, this benefit is only realized if
the containers are managed and configured securely. Adhering to best
practices in containers security also
to say you don't really need advanced security tools
to start with containers. There's a lot of open sources, there's a lot
of technology in there which you can use,
but you really need to consider security to effectively use containers.
Using containers without thinking about security is
a recipe for a disaster. So always
good to understand implement security best practices like let's say images scanning
container isolation list privileges
access zero trust principles are really essential to maintain the
security and the integrity of the containerized environment.
So challenges in container security first of
all, there's a couple of points here, I just state a couple of them.
There's a lot actually. First, the daemon
attack surface. So it's
inherited from the essence of the technology we are using. There is a
potential vulnerability in the containers own systems. It's relatively
a new technology similar to the
virtualization on the VMS and virtual machines, but it's far
behind in regards of vulnerabilities
in this new technology, secrets management.
And here, when I say secrets, I'm not only referring to
credentials, passwords, et cetera, et cetera,
but more also referring to the containers
images itself. This has to be considered as also
as a sensitive, and we'll see this afterwards in a couple of slides.
There's also untrusted content risk.
There's a danger of using, for example,
compromised and vulnerable images.
There's challenges in the growing environment of containers and
also the ephemeral runtimes, which can
have kind of special characteristics in incidence
management and such, also in the lightweight
isolation risks. So this can have also a lot of challenges to
be considered. For example,
when speaking of the daemon, only trusted users should
have access to the API. We have to set also operation system
permissions. We shouldn't expose this API
unless it's really needed and using KLS
and patching the system whenever possible.
There's a couple of challenges actually in tracking and managing this
on a large scale dynamic environment. Special limitation
from WAFS and ids and ips
in this regard, containers offer
relatively weaker, as I mentioned, separation than VM.
So this has to be considered in many scenarios of
breakout. There's also security operations.
Teams need to have some kind of a good pictures of
what threats are going on this dynamic environment. So collaboration
is really important. He has to come to the organizational
culture to be coherent
with this technology and to be empowering the team.
So without help from SEC Ops,
the build process could be really stalled due to allocate undetected
vulnerabilities, since containers in the
nature are ephemeral, meaning that
they quickly spin out and really fast being
destroyed. So it's really hard to detect and monitor changes on
it, especially in complex systems. Also,
it's sharing resources like cpus and then a lot of
resources from the host. So it's really challenging to track,
to have a track of records of what's going on on the physical system in
my opinion to help really the SEC ops to help you look
into the security tools that provide comprehensive visibility without interfering
with your job. So the right tool should give you the sufficient metrics,
numbers, logs that you need to properly monitor
and measure the health. Don't forget
also to observe the network as this is kind of, let's say
no brainer in security and cloud security cloud
containers vulnerabilities are here. Basically it's kind
of a summary. This list can go on and forth.
There's a lot of points that we cloud mention, but here
are a couple of points. So the images images has to
be dealt really as a sensitive information.
These images can, if it's not tracked and scanned, it might
contain vulnerabilities or any outdated components.
Also, if these page images are not regularly updated or scanned,
this can pose a potential security risk.
There is also the insecured containers runtime configuration.
I will touch about this a little bit further, but in essence default configuration
is not secured containers and
misconfiguration is kind of tight. There is no
default by sorry, there's no secure by default setup
in contest, so it has to be looked at from
early stages. Usually we found
vulnerabilities in the network segmentation. This is sometimes forgotten
from the setup containers sharing resources on
the network. So if one compromise, this can be potential
privilege escalation or
a container escape risk. Without request segmentation,
the attacker can potentially gain access to other containers on the host system.
Also the escape vulnerabilities I just mentioned orchestrator
vulnerabilities that the orchestrators like for example kubernetes
can have. Vulnerabilities that if exploited
can really lead to a cluster wide impact. So it can have
really hard and tough implications on your organization.
This includes issues with API configuration and setup
and authentication mechanism. Also sometimes dependencies can
be kind of challenging or a challenging vulnerability.
And container registry there is solution out there so keep
track of what container registry you wish to use.
But it's crucial to use trusted registry and scan the images
for vulnerabilities of course, as well as logging and monitoring
the gaps. Finally, using immutable
and informal nature,
this can pose really vulnerability of incident
investigation and containers might
be terminated and replaced before the investigation can be taken place.
So that has to be in the incidence plan being somehow
tackled as well as with the logging and keeping all the records that
might be needed for such a case.
So let me share with you kind of a little of insights
of a cloud setup regarding contentious. However really
you can use any technology here, I'm referring to the AWS
cloud, but you can use Azure, you can use Google,
all is good. Good to mention a couple of points here.
So for example you can use the code commit
service from AWS, but I really highlight
the use of code guru for tracking
if there's any credentials or any sensitive
information that is embedded in the code. So you can have early stages
check. You can also use tools on
the dev team with the dev team, but this is also kind of a second
or multi layer defense methodology.
I would like to highlight. Well also probably possible to
use the AWS secret manager here. You can see that we are using it
for managing the secrets on the production and on the
environment. Good to mention
as well the use of for example the SAS
scanning. Well there is a lot of technology that here I kept it
open, but for example Dockerfile
lint, it's a rule pays linter for docker files from Red Hat,
can check the syntax and run semantics and check for best
practices. And it's really customized with the Yaml language
so you can just right away use it. Also another smart SaaS
tool can be used is hadulint,
which also you can get access to it. It's available and
it really gives you really good insights regarding
your container or regarding your image.
Also you can have, well obviously you might have
DAS protecting. This is on the interface level so your options
is quite wide and open. And finally use
the identity and access management on your cloud setup. That's kind of no brainer.
And keeping your watch, cloud watch here,
logging and checking all the logs on production and
also as needed on the other environments to
ensure integrity and track of records.
This is in a nutshell.
Typically when you are using cloud and
especially with devsecops, we are in a race
for deployment and for speed of
pushing features. So it's a good practice to use infrastructure
as a code. It can really streamline the process and keep the consistency
in the environment. So how
to enhance the security? Let's go a little bit beyond defaults and
this is let's say a good takeaway from this presentation.
So always the dockers. For example, built in sandboxing
and runtime protection are a very good start. However, it's not a
never complete solution, so always have to work a little bit further.
Always the balance between developer flexibility and the security
on the other hand, so find the right equilibrium between
the ease of the developer and make a robust security protocols.
Finally, managing images with care it's very good to highlight treat containers
images as sensitive data, implement strict
access control, jugular review and scan the content of images.
So also how to enhance the security. Also beyond the default
here I made a kind of like further points that
were good to mention. Always use trusted paste
images. So start with official minimal as
much as possible base images avoid unnecessary packages,
unnecessary tools to reduce the attack surface.
Regularly scan for vulnerabilities so make
this part of the pipeline of deployment and development.
Implement list privileges access this
is kind of essential and
use immutable containers. So containers should be always immutable and
disposable only deployed and they should
not be modified. If any change needed, we replace
the whole containers with a new one. And as much as possible
let's use read only file system. So this will reduce
a lot of potential persistence by malicious
actors. Manage the secrets securely
so use a good tool and good system to handle sensitive data and
never hard code secrets. In containers images
use secure network best practices,
network segmentation and also good to mention
resource limitation. So enforce some limits
on your resources to prevent any DOS
attacks and exhaustion on the system resources
using policies and security context
for example when utilizing orchestrator features like Kubernetes
security context, pod security policies or
equivalent in other orchestrator to enforce these security policies,
use isolation as much as possible, especially when
speaking with sensitive data. For example a strong mechanism can be used.
The GVSR or kata containers can be
really good tools or also you can use
the native hypervisor based containers to isolate it
on the host system.
Configuration management will touch on in a couple of slides
and of course keep the security embedded in your pipeline.
So integrate security with checks, continuous development and deployment
and make education awareness among the whole organization.
A couple of tools here just to highlight for automated vulnerability
management is really useful to use anchor it's an engine. It's an
open source tool for image inspection and vulnerability scanning.
Can access via GitHub. It provides a really centralized
service for inspection and analyzes. So the anchor engine can
be integrated with the CI CD pipeline to
ensure the odd that only secure and compliant containers are deployed to production.
Another also good tool is Claire,
developed by Coreos.
It's possible to get it from GitHub designed to scan
containers for non vulnerabilities. What is good and nice that give you the
ranking of the CVE so you can get the numbers and
you can identifying security issues in early stages to be addressed.
There's a lot of tools out there. Also good to mention AWS image
scanners in private registry, so it can be also used
for making sure that your images are scanned and in
a good health before deployment.
Few points regarding configuration management and network segmentation.
I would highly recommend implement micro segmentation. So always
fine grained network policies as much as possible control communication between
your microservices and containers. Leverage the
namespace so utilizing this in kubernetes to segment the resources,
it's kind of a good boundary for the network policies.
Also use network policies,
for example especially in kubernetes to define which network
configuration connection is allowed or blocked by default.
Make block or deny for everything. Then start to add what
you need based on your setup.
Isolate sensitive workload,
especially when dealing with compliance.
If you have like a compliance issue that it's really helpful if you
start from sensitive cloud workload isolated
and then opening, let's say what you need
from this workload to be processed or to be used so that can help you
in your journey for compliance always.
This can reduce the risk of exposure to other network
traffic. Encrypt the container's traffic.
Use tls to communicate.
Make audits regular and periodic audits
so it can give you some insights regarding also your policies.
Good to mention. Also using the service meshes, it's really
good technology. It can help you to go deeper on
the level of containers. So for example istio
or link card, you can use it for advanced traffic control monitoring
between your services. Monitor these activities
and integrate with your security tool. So if you have a WAF or
technology you are using ids or IPS, you can use it
for make another layer of logs and checks
on your network. So let's recap
few points here I'd like to highlight. First of all, containers can really improve
your security if used wisely. So as
we've seen, it has a really good potential has to be took into
consideration all the setup beforehand. Docker is not
secure by default and in a sense containers is not secured as a system
is not secured by default. Never depend on the vanilla configuration.
Always do your own setup and your own care
of this technology. Always read images
as a sensitive data. As we
could see there is a lot of vulnerability and potential gaps
that could be happening if you are not tracking your
images.
Finally, also follow network and configuration best practices.
I shared with you a couple of them. There's a lot more so you can
always keep track of these kind of best practices.
Finally, use automated tools as much as possible to integrate your
security into rescue into your DevOps pipeline.
Finally, I wish you that no image
of yours has any image
problem. So thank you for joining me in this session
and feel free to connect with me via LinkedIn and happy to
be with you here. If you have any question, reach out to
me and have a great day. Thank you for joining me
in session and have
a good day.