Hello everyone and welcome to my talk. As I mentioned in my introduction,
today I'm going to present Piacere, a research and development
project founded by the European Union.
And Piacere is all about DevsecOps, all about automating
devsecops, all about ensuring that Devsecops is usable
in customers'environment. This presentation has
been prepared by me and Pablo Schibeck.
We are both from seven bullscom and a
little bit about ourselves. So in this project especially, we are
acting as a research and development center in polish center
Badavcheros voyove. We have the status in Poland and in
France as well. And I guess this is
enough about us. Let's get going with the topic of the
presentation. So regarding the devsecops,
quick reminder. So in general this conference is all about devsecops.
So I'm guessing you know what devsecops is,
but a little quote from Gartner's it glossary on
what devsecops is. So Gartner claims Devsecops is
the integration of security into emerging, agile it and DevOps
development as seamlessly and as transparently as possible.
And basically as it goes on. Ideally this is
done without reducing the agility or speed of developers or requiring them to
leave the development toolchain environment. And precisely
this is where Piacere aims to fit in.
As we know, devsecops is hard
in general. So the experience shows that
many companies are struggling to add this sec to DevOps.
Even if they moved already to DevOps. Some companies are still
struggling to move to this more agile, formal DevOps. So that is one part of
the equation. Another part is that adding security to DevOps
is not as easy as it seemed, at least initially
to some. So this is the framework that is going to make
it easier for those companies who struggle with
adding security to their DevOps pipelines.
And a little why
do we need SEC in DevOps? Again, based on
this conference, I guess I don't have to persuade you too
much at least, but a quick slide about that.
So security, security.
So security is important in general. But then if we consider DevOps
and agility that comes from DevOps, when you have
your infrastructure all software defined, you have software that
powers your infrastructure, that powers your software.
Again, you are adding new points to be attacked
in those scenarios, and thus you need security
for your DevOps as well.
Additionally, if you consider the agility, the agility comes
with increased frequency of built and deployment
processes, and this increases the attack surface.
So in general, recent news about the attacks
on the delivery chain,
on the way that we deploy our infrastructure, the way that we deploy,
for example, our containers show how security is important
at this stage as well. And another point
to mention is that heterogeneity of infrastructure is another
risk. So if you consider agility, if you consider the
frequency, if you consider the heterogeneity, then the
security part is a must, in that if you want
your DevOps to be sustainable, to really affect
your business in only a positive way, let's say security
in DevOps is crucial. So devsecops all the way.
And here I introduce piacere. And as I mentioned
the introduction, piacere is actually an acronym.
So it's this very long sentence
being acronymized into piacere. So Pichera is actually programming
trustworthy infrastructure as code in a secure framework.
So the framework itself is supposed to be secure. The framework
is all about the infrastructure as code. So the way we do DevOps normally,
and making sure that this infrastructure as code is
trustworthy so that it is secure as well.
And a quick recap, this is a horizon 2020 project in
software developers call our consortium consists of twelve organizations,
and those range from academia, business and government.
And consortium is led by Technalia and
Technalia is from Spain. So the project started a
year ago. Now that you're watching this video, it has already
been a year since it started. And we at seven
Bluescoscom, we are responsible for the integration part.
So ensuring that everything works in the end, let's say.
And also the part about the Canary sandbox environment, more on that
later. And here about the tools
of Piacere devsecops. So this is probably already
familiar to you, what could be the goals of DevOps
and security in DevOps. So first and foremost is obviously
to develop, build and deploy applications, because otherwise what's
the point of doing this? Then again, as I mentioned,
this heterogeneity, so we are moving
towards the cloud. If someone hasn't moved toward the cloud,
then they are probably going to
hybridizing the environment. So doing something on premises,
doing something in fog, doing something in edge, and also
having those multi cloud deployments when some services are running
in a different crowd from the other services, or even load balancing
the traffic via those multicloud
deployments, similarly maintaining
and figuring the infrastructure, because if you want to get your applications on
something, then this something is the infrastructure. So the infrastructure
is actually the main part of
modeling in piacere.
And with that goes the optimization of the
usage of resources. So the infrastructure resources that are given
to our applications are going to be optimized so that the
optimal set of resources is being used at all times,
as well as given this framework for testing the deployments and
testing the infrastructure in general. And the
final goal is what usually butchers the
security in DevOps, in infrastructure in general,
is the concept of snowflakes. So if
you don't remember what snowflakes is, I urge
you to look it up quickly. But in essence,
Snowflake is a server that was specifically
crafted for some purpose and it
hasn't really gone through some regular procedure.
Let's say in a company it has been manually configured,
for example, to achieve some level of performance, to deploy
some very custom application that is generally not supported
inside an enterprise, and then left as it is,
perhaps some administrator has already moved on to another
company, and then you are left with this snowflake that has been very much
cared for at some point in time, but in general the
time has forgotten about it. And then you've got this conflict drift and
the conflict drift. So anything that you are not expecting,
that you are not monitoring, that you don't know that has drifted
from the great standards that you have set for yourself,
may affect your actual security. So that
is some point to consider and the framework is actually disallowing
you from doing this. So this is discouraged
both in documentation, let's say, as well as
in the approach that is kind of forced on you.
So moving on to the key features of your chair.
So yet again, the integrated security principles
in those DevOps operations. So the development and
the actual deployment as operations agile approach
without losing security level. So that's
the key feature, one of the key features, sandboxing guide to test
the dynamic properties to be deployed infrastructure.
So this created to the cannabis sandbox environment. I'm going to talk about
it more soon as well.
Another important point, and I want to stress this
particular one out as single source of truth. So if
you've been exposed to term such as git ops,
when you are supposed to control all the
config that you have via git repository,
this framework is actually designed to work with that.
So that you have this single source of truth, you have this git
repository when you have all the configs,
when you version them, when you ensure that they
are managed properly, et cetera. So this access control, accountability of
that procedure, this is probably one
of the most important points to take, if anything,
from this presentation. Basically,
if you consider those snowflakes that I have just mentioned,
the way to ensure that you don't end up
with snowflakes is to have procedures to control access
to the actual config that is being deployed. And the best
way that we have as a humanity developed so
far is the usage of version control systems. And nowadays
this is most of the time git knowing that
some folks still using subversion. So if you are using subversion then it's
fine as well because the general principles are the most important ones.
But you know the drill. Another key feature already
mentioned as well regarding the multi cloud approach, cloud agnosticism.
So that we are not fitting into one offer,
for example from Amazon Web services, but we are considering all
the other potential cloud providers,
obviously the major ones like the Microsoft Asia,
like the Google Cloud platform, but also all those
platforms, public clouds with running OpenStack.
So in general the cloud agnosticism is a key feature of petrare and
also important part automatic healing and
optimization. So ensuring that the
infrastructure that has been defined first
of all doesn't drift away from the actual configuration and
is healthy at all the times, and also
proposing optimizations to the way that the infrastructure
scope is defined.
And here is how we are going to go about that.
So as I mentioned, this is quite
a young project. So we are only a year in and
this is some architecture that we have designed
so far for piacere. First of
all, we are going to have some ide for the user where
the user is supposed to actually design the
infrastructure as code, and the infrastructure as code is actually designed
using an intermediary language called Dumml DevOps
modeling language, more on that later as well.
And as you can see on this diagram in the left upper corner,
you have design time. So these are all the parts that are for the
design time. So first of all, as I mentioned, eclipse ide,
very likely this is going to be the web based ide as this is
the most modern one and what most people nowadays
expect to be. So the eclipse chair based
on Eclipse TIA, and in there
you're going to have those modeling tools, the support for the DamL language and
also the interface to the other piacere
tooling so that it is callable from the id itself.
So having the user modeling the doml,
then the ICG, the infrastructure code generator
is used to generate the IAC that could be
actually deployed on the infrastructure as we
generally rely on the existing tooling, for example
terraform for example, ansible to do the hard
job of running the infrastructure as
code, let's say. But the modeling language
has to be. So the designing the modeling language in the domal
has to be converted to that runnable IAC and this
is where ICG comes in. Also, both the DOM model
as well as the generated IAC go into this verification tool.
So the verification tool is a general verification tool as well as security
verification tool. This is where the emphasis is on the static
testing of the generated IAC. More on
that later. As well as I mentioned already,
some git repository tooling. So this is kind of agnostic
what that tooling is. It could be, for example GitLab, it could be something
else, something like Garrett and
Gitia for example, and creating
those pull requests or merge requests, whatever,
with the Domal and IAC that have been verified using the static
verification step.
This all goes into the runtime control that ensures that
the processes relevant to the deployment actually
start and ensure that the flow completes
for that particular deployment. The IAC
executor manager, the IEM is what actually calls the
ansible, the terraform, whatever else to execute
the IAC that was presented to it. Information about
what is being deployed, what has been deployed is stored in the infrastructural
elements catalog. And this is used for
two purposes, as you can see. Well, even free purposes. But two purposes
have already been called out, let's say.
So the infrastructure elements catalog is used as database
for querying from the id. So what are the possible
choices for you as the user? What cloud be deployed?
And then again, the information about what has been deployed
is also saved in this catalog.
So moving on, the flow then moves on to the infrastructure
advisor. The infrastructure advisor sets up monitoring and
analytics. The self healing, the optimization part
of piacere is all in the infrastructure advisor,
and the infrastructure advisor is also connected to
the infrastructure elements catalog. It's actually the third
usage of the infrastructure elements catalog that I've mentioned in
that all the data, all the performance data,
all the information about the state is
stored in the elements catalog for easy
querying. And this easy querying is for the optimizer
part to be able to decide on the optimal
strategy to propose.
And all the others are concerned with the resource
provider. And there are two kinds of resource providers from the PHRA perspective,
the production resource providers. So those that actually exist for some production
purpose, even if you're using it for testing.
This is something that is generally considered to be production like. But there
is also this tooling Canary sandbox environment tooling that is about
provisioning specific kinds of resource providers,
the canary sandbox resource providers, and those are
especially to be used for development and testing
of the generated infrastructure as code.
More on that later as well. So in general,
that's the diagram that's showing how the workflow
of your cherry could be because it's not
there yet as this is only a year in. So we are presenting how we
are thinking about it, but not how it works already.
But this is the general concept and the general view of that.
So we are proposing something else.
We are proposing something else again. And I
bet some of you already know this image from XKCD about
how standards proliferate and well,
we have to really show why
we are doing this instead of just saying that
we have to do this because so,
and our main point is that it hasn't been done yet.
So many companies are struggling, as I mentioned already,
with deciding on the approach to
security in DevOps. There's really no
complete, let's say standard for devsecops
only. Kind of like parts of what piacere
is going to propose are kind of standardized, say.
But other than that, the devsecops is just wide west
nowadays. Still, this is unfortunate
and we are working to change that, to change this perspective.
So first and foremost, this is to be simple and easy way to use devsecops
approach so that you don't have to think too much, so that you don't
have to worry about whether you are doing the devsecops right or
not. We are proposing this as end
to end solution for you. Unified way to build and
deploy into the multi cloud environments already mentioned as well.
Not relying on a single target platform but supporting
all the environments, the ones at the bottom are the ones
that we are thinking about the most at the time
of this project. But in general, the project is going to be extensible.
So if you find a need to
use another resource provider then this is easy to actually
add. So thinking about the other providers that
aren't using OpenStack but are still public resource
providers, cloud resource providers, then this is easy to add later
support for multiple IaC languages so that you
are not bound to a single IAC language. So again,
the extensibility point comes in here. As I
mentioned, the ones that we have considered so far,
we have considered so far include terraform and ansible. But this
could change as well automatic deployment to different cloud
providers so that you don't have
to worry about the details, how to contact the different cloud providers.
This is already abstracted away from you. For you,
automatic optimization of cloud resources.
This is again important that you
are not left alone with the optimization stage.
If you require the optimization.
The way to do it securely is also to
be built in in deputy framework. And finally the
embracement of Githubs with a single source of truth and
streamlined access control. As I mentioned already,
these are the selling points. As for why to go pitcher
with your devsecops and the key
elements, I've already kind of mentioned them, but a quick recap,
those will be now described in much more
detail on the different slides that are coming. So the first
one is devsecops modeling language. So actually this is only
for the D ops or DevOps modeling language. But in general, since we are dealing
with security as well, this is Devsecops modeling
language. Then you've got the verification tool.
As I mentioned, this is both for the security as
well as the formal verification of the DOM and the IAC,
the central DOM and IAC repositories and running control.
So this is actually the git repository I was
mentioning and the random controller that
is providing the general workflow of the petrol
framework. Then we've got the IAC, the IAC executor
manager that actually executes the IAC, the kind of sandbox environment tooling that
is kind of a helper service in here, the infrastructure
elements catalog that contains all the different information still
to be defined as well. So let's wait a couple
of slides more to learn more details about that and the
infrastructure advisor, which is about
the random monitoring. So for the performance and security as well as this
infrastructure optimization platform, and also the bits that are not
shown here will be shown later for the self healing and self
learning of
the data. And all this is integrated
together in the Piazza framework. So as I mentioned, this is
an end to end solution for devsecops. And now
moving on to this first component mentioned. So the Domal, the devsecops
modeling language. So this is where we are going,
cloud agnostic. And the way
that it's phrased in the slide, the cloud agnostic able
language, is because we are allowing the user to actually
ignore this fact. If the user is willing
to use a very specific feature of a
certain cloud provider, and that is not available anywhere
else, or that needs special configuration for that particular provider,
then the user is welcome to do that. This is obviously
blocking the multicloud approach for that
particular part of the IAC, but otherwise there
could be more generality in other parts. So to
achieve that we offer multiple layers of modeling and presentation.
So we are showing this abstract modeling when you
have it, environment agnostic. So for example,
this cloud agnostic and complete level where you have environment
dependent data. Application modeling is minimal.
In here we are focusing on the modeling of the infrastructure.
So digital parts like the complete,
what is to be deployed, how it's connected, what are the security
relevant aspects that's in there. But other than that,
the very detailed like it could be application modeling
is not part of the dummy. The target act
generation is possible and it's into multiple languages,
as I mentioned, terraform ansible, the basic
ones that we are offering at the beginning that we are
thinking about at the moment. And the modeling toolbox is
available in the eclipse id and I mean the web actually the
eclipse share id based on eclipse there.
Okay, so that's for the demo, now for the verification tool.
So as already mentioned, static analysis of the
domino and the generated IAC to verify the
correctness according to select criteria. So it's
also configurable to ignore certain parts
if the user wishes to ignore them. But in general this
is offering a wide range of criteria to
analyze the domain IAC for those formal
correctness as well as the security aspects of that.
And this is to ensure that the IAC and the companies that
are used are free of known vulnerabilities and that they follow
best security practices. So this is what can be
achieved at the static analysis level and this is the tooling
that does specifically that. And this is very much related
to the code generation. So this again
for the time being focuses on ansible and
terraform and is made to be extensible
to support other languages for
this single domain IAC repositories and runtime controller.
Again think repositories like the git repositories
or subversion repositories if that's your thing.
But in general this is about the single four operations.
So pushing to the repository, getting your deployment updated
via that, probably with some procedure like using the
merge request, the pull requests to actually
confirm that the OPS person is willing to
proceed with this change. This allows for the single source
of truth approach where everything infrastructure,
it's all in one place, it's defined there, it can be compared
against the state. This is also
the way that for example kubernetes pursues this, where you
define the desired state and then you can compare against this desired
state. So this movement was
inspired by this, by this
approach in kubernetes, again simplified and
streamlined access control. So control access via repository
permissions and any procedures that
your repository tooling allows you to do,
to verify, to control, to ensure that
the right people are stamping the
change to happen in your infrastructure.
That's all available to you with that approach.
As for the random control, as I mentioned, this is for the workflow
of the general framework and this is based on BPMN.
So the business process model annotation and
this allows for quite an extensible vernacular,
this mostly not to be modified
by the end users of piacere, but it's there,
it's flexible and it allows for further customization
if such it arises. And now on to the IAC
executor manager. IAC executor manager is all about the
execution of IAC, so it has to understand the tooling
that deploys the IAC. So for example the Ansible playbook command,
the terraform comments and outputs
of those comments, and the state that they save, the logs that
they produce. This is all in the IAC executor manager which
understands those. Again, I'll be repeating myself thinking
in this first release about Ansible and terraform, but yet again
being extensible about that.
What's more, it actually is to understand the deployed infrastructure.
So to be able to save this information to
the infrastructure admins catalog that something has been deployed. The infrastructure
as code executor manager is to understand
the deployed infrastructure, understand what has been deployed and where,
what the parameters are, et cetera, that are relevant
for storing in that catalog, as well as
support for reconfiguration scanning is also in the IM.
So reapplying the
ansible pegboards or the terraform terraform configs
and scaling, applying the scaling procedure via
the IM is also in here.
This is also what supported both the actual resource
providers, the production resource providers, as well as the canary environment resource
providers.
So it's like the universal solution for using IAC
infrastructure and secure use of credentials to the target environments.
This is also the part that actually integrates with
your, for example Hashikov's vault where you
store your credentials. And those are obtained by the aims itself,
not the other components.
As for the Canary sandbox environment tooling in
here, we are proposing two tools. One is the provisioner.
So the provisioner is about the deployment of select environments in an opinionated
way. So as most of you may
know, especially OpenStack. But kubernetes as well
could be quite daunting for the deployment
part. And we are proposing an opinionated way
that is deploying the minimal set,
let's say, of those complete that are required to run
applications models specifically for OpenStack and Kubernetes.
So you have this like one click,
one button way to deploy your OpenStack cloud,
your Kubernetes cloud, so that it can be used by
the rest of the framework. So this is mostly for
the testing and development aspect
of the framework. And the other tooling that we are working on and
we are proposing in Piacere is the mock cloud. And the
mock cloud is about the mocked APIs of selected
cloud providers. So like for example,
when you have Amazon and you interact
with Amazon Web services,
you might actually be interested in checking if your infrastructure
as code behaves a certain way without
actually calling the AWS. And there
has been some work in that regard in general public.
But this is what we are going to elaborate more
on in this project as part of
the smoker and in general the Kanai sandbox
environment. As I mentioned, this is for testing of
the dynamic aspects of the deployment. So like the verification tool lives
at the static stage at the design time, but sometimes static
analyzes is not enough. Some bits
could be omitted in that some could be not observable.
And dynamic testing is always closer to
the actual behavior that is going to be observed
in production and
for the infrastructure elements catalog. So like I mentioned,
this is storing all kinds of information. We are calling
this the central storage of local phrase knowledge local
because it's relevant to the deployment of the user.
So it stores both the offers, but it also
stores the historic data. The information that was obtained about the performance metrics,
security metrics of the actual deployments,
and the details on actual deployments as well are all
in the infrastructure elements catalog.
And the infrastructure elements catalog can be used to answer
the questions as to what providers are available, what the offers are
so like for the optimization part, if you are
optimizing for the cost, the way that the PSA framework
knows what the costs are, what the available options are ahead.
This is where infrastructure elements catalog comes in.
As I mentioned already. Yes, it stores the history characteristics
of the offers. So if you are optimizing both against the
cost, optimizing for the cost as well as for the performance characteristics,
because you are interested both in ensuring that your users get
the right levels of SLA and you
are optimizing for the cost because you don't want to overpay for the same performance,
this is also useful information for the optimized
and the optimized. And the monitoring comes
from the infrastructure advisor, and the infrastructure advisor
has those two main parts. The first part is the random monitoring
for performance and security, and the other part is the actual optimization
platform. So the goal of
the monitoring is to collect those metrics and events related
to performance and security,
actually to self learn and self heal from that.
So discovering those small discrepancies
and healing them right away, and also self learning from
the data to discover that certain issues
are going to repeat soon. Like for example from
the data, the last time that you've seen those spikes,
you soon needed another instance to be provisioned.
And this is especially what the self learning is about.
But similarly, the self learning is about the security.
So discovering patterns in how the security
could be violated, what aspects
of the security are relevant to that, is also
in that self learning and the
infrastructure side. So like you probably recognize.
So when you want to monitor something, you need to somehow
access the systems. So this is an approach
with agents. So the agents are actually deployed during the IEM run.
So the IEM gets those additional,
let's say for example ansible playbooks or otherwise,
the infrastructure scope to deploy the actual agents to
be configured with the infrastructure advisor
so that the metrics can be collected from there.
The IOP, as I've mentioned, the platform for the optimization,
it actually computes the optimal
solutions based on those collected metrics. So it collaborates with the infrastructure
elements catalog and
the trade offs that are to be optimized of the cost,
performance, availability, et cetera, style.
So those aspects, and this
is using multi objective optimization based
on machine learning. And that's
it for the optimization side. I guess this was also the
last slide. Yes, I was right. Okay, so that's
it from me for this presentation about piacere. Thank you very much for staying
with me, for listening to me and let's stay in touch.
If you want to reach out to us, this is our website.
If you want to reach out to us for seven boost.com,
our company name is our domain, so you
can find us there. Thank you very much again and see
you.