Hey everyone, today we are really excited to present this talk,
which is kubenation. And here we will be understanding
the architecture of Kubernetes in respect of an analogy
of a country. It will be really fun, it will be really visual.
So we are really excited to present
this talk to you all. So about us,
I'm Aakansha Priya and I'm currently a deverel at
empathyops. So I love going to meetups
and conferences, love hosting spaces.
And yeah, I also love
to deep dive into new cloud native technologies.
And I'm Siddhant Khisty, a developer advocate at Siglens.
I am also one of co organizer at cloud native community groups
NASC and I love to geek out around Linux,
DevOps and various other technologies.
Recently I've also gotten into fitness and health, so if
you want to chat about that or just tech in general, feel free to hit
me up on Twitter. So before we get into the fun
stuff about actually building a nation, let's just get
a very high level overview of what exactly is Kubernetes.
So if you've gone ahead and googled a little bit around kubernetes,
you'll hear that it's the de facto container orchestration
solution. So thats. Does that exactly mean container
orchestrator basically means that Kubernetes is instructing
these tiny little things called as containers to go
ahead and do something now. For now all you need to understand
about containers is containers are a box which
do something. Kubernetes is also used widely in our
industry. Whether you go and look at a big company such as Google or
Microsoft or Apple or Netflix, they are all
using kubernetes at some level. It's also
a really great distributed system. That means that you
can use it using multiple computers. And these
computers can be spread across the entire globe and it will still
work. But Kubernetes is also very complicated
and it's quite easy to get wrong.
You might type one single letter in the wrong way in
the Kubernetes configurations files, and you might have
just opened up an entire range of security errors or
performance issues. But we're not talking about Kubernetes today,
so let's just throw it out of the window for now. And we
will be actually building a nation, right? It sounds interesting.
So we will be requiring a few checklist items.
And those are like six main items that
we will be requiring. First is land. Of course.
We can't build a country without a land, right?
Then we need some authority who will actually govern all
the actions that is being taken place in the country,
then we have people who will be staying in the country and working for the
nation. And we need homes so
that those people can stay. And of
course, all of this requires a communication set up. So we
require communication and then we need the hard workers
who will be building the homes and doing the communication
work, everything. So this is what we will be
doing. Now, why do we require a land?
As I mentioned, we need the land because we
need to build our foundation on it, and it has
all the resources, like the nutrients and minerals. And we need
those resources to build our homes or
supply food to our country people and so on.
Now, how to actually acquire a land? There are
a couple of ways. And first is that if you buy a land or
you can get like someone rents you the land, then you
can conquer the land. And of course not so suggested
option, but you steal a land. Now,
every country has a capital nation, which is like the
main city in thats main city, all the
authority people who will be actually governing the nation
will be staying there after the capital is established.
We need some cities, right? And so for example, we have
taken Park City, industrial city and the night city.
So if you are into gaming and all, you can actually
understand the reference of night City.
Now this nation will have some important stakeholders.
So the first that comes up is the president, who is
the face of the nation. He's the one who will
take all the major important decisions. So if
there is something that needs to be done for the country,
all that communication will be like all
the communication will go through the president, and all the important
decision making skills will be in the hand of him.
So he basically governs the nation. Now, of course,
the president cannot run the whole country.
He needs some people who are in the lower hierarchy and manage
the nation. So we need some managers. And he makes sure
that everything is working properly, every city is working
properly, and people are
having no communication problems,
they are having no food problems and anything.
Now making sure that the nation is healthy.
So for example, if there is a terrorist attack or anything,
it ensures that the city is working properly and it's
in a stable state. Then comes the task manager,
who basically does all the micromanagement of the people who are
staying in those cities. He decides who does the
work, ensures that the task that is being assigned
to the person is being done, and also decides whom
to give which task and where to give that task. And now
all of this information is being stored
at one central place. So for example, I want to look back to the tasks
that were assigned in that city or if something went wrong,
how it was called, I can actually go to that repository or
that central reserve and see thats what was
being done. So all the status, all the history
reserves of the country are there.
So now comes the home. This is a home. And there could be one person
who is staying or there could be multiple people
who are staying inside those homes. Now in the
city there will be of course a neighborhood.
So there are these four isolated homes and.
Right, currently they have no communication and totally isolated.
And in order for a city and a nation to work,
we need to have communication set up.
So we bring in telephones so
any house can contact the adjacent house,
right. Or even someone from the other
city. So that's how communications are being set up.
Then comes the hard workers who
will be actually building those homes and who will be actually setting
up the communication system. So when we talk
about builders, they ensure it's very self explanatory
that they will be building the houses. If the houses requires any
maintenance work, they will be doing those.
And they make sure that the people who are staying
in those home are safe. And of course
every city needs to accommodate every person who is
part of the country, right? So they make sure thats the accommodation
is well established in every city. Similarly,
it goes for the communication that all the telephone
providers or Internet providers are there in
every specific city. They make sure that everyone can
talk to each other. The messages are being delivered efficiently
and timely. If there are any communication
rules that needs to be enforced, they are responsible
for that. And of course they ensure thats it is
existing in every city of the country.
So congratulations, you just learn the
entire Kubernetes structure in
a country form of way. But how it relates to the Kubernetes
architecture in technical terms, I will now pass
on to Sudant and he will be explaining that analogy.
All right, so I'm pretty sure you had fun.
If you've played makes like Simcity, for example,
you probably could relate with a lot of the elements which we just talked about.
Now let's bring it back to technical discussions for
a while. Let's see how all these components
for a country are relating to Kubernetes.
So first of all, we had land. We explained land
as the foundation for building a country,
right? So in technical terms, this is just your
servers, your computers, you have your ram, you have
your cpu, you have your memory, you have your storage devices and
all these other things. These are the resources which we
are going to use for building our Kubernetes clusters.
So we have our servers. Right now every single
one of our cities is actually a server.
And in Kubernetes terms we call them as nodes.
Now the capital city, which we talked about, that has all the
authority figures in terms of, in Kubernetes terminology
we will call this as the control plane node.
In some other ways to refer to
it, you might also call it the master node. But the control plane node
is basically where all your core Kubernetes components will
exist. Then all your other node, all your
other cities are just some regular nodes.
Each one of these nodes is a dedicated server
or a dedicated computer within itself. Kubernetes at
the end of the day is just one control plane node
and multiple other nodes or computers
which are all being instructed how to work and how
to orchestrate containers. Again, at the start we mentioned that
containers are just a box that do something, right?
Now let's see, what exactly are these important
components within Kubernetes? The components that pretty
much govern the entire cluster. So let's start off with replacing
our president. We'll replace it with something that we
call as the Kube API server.
Now the Kube API server is again pretty much like
the face of a Kubernetes cluster. The API server
is your entry point to a Kubernetes cluster. All the requests
that you make, all the actions that you make inside a cluster, they will all
go through the Kube API server.
Now from there you also have the controller manager.
Now like we mentioned earlier, the controller manager.
All it does is make sure that everything within the cluster
is healthy, everything is running. If it's not
working properly, it's the controller manager's duty to restart
the process or heal the process. Then the
task manager, which in Kubernetes terminologies
is again called as the Kube scheduler.
The scheduler basically decides thats
actions to take and where to take them. For example,
if I want to run some action
in the park city node, the cube scheduler will
instruct the components within the park city node to do
it there. The scheduler makes sure that the actions are
not executed in some other city, right? And then we
have the central reserve which is just like a history books for the
country. In Kubernetes that's what we call as the
ETCD. Now in technical terms the ETCD is just
like a database. Like for example, you have a
SQL based database, you have MongoDB and all these other amazing
databases. ETCD is a database in
the same sense. But this one has been specifically created to
work well with kubernetes. Yeah, so as I mentioned
earlier, the homes and in these homes people were
staying. So these people are actually the containers.
And the containers are consistent like it's
inside a pod. And these
pods are represented by the homes, which is
in the city itself. Now we also mentioned
that you need some sort of communication between the homes,
right? So we gave each houses its own telephone,
but now instead of telephones we will
assign each pod with a service. Now these services
are of many different types. You have a service called
as cluster IP, you have a service called as a node port,
you have load balancers and these are the three main
types of services within kubernetes. We won't go into the technical
details of each of the services, but they essentially just help
your pods communicate with each other.
Now let's talk about the hardest workers within a Kubernetes
cluster. So we talked about the builders and communication
agencies who build your houses or rather build your
pods and establish your networks. So within a Kubernetes
cluster, the job of building all these pods and
running the containers within the pods is handled by a component
called as the Kubernetes. So this cubelet
is going to exist within every single one of your nodes. Whether it's
a regular worker node, whether it's your control plane
node, doesn't matter. This Kubernetes will exist everywhere.
And the second component which is essential within a Kubernetes
cluster is the Kube proxy. The Kube proxy
essentially handles all your networking related
activities within the cluster. So again, just like the Kubernetes,
even the Kube proxy will exist in every single
node. And now we have
gone through all of the core components of Kubernetes and if
we visualize it, it looks something like this. So on the left
we have the control plane with the API server, the control
manager, the scheduler, the kubeproxy,
and it also has the kubelet and the
ETCD. And then we have our regular nodes
which are our worker nodes. Thats is park city, industrial city and
the night city node. Now the control plane node
and the worker nodes, they can have absolutely any names,
you just need to give them the proper name and you can work with them.
So yeah, that's all for our talk. I hope you enjoyed.
If you want to learn more about kubernetes then we've
made a GitHub repository with a couple of resources and
we've also shared these slides in that GitHub repository.
So feel free to scan thats QR code to view
those slides. And you can also follow us on our
Twitter handles. They're right here. And, yeah, thanks for listening.
Thanks for tuning in.