You. Hello. I'm Reuben Rajan
George, and I work as a cloud reliability architect with Accenture. I've been
involved in quality engineering roles for over ten years,
primarily in the area of performance engineering and optimization.
Now, today's talk is directed to the following folks.
Now, these are quality engineers who are currently looking to make a career switch
into SRE. The next folks are the QE engineers who are
currently asked to take up SRE roles, and finally, the product managers who
like to engage their existing QE engineering pool in
operations or SRE activities. And I hope this is going to be helpful.
Modern day sdets, or in other words, software development
engineers in testing, or in other words, quality engineers,
are actually highly skilled automation engineers with not just the
functional knowledge of the applications, but a clear understanding of how systems
function under the hood. Now, these engineers must be aware of all
the black box testing techniques along with hands on development or
coding skills. Many of these sds are equipped with programming skills,
making them capable to read, analyze, troubleshoot and recommend
appropriate grammar and optimized algorithms. Now,
sds today are actually embedded throughout the entire application
development process right from the very beginning. Here are some of these roles
that are played by sdes today. Unlike traditional testers,
sdes today have varied responsibilities.
Traditionally, quality engineers used to focus on manual
functional testing, functional validation, manual testing of all the
application screen flows, and so on. However, today they
have varied responsibilities ranging from functional performance,
security, usability and accessibility validation.
And second thing is that they have a clear understanding of the end to
end functionality of an application from domain and user points of
view. And they always strive to add a bit of sense and context to everything
that can be seen in the way they do their documentation, their test scenarios and
test planning and so on. They also have strong programming skills
to automating repetitive tasks. This could be your test scenario
creation, test data preparation if they have to create
frameworks to do parallel execution, reporting and even
dashboarding, and they have an understanding of potential edge case scenarios.
So they will always look for thinking. They're trained to
think outside the box, and they
help in identifying those edge case scenarios that are usually missed out in application design
and development. And they are also trained to think,
like I said, to think outside the box and create these what if scenarios
that are actually a basis of any hypothesis based testing
techniques. Quality engineers come up with this with a mindset.
These are three words that I use, curiosity, adaptability and exploratory.
Let me explain. Now, they come with a mindset that is very curious to
know things and query whatever that's placed before them,
that actually breeds a positive culture to query why a certain functionality or feature
works a certain way. This leads to more questioning as to why
does even one do the same task over and over again. In other words,
in our modern SRE terms, they always wonder why
are we continuously doing these manual tasks?
We automate those tasks and thereby reducing toil. They also
help create these what if scenarios that probes questions in the house
systems would perform if a certain parameter is changed.
The next attitude that they have is adaptability. And I'm talking from
a third person point of view, so don't mind me taking that angle.
They have an open mindset, and first and foremost is since there
are a lot of new technologies that are coming
out every month quarter, they're open to learning new scripting tools or
languages to enable them to do thorough testing
of the applications that have, irrespective of the technology stack,
whether it be Python, Java, et cetera.
As these architectures evolved, these sdates SRe able to
develop cloud fluency and be able to validate the architecture's
effectiveness, performance and security. What they also are open to do, and are
adaptable, is that they're open to switch roles between functional
validation, which includes API testing and so on, database validation
to test the data consistency, performance validation,
load and stress response resilience, fault orance of the system and the
threat of chaos. And most primarily, they also take up the hat of
the end user and understand how system response actually affects them.
So they see it from an end to end perspective, not only look at the
particular architecture component, and finally they come with an exploratory mindset,
they look out for what can be automated,
so they automate the repetitive tasks, like I said earlier, all those test
scenario creation testers and result analysis, test data generation,
result analytics and inference and so on. And they also would be
helpful in architecting, even architecting and
automating test infrastructures to integrate and orchestrate environment setup,
validation activities, even monitoring setup.
Now, testers today and tomorrow would be involved in these following areas,
and they are mentioned as four bullet points. First thing, and first and foremost is
the autonomous functional validation. And there are a couple of things under that.
They would be able to create automation tests, automation frameworks that are
self maintaining or autonomous. They would be involved in also validating
deployments that are being pushed to production, basically your cloud formation and
your terraform templates.
They are also involved in setting up observability in
the testing space. So in this way that they are able to monitor what
happens under the hood for your test sessions. The second thing that they
would be involved and they have to build skills in the area of machine learning
and so on for any optimization of testing to derive
any sort of analytics and decisions based on those analytics
capture. We'll talk more about that in the coming slides.
Rather than moving from a very reactive performance
testing approach, they will be more evolved in setting
up autonomous frameworks for continuous performance optimization. And I'll talk
some of the key points in this area as well. And finally,
as there is a great impetus to make our systems more reliable and
resilient to any sort of fault, they would be involved
in the evaluation of resilient design patterns.
They would be also evolved in injecting failure scenarios
into production and validating the system behavior.
Now let's go on to the first point now. Autonomous functional validation
in autonomous functional validation, the key points here is that they would be
involved in setting up these test automation frameworks that are autonomous
or self maintaining. Basically what this does is these
frameworks should identify changes in architecture every new
deployment or code push and automatically
update their test code to match up to the updated architecture
and business knowledge. So they would have automation scripts that will be running
and as soon has a new deployment is pushed in,
it senses this new deployment, the new variables, environment variables and so on,
and also updates their test code automatically. The second thing is
this environment provisioning template validation basically is testing
deployment templates. This could be transformation terraform and so on.
And what they would do is validate how
this template ties in those various resources together into an integrated application.
So what the queue would do here is would create the entire stack cloud transformation
stack, for example using the SDK and validate whether the
stack outputs matches the expected behavior and
they pass the test if the stack creation is successful and they'll fail the deployment
if the stack creation integration test fails.
Test session observability what we sre trying to do here is to evaluate
performance regression across application builds while they're doing the functional validation
and identifying any contributing parameters, making use
of your APM tools and applying usage patterns.
This involves setting up observable, even lower environments.
There is trade off with cost and licensing and so on, but there are
a lot of open source solutions that actually your QE
engineers actually use today that facilitate capturing
performance data during your functional validation. This could
be like changes in number of DB call that SRE meta servers API calls metro
service, the time it takes for the DB to read. And since
these environments are actually, as these environments are generated
using transformation thermal, they can be killed even after execution.
So here the test automation engineer
is able to automate even that piece of activity. So it's purely
autonomous in a way. Now, the second thing that
the functional or quality engineers are able to do is to identify
latent failure causal chains because they sre now able to look under
the hood, resulting in outage or
poor experience. Mine usage data from
logs and analyzing key failure patterns and failure propagation across the
stack in test optimization, analytics and decisioning what you see on
the right hand side, the main goal here is to reduce as much toil as
possible. And so how they do this is where quality
engineers should be skilled in statistics and
NLP machine learning techniques to optimize test
suit by performing requirement risk analysis,
removing redundant scenarios, merge these defects,
identify opportunities to sequence test cases,
test scenario prioritization, and improve
test coverage. It also evolved testing failure propensity,
vitality and so on. And one of the
other outcomes of this activity is even optimizing test data
repository. All right, so let me move on
to the next slide. Continuous performance optimization
now this is an interesting area because this applies to my line of
work. And what is the goal of these autonomous
performance optimization techniques is to automatically configure
applications, runtimes, databases, cloud environments individually,
because each of these have their own separate parameters,
and they analyze the relationship between these configuration parameters,
between databases, cloud environments and so on, by continuously
doing performance testing and tuning activities. So for this performance,
engineers today are actually skilled in a couple of things. Earlier they used
to be skilled with your performance testing tools like Jmeter,
neoload and with your pipeline tools and so on, and monitoring tools
like Prometheus, dinosaurs and splunk. But today they should be also
skilled with configuration management tools like
ansible and so on, and also be able to do bash scripting
and able to work with APIs and so on. In addition
to automating the performance test, they're also involved in automating dashboard
creations, which involves automated monitoring environments,
deployments, build version control,
and applying dashboard as a code tools and
techniques. Now, there are cost benefits to this, obviously, there's cost
benefits to any sort of performance optimization. First and foremost
is the system utilization, improves system utilization,
optimized infrastructure and license cost, and improved
customer experience, and improved observability. Now, finally, and one of
my favorite topics is the reliability evaluation. There are two parts to this evaluation
of resilient design patterns that are applied. This involves creating
automated scripts to validate effectiveness of resilience patterns,
applying probably whichever library you use today historics or
Lins four g and so on, and validate patterns like circuit breaking,
rate limiting, bulkheading, timeout handling, and result caching, and so on.
So quality engineers would also be evolved
in determining potential single points of failures and fault
modes using FMEA and STPI techniques. They would evaluate
potential failover scenarios for multi region deployments and testing fallback
scenarios. They would also be involved in identifying potential
dependency failure scenarios. They would also be involved
in evaluating effectiveness or recovery playbooks from a functional
end to end perspective. And not only that, they would be evolved in conducting dry
runs of failure scenarios to validate and finally, chaos testing.
There's a huge ocean of information on this area, but however,
quality engineers will be involved in two key things. One is to automate the
identification, the scenario creation,
the injection of those failure scenarios for pre production and production
environments, and verify whether those testing results match expected system
behavior. This also involves testing failure of all components and external
dependencies, and these failures could be network brownouts, instance failures,
et cetera. So that's all I has for today. I hope this quick
lightning talk would have given you some ideas. You are free to ping
me on LinkedIn with my name, Ruben Rajan George, or on Twitter.
I'm available on the handle. Ruben Rajan
thank you very much. See you later.