Two cloud native I'm very happy to be with you today to
share some knowledge, some content, some news about Java in the
cloud native world. My name is Audrey Morice. I work for Red Hat.
And today I will give you the session, your Java code called
native. Ready? A live experience. And why live experience?
Because everything that I'm going to show you starting from now,
it's based on live coding sessions and live coding.
Okay, so I will start by showing a demo.
So it's demo time right now. Okay, I will switch
here to my terminal and I will move here to
my blue green. Yes.
And here OC project Blue
Green Canary. Let me explain
a little bit before it starts. Let me also increase the
size of my phone. Okay, great. What I'm going to
do right now, well, we are talking here about cloud native applications.
When we think about cloud native applications,
we hope, we expect that this application
has some features. Like for example,
what I'm going to show right now, it's what we call servicing
mesh features. What is servicing mesh? It's a layer that
you can have on top of your application that will manage,
that will handle all the traffic in order to provide your
application the security that it needs, the cloud balancing,
the traffic management and other stuff. Okay,
so this demo that I'm going to show you right now,
it's for this matter, okay,
so this is what we call blue green
deployment. So I will open here,
here it is my demo. So if you pay
attention, you will see that my screen is
switching between blue and green. So this is the
same application with two different versions.
One version is a blue version and the other version is
a green version. If I check here my kubernetes,
we will see that I have, so I have
here the blue version of my application and the green version
of my application. Okay. So of course I have a
cloud balancing working in this application.
And each request to the application, the load
balancing is switching between green version
and blue version. Okay. All right, so what I'm going
to do right now is to add a new version for this
application, a Canary version. What I'm going to do is
right now I will deploy the deploy
here the version canary.
Just to explain why we wait a little bit.
I have here tons of scripts as
you just saw, because it will make my
life easier in order to show this demo to you.
You can see that the Canary version is already working. We will
see it on those browser a little bit. Okay. It's already working.
So I have all those scripts just to make my life easier of
course, when you are working in production, you will also
build your own scripts to make your life easier.
But basically what I will do in this few minutes
showing this demo is switching my yaml files
in order to manage the traffic and the route
to my application. Okay, so great. Here I have my
application working with three versions right now. So I
have one version that is blue, one version that is green,
one version that is yellow, the Canary version, and my
load balancer is load balancing the request
between those three versions of the application. Great,
awesome. Right now let's play
with the traffic to this applications. So I will
check my scripts here. So now let's
switch the traffic only to blue version.
Wait some seconds to this.
Okay, now it's done. Let's wait. And now we have just
the blue version of the application being considered
by the load balancing. Okay, so now just the
blue version. Now let's switch to green
version. Wait a few seconds to switch to green
and stick with the green version. And now we
will switch to yellow version,
canary. And now we have just
the anery version. Again, what does it have to do with
cloud native? One of the main aspects of cloud native
application is that you should be able to
make some changes, this is the
right word for this, without downtime to your application.
So you can see that I made three
changes on the routes to my application, the traffic to my application
without downtime. Okay, so the users are still
accessing my application and there is no downtime.
Right. Let's try something else.
Where are you? Great. So now, as you can see
here, I'm using a chrome browser. So what I'm
going to do right now is to change. I will make the
chrome users will stick with the green version
and the Firefox users will stick with canary
version. So we'll change here, the Canary to Firefox,
and let's open a Firefox window
here. Just a second. Great. So,
demo.
Okay, so everything is working? Yes,
it's working. So we are using here Firefox.
Firefox is sticking with the Canary version and the chrome
is sticking with the green version. Right.
Great. I have some other options here,
if I show you, but as we have some limits
of time here, I could, for example,
move everything that everyone that is working with
Android to the Canary version and everything
else. Every other users stick with green.
And here just with iPhone, and here just
with everyone that's using mobile. Okay, so by having
this kind of approach on your architecture and your
application being built using this approach,
you can have all these options and this is a
very simple example, but just to give
you those kind of possibilities that you have. Cloud native
approach when building your application. Okay,
just for starting right now, I will show you
much more code in a few minutes. But here, this is
our first example here, this application is a Java application
using cloud native approach. Good,
let's switch to slides again.
So this was our first demo and just for
you to know me, if you haven't, my name is Elder Moraes,
I work here for Red Hat as a developer
advocate here. I'm in Brazil, I'm brazilian based in
Sao Paulo. This is a QR code for my mailing
list and also the URL if you would like to
receive some content, but Java cloud native microservice
containers kubernetes I share in this list.
Okay, so just subscribe, I will not
send you any spam. Okay. I'm a board
member also at Java, one of the biggest Java
user groups in the world, and I'm also the author of the
Jakarta e cookbook and I'm very happy with this book
because in the first 24 hours it reached the top
one on Amazon United States. So it's a great
book. If you work with Java on enterprise environment,
maybe my book would be helpful for you. And also my mission
here as not only a red hat but as a professional is to
help Java developers around those world to build and deliver
awesome applications, right? So our cloud native
application today we have some stuff. So basically I will use microservice
approach, that's one of the fundamentals of cloud
native application. Not that you have to use microservice
but you should use because some features that I will show
you in a few seconds. Also I will use rest client,
I will use health Shack because your application will
run on some orchestrated environment and by
that it should have some health shack possibilities
for your orchestration being able to manage your
application. Also we will work with metrics for scalability,
we will use reactive both with mutiny and kafka,
and also we will deploy our application using containers and
kubernetes. Okay, and let's move to code time starting
from now we will not see any slides anymore.
Okay, just one last slide in the end of the session.
Amazing. Let's change some stuff here.
I will move here, check if, okay,
so let's forgot
the dash.
Perfect. And also I will switch my
namespace to this one.
If you don't know what I'm doing here, I'm connected
to a Kubernetes cluster that is hosted on the cloud,
in this case on AWS. So I'm really working
in a Kubernetes here so let me just check this
namespace is clean so we are able to move
on. Okay, no resources, so all good here.
Okay so I will build a Java application from scratch
and you will keep adding some features
to help this application to work with the best approaches,
best practice when we talk about cloud
native application, cloud native word cloud native
approach and whatever you name it. I will build
a Java application using Quarkus.
Why Quarkus? Because Quarkus will give me a lot of productivity.
I have a lot of extensions, Quarkus extensions
that will make my life much more easier when
building this cloud native application here today. All right so I
will just open not a comma let's say.
Okay, all good. So it will open
my virtual visual studio code
and I will use can
integration with maven and there is a
feature in this plugin called developer mode.
So by using mVN Quarkus dev, what it
will do right now is to compile my application to bootstrap
this application. So this application will keep running and every
change that I do in this application will be hot deployed.
Okay so once I call this application, all the changes will
reflect on my application, right? So this application started
in 1 second. It's great, especially for a Java application.
Okay so let me tweak
my here and switch to this.
Okay oh good.
So let me show you. Oh good,
great. I will remove the best folder. Don't do that.
Right? I will just do that for those sake
of the time here while we are working on this demo.
But you should not remove the best, right? Okay guys,
what am I going to do right now is to start building this
application. As you said, we have a base
project built when we created this project
using Quarkus. I have even a rest endpoint ready
right here. So I'll call here. Okay as
easy I can change here to hello and
I change this application. And this application was hot,
deployed in 600 milesconds. Okay so
this is very fast.
Okay guys let's build this application because
we are really excited here today.
We'll start by adding some data management in
this application. So by data we'll add some extensions.
So first we will add extensions to work with data.
So JSoNB, JGBC and
hibernate to work with panache. That is the default
data management for. Okay so
let's start building our classes.
First we will add some configurations,
blah blah blah blah.
I will not deep dive in too much details.
My intention here is to give you a bigger picture
of this because it would take hours to
explain every single bit that I'm showing you right now. But I
will give you a whole picture of all the
possibilities that we have with Java in the cloud native
world today, especially when working with quarkus,
I will build this, it will be my
entity. So this first
application I will build here will manage fruits, okay so
I have here first my entity for fruits
and I will build my rest endpoint here,
my resource, the fruit
resource and it will have
a wheel list of course the fruits.
So if I go right now on my terminal
and using this guy, okay so change
detected, 1.5 seconds to do
it hot deploy. Of course my data, my database,
it's empty.
And let's right now add a
new method here to add a new fruit.
Okay so I just created this
method here, I will call this,
I will call this new method by not
hot deploying application because it will do for me in
475 seconds. And now
I have a banana in my database,
okay but I would like to do something more
scalability. So I will add a new file
to this folder here which
will be a import SQl and
add some new fruits to my database
and it will call train. Okay I still have a
banana. Sometimes I need to redeploy.
The good part even if I need to redeploy is that quarkus
will do it really fast. Okay so how
many? 2 seconds, 2.7 seconds. Okay so not
anything at all. Okay so now I have a lot of
data in my database, what I'm going to do right now is
to add a custom finder, okay so because
if you paid attention here I'm using a list
all that is from my entity, okay so
I will add a new finder here,
that is my finder where I will pass
a season and will list fruits based on those season.
So right now we just change our rest
endpoint to be able to
use this new parameter, okay so I have a new parameter here
where I will use to list by season and
I can again run this call
here but for example using summer and now
I have just the fruits that is based on summer.
Now we are good to take this application and
deploy on those cloud deploy on my kubernetes
cluster. So what we're going to do right now is to add a
new extension, two extensions, one is quarkus kubernetes
and the other is quarkus Container image,
okay so one will build the container image and
the other one we should deploy on the Kubernetes.
Okay so we add some new
properties for this application.
So let's switch here. Okay I
will make some changes. This one will be docker
I o. This one will be
elder price. Let's remove these spaces
because YML will not work with spaces.
And right now how can I take this application and
create a containers image and deploy it into the cloud.
It's very, very simple. MvN clean package.
Okay we'll package those application but I will pass one
parameter, quarkus kubernetes
deploy equals true.
Oh I forgot something. Stop. I need
to log on my docker registry.
Okay great, now we
are good to go. So right now it will package
the application, will build the container image and
will deploy this application on my kubernetes
cluster if you don't have any mistakes. All right,
bet me check here. This is the beauty of the live coding session.
We are able to debug the applications. I need to add
one guy here to trust on
the certified certification.
Now I hope we will work.
All right. Okay guys, this is
the real life, on your daily basis you will face
this kind of. Yeah, now we are going. Okay guys,
so it's basically building the image and we'll start the
process of pushing this
container image on my
kubernetes. Okay, so let's watch QBctl
get bots.
Yes. Okay so my application is already running.
Okay. It's really fast because Quarkus
starts really fast. How can we access this application?
I have a service,
let's see the DNS of those application.
Is this guy here. And by experience I
know that we take like one to two minutes to
really respond. Okay but let's check curl
those guy.
Hello. Oh it's working.
Wow, it was really, really fast. Today I
change here to fruit.
Fruit,
wow it's there, it's working. Okay, so sometimes
it takes like one to two minutes but today we were looking, it's already working.
So I took this application I just created on
my machine and deployed on the cloud. Okay of course
we are not done. We still have a lot of stuff to do here
and let's go forward. Right now what we are going to do
is to add some new features to those application. So first
I will add another extension,
the rest client extension and
we have fruits here, but we have just the name and
the season. I would like to add some data to these
fruits and I will do that by using an external
service. So I will connect to this external service
using a rest client. I add the extension
and we'll create some other classes here. So I will create
another class
here to work with. This is the fruit
device. The name of the service that
I will use, it is called fruit device. I will create
another interface that
will be my interface between my local
applications and the remote.
Okay so basically this is the API,
it's an interface, this is the path and this is the
method that I will call on this remote application.
I will add the address of this
application is this guy here? Okay you can check afterwards online.
Printvice.com is where I will get the data that
I need to improve my application.
I will create adto java,
blah blah blah. As I said, I will not
deep dive into too much details to save time
and show you much more stuff than going too much details.
And now I will change my fruity resource in
order to use our new rest client. Okay so
now we are using the fruit device to add some
new data to our fruits. So let's
fall again our
application. So again using summer detected
some changes 1.2 seconds and
now I not only have the fruit name and the
season but I also have carbohydrates and calories.
These two guys here are coming from the fruit device.
So by using my rest client I'm able to connect with remote
applications and get some data and add to my local
application. Great. So moving
on. Now I'm adding some health shack
features to my application.
And why I'm going to do that because as I said in the beginning of
the talk, when our application is hosted on can orchestrated
environment the orchestrator should be able to look
to our application know two stuff. One, your application is
live and two, your application is ready because
if it's not live it will queue the application and create it
again and it's not ready. It will wait until
it's ready. So your application should be able to provide
this kind of information to the orchestrator.
And here we are using kubernetes. So that's how Kubernetes will
manage the application. I just added the
extension for health shack those this application and one cool
stuff I will even open on my browser,
better picture of this, if I
just call here health
it will give me the information because by just adding the extensions
it add the feature to the application. So I didn't need to
code anything but I will because I would like to customize
this health shack feature. So I will create two
probes, one liveness probe and one redness
probe. So let's create them.
So liveness probe and
those liveness probe will just say well I'm alive,
says nothing is not live. Okay. But if it's
working, it will just respond. This guy here and
here you can customize I'm live c 42
for example. And the other guy is the redness probe.
The redness, it's where probably you will add
some rules, some more complexity because
it's what is ready for your application. It could
be to be able to access some database, it could
be to be able to access some other service.
So until you are able to check this, you will
not respond as I'm ready. Okay, but in
this case we are just building a custom example here.
And if I just call this guy again now I have
the specific responses both from
the liveness and from the redness. Okay good.
So we are now our application is connecting with remote
applications. It's giving health check responses.
Now let's add some metrics. Here we
add the quarkus micrometer. Quarkus has integration
with also the microprofile,
but those default today is micrometer for Quarkus but
it still have support for microprofile
metrics. But here today I will show you using micrometer.
Here's the only one that I need to change the pond
file. So I will let
me this guy,
okay, I will create a specific class
to show you how to use
the metrics.
Let's go here new file Java.
And here is my timely resource.
So basically here it will work by using annotation.
So I define it that this
method here is being counted. Okay, so the metric
that we use here is counted and the name of this
metric is time. Now this guy
here I will use by this way.
Great. Let's compile
this application. We're not compiled, just call.
Okay, let's see if it will work
without, okay great.
So took 1.4 seconds
to auto deploy the application. And here we'll
call a few times just to have some data.
And right now I will open as we did with
the help we can did with metrics. So just use here metrics,
voila. Here time.
So here we have that metric that we
created and we know here that we call it 30 times
and we have some other information. Basically it's just
a counted metric. So it's just counting. Okay, so here
you know where it is, deception and so on.
Now the two last
parts of this session, we will start working
with reactive features. So let's
add an extension for rest
easy mutiny that we will use right now.
We will move away from the fruits and
we'll dive into beer. So our application will start
working with beer. We'll create here
a beer class that will
be our kind of entity.
So I have here, actually it's a
pojo. Okay, it's not an entity, but that's fine.
Let's create now a beer service.
Beer service that is our best client for
this service will work with beer.
We will add again another
address for this guy. It's not roots
anymore, now it's API, punk API.
And we'll create a resource,
blah blah blah java.
So this is our service. And pay attention that
as we work with reactive using the mutiny extension,
the producers keep doing the application
JSon. But here on the method, the return is
a mute, okay? That's the kind of return using
by mutiny. Okay? All right. If everything is working,
we should be able right now to call our application.
So let's call here,
let me try again. If not, we will sometimes
took some time to connect to the revolt application to
get the data. But if not, we will just
redeploy. All right?
Yes. Now we have this beautiful list of beer.
I love beer. Okay, so if you love beer as well, maybe you
know what I'm talking about. So we have those remote
service. But right now I'm using a reactive
approach to gather all this data.
And the last part, now we are almost done
here. We will keep doing reactive
approach, but right now using reactive streams with
Kafka. So let's add a Kafka
extension here.
Okay, good. And this application,
now we work it in this session with fruits,
then with beer, now with wine. I do
love wine as well. So let's work with some wine
here.
But boom. We already
also have a audio. This new
application we will work off with prices of
the wine. So let's create a
priced wine class,
okay? And we will create,
we not have a database of course, but we
will create a class called here
wine generator that will help us to guess
what generate wines. Okay,
we will create a resource that
will be our endpoint.
So,
and this guy here,
okay, so we have here the channel that we will connect
on the kafka that is priced wine. The return is
also a mutey as we saw on the last example.
And we will bet the information that are priced
wines. Okay, for doing that,
we will also need, guess what? A Kafka. Okay,
so we will add some new properties
here. I will create a docker compose file
to spin up a kafka on my
machine, my local machine here. So basically we
create this docker compose.
Let's edit this file and I will red
hat we need here. Okay,
let me see basically those example
we work with Kafka zookeeper and a
price generator service that I just created here.
So I will restart
this application, I will split
this guy here compose
app. Okay, so this will spin up
a Kafka on my machine.
I hope everyone is connected right now and
let's try it. I will call this
new service and voila.
I'm using a wine generator to populate my kafka
and getting a list of wine with prices.
All right, good. So well, we did it.
We made it. Okay guys, I'm really help when
things just work. This was our call time so
I would like to end just sharing with you those QR
code and this URL from developers Redhead.com,
our red hat developers program where we share a
lot of content about Java containers, microservice,
kubernetes, all the cloud native related stuff you can
just describe and we will send to you when we
have news about it. Okay, so in the portal there are
a lot of content, all free, all open source. Because everything
that we did, everything that we do on red hat is open source.
Okay? So we are very happy to share all those with
you and just to say goodbye to you. I'm really happy
that you shared your time with me in these few minutes
in this session. I hope you enjoyed and you have here my
twitter. Okay, so you can reach me on Twitter. If you have any questions,
any comments, just please share with me. I will
be very happy to talk to you. See you next
time. Have a great confidence and bye.