Youll. Hello. Thanks for
joining me here today. It's a pleasure to have you.
Please do leave a comment and let me know who
you are, where you're joining from. It'd be really kind of great to kind of
get a feel for who youll guys are and who's interested in
this sort of thing. Okay, so the elephant in
the room policy is kind of whole
thing to make it sound sexy, but I'm
going to try and at least get your attention, so just bear with me for
a minute. So to set the scene, I'm in a lift.
Yes, american friends, we really do call them lifts.
And four people walk in. I think to myself, Chris,
this is youre moment. Now or never. As the doors close,
I position myself in front of them, a captive audience.
They're mine. I've got them. I take a breath.
I look to the first person on my left. She's in a suit. She looks
really important, too. I gesture to her. See?
She looks back at me as if to say, yes. Go on. I she nods.
Oh, perfect. The CIO, the policymaker, the one whose neck
is on the block. What are the chances of hindering you in my imaginary
lift today? Well, I ask her, well, what keeps you up
at night? And she tells me,
I don't know what teams are really doing, what the
volume of risk is, and what I should be showing more interest in.
Setting and changing policy is often slow and hard
to communicate, and people ultimately just go off and do their own thing.
They think they know better, and to be honest, often they do.
But ultimately I'm then left playing catch up with the risk that
they've signed me up to. Okay, I say, trying not to sound like a
patch noising snake or salesman. I can help.
I turn my attention to the second person in a suit.
They look maybe slightly less important. I make a guess. Let's trace
it. It's my imagination here. It'd be weird if I was wrong.
Product manager, I say. They nod. The whip cracker, I say.
What's important to you? So managing risk,
mostly opportunity risk. So the fear of missing out, getting features out the
door and avoiding getting bogged down with. They glance to the CIO
Bureaucracy. That feels, though, it's almost designed
to slow me down. Awesome, I say.
This is your lucky day. I turn to the next person
dressed in overalls. I'm in a trendy part of town. They could
be the CTO. Before I ask, they sense me staring at them.
Cleaner, they say, how did you get in my imaginary lift
today? Okay, I'll come back to you. My attention goes to the
last person. Hoodie, headphones around their neck. My stereotypical developer.
Yes, I know you well. What code do you write? Ask.
It doesn't really matter. Python. Cool. Have you got everything?
Updates to I work with. I pause. Python three?
They offer. Yes, Python three. That must be hard,
I add. They don't know it yet, but I've kind of just won a bit
of their trust, which is important, nearly. They say.
Cool, what's important to you? So, staying on top of patching
things so we can react to the next fire,
knowing what rules exist, what ones I can bend,
break, and ultimately what might cause me to lose my job.
Writing consistent, good quality code and avoiding
technical debt. The rest of my team being
able to cohesively work as one.
Do you use any tools to help you with that? I ask. Yeah, Linta's code.
Quality test coverage. The can I use all remit.
Great, I say. I wrote code, too. Let's be friends. And I hand them a
printed QR code. Here's my public GPG key, so you know that
you can trust what I say. I return my focus to the
cleaner. I've got it. How do you get told what to do and then when
it changes? Well, we get a memo or something stuck to the
notice board. Last week we got a memo saying that all the meeting room
whiteboards needed to be cleaned every night. Interesting,
I say. How does that then work out for you? Well, it's up
to us to then maintain that to do list so we can onboard new people
and just kind of keep a list of what we're up to. Does it go
wrong at all? Yeah, sometimes. If when we compile
that operational manual and we miss a memo or don't apply everything
all in the right sequence, we get things wrong. They glance
apologetically to the product manager, like when we hadn't updates
the guide that the meeting room on the third floor was being used as
a dedicated war room and we wiped all their boards down.
I looked to the dev. Sound familiar? They nod.
Turns out we're not all special snowflakes. Hey, all is not
lost. I knew there was a reason that I imagined you here today.
The lift is slowing. I feel it coming to its destination.
Great. I've got the silver bullet for you, too.
The CIO looking to me, ready to buy literally whatever
it is I'm selling. They ask me, as the does open, who are
you and what team are you in? As I move out the way. So to
stop obstructing the door. Oh, I don't work here. I'm just here to
fix the lift. People have been complaining it only goes to the top floor and
no matter what button they push, and it's actually pretty slow.
My audience storms out furious, heading towards the stairs
and the door shut. I get back to my job.
Okay, so if any of that sounds a bit familiar and you can relate
to my imaginary friends, I may have some answers for you today.
So what if I said you could update
policies easily, even releasing several versioned updates,
not just in a year, a month, what about ten updates
in a single day? And then seamlessly communicate that to the people that need
to consume it without derailing them. You could have visibility
on compliance using tools that you maybe already use, and that
policy could be readily consumable, easy to pass,
demonstrate compliance, make sense, and not be bureaucratic to
change when it needs to, and not ultimately going to get in the way.
That same policy could be treated as a dependency and operate like
a linter. So you can run compliance checks locally in CI and
then ultimately kind of guard production that multiple
versions of the policies like a dependency are supported.
So emergencies like you must update now because there's
no and vulnerability type updates are, in effect of business as
usual activity in order to actually communicate to those that need to know.
Does it sound interesting? Great,
let's crack on. So hopefully
I've got at least a little bit of your attention. It's time to introduce myself
and start explaining things. So, my name is Chris Nesbittsmith.
I'm currently an instructor at Learn KX and also control plane,
a consultant to the Crown Prosecution Service which is
part of UK government and a tinkerer of open source
things, I've spent a fair chunk of my kind of professional career now
working across UK government and large organizations
where problems like this are rife. I've been promised
we'll have time to be able to kind of handle questions and
heckles or whatever. So please do leave those in the chat as we kind of
go, and I'll be around to try and do my best to respond to them.
If I don't get back to you, then please find me on LinkedIn or message
me somehow.
So while this is not a live or in person
recording where I could ask you to say raise your
hands, we can still try some audience
participation. So if you could leave me
a comment of policymaker if you're with
my CIO and have ever set, written or applied
policy before. So if
you've ever written, set or applied some policy before,
say like some coding styles or anything else,
like cloud policy, things like that.
Anything like that. If you've written it or applied it or implemented it,
can you write policymaker in the chat?
Policymaker. Cool. Hopefully I've given you
enough time. So next round,
if you've ever maybe sought exemptions or consciously bent,
broken, circumvented, ignored, bypassed,
whatever, a policy with hopefully, let's just say maybe
some at least good intentions, youll you leave a comment
of policy breaker in the chat.
So if you've ever kind of worked around a policy, done a
workaround, circumvented it, found a loophole,
everything like that, kind of hacked around with it. Policy breaker.
Well, great, you fell for it. Hopefully,
if I've got anyone to do this.
So we've got all of your names and employers details down thanks
to the organizers. So you can put your phones down,
lend me your ears, give me your full attention. Ultimately,
the stakes just got raised.
So where do I see policy as code generally going
wrong? Well, before we dig into that, what do I mean by
policy? Well, it usually comes in one of
two forms, so security enforcing like data at
rest, being incepted, for example, or maybe consistency enforcing
such as code style, with tabs being two or youre spaces
perhaps, or maybe you can think of some others,
but in any case, it's hopefully intended to mitigate a
risk of some sort.
Hopefully with the best of intentions, though,
these are often emotionally led rather than being grounded
in a proportionate control, which then lends
itself well to being the open door to case by case exemptions
being required when you come against a situation that you weren't expecting.
So this actually is not unlike how typically the laws
of the land are created with causes law making for a complex
if not impossible to navigate rulebook, and then ultimately,
then harder still to measure for compliance,
can often look like the thin end of a wedge where the precedent,
which may have been an uncomfortable pill to swallow the first time round,
becomes dangerous, with others looking to expand upon its
scope, which can lead us to sometimes wonder
if the cure was worse than the disease. But that's
not how we at least typically develop software. So why does this
sort of code have to be so hard? There must be a better
answer. Well, we codified everything else, so isn't
that the answer? Well, yes, in part, but my point of this talk is
that we do it wrong. So maybe some of you
are out there kind of screaming, or maybe even typing your favorite product name
at me as the solution, and you're
not kind of wholly wrong, necessarily, but the devil's
in the detail. Throwing some curly braces or
yaml at something doesn't inherently fix things.
So if it's a security control, it's often tempting to
keep that policy a secret. Exposing it could be used against
you, perhaps as an adversary. However, that does
not support us in the kind of shift left culture at all.
It results in devs effectively reverse engineering what that policy might
be by finding out when we kind of smash our heads up against it,
and good thing, says no. Therefore, it doesn't
take much imagination to see that in the scenario of an application deployed
midway through, hindering one of the resources is noncompliant
and gets rejected would leave the overall deployment in can inconsistent
halfway state. This could result in some downtime,
which begs the question of was that policy better than the downtime
to the business? Especially if that consequently leads
our engineers, who are all hopefully or plenty smart at finding
inventive, shall we say, ways around the computer, says no
response that they'd got. This is then further exasperated
when updates to the policy are versioned. So maybe you get a pen test or
something goes wrong. So you form that case law and
need to apply a new policy. So maybe all s three
buckets now need to be encrypted, a change that could be considered
a breaking one. Youre, you might say that you provide warnings
on at least the less important issues or new emerging
policy, which is great so long as
someone sees them. But if you've adopted
Gitops or at least CI CD and somewhat guys,
is anyone seeing those warnings? So who studies the results of a
successful build log every time?
Anyone? Every time?
Well, if you are, I'd probably politely suggest that you're
kind of missing the point of CICD, you should really
be able to trust your job status. Okay,
well, I'm not just here to throw stones, so if you remember my
implied promises to my four imaginary friends of what the kind of utopian promised
land might look like, well, there's nothing new
under the sun. We've actually already unwittingly solved
most, if not all, of these problems elsewhere. We just need to be reminded and
kind of join the dots up and remember that it's code and it's software.
So. Well, the first is, if it's something you're probably
doing kind of policy as code, probably, or doing, say, put it in
versioned control. The thing you might not be doing, though, is making that
visible. So at least in a source set, by which I
mean anyone within your walled garden of employees,
suppliers, subcontractors, whatever to see the policy.
I'm not saying give all away, give all your threat monitoring and
intel away. You can probably keep that to yourselves.
But I'd argue that the visible policy and the gaps therein is
often better than the downtime, reverse engineered workarounds
and opaque legacy exemption spaghetti soup.
If you're brave, youll might even open source it. You will find that it unlocks
the ability to work well with prospective suppliers without NDAs and whatnot.
And widely distributed secrets are often expensive to
maintain, difficult to handle, and often only stay secret
for so long, after all. Okay,
well, we're off to a good start. Our policy is visible now to those that
need to see it. Many of you, no doubt, are used to semantic versioning,
but a quick recap. The first segment is used to indicate
breaking, perhaps conflicting, change in the context of policy.
Let's say it's requiring resources to have a department label.
Maybe that will help with some internal cross charging. Who knows? I'm not judging.
An increment of that might look like requiring that to be from a
predetermined list rather than just be free text.
The second segment is to indicate minor changes that
shouldn't really break anyone. An increment to this might
look like correcting a spelling mistake on one of the department names.
The third segment is to indicate patch changes, so these should be a
no brainer for everyone to keep up to date with, and increments
that might look like adding a department to the available options.
Okay, so our policy is visible. It's in a repository now,
it's versioned. So we can easily communicate that policy. We can
trace on the release notes and expectations are
all managed by semantic versioning. In software we're
used to handling dependencies. So what if your policy was just another
dependency? You might unwittingly already
be doing this if, for example, you have, say, eslint as a dependency
in your JavaScript package, for example.
Okay, so our policy is visible in a repo, it's versioned,
we can easily communicate it. We can tack on the release notes and
expectations are managed by semantic version.
It's beginning to look a lot more like software.
Okay, I know testing is a dirty word,
but in order to make this an asset that everyone can depend
upon, it's also important to have some good examples
and best are essential to give everyone
confidence in the stability and surface any potential side effects
before they hurt everyone involved.
Consumers of this policy need to be able to test themselves against
the policy locally and also in CI CD,
thus shortening the feedback loop and better informing things.
And as a bonus, we should therefore find ourselves and
our consumers able to rely on that artifact that we're sharing with them.
Well, we're well and truly on the home stretch. It's a
dependency, so updating it should be no different to any other.
We can even use some magic like GitHub's dependipot or men's
renovate to do that for us. So think automatic pull request best,
even auto merging if you like.
Okay, so to check you're all still awake,
can anyone leave me a comment and let me know
of a recent event that caused people to want to know what
version of a certain logging Java doohickey
you were potentially running literally everywhere in
the estate? Leave me a comment, let me know what that is,
what topic and theme of that is.
Yes, as you know, all presentations this year are
contractually required to reference log four j,
even when it's almost entirely out of context
and include some memes about it. In just a few short
months I can remove these and hopefully just point
broadly at a list of scary looking cves in order to command your
behavior through fear. What I'm getting at here
though, is the situational awareness piece around software
supply chain is something your organization is hopefully already
thinking about, if not already addressing. So if
our policy is a dependency, this is at least not a new problem software
kind of bill of materials for the win, right?
Which ultimately gives us the abilities and to measure
the compliance across the estates. Okay, so I've just covered
a lot of ground and hopefully sounded vaguely convincing.
And this isn't just a fictional utopia that's been painted in PowerPoints.
Well, it's time to look at how youll might be actually able to do this.
And I know you really came here wanting to see a million words on
a slide and not just the odd emoji or two that you've seen up till
now. So we've reached the point where I get to show you some code.
Hooray. To maintain the scope, though, I'm going to be limiting this to
talking about two things to prove that it's not just one tech or tool.
I've arbitrarily picked terraform and kubernetes,
but I could have picked anything. And naturally I'll need
some tools to go along with this. I'm generally too lazy to invent
too much here, so likewise I'm going to pick two tools.
But again, I could have used any, some, or even
all, probably. So Chekhov is going to be doing my terraform
and Caverno will be doing my kubernetes.
If you want to browse along with me, I've created can example
GitHub organization here. I'm not expecting you to read or grock
the code on screen too much, so don't worry about it
really, it's just to prove that I've made a real thing.
So the policy is stored here.
So here's where my policy starts. At version 1.0
I've got policy that requires a department label on all
the resources, so as long as it's set, it doesn't actually matter what it is.
I've written tests for this, so note how the passing test cases
are really useful as a great example of what good and bad
looks like. We pushed a tag in git.
We've added release notes. I can sign it to provide
further assurance if my heart so desires. Obviously it
does, but moving on, version two point
looks similar only now that the department field has to
be one of a predetermined list like before test exists.
Release notes are written tags assigned.
2.1.0 is where we notice and correct that spelling
mistake of one of the options in the list of the departments
two one one, and we've now added a new department to the list
and app one and infra one. Some other repositories in
that well, those depend on version one point of
the policy if it's
not compliant with version two point or beyond. But how
do I know that it's not compliant with versioned two? Well, I configured
renovate to actually be automatically make me a pull request.
So when there's a new version of the policy it's super obvious. If I can
update my dependency and I can also see clear feedback about
where and why I'm not compliant.
I can also see all the pull requests over my so I can
now measure the compliance of my policy.
So moving on from that app two as
other repositories and infra two other repository,
they depend on version two point of the policy.
However, we could merge the open pull request there all the way
up to two one one. Finally, app three and infra three,
well they're dependent on two one one and they get a gold star from the
CIO. So there is a small touch of magic
here and it's not pretty. I've written some bash,
so don't judge me, even though I probably definitely
absolutely written a lot worse. But what this does
is allowing me from my dev laptop or in CI to evaluate
my code against the version of the policy. Ideally this might be a
bit less cumbersome, but it is what it is for now, pull requests and collaboration
are very welcome, and the last piece to the puzzle is
managing the lifecycle of the policies and allowing multiple versions
of the policy to coexist be accepted and evaluated
within a single runtime. I cheated a
bit here. Kubernetes gives you admission controllers. It's not so easy
to get that same policy evaluation in a cloud done locally.
They've got their own policy engines, and I've just not figured out a way
to be able to execute and evaluate that locally. Again,
pull requests, collaboration contribution are
really all very welcome in this space, and I'd love to hear from you.
So you may have noticed that the way the policies is actually
designed and written and distributed lends itself well to coexist
with itself in a Kubernetes cluster. Which brings
us to cluster one, which describes a cluster that accepts all of the versions
we've described in the cluster,
all the versions of the policy that we've described so far.
And the reason that's happened is I've applied all of those policies.
Likewise, cluster two exists. However, this only
accepts two point and greater, and we can
automate some of this and to prove the point by using
kind for some CI to apply that policies and deploy
our applications. And there we have it,
a full organization, all done, wrapped up compliance policy,
all versions CIO, all aware of what's going on, everyone well
communicated with. So this sounds great, right?
But just one more thing. Wouldn't it be awesome if
the policy carried a story about why it exists?
After all, if your agile delivery teams are even half
effective, they should be rejecting anything that they perceive
as friction. If they don't see the value in it, it could
allow our developers to know why they are compliance,
and if they want to do something outside of what the policy permits,
they don't need any sort of exemption granted per se.
They can actually go and have a well reasoned and informed debate
with a rationale behind a pull request to the policy that
is attached to an understood risk of why the
policy exists. So if you imagine, if you will,
it's going through a stage of versions with risks that
inform kind of the mitigations manifested as the policy,
all maintained as kind of one living thing.
So when the risk landscape changes, your policy can move with it.
So, for example, when some new privacy regulation comes out,
or your latest marketing strategy pays off and you acquire more data,
even if your policy was perfect at one point in time,
the risks and the appetite will stand still for
no one. So we can liken this in some ways to
over provisioning that we might be familiar with from elsewhere.
Where lead times are long, changes hard, and there is a significant pressure
in nailing it the first time, which can lead us to hedging bets
against what that future state might be, rather than proportionate
mitigation to the risks that are actually more tangibly in the real
right now. So that's where the real
culture change is needed, and the exemptions of that is likely
a long series of talks in of itself.
So now this is really all over to you. Honestly, the best
thing that you could do right now is tell me this is all madness,
already done, irrelevant, or just otherwise unachievable,
something my esteemed echo chamber of peers have yet
to do. But beyond making Paul requests
and developing the theory more, I'd really like to start building some test cases
with other willing organizations, and that will allow me to
swap out more of my imaginary friends for some real ones.
But the most important thing that I want you to remember from our time
together today is, and please do feel free
to say this out loud with me.
Purposeless policy is potentially practically
pointless policy. I've been practices
saying that far too many times. I've been Chris
Esbet Smith thank you so much for your time. You're now free to disconnect
and leave. I will work with the organizers
to make sure the evidence of your guilt admissions earlier are destroyed.
I'll try like subscribe whatever the kids do on LinkedIn,
GitHub and whatever you can be. Rest assured that there'll be no spam
or really much content at all, since I'm pretty awful
at self promotion, especially on social media cns
me that just points to my LinkedIn and talks. CNS me contains
this and some other talks. They're all open source on my GitHub.
Questions are very welcome on this or anything else.
Be around in the comments for a while.
So please do. Please reach out or
ping me a message on LinkedIn. Be great to hear from you and
hear what your thoughts are. Thank you very much.