Hi, I'm Dol. And today we're going to talk about a team that
rises from a rises. And in order to do that,
I want to start with a small story.
Let's say, I'm sure you're familiar
with this. The sky is clear, the grass
is green, everything is great.
You're in your car, traveling to your work, everything is
just superb. Your new feature just
got up yesterday, and the customers are using it. And happy,
your product manager is happy, your own manager is happy,
everyone is just happy. Until you
have a bug. Now, you don't know exactly
when it started, you don't know exactly where, but you're
seeing a tremendous amount in support calls.
And you notice when you arrive to the office that three of your teammates
are looking at the same screen. And you know that's bad news.
So when did it happen?
Okay. I mean, like yesterday, you were okay,
everything was great. But now this is what you're dealing with,
right? And think about it. We all know
we're going to have bugs in the future, right? We all know we
had bugs in the past. But let me ask you this. Do you
know when does your next bug will occur?
Do you know where? Do you know what kind
of effect will it have on your product?
Weird, right? Because you know that there's going to be a bug.
You're certain about it, but you don't know where.
You dont know where, you dont know nothing, right? But it
doesn't have to be a bug. It can be your best employee saying
goodbye and leaving for his startup. It can be a
pivot you have to do in the product because the market demands it
could be a million things. My point is,
shit happens, right? And today,
this is just what we're going to talk about. We don't know
when, we don't know where, but we know it's going to happen.
And the essence of this talk is how we're going to
deal with it. So, hi, I'm Dole. And today
we're going to talk about your teams and how will it affect
the next rises. So, a few words
about me. I'm married with Elle and father of Ayala.
I'm a senior software engineer. I've been around nine
years, give or take, in various amount of teams. And this is
amount of incidents I had to deal with, so to say.
Okay, so now that we've introduced,
let's talk about the reason why we're here. So basically,
we sailing in rough waters, right? We know that,
and we don't know when the storm is going to hit us. We don't
know where, but we know it will. It's out there waiting for us.
And the question is not when it's going
to be. The question is, how will this affect your team?
And by asking these questions, I actually want
to ask another question. The lead question I want to ask is
how resilient your team is for this kind of storm.
Okay. Because it's out there. We know that.
So in order to answer this question, I want to answer three
smaller questions or maybe address
three issues. The first is growth culture,
which stands for, can your team really absorbs the
shock? Okay. The second,
does your team can handle the incident? I. E, can the
team respond to the shock? And the third,
rise. Can your team evolve from the shock?
Okay, three questions. So the
first one, growth culture. Growth culture is
the foundation of every going organization.
It's a set of skills and principles that
every organization depends on. And basically,
this is the first thing that determines how will
your teams reflect this incident
and how will this affect it.
There are a few principles I want to discuss,
and the first thing is to focus on learning.
What does it actually mean? Focus on learning means
that you want to make sure every day that tomorrow you'll
be a bit better than you were today.
It's true for yourself, it's true for your team. It's true for
your company. It's true basically everywhere you look around.
But how do you do that? So the first thing you might
think about is online recesses, right?
You have courses, you have books, you have lectures, you have meetups,
you have whatever. Everything is available
nowadays for free or for minor price.
And it's out there just waiting for you to reach and grab
it. Do it. You don't know the tremendous effect
it will make both on you and your team.
The second thing I want to talk about is guilds.
Now, what actually a guild is, a guild is a group
of people with a certain domain that come together
and talk about a certain subject. They ask questions,
they discuss things. They try to get to improve.
Now, if your company does not have a guild, start one today.
Don't wait. The people around you are waiting
for this kind of platform, and the
sooner you do that, the better. Now, this doesn't have
to be necessarily with your own people from your own team or
your own company. This could be in the form of meetups where
you can meet with people from other companies and discuss
their issues, which I'm guessing quite similar to your issues,
and think about the way you can resolve things.
Learn from experience of others, share some of your own
great work. Now these are all
pretty standard ideas, but I want to talk about a few more.
For starters, system design, or let's say
system documentation. Okay. Think about
it. You're in a company. You have a product, a big one, a massive one,
complex one. It does tremendous
work. It does all kinds of. But have
you ever stopped and read that it's documentation?
Have you ever stopped and read its entire capabilities,
whether it's weak spots, its strong spots, what it can do,
what it cannot do? Think about it. This could
be a great way to see, to look for the next storm.
Okay, the next thing I want to talk about is
design reviews. Design reviews is a way for you
to tell people what you plan to do before you do it.
You address an issue, you find a solution, and before
you start to implement it, you present it to your team,
to your manager, to everyone relevant to this issue.
You're saying this is the problem and this is how we're
going to face it. These are the drawbacks. These are the strong
parts. This is my solution.
And then you wait. You wait for the feedback.
You wait for people to tell you you should look at this part.
You wait for people to tell you, I don't think this is possible.
You wait for the drawbacks and they improve
your solution. Do that before you start to implement,
not after, because then it gets incredibly harder.
The last but not least thing I want to talk about in this subject
is tests. Think about it.
Tests are your best way to connect with the mind of the person
who wrote the code you're dealing with. It's as if
he's telling you, this is what I meant for this code to
do. This is what I want to check.
This is what considered to be a good behavior.
This is what's considered to be a bad behavior, okay?
Whether if this person is one of your teams, one of
your teammates, or even you from the past and you don't remember why you did
what you did. Read the test, not just pass them.
Okay? It will give you a clear view what the writer
meant for. And finally schedule
a time for it. I cannot stress this enough,
schedule a time for this. If it's not in your calendar,
it does not exist. Okay? Make a slot
every week, every day. I don't know. It doesn't matter.
A few hours every week that you invest in these areas,
it will get you better. It will help you improve.
The person you will be tomorrow is much better than
the person you are today. Please schedule
time for it. The second point
is continuous communication. Continuous communication
starts with basically communication
and open communication. What does it mean?
Open communication means that you feel free
to tell people what you think.
I know it sounds simple. You'll be surprised
in how many teams. That's not the case. Tell people what
you think. You think this feature is wrong. Tell them you
think this solution is too complex. Tell them you
think we have a problem that we don't see today but we'll see tomorrow.
Tell them open communication is one of
the pillars for a team that evolves and
grows and improves.
Okay? You have to feel safe to talk your ideas.
The second thing is clear goals. When you
are given a goal or when you give a goal, both you
and your manager should know what the outcome should look
like. Again, simple. I know, but you'll be surprised.
Both you and your manager should know what your goal is,
how you plan to implement it and what will the final
outcome will look like. It's as if he's telling you to train
a horse and you draw a dog instead. You don't want to do that.
Okay? You want to set clear goals and you want everyone
to know what it is that you are changing to do
and how will you achieve that.
Another thing is transparency. This is super
important. You don't want to hide the
bad stuff. You don't want to. Don't talk about
the weak spots. You want to be transparent as possible.
If something is too complex, tell the
people about it. If you made an error, if your
data is corrupted, if your system is not going to stand
the overload, talk about it. If something happens,
communicate it. Okay? This is the ground
rules of communication. You need to talk about the bad
things as well as the good things. And this is super
important to be as transparent as possible. Not just in your own team,
but with other teams as well. If your
team made something, it affect another team, tell them
about it before they find out themselves.
Okay? And the final thing
in this subject is regular check ins.
By regular check ins I mean talk with the people
in your team and ask them how are they?
Are they okay? Are they feeling well? Is the subject
they're trying to deal with the last week or
so is bothering them. Do they need any help?
Okay. You'll be surprised with some of the answers you may hear.
Make sure you do this on a regular basis and not just once
a year when you have to. Okay? This is super crucial.
This is super important. You want the people in your team to be happy.
You want to know that they enjoy the work you're doing. You want to
know they understand the work they're doing and why they're doing it.
Okay. And why not something else? This is super important,
and you want to make sure every once in a while that everything is okay
as you expect it to be.
The next point I want to talk about is supportive environment.
Now, what does that actually mean? Supportive environment,
again, is with the culture of your team. It takes a long
time to build it, but once you have it, it is a strong tool that
you want to hold on. How can you do that?
By first, you want to encourage collaboration. You want people
to work with each other. You want people to understand
each other's ideas. You dont want one person walking on
something and the next day another person trying to work
with it and doesn't understand what the hell is going on
and why that person did what he did. You want people working together,
talking the same language, understanding the same problems,
working together and solving them. Okay?
The next thing you want to do is provide support and resources.
If you have a teammate that struggles on some mission
and needs help, help them. If someone needs
an extra time or an extra tool or skill or
whatever, help them make them better,
because if they're better, your team is better. Okay,
straight up. If they are better, your team is better,
and you want to give them all the tools and resources you can
in order to make that happen.
The next thing is to forego blame.
Let's say something did happen. Something broke, something was corrupted,
something was. I don't know, things happened all the time.
You don't want to look for the person responsible for it.
You don't want to look at the past. You want to look at the future.
What will we learn from it? How can we use this to improve
next time? How can we make sure this will not happen?
Okay. These are the questions that will help you lower
the chances that this will happen again. Not who did
this and should we fire him? This is not
helping anyone, especially not your product. Okay.
In order to improve your product, you need to learn from these mistakes and
not looking for the person who didn't.
The next point I want to address is experimentation,
or space for experimentation.
What does that mean? So you have your team,
and you're working on your solution, and you're advancing
with it, and it's going well, but you want to keep
enabling these parts of the work as well. What does that mean?
You want to encourage creativity.
Just because you have something that works does not
mean it cannot work better. Okay? You cannot
improve it. Now,
beware of premature optimization, because that's a lesson
we all should learn. But basically,
just because something works does not mean it cannot
work better or faster or cheaper or,
I don't know, maybe there's a way to improve it. And the
best way to find out is to be creative.
Try look for new angles, new solutions. Maybe we can do
something today we could not do before. Think about it.
The next point I want to address is the resources
and time again, like in the last point
I said, you want to provide your researchers,
your team, the people who is in charge of this
task, the means to do so. Okay?
If something is a bit complex, if something requires
a new approach, give people time to investigate.
Give people the tools they need in order for them to provide with
a full solution and not something they made just
to make you happy. Okay? If you give people
the confidence and the feeling
that they can do and whatever they want,
and explore new boundaries, within limits, of course, but explore
new boundaries, you'll be amazed how much
progress it will achieve for you.
The last thing I want to talk about is the culture of
the teams and the continuous improvement of it,
okay? Again, just because something is
working does not mean it could not work better.
Now you want to do it on your own level, on the team level,
on the company level. Okay?
You want to always ask yourself, can we improve?
Can we do better? Why are we doing what we're doing today?
Are we sure this is the best solution? Or was
this the quickest solution we can find? And we
quickly moved on. You'll be surprised.
Sometimes you'll go and you find something in your code or
your project or whatever that's been there for years because
someone meant for it to change one day and that simply
didn't happen. Okay? And you can
achieve from it. You can grow from it. Continuous improvement
culture is a major tool in your toolbox
that enables you to move on and progress.
The next point. Sorry,
the next point I want to talk about is empower champions.
Okay? What does that mean?
Traditionally, we used to talk about, or we talk about a lot about
bad things, when things break, when things need
to be removed, to be fixed, to be changed, to be improved,
how often do you talk about the good things, the achievements,
the progress, the people who made them?
Okay. Now, empowering champions can be done in
a lot of ways. First of all,
celebrate victories. Okay?
If someone made a goal, he deserves to dance after
it. Okay? Messi can tell you that need
to recognize the team achievements and talk about them and talk
with other teams about them for them to learn and improve.
You want to share success stories. You want for the
people who've been in the trenches to talk about it and how they made
it out. Okay? It will inspire the people
in your organization. It will give great motivation.
It will give the people the thing they need. You want
to take time to reflect about it. It could be once
a week, once a month, once in a quarter, once in whatever.
Okay? But you want to share and celebrate
the success stories. You deserved it. You made it. It's yours.
The next point I want to talk is task pitching now.
Okay, think about this scenario. You're at the
beginning of your sprint of your quarter. I don't
know. But at some point you
think about the new tasks and goals you want to achieve and you give
them. If your manager giving you the tasks, if you're giving
the tasks to your employees,
basically orders come from up below.
But what if they work the other way around?
What if your employees could pitch some of the
tasks to you? Okay, what does
that mean? Like, let's say every sprint,
you talk with your employees and you decide to do. You want to do a,
b and c, but what if you save a place
D, where your employees can say,
we noticed that there is a problem in this area and we know that
people are afraid of touching it, and maybe we can change that.
Or you remember the bug we had earlier
and it caused some disruptions in
something. Let's take a look at that. Or remember that algorithm
we said we wanted to explore? Let's do
that. Now, by giving your employees
the opportunity to pitch their tasks, you're basically giving
them a sense of responsibility because it's
their own tasks. They pitched it, they made it,
they present it to the team. And if the team or you
decide to accept that pitch, great. It goes
on the board and it's a proper task.
But it's not a task that you gave and your employees now
need to do. It's a task that your employee gave to themselves.
Okay? The feeling of
commitment, the feeling of responsibility. The ownership of
this task is much higher. Okay,
think about it.
The next part I want to talk about is lead hackathons.
And I'm pointing this with
a dot here because it does not have to always be hackathons.
It can be initiatives in general.
Okay. It relates to the point we just talked about.
But basically you want to give your employees stronger sense
of ownership, stronger sense of responsibility.
Now, hackathons are a great way because you can take
the junior employee and make him the team lead of your manager,
for example. But it doesn't have to be a hackathon. It could
be any initiative someone in your team is trying to advance,
help them with that, teach them with that,
make them become more responsible
for that action. It will make them feel
much more empowerful in the organization and much
more sense of this is done because
I wanted it done. I wanted it to be done. And this is
what we came up with. Great, great success story to
celebrate. Think about it.
So, let's recap.
We said we want to focus on learning. We want to keep advanced
and enrich our knowledge. We want to have
a continuous communication. We want the team, the people in
the team could be able to talk with each other and have an open
communication as well with other teams.
We want to have a supportive environment. We want people to
not be afraid to make mistakes. We want people to know that
it's a safe place that can advance
with. They can be bigger with. Okay,
we want to enable space for experimentation. We need
to enable to do mistakes and
to go the wrong way in order to find the right way.
Okay. We don't just simply land on the right way.
We find it after spending time in the wrong ways.
Okay. We want to enable space for experimentation.
And we want people to know it's safe to experiment.
Super crucial. Finally, we want to empower
the champions. We want people to have a strong sense of
ownership about the things they're doing.
We want people to advance
more initiatives. We want people to not just do what they're
told, but also to feel part of
the company, the solution. We want people
moving new ideas.
Great. So you have a growth culture.
But the second thing we want to ask, can you handle
the incident? Okay, so let's
go back to our story from before.
The first thing you want to do is to identify the incident.
What does that mean? Remember earlier when you
were driving your car? Everything was great. Suddenly, you reach
to the office, three people looking at the same screen with
sad faces. The first thing you want to do is to identify
what just happened. Let's say that this is your system,
okay? This is your algorithm, this is your whatever.
And you see that people are looking at one of the monitors with
long faces, and you understand something went wrong.
The first thing you want to do, activate the response team.
You need to understand who are the best people
to address this type of issue. It could be from your team,
it could be from other teams. It could be collaborate, cooperation,
I don't know. But you want to activate the response team because this is
what you're doing right now. We have an issue in production. We need to
fix this now. Activate your response team.
Great, so you did that. But let's say that the
time it took for you, your bug is not only in this
component, but you also have it in other components,
okay? It's spreading and you don't know why or
where it's going to spread next. The next thing you want to do
once you've activated your team, is containers.
You want to make sure that this error, this mistake, does not
affect other teams, other services,
other protesters, okay?
Containment, it means shifting
traffic to another service. It means using
a different data than you used to because this data is corrupted.
I don't know every bug, its own solution. But the
first thing you want to do is to contain the bug so you can control
it, okay? So it doesn't spread to your entire system.
Great. So if you've contained the problem and you have a team working
on a solution now, what you
want to do is to investigate the root cause. You want to understand
what happened that caused this issue. Why didn't you saw
it before? Okay? You want to
address the issue and figure out what's exactly
happening right now that is broken in your system
in order for you to fix it. So let's
say you did that and you saw this
small part in your data that is causing something,
that start a chain reaction,
that this is the outcome you're seeing
now that you have people working on the incidents and
you have contained the issue, now you can try
and to restore and recover. You can fix the
bug, make sure it works, make sure you can reproduce
the problem and your fix is actually fixing it.
And after all that is done,
you can now deploy and make your system smile again.
Okay? Make sure.
Okay, so this is basically the process. Now you
have to make sure throughout this entire process that you always
communicate with the stakeholders. If there's
an SLA issue, if something is broken,
if something is not doing what it's meant to do,
you want the people that could be affected from it, whether it's other teams
or your customers, to know about it, okay?
People are relying on the information you're given.
You want to give them the right information. You want them to
act accordingly. Okay? Super important.
Especially while you're still handling the case,
okay? You don't want to wait for the case to be solved,
which sometimes can take even hours,
maybe even more, for people to know that
something happened, for people to suddenly see
that the thing you're saying is not actually right or it's not correct,
and to lose their trust in you.
That's the worst thing.
That's the worst possible thing that can happen and you don't want to be
there. So communicate always.
So let's recap. We said
you first want to identify the incident. After that,
you want to activate your response team and have them start working on
it. The first thing they want to do is to
contain the incident. Make sure the incidents does not spread
to a different part of the system or different process that could
affect other teams and other logics.
After you have contained the incident and you know that
it's not going anywhere, now you can start and find the root
cause of the problem and try to solve it.
Once you do and you feel confident with your solution,
you can restore the system to its forking state
and recover from the bug. And finally,
always, throughout this entire process, communicate with
the stakeholders. Super important. Super important.
Sorry.
Okay, so we know
now that your team can a, absorb the incident,
right? And b, solve it. But there's
something missing, right? I mean,
we had a bug, we handled
it, right? But what's next?
Now, Churchill told us, never let
a good crisis go to waste. And this is exactly
the part I'm talking about. We already have that incident.
We already had that bug. Let's use it. We've learned
something today, right? Let's use it. Let's rises.
Okay, so going back to our story, you came in the
morning, you saw the people in your teams looking at the monitor.
Long faces. Activate response team.
Great. You solved the bug. Everyone is happy. The first thing you do
is postmortem, right? You want to understand
what happened. You want to investigate how can this
not go not will happen. Sorry.
You want to make sure that this will not happen again, right?
Great. Now, two major
important things I want to talk about postmortem and these are action
items and follow ups. Every postmortem should
have action items. I could not stress this enough.
If your postmortem does not have action items, you did not
did a postmortem. You simply wasted an hour of your team.
Okay? If you don't come up out of that
postmortem with action items, you're simply saying, we had
an issue, we solved it. Let's just wait for the next
issue. You need to have action items that will
make sure that next time, this will not happen to you.
Now, action items are great, but if
you don't follow them, if you don't make sure that you actually
did them, they're useless. Okay,
let's say you came out of the post mortem, you wrote your
action items. We need to fix this. You need to check that. We need
to make sure that this happens before that.
Great. But did you did it?
Is it actually done? So what I'm saying
is the minute you go out of the postmortem,
you want to schedule a new meeting for a week,
for two weeks, for a month, I don't know. But you want to schedule the
new meeting where you will follow up the action items
and make sure what has been done and what hasn't.
Okay. If you dont do these two things, you don't
have any point in making postmortem simply
a waste of your hour. Okay,
great. So you did a postmortem, you did action
items and you followed them. Great. But I
want to suggest a new idea. Like,
think about it. Instead of being
reactive to the incidents that just happened,
like something happened and you react to it,
let's become proactive. Let's try to
handle the incidents before they're happening and not after.
What do I mean? I mean, instead of
postmortem, let's do premortem.
Okay, bear with me. So basically
what just happened. You had an incidents, okay?
You fixed it. Great. And you post
mortem it, you understand why it happened. How did the fix work?
And now you're just waiting for the next incident, which will you
fix postmortem and so on.
But what if we reversed that cycle?
What if instead of waiting for the incidents,
we will do a premortem? We will understand
what the next incident might be. Because we
know this area of our system is
a weak area. We know that this area of our
system is relatively new area.
I don't know. We know something. Instead of waiting
for the next incident to occur, fix it. And to
discuss about it, let's discuss about what
will happen. The stuff that we are afraid of,
the stuff that we are not so comfortable about, we're not so
sure about. Let's understand why.
Let's make a plan of how we're going to fix that, how we're going
to improve that, and let's upgrade our system.
Okay. Instead of waiting for the storm to
come to us, let us come to the storm,
but better prepared. By doing that, you can control
some of the variables of your equation and not just wait for
your equation to find you.
So, great. So we talked about this.
Let's talk about another thing. Increase your resiliency.
Think about it. Something happened. Usually something small
happened that caused the chain reaction. That made something big
break, made something big corrupt.
If your system was more resilient.
Maybe the small thing still
happened, but maybe the effect was not so big.
Okay, if your system is resilient,
it can itself absorb some of the shocks,
like we talked in the first chapter.
Now, what does it mean to make your system more
resilient? First of all, you can upgrade it.
You can find the areas in your code that needs to be upgraded,
that needs to be shaken up, that needs to
be improved. And do it. Do that before
something happens, not after. Don't wait for the
lessons you learned from the incident. Try to discover. Try to explore
and to find the things in your system that
are broken. You just dont know it yet. Okay?
Upgrade those.
The next thing is to invest in your toolbox.
Sorry,
what does that mean? Do you
have enough documentation? Do you have
enough tests? Do you have enough visibility?
For when something breaks, you will be alerted
on okay, you don't want for the
Customer calling for you, telling you there was a problem in your product,
in your system. You want to know that
before it happens, in a different environment,
always better before it happens, and fix it
before it even actually gets to the customer. Okay?
I mean, you do stuff all the time. You break and
repair stuff all the time, you improve stuff all the
time. Sometimes you don't know its effect until
it's too late. You don't want to be there, you don't want to be
that spot. You want to understand the actual
effect of the change you're doing now before it
reaches the customer and address
it before it's too late. Okay?
You want to have playbooks. You dont
want that when something breaks, the people to start scratching
their heads and don't know what to do. You want to write a
fixed protocol of what to do if something happens.
Who are the people that needs to be alerted? What should
be checked, what should be backed up, what should be?
I dont know. I don't know about your system, but you want for
the people, for your response team to have the right tools, the right playbooks,
for them to solve the incident. You want to make sure
that while in an incident, which is a stressful situation,
they fought about everything they need to think about.
They touched all the points, they covered everything.
You don't want them to miss something because they
were stressed about it, okay? Because they didn't think about it.
And now you have a new bug somewhere else and it will take you
some time to reach for it. Write playbooks.
Also invest in your transparency
and discoverability.
You want for something when something breaks,
when something acts not the way it should be for a
notification to pop up, for a dashboard to go red,
for something to happen. Okay.
You want to be as visible as possible so that people,
yourself included, will understand as quickly as possible
what happened, what kind of effect it did,
what we need to do for the containment of this
incident. Okay? The better transparency you have,
the better visibility you have, the sooner you will be able
to answer these questions.
Finally, you want to share your knowledge.
Okay. You've been in the trenches. You've suffered an
incident. You fixed it. You came up with a new solution that
can fix the problem you didn't think about before. I don't
know. Tell people about it. People want to know.
People want to learn from your mistakes. Go learn from other
people mistakes. You want to share your knowledge about
how people, your people handle
this incidents in order to make everyone better, in order
to make everyone smarter. Okay? Share your knowledge.
Share the stuff you've learned. Make other people rise from your incidents.
So let's recap. We said
we want to do a post mortem. We want to investigate what
caused this incident and how we can fix this.
We want to do a pre mortem. We want to imagine what could
go wrong, what could break. We want to fix this before it
breaks. We want to test this new behavior before it reaches
something critical. Okay? Do a premortem,
even though nothing is currently broken, as you know of.
You want to increase your resiliency. You want your system to
be stronger. You don't want any tiny bug to
disrupt your system entirely. You want the containment
of it to be full. You want your system resilient.
You want to share your knowledge. You want people to learn from
your mistakes. You want to learn from other mistakes.
Again, you don't want everyone to fall in
the same pit for them to know how to avoid it.
Okay? If you step on something, tell people
how to avoid it for them to not step on it as well.
So we now have a teams that
can absolve the incident,
solves the incident and benefits from
the incident. Okay. If you
have a teams that's doing all these three things, your team is
no longer afraid of bugs,
is no longer afraid of incidents, your team a
bit, wait for it. I know it's weird, but it
recognize there's a chance of growth in
these areas, in these
things that we all know that will occur one day or another.
Again, think about what we said earlier. We dont know
when, we don't know where, we don't know what it will affect,
but we know the storm is coming. Okay? Use it.
Use it as your tool. Don't be afraid of it.
Look for it. Okay? Evolve from it.
And finally. Sorry. I want to finish
a few words. When the winds of change blow,
build walls while other build windmills.
Think about it. Harness the wind at your power.
Thank you.