Hello, everyone. Welcome to this presentation on demystifying
the card payment lifecycle. Today we'll be exploring the
various components and processes involved in
card payments, as well as the role of machine learning in the
domain. First, let me introduce myself.
My name is Michael. I'm a software engineer. I began my professional
journey in 2014 and over the past
decade I've had the privilege to work with leading companies
in several sectors of the payments industry.
My experience actually in payments spans across a
wide range of sectors,
from working with a smart data,
smart card data personalization company where we
embed EMV data into payments
card chips, to payment
processing, fintech issuer
banks and so on. And for me, it's been
a very exciting journey. I hope for you
either you are looking to move into
the payment industry or you're already within the payment industry. It will also
be an exciting journey for you. All right,
so before we go into all of the
things about the payment lifecycle,
I thought to share some stats to even let you know.
Why is it even important to want to know what happens with
payments or with card payments? Basically,
first, as of 2022, and this
number has increased drastically, but I couldn't get the more recent
stats. There were over 600 billion
transaction volumes per annum from
card payments and this amounted into $4.2
trillion in spending annually.
That's a huge sum of money. However,
unfortunately, there's also a substantial $30 billion
loss to fraud every year from
card payments also. So let's
identify some of the main components and parties involved in
the card payment ecosystem. The first and
foremost is your, you know, the actual payment card itself.
That's the card that your bank or your financial institution
issues to you to be able to spend from your
account, right? And this could be a physical card
that you tap or swipe at a pure
point of sale terminal or a virtual card which
could be on your wallets, on your phone and so on.
And these cards generally or typically
contains a 16 to 18 digits number in front
of them, which is called the pan or the primary account number.
Next component is the cardholder, which is you. This is pretty much straightforward.
If you have a payment card, you are a cardholder.
So basically you're the person who initiates transaction using the card
by swiping, tapping or entering your details online.
The next component is the issuer or the issuing
bank. Now this is the bank that the cardholder
has an account with, and that's the bank
that has issued the card to the cardholder.
Next we have the card scheme or card network. Usually these are
companies like Visa, Mastercard, American Express, you know,
China Union pay, and so on. They facilitate transactions
between issuers and acquirers.
Usually this, the card you get issued by your
bank would have the logo
of who the card network is or the card scheme.
Next is a merchant. The merchant actually is a business itself
that is accepting card payment for goods and services. This could be
Tesco, Sainsbury, Amazon, name it.
It could be a physical store merchant or an online merchant.
Next is the acquirer bank and the acquirer bank,
or the acquiring bank, or the acquirer is a financial
institution that actually processes card payment on behalf of the merchants.
Usually the acquiring bank is the bank where the merchants have their
own bank accounts, you know, so if you think about you as
a cardholder having your bank account with the issuer
who issues you a card, then the acquiring bank is
the bank where the merchants typically have their own account.
And typically the acquiring banks provide
the terminals that merchants, especially fish, scout store
merchants that need point of sale, like PoS terminals.
Usually the acquiring banks provide. Not always,
but usually provided by the acquiring bank. Those terminals,
last but not the least, is the payment gateway
or payment processor. These usually have technology providers that
help securely transmit transaction information between the merchants
and the acquiring bank. In most cases, these are more
likely to be used for online transactions,
and if the merchant has the technical capability
or expertise to be able to do this, payment gateways are not necessarily involved
in card payments. Transaction flow all
right, that was a lot. Please feel free to come back
to watch this part over again as
necessary if you missed anything in the first go.
So what do customers see when they make card payment?
Right from the customer's perspective, they interact with the card by
tapping their card on the terminal or entering their card
details on a website. And they
either get an optional, like verification
or authentication step in the old flow, which could
be asking for Pin or three deciseconds.
And after that, the next thing the customer says is whether the
transaction is approved or declined. So you either see that on the
POS terminal, or maybe you are redirected to a new page,
the success page on the web
portal for the merchant. And that's
it. You done? Payment done as
far as the customized concern, right?
Looks easy, right? Like my daughter would say, easy peasy.
Well, not quite easy
for the customer, which is good,
but not so easy for other parties involved because there
are a lot of other processes behind the scene that actually take
place, you know, and this includes authorization,
capture, settlement, reconciliation. We'll be talking about this
in detail. One after the other.
So starting with authorization, you know, this is actually the process that was described
in the previous slide where the cardholder initiates
the transaction when they want to pay for some goods and services.
You tap your card or, you know, enter your card
details, and then it initiates the authorization
request flow. So basically, what's the authorization request flow?
We can see from the diagram. The first step in the authorization request flow
is that the cardholder
swipes their card, tap their card, enter the card details, whatever initiated
by the cardholder, the merchant receives this and
then sends this request to the
acquiring bank, either directly or again through a payment
processor. The merchant sends that request to the acquiring bank.
It's called the authorization request. Now, the acquiring bank
looks at this request
and based on the
PAN, the first few digits in the PAN, it identifies
what issue, I'm sorry, what card network
the request should be routed to. And this could be either visa,
Mastercard or American Express. And once this
request is sent to the card network, the card
network itself, then based on the first six digits of the
PAN, determines,
actually six digits of the PAN is called the biN. That's a bank
identification number, or IIN, which is the issuer identification
number. So based on these first six digits,
the card network determines
what bank or what financial institution issued
that card and then they send a request to that financial institution. And this
could be bank of America, Citibank, or it could even be
one of the fintechs like wise revolutes and so on.
Right. Then the Ishwa
bank performs a number of things which could be include balance
check, to be sure you have sufficient funds to pay
for what you're trying to do. Fraud check.
You know, to prevent fraud,
there's also transaction limits, checks, right?
Have you gone over your daily limit, your monthly limits, you know,
and any other transaction rules that apply once
all of this is done, if successful, the bank would,
the issuing bank would freeze that
fund from the cardholders
account and then send a successful response
all the way back. So sends the response back to the card network,
the card network sends it back to the acquiring
bank. We then send that response back to the merchant.
And then you see you as a cardholder,
you see the result on either the terminal or
you get redirected on a website to the successful page that
the transaction is done. So again,
mouthful, this is everything that goes on.
Well, when I say everything, even still on a high level,
because there are a lot of other things that issuers
could do in the background and all of that. But, you know, this is like
an overview of the process and what happens when authorization
takes place.
Now, next would be capture,
right? Because when a transaction
takes place, the money is frozen from the
cardholders account. However, the merchant doesn't have the
money yet. The money is still technically with
the issuer, actually with the issuer.
But somehow the issuer knows that they owe some form of money to
somebody, right? So the next step that comes here
is at the end of the day, usually, not necessarily all merchants
do this, but usually at the end of the day, sometimes it
might take two days, three days. Merchants then compile
a list of transactions that they've sent for
authorization on that day and send
it as a batch request to their acquiring bank,
right? The acquiring bank takes this batch
request and then splits it, categorizes it according to
Whatcard network. Because take for example,
an Amazon or say, Tesco.
Hundreds and thousands of people paying every day would
definitely have paid with different cards issued
by different banks and which have different card networks.
Could be Visa, Mastercard, American Express, right?
Usually Visa, Mastercard in the UK.
What the acquiring bank would do in this
case is further categorize or
split that request into two. In this case,
Mastercard and Visa request send one to Mastercard
and send the one for Visa to Visa, right?
Once that request is sent to
those card schemes, the card scheme themselves,
or the card network would then say, in this example,
I'll just go ahead with the Visa. Say Visa receives that request
from the acquiring bank. Visa then further
splits the request based
on. Because this could be, again,
say, hundred transactions
and 50 of them could have been from cards issued
by bank of America or 30 of them from banks,
from Citibank, you know, 20 from HSBC
or wise, you know, and so
on. So the scheme splits
this and then send the request to the capture request
to all of those financial
institutions. Now, what the financial institution would do
is they received a request and then they try to match each capture
record to a transaction that they've previously authorized.
Right? To show that, okay, we've authorized this transaction before to
freeze this money. Now we are confirming that this transaction is
completed because the merchant is now asking that they would be
collecting this money, right? So that
happens. Now, for some banks, the user experience is
usually different. For some banks or for some financial institutions,
when you initiate a transaction, you see
the transaction with the status of pending. And when capture actually
happens, the status changes to completed.
While for some other banks,
when you, they show this to you in a way of showing
you two different balances, you could have an
available balance and a book balance or booking balance. Available balance
is the amount you have to spend, which usually is less than the
booking balance, because available balance would be booking balance
minus any pending money that needs to go out.
So, yeah, so that's
how capture is then done. And still
there's no money movement in capture. That just confirms that the merchant has
stated their intent to, you know, capture this money.
To collect this money, there comes settlement,
which is the step four of the diagram. Right. The issue bank
will then initiate after receiving settlement requests,
usually, sometimes through the card scheme, initiates the actual
money movement by paying this fund, maybe to the card
scheme or directly to the acquirer bank,
and then the acquire bank would then settle their merchants.
And yet again, this process,
even though it's technically the end of the
card payment life cycle, there's still reconciliation
that has to be, or that needs to be done by some
of these parties, especially the issuer bank. You need
to confirm that
the money that was paid in and the money that is paid
out actually matches. Right.
So what do I mean by that? There are several types
of transactions that could happen in a day. You know, you could have authorization requests,
could have reversals. You have chat box, you have fees.
It's even more complicated or more complex if you have multi
currency transactions. Right. You would need
to. A transaction could be done in one currency,
and the settlement is done in a different currency.
Companies have to implement very sophisticated
functionalities or very sophisticated systems to
actually do reconciliation.
Reconciliation, as far as I'm concerned, is, like,
the most difficult, the most daunting part of this whole process. Not to
say orders are simple. Mostly, they require speed.
When I type my card, I need to get a response as soon as possible
as to whether it's successful or not. I don't want to wait too long.
Every other thing is, it happens in the back end.
And for some of these, they are very computationally heavy.
So that's why I consider it one of the most,
you know, daunting parts or the one of the most complicated parts
of this. And just
before I move on, you know,
one reason why this is very.
You know, why it's a very daunting task is that
in addition to all of the types of transactions I've mentioned here.
Right. You could have something. We have something called
preord. I didn't want to go too
much into this, but we have something called preord. Right.
And basically, imagine when you go to a gas station to buy
fuel. This doesn't happen in every country anymore.
In some countries, you tap your card before you buy the fuel.
So gas station actually like,
sends authorization requests to reserve a certain amount. This could be say 100
pounds, and then you end up buying fuel.
And you might just buy foil for 60 pound and then there's a 40 pound
difference. When they send the captcha to the
issuer, they are going to be capturing the actual amount of the
foil you bought, which is 60 pounds.
And again, this is going to reflect the, the issuer
would have authorization request, which is 100 pounds. And then when they get the capture
request, it's 60 pounds. They need to be able to identify that this
is the same transaction. Also, when you go to hotels,
for example, you make payments, or sometimes they reserve some money just in case of
damages and of that, which brings me to the
point of where after authorization is done,
every merchant actually has a limited
amount of time to send
capture request. Otherwise that transaction would
be reversed or cancelled and the money will be refunded to
the customer. So even though you provided the
service and the person has gotten either the goods or the service,
if you don't capture within, I think there's
for pre authorization and authorization, you don't capture within seven to
15 days, then the transaction is reversed and
that's it. You have no legal rights to,
or the customer has legal rights if you try to capture their money to tell
you that it's now their money. So, yeah,
maybe something not to note,
but yeah, so that's on what actually
really does happen.
So where does ML come in in all of this?
First is fraud detection and
prevention. Right. We already said earlier that there's
over $30 billion per year in
fraud loss.
Usually all of the parties involved,
the issuer bank, the card scheme, or the
card network, the acquire bank, usually have
some form of fraud detection or fraud prevention
systems or mechanisms, right.
And usually these systems are
more efficient if you have some form of machine learning models
that are learning new tactics that
like basically getting new ways to identify what could be a
fraudulent, or detect what could be a fraudulent transaction.
Next is, yeah, again, it's very similar to the previous,
but in this case, identifying transaction data discrepancies.
Right. This is not necessarily used for fraud,
which is why I've separated them. Right. You might be using this to maybe in
your settlement flow or, or something just
to, you know, either rather than waiting for human
to find out that something has gone wrong somewhere. Because a lot of things go
wrong when it comes to payment authorization,
capture, and, you know, settlement reconciliation.
You could use machine learning to at least help you
automate and suggest, you know, it helps you
debug in sort of a way and shows you, hey, I think this could be
wrong. And then you can then go and find out
if it's truly wrong or not. Next is
predictive analysis, right. If you
are an issuer, that you're
global, if you're a global issuer, meaning your
cards, which is actually the case for most issuers
or for most banks, if you really want to try right now, in this
day and age, your cards will be used internationally, right.
This means that there would be multi,
multiple currencies you might need to
settle in, pounds, in USD,
name it, swedish krona, and so on.
And this could translate into you having multiple
bank accounts where this
liquidity would be just to have pounds to be able to settle
and all of that. Now, this is one of the most.
One other part that is very challenging for, I would
say, especially the treasury team of these companies,
where you need to know whether you should
owe more pounds or more USD.
And this could depend on what are the interest rates on these currencies
or what's the fluctuation, like,
how the volatility of the currency and all of that.
Machine learning could be used to help at least try
to narrow down how much,
approximately you need to hold in that
currency for settlement.
And last but not least is customer experience.
For customer experience, machine learning could be used to personalize the
authentication experience. You could understand what
kind of authentication method the customers prefer to use the most.
You could use this to customize rewards and promotion based
on the kind of transactions
that the cardholders are executing
and or initiating. And lastly, you could use,
this is used in some form of credit scoring
and risk management.
So, yeah, those are some
of the main use cases of machine learning.
Of course, machine learning is used in a lot
more places in payments, but the list will go
on and on. But there
are still several challenges, because I'm not
sure if there's been some bells ringing when I was mentioning the last
set of use cases for machine learning,
which involves things around customer data.
Right. One of the challenges is data privacy and
security. Now, this goes in several ways.
It could be, I like
to say something that where there's money, there's tendency for fraud.
So in terms of security, you need to ensure that
customer data is secured. And of course, you also need to
respect the privacy of, you know, those customers. Right.
Customer data has to be secured. Even if you have any system,
either machine learning or AI or whatever, any other system that you use in
dealing with customer data, it has to be secured so
that you don't expose sensitive cardholder information. And also,
in most cases, which we'll still talk about a bit later on,
it has to also adhere to regulations
such as GDPR, PCI and all of that.
We've seen that machine learning models can introduce bias,
leading to unfair treatment of certain groups.
It's really essential to monitor and mitigate this bias
to ensure fairness. And lastly,
which I already entered on in the first is regulatory
compliance. I mean, it's not surprisingly, the payments industry
is highly regulated, with different regions
actually having varying or different compliance requirements.
Right. And organizations need to navigate these regulations carefully
to avoid penalties or reputational damages.
So what other way to try to end
this presentation than to, you know,
make some, I don't know, keep the
room light, right. You get AI,
you get AI. Everybody gets AI. We've seen that AI
is becoming more and more injected
into a lot of industries
and the payment industry is not exempted from that.
A lot of products, a lot of features,
a lot of these things that are manually done would have
very good use cases for AI to come in in the
nearest future. So keep an eye out on that. And yeah,
thank you for listening. I hope that you
actually gained a clearer understanding of card payment lifecycle,
the role of machine learning in terms of improving efficiency,
security and improving
customer experience, and also the future trend in terms of
where we think AI might be used.