Hello, good day. Welcome to this presentation how to develop a
web three app in blockchain with JavaScript Frontend
and Python backend. You can develop in JavaScript or
JavaScript but focusing in this presentation
we are developing in JavaScript and Python,
Python in backend or any language in backend.
Cisco Rodriguez is my name from
latin chain introduction
to PI Network and PI browser.
The first step we will
have here Latin shame the repository and how
to develop a app a web three web app
in blockchain with JavaScript Frontend
and Python backend introduction
to PI Network, TM PI browser
and Pyap platform PI
Network TM is a
new crypto based on stellar where you can
mine cryptos from your phone daily.
This like bitcoin
or any other crypto.
The mining of the crypto with
PI app in Android or
the other system like for example
app PI browser is a new browser
kind of metamask but specifically for
PI network. For that crypto.
PI app platform is the app to develop
PI app latticent repository
Lattice is a PI app webtress app winner of
PI Hackathon 2021 where you can play games
daily using cryptos. The hit hub repo is this
with code in Python, JavaScript and HTML.
We are going to see this repository more
on in the following presentation.
How to develop a PI app use
app platform to develop your front end in
JavaScript or JavaScript in back end in
any language following these instructions
you can develop JavaScript with JavaScript
in frontend. What are you going to do with
frontend? You can capt
or catch from the users the
request to pay and
that payment request is going to the back
end. That's why it's important the
front end to catch the user requests. And then
in the back end you can do the request to the
PI app platform not only from users
but for PI app platform. When you get the request
from Piyabi platform,
you get the response from there and
return the response to the frontend and
the users will have an answer
for his request.
Okay then here web are
going to see the heathub repository for Latin chain.
Then we are going there and the Heathub repository
is that link you saw in the presentation.
In the slide is hithop.com
piaps Latinchain PI apps is an
organization in Hithub for PI
app ecosystem.
Latin chain is open source. You can develop
over Latin chain new apps,
but only if that app is
inside the params of PI network.
I mean if you want to develop in Latin chain, you have
to use that new system
you made in PI network. You can't use
that system in other platform
that is competitor of PI network.
You can watch here the license. The license says
that the copyright Cesar
Cordero Rodriguez and Latin
chain and the SEC permission had to be granted
and all this and the
permissions you have.
Okay then how
to develop a PI app here with PI network
and with the help of Latin Shane you
go to the repository and there is a
folder called Docs
Fierce app.
Here you have how to develop a fierce Pynettor
app. I use Odo to develop this app.
Mainnet you have it the link
testnet this link you maybe could
use your framework election.
The link I have said
before is latinchain.com
for mainnet and Testnet test latinchain.com
okay this is the official documentation to build
a PI app in Piabi platform.
Okay you have the link developers
mindpie.com official Pyap
demo example code hillhop.com pyapps
demo simplest
example for users two app
payment and the following is a working example
for receiving the payments in PI platform.
This is for client side HTML.
We have this example in Javascript and
the example in backend in PsP but
going back for a moment,
you have the latin chain
system working the working latin chain system in
latinchain.com that you have the
code here and you can watch in the code
website PI network auto and website PI network
PI network games Odo you have models
and you have in Python how
to develop here you have to use ODO
14 to develop over these
models of Latin chain.
Okay but in the simple example you
have in the docs first app you
have a server side PSP in
PsP you have example in PSP to
let you know you can use any backend.
I'm using backend in Psp
for example for an example and
in Python for my working app.
So for you you can use Psp
or python if you want to develop over odo
using my app to make it work
in several one php you
need to change the app code as out app
one by the one coming from client request example
if you have out example in client Javascript
site you must
set it in several one php.
Then you have to access
this link PI app example
in latin chain developments and you have in
main HTML you have okay,
you have here the
code and you can
let me check here. Okay here
app client out example if
you have example here you need
to use the same out example in
JavaScript,
the same out example in the back end side.
Then I'm using here auth example and
this is all developed.
You just need to use a configuration out
example out example in the front end out example in the back
end and you have it working. You have to set here your
app key from the PI browser,
okay, there are some steps you need to use,
okay, you have the
documentation, the official documentation
in PI SDK documentation, okay?
And you have working an
example you have here
read me and you have the official documentation from that
link I said in the presentation.
And you can watch the official documentation here
to develop in a PI app a
web dress web three PI app,
okay. But here I'm giving
you all examples in just one side app
to user payment because the first example is
user to app payment when an end user will pay
to an app and this
is for app to user payment. You have to read the documentation
and the official documentation that you have here in
developers developers mindpie.com
official documentation and you have app to user payment
in Ruby node, JS,
Python, Go Blazor and C sharp.
If we find here PI
browser we
will watch the
apps working for
example Latin Shane or any other app
and you will watch many apps here latin
shame for example and
you will see it working with
cryptos.
Play games using cryptos, okay share Sudoko
Snake if you are a developer that
is a thing for us. We are
developers,
okay, for developers the
the documentation is
the following.
We show you in this video and
in Py browser you can watch as developer
Brainstorm Py and develop PI where
you will create a PI app that
is in the documentation PI app project
in a Pyap develop Py okay
thank you for your attendance
and see you.