Hello and welcome to this talk about contract driven development.
We're going to be talking about deploying your microservices independently without integration
testing. My name is Hari Krishnan. I'm a consultant and a coach.
I help both unicorn startups and enterprises with their transformation
activities. My interests include distributed systems and
high performance application architectures, and these are some of the conferences
I speak often at. Let's start
off with some context setting on the topic. Why do we really need
contract driven development? Let's say we're
building a mobile application that requests data from a back end and
then displays the same the application requesting the data is
the consumer and the application responding with the data. Let's call
it the provider. Now, with the terminology out of the way, let's look at
how we would go about building the consumer. Now. One way is to wait
for the dependency, which is the actual provider application,
to become available as a reference so that then we can build it
out against it. However, this is not very production because
it's a sequential style of development. So usual practice would be to
stand up a mock server to emulate the provider so that the
consumer application development can progress independent
of whether the provider itself is actually built or not.
While this looks good on paper, there is a fundamental flaw with this approach,
which is the mock server need not be truly representative of
the real provider. By which I mean as a
consumer application developer, I may wrongly assume that I could send
the id as a string wherein the actual provider application
may be expecting an integer, and likewise the provider
may be responding with the name and SKu of the product, while I may
be wrongly assuming that I'd be getting the name and the price.
Now what does it all lead to? When we deploy these applications together,
there is going to be broken integration, and such issues are not really easy
to find on our local environment for the consumer application developer like
we saw, and also in the continuous integration environment, because we
might pretty much be leveraging the same hand rolled stub.
Right? And for the provider there is no emulation of the consumer,
so thereby even provider application development is also happening in
isolation. Now when you put these two applications together in an environment
such as integration testing, that's when you realize there is
a compatibility issue. Now this first of all compromises
your integration testing environment, and worse,
if at all, you have a break from integration
testing and these issues do happen to make it to production
ends up in creating incidents which we do not like,
right? And because these issues are usually found on the right
hand side much later in the cycle they're also quite expensive to fix.
Wouldn't it be nice to prevent such incidents
from happening altogether and to be able to identify such compatibility
issues very much on the left hand side. What do we want to achieve?
We'd like to shift left and identify compatibility issues
without really integration testing applications.
Now one way of solving this problem could be to
reduce the ambiguity in communication between the teams so that there are
no assumptions which can lead to problems, right? So putting
it down in an industry standard specification such as OpenAPI
or WSTL is a good way of governing both application development
on the consumer side and provider side, so that you have the
two applications talking to each other well when they are deployed together.
However, do you think just having an API specification standard
or adopting one solves your problem? That we are
trying to look for a solution?
Not necessarily. API specifications in themselves are just
describing what the API looks like. It is up to us
how we enforce these API specifications on the
application development itself. And that's where the difference
is between API specifications and executable contracts.
What we'd like to achieve is to be able to take API specifications
and treat them like executable contracts. Now that's exactly
what specmatic is able to do. Specmatic is a tool
which can read your open API specification or WSDL specification
and then convert that and make it available as a contractor
stub server for your consumer application so that you
can independently continue on the development of the consumer
application. This stub is significantly different
in comparison to handrolled stubs because it is truly representative
of the provider, because it is based off of the mutually agreed
upon API specification. Now we have to keep the equation
balanced on the provider side also. So for which specmatic
is able to convert your API specification into contract
as test and make sure that it is verifying that the
provider is adhering to the contract also.
Now with this you are able to independently develop both consumer
and provider applications while still being sure that when you deploy them
together, they will work well with each other.
Now let's take a look at a live demo of
what this will look like on the provider side.
Let's say I have this API specification and then
I have the system under test, which is the provider itself.
Now I'd like to be able to test if the provider application is
in line with the API specification. What I'm going to do is
take specmatic, leverage the API specifications
as contract as test, and then verify if
the provider is able to match up.
So for this, I'm quickly going to show you
an example of an API specification. I have a
typical e commerce like open API specification
here. It's got a bunch of paths with products
and orders, and on each of these paths it's got multiple operations to
support crud operations for a product or an order. And it's
also detailing out the schema in terms of what are the type of values
you can support and whatnot. So that's typically
this API specification. And then I also have this
application here which says the
team is claiming that they have completed building this application and it
should be able to support all the operations that we saw in the API
specification itself. Now how, as a person who
is supposed to be responsible for this application going live in
production, that this is indeed adhering to the specification
we saw earlier. So what I'm going to do now is leverage
specmatic to take the API specification and run
it as a test. So what I have here as a basic
setup is I'm using Specmatic's junit support while
I am using the junit support within a Java springboard application Kotlin
application. Specmatic itself is language
agnostic and platform agnostic. You could use it from a command line.
Also, it's just an executable, but for the purpose of convenience,
I have this junit support extension here and then some plumbing
to start and stop the app and the coordinates
of where the app itself is running so that Specmatic can hit it.
Now, how does Specmatic know where to pull the API specifications from?
That's where this JSON configuration comes in. I've directly pointed it
to one of the git repositories where I'm adopting the API specifications
which we saw on the swagger editor. Now with this,
let's actually run the test. And what you
will notice is a bunch of tests getting generated
and run against your application without you having to write any
line of code. And this is all I have done.
And you notice we got twelve tests,
right? That's money for nothing and tests for free.
Who doesn't want free tests, right? And let's actually analyze what
these tests are actually doing. Let's take the first one for example.
It says fetch product details response okay,
get products. Now if you recollect the gaps specification,
the first operation, if you remember, is a get operation on
the path products and its fetch product details. So Specmatic
was able to convert each of these operations inside your open API specification into
a test scenario and run it. Now what did it do?
It generated a request based off of the API specifications. It knew that
there is a URL called products and there's an id and that
id is supposed to be number. So this
specmatic kind of went ahead and generated a value which is adheres
to the specimen. And then when the response came back from the
application, it verified that this is indeed in line
with the schema that is expected from the actual
API specification itself. So thereby the tests are green.
Now that's great. Obviously it's good news that the application
is in line with the API specification, but that's
not necessarily the reality for most of
us, right? Incidents do not happen in the happy path scenarios.
Incidents are hiding in the places that we are not looking for them,
right? So let's throw a curveball at this whole application.
So what I'm going to do is I have this quick snippet
here called specmatic generative test.
I'm going to paste that in and say specmatic,
I want you to do some extra testing on this application and see if there
are any loopholes beyond what you have already verified.
So right now you're saying twelve tests. Just hold on to that number in your
head and let's rerun the test and see what happens.
Now the interesting
bit here is we want to test boundary conditions.
Correct? The happy path is when you expect given
a we are just checking, right? We are not really deploying. What are
the possibilities? We just checked so far, but this time around we are going
to be deploying what are the boundaries of the application itself.
Now this time around you have 26 tests, which is a lot
more than twelve, and only 16 of them passed, which means we also have test
failures. Now. Now that's interesting. Let's take
a look at and analyze what these scenarios are
like. So earlier you saw only scenario I did not have positive
or negative. Now you have labeling. It says this scenario is a
positive scenario and this one said negative and the negative one
is what failed. So let's take a look at it.
So on the negative scenarios, the first one I'm looking at the
error we see here. Oh my, it's a 500 internal server
error. Now how did that happen? It looks like specmatic
tried to send a null for a value that is not
supposed to be null according to the API specification. Right.
Now, what would have been ideal is if the application had done a null
check and then responded with an appropriate four to two or a 400.
But then there is no null check in the application, which is evident here.
And the application instead threw a 500,
which is not desirable. This could easily have become an incident in
production. But lucky for us, we have specmatic and we
were able to identify it right here and we can now fix it. Now isn't
this awesome that I did not have to write any line of code
and I have so much ability to both verify the
positive and the boundary conditions for an application all with just
open API specification. Okay, now that we've
seen the power of OpenAPI specifications
and specmatic and how it is able to leverage it
on the provider side, let's switch gears and look at how this
can help the consumer side of the equation.
So let's again look at a quick demo here. What I
have is an API specification
called Products Yaml. This is a fairly straightforward one.
This is not even like 30 40 lines, which is fairly
straightforward for any small application.
All it says is I have a path called get products and
given an id, it gives me back a product for
that particular id which has the name and the SKU.
Now this is all I have to start off with and I need to build
a mobile application. Now how do I go about my
business? So first thing obviously is I want to play around with
this API and see what values I get. So what I have done here
is I've imported it into Postman and I have
pretty much the ability to do that because Postman
recognizes open API and I've got it in. The next step
is I need to have a stop server, right? One option is to hand roll
it. I could just hard code some values in a block
or a record and replay service, but why will I do that? I have
the ability to use specmatic. So what I'm going to do is
start a new terminal and I'm going to say go
into this folder called smartmocks where we have this file
lying around. I'm going to say specmatic,
stop this file called products Yaml.
And that's pretty much all it says. Hey, there is this
server called 9000 running on localhost and
we have a step server going. So what does this mean? Let's actually
take a look. Let's try sending a value. I just have
some random number and I send the
request and I get back a response, which is a name under an SKU magic,
right? And this is specmatic doing the job for us.
And every time I send a different value, or just send the same
value, it gives me different responses for the name and the sku.
Now this is happening because specmatic is able to guess
what data it is supposed to respond with based off of the
schema which we saw earlier which said both name and
SKU are strings and so thereby specmatic is generating values
within that boundary. Now usually this is not useful.
As a mobile application developer or a client application developer,
I would want specific values. Like for example,
I want for one, I want a particular book to
come back to me. So I'm going to say one.
And magically specmatic gave me back the name mythical man month
and the sk for that book. Now how did this happen?
What we did here is, if you notice there is a folder called products
underscore data which has a convention based
naming here which is based off of the products. Yaml I just
have underscore data. Now under that I can have as many jsons
as I want and each json is basically a request response pair.
Excuse me, what I've done here is for the
product id one I want to return mythical manment and
this status code and whatnot. Now thereby I'm able
to get back this information. Now let's actually see
if we can fool specmatic right? Now. The issue
earlier, which we noticed was that as the mobile application developer,
I was wrongly assuming that the server is going to
be giving me name and price and not name and Sku.
And I was going to say name and SkU, sorry, name and price
is basically this $10 for this book, for example.
And now let's take a look at what happened. The stub server
running picked up this file change and then
said error, right?
And it says in scenario get products key
name price in the stub server was not part of the contract.
Now that's very helpful for me, right? Because I would have otherwise wrongly
assumed and set up my stubbing incorrectly. And maybe
this would have turned out to be a production incident. But instead what
now happened is I am completely safeguarded
as an engineer from making any wrong assumptions because
every time I make a mistake, hey, specmatic is
able to point me, hey, this is not the right value.
You should probably be adhering to the specification and only if
you go back to saying SKU and give
any value which can be any string right within
that format. And now it's going to be fine and this error will
magically go away. Now that's why we call
this smart mocks. And now when you
go back to your postman, then I send the request again.
This time you get back any string. So now that we've seen both sides of
the equation for the consumer and the provider,
let's actually look at the anatomy of a test for the consumer
itself. Now typically for a component tests. Your system
under test needs to be isolated from its dependencies,
and that's where specmatic comes in to provide your smart block. And for
a component test, there are three parts to it. Any test to that matter
has arrange act assert, which is the standard set of steps,
and during the arrange step, just like you would use any tool, like in
unit testing, like Mokito. Here you are testing an API,
so thereby you're setting up an expectation at the API level with Specmatic.
You saw how I set up the expectation with a
JSON file, but you could also do this over an HTTP endpoint
if you were to dynamically if you want to set it up dynamically at
runtime. Now specmatic thoroughly verifies
this expectation against the open API and only then stores
it into its local storage.
And then your component test can invoke the actual
system under test. And in turn the system under test interacts
with specmatic stuff server and specmatic stuff server
looks up if it has any corresponding data based on the expectation,
or it will generate some random data and give it back to the system
under test, and which in turn returns to the test, and the test asserts if
the response is good. Now if you look at this setup, this is
very helpful to isolate the system under test while still
being sure that you are emulating the provider fairly
well. Otherwise, now that we've seen both sides of the
story for the consumer and the provider in terms of how we could use
contract as test and contract was stub server, let's block at backward
compatibility. Compatibility issues begin to
grow a lot more with API evolution and now API production
is natural, right? We want to be able to add ensures. The difficulty,
however, is when you are adding a new capability to an API
for supporting a newer consumer or a client or a new feature,
existing consumers and clients can potentially
become incompatible. And that's where it might be helpful
if you could just take a contract and another version of the same contract
and just verify it and say, are these two compatible?
That would be a nice experiment to run, right?
Without really getting into a situation where you have to make the changes on
the consumer and the provider applications deploy it, and only then realize that they
are not compatible. Let's take a look at a live
demo of this sort of comparison. So let's take a
look at a popQuest. Which of these changes are backward compatible
in a request? If I add a mandatory or a required field,
is that change a backward compatible change to the API?
Now this is a fairly straightforward answer because it's easy to guess,
right? Because if you add a new parameter to the request,
obviously existing clients will not be able to send it,
and thereby it is a backward
incompatible change. Now why take my word for it?
Let's actually test this out. So I'm going to kill
this subserver which was running before. I'm going to go back and
go into this folder called backward compatibility.
And what I have here are two
files, products v one, products v two.
At this point both of these files are pretty much identical,
and they have this one operation wherein you can create a production by
posting product details. And by now we are quite familiar
with what the product has, right? It's got a name and an SKU of
which only name is required. SKU is optional and then
in response it gives you the id of the product. Let's assume
this is the API we have to work with, and we need
to understand if these two are backward compatible. So obviously
before we make changes, we want to make sure that we are starting on a
clean slate. So I'm going to say specmatic compare
products v one with products v two.
And when I do that, you will notice,
my bad, I did not put the extension
then yes, the newer contract is backward
compatible. Now for the change that we saw in the block quiz, right,
which is basically if I add a new parameter,
if I add a parameter which is required. So the quick one
to do here is maybe I will make SKu also
mandatory. Now if I do this, what is
going to happen? I'm going to run the compare command
again, and this time around, you see this issue, right? It says
new contract expects key named SkU in the request, but it
is missing from the older contract, and therefore new
contract is not backward compatible. Okay, so that just
proves what we already guessed. That's not really very groundbreaking,
earth shattering. Let's look at something more complex.
What if I change an optional nullable field to
an optional non nullable field? Let me repeat
it. An optional nullable field to an optional non nullable field.
Let's actually look at it with an example, right? So it's easier to
process. We are back to square one here.
Both contracts are compatible. And you will notice in
the v one SKU is the optional field
and it is nullable. Now what I'm going to do is,
according to the quiz question, going to take the optional
nullable field and make it optional non
nullable. Now this is not
straightforward to process in order to guess whether it's going to
be backward compatibility, breaking change or not,
because there are at least three or four permutation communication.
So let's try and check what happens. And this time specmatic
says, hey, this is a string in the new contract
and nullable in the old contract, which is basically you made something mandatory,
but the older contract, it was nullable. And that is actually correct.
How specmatic is able to point it out to us, because whenever
you are going to send SKU, you are supposed to send the value and not
a null. But in the earlier case you could send a null,
thereby it is a backward incompatible change. Now this
is getting progressively harder, right? To figure out if this is a backward
compatibility change or not. Compatible change or not.
Let's take it to the next level. What if I
change a schema component that is referenced in request and
response? Okay, I have an example
of such a contract here, which is a fairly large one.
I do not expect you to read all of it,
but what I'd like to draw your attention to is this one
particular schema component called address.
Now let's actually take a look at where address is used.
So I'm going to see address is part of storage,
it is part of warehouse, and it
is also part of cart response.
Okay? Now the other problem is storage
itself is
part of request,
but address is also part of directly response.
Now if the same schema is part of
both request and response now, how would you
make a decision whether it's backward compatible or not? Now that doesn't
stop there, right? The next one is the hierarchy, which is basically what
you noticed, because address was directly part of the storage
and one more element, and it is also directly appearing
under the master element, which means you don't know what
sort of issues it can create if you change a value.
What can make it even more complicated is if this schema
is referenced across multiple files, which is normal,
for example with open API remote references, then that can make
life a lot more harder. So for an engineer who's
probably just joined the team, and you ask me to make the change here
to say address, which is required now, and it's
got these four parameters which are required. I want you to
remove this from required to making it optional. Now is
this change backward compatible? I'm pretty sure at least
I am not smart enough to compatible this mentally.
I need the help of something like specmatic to figure this out.
And isn't this very powerful to do? Because all you've noticed is
I've been able to experiment which change is compatible
or not, just by changing the specifications and not really
writing any code now this would be a great way of collaborating between teams
to understand if a change made for one team can
break the compatibility with another consumer or
client team. Now with that out of the way,
let's further move to the next topic, which is called
central contract repo. Are we on the same page?
What do I mean by that? Now we've seen contract
was tests, contract as stub, we've seen backward compatibility verification,
and all of this hard work that we've done.
And still it is possible that let's say I am the provider
developer and I make a change to the application and
then I either miss updating the open API specification
or I update the wrong file for whatever reason.
And likewise, let's say if I am the consumer application developer,
I somehow ended up referring to the older version
of the contract, or I am not looking
at the largest version that someone sent me over email,
and thereby I have ended up using
the wrong API specification as reference for building my consumer
application. Now if this happens,
irrespective of whether you're using specmatic and all the smart block
and contract test and whatnot, you can still end up with
a broken integration. Now that's not a desirable place to be,
right? What we want is to have the API
specification as a single source of truth. It is code practically,
and how do we treat code? We keep it in a version control
system and that's where what we believe is
open API or any other API specification standards you're
using should reside in a central contract repository
which is a version control system. And if you are treating it like code,
then you will end up having something like a pull request or merge
request process, which is a good thing because you can now have
some sort of a style or an API enter with
probably tools such was stoplight spectral. And once
you have gone through the basic process there, then you can do the backward compatibility
testing which we just spoke about, right? And verify that the
change that is being proposed is compatible or not. Now specmatic,
you noticed I was able to compare to files. Likewise it
can also compare to versions of the same file in a version
control system, right? And thereby give you a go ahead whether
it is compatible or not. If it is compatible, you'll go ahead and review
and merge it manually after,
sorry, you would do a manual review and then merge it
and pretty much evolve the API further.
Or if you realize that it's a backward incompatible change, then you may have to
think about a versioning strategy
for your API itself. Now with this
pretty much we have covered four topics right, which is
contract was tests, contract was stub contract versus contract backward
compatibility testing and then the central contract repo.
How do all these pieces come together eventually in the
CI pipeline to solve our initial problem, which is
to shift left the identification of compatibility issues.
Now that we know that the gaps specifications is being stored
in the central contract repository, which is a single source of truth
and specmatic is able to read it, make it available as contract was
step services for your consumer application and
contract as test for your provider application. Let's see
what happens further in the continued integration environment of the consumer
application after the unit tests are done. For component testing, you don't
need to look for another tool to stub out the
provider. You can use the specmatic stub server which
you are using on your local environment itself. Spec environment
was well, like I mentioned earlier. So now that you've been
able to emulate the provider for the consumer,
let's look at what happens for the provider itself. Now after the unit testing
is done, we run the contract test first to verify that the
provider is adhering to the API specifications, and only after
that we run the component testing. Now that we have adhered
with the API specifications both on our local and on
our CI for both the consumer and the provider applications,
we can confidently deploy it to this integration
testing environment and be sure that it's going to work. And you also
have an unblocked path to production. And pretty much
none of the compatibility related incidents are bound
to happen now in production at all because we have completely
shifted left the identification of compatibility issues to
the local environment or at most to the CI very much in the green
right, which is what the heat map is representing. So which means the
cost of fixing such issues is also fairly
low. And that is how specmatic
and contract driven development can help you identify
compatibility issues early in your development cycle without
depending on integration testing, and then allow you to confidently
deploy your applications independently to production.
With that, I'll open up for the Q A on the discord server.
And thank you very much. Please do feel free to reach
out to me on my social handle here and do check out specmatic
in thank you.