Everyone and welcome to Conf 42, cloud native 2022.
I hope you all been having an amazing conference so far.
In this talk we are going to look at the changes that have taken place
in the deployment ecosystem over the last few years
and see how they have affected developers. I'm Arsh
and I work as a devex engineer at Octeto. I'm also an active contributor
to the open source Kubernetes project. So let's get started.
In this talk I want to introduced you to Jane a couple
of years ago. Jane's life was simple and she got to do
what she enjoyed, write code. Most applications
had a monolithic architecture and all she had to do was open up
her favorite code editor, run a command or two, and she'd
have her application up and running. Then she would just write some code,
hit save, and see her changes interacted based on that, submit a
pull request and things would be good to go.
So what happened to our happy dev experience?
Containers and kubernetes in the last couple of years,
containers made our lives super easy and containerization basically
became the norm. Everyone reevaluated
how they were structuring their applications. Containers made us
realize that instead of working on this one single large application,
it is so much more easier to scale an application that is composed
of multiple smaller pieces, that is microservices.
We also started using container orchestration tools like kubernetes
in production to further scale our applications more effectively than
was possible before. Now all of this changed these
world of a happy developer Jane.
Suddenly Jane was having a tough time bringing up her application locally.
She could not just now continue developing as she was before.
The thing with microservices is that they are interwoven and closely
linked to each other. So let's say Jane has to make a change
on a particular microservices. The only two options she has available
with her are bringing that microservice up locally
and working on it. The problem in this case is that
she isn't able to see how the change she makes could interact with the other
microservices because she hasn't brought them up together.
Now this might not be a problem when you're working with two or three microservices,
but imagine making a change in an application consisting of
1015 microservices. It is almost
impossible to predict how your changes would affect other things if you're working
in isolation with a particular microservices. The second
option Jane has available is to actually bring up
all the microservices and configure things between them so that
they all work like the actual application locally.
Now mind you that this is no easy task.
Jane would have to read and make sense of a bunch of readmes written by
infra people or some hacky bash scripts which often break and
require debugging. And these readmes and scripts
are anyways hard to maintain and keep up to date. And you know what
the worst part is? Even when Jane does spend things time
bringing up and configuring all the microservices, she still can't be sure
that everything would work as it works in production.
Reason being that locally bringing up all the microservices is no longer
the same thing as how they are brought up in production. Her environments
still be won't exactly like the production Kubernetes
clusters which run the final application.
So what did we do to solve chains wars?
We told her hey, work locally on an independent microservice and
take these CI CD pipelines. Once you push your changes,
we'll run them in the CI against a production environment and let
you know if things are working as expected or not.
Or we gave Jane access to staging environments where
she was like after she was done, she could see her changes brought up like
they would be in production and verify if everything is working as expected.
But ask yourselves, did we actually solve Jane's
problems? No.
The workflow Jane was used to was this bring up
the entire application she needed for development in a
command or two, write some code, see her changes immediately,
and iterate, all while being sure that things would
work exactly the same in production when she pushes her
changes. But the flow we currently gave her
is not the same. It is too far from the code writing phase.
With this flow, she only gets genuine feedback after she
is done committing and pushing her changes.
And that too is not instantaneous and takes a lot of time.
Like bringing up the environment in CI often takes minutes if
not hours if you're working with a pretty big application.
So the question still remains, how do we fix things
for Jane and make her happy?
Before concluding, I want to discuss a solution which has these potential
of solving all these problems developers working on
microservice based applications face.
And that production I feel is cloud development environments.
The way they work is that they first deploy your application to
a Kubernetes cluster using these same manifests you deploy
to production. So the idea is that you deploy your application to
the cluster just like you would in production, and then you see
the result of the code you write as soon as you hit save to
explain this in a bit more detail, let's consider a simple application
which has two microservices. Now this is just for explaining
like in an ideal world you would have like around ten microservices and
things would get complicated. But let's just work with a movies application which
has a front end which is interacted with an API.
Once you have your application containers running in a cluster,
these cloud development environments replace the container
for a particular microservice you want to work on with
a development container. So if you see the second box,
you'll see that if you want to work on the API microservices,
we would first deploy both the front end and the API to a cluster,
and then we would replace the running API container
with a development API container.
Now what's special about this container is that it syncs all the
code you write with the code which is running inside the cluster.
So the changes you make will be moved to the cluster and you
could see the results live as soon as you hit save.
And the best part is that since this replaced container inherits
all the configuration of the original container as well,
so the other parts of your application continue to work exactly like these
were working before. So that means you are
working in an environment which is exactly lives production, and all
you had to do was use the same manifests you were already using.
How convenient. No?
So I think you can now start to see how cloud
dev environments solve all the problems we discussed
and also provide a better developer experience for cloud native
application developers. Con is the problem of developers
working in an unrealistic environment, because cloud dev
environments use the same manifests as production to bring up your application.
Working in an environment which doesn't mimic production is the most common cause
of bugs which creep in late in the dev cycle and are hard to
debug. The reason they are hard to debug in the first place is that
because finding them locally wasn't possible, because if that
were the case, they would have gotten caught a lot earlier in the dev
cycle. But the fact that they appear later and are tough to
replicate locally is what makes them nasty to debug.
But if you use the same manifests you use in production when developing
locally, then you catch these bugs in your
local environment even before you push your changes, and you would have
a much easier time shipping features and you can be sure
that the changes you push will not have these bugs these
second thing is that with cloud dev environments you also get instantaneous feedback
like you saw in the previous slide. The code gets synced as soon
as you hit save. So you see the result of what you have written
immediately. You no longer have to build your application,
commit your changes and push them and wait for CI pipelines
or just lives. Wait for access to a staging environment to
be sure that your code is working.
Because once your application is live in a cluster,
all you need to do is hit save and then you see the results for
your application. Now this speeds
up the inner dev cycle, and not only that, but it also gives devs
the confidence that what they have written will work in the CI and staging
phases. Now I'm not saying that this is like a
replacement of CI and staging. Both of them are useful and
have their place, but this approach is more
close to the developer and therefore it feels just like it was
like a couple of years ago when we were not working on microservices
and we had these monoliths we could bring up and hit save and
see our changes. So it brings back that feeling of getting feedback as
soon as you write and not waiting minutes or hours to
see how your changes look. The third thing
which makes most developers like chain very happy is
that with cloud dev environments, devs don't have to
spend time configuring things. All the configuration
required to bring up a dev environment goes in a single file,
and every developer can just bring up the entire application using a single
command, which deploys to the cluster and replaces the required
microservice container, as shown in the previous slide.
So this idea of using dev environments
as code makes dev environments much more reproducible
and ephemeral. So if things go wrong, you can simply
destroy a particular dev environment and spin another up in a
matter of minutes. There are other added benefits,
like since you are using cloud resources, everything is faster
and you no longer have to be limited by the capabilities
of your local machine. And the
other good part I feel, is that these cloud dev environments
do not force you to shift from the tools
you've been using. You write code just like you would,
except that it's being deployed and run in a cluster.
So not only is the process faster and the feedback more genuine,
but you do not have to say goodbye to the tools you
love, like change your id or anything else.
I want to end this talk with a quote which I feel beautifully sums
up whatever we have discussed. If everything
is happening in the cloud, then why should your dev environments not
be there too? Thank you
so much for attending and I hope you have a great conference. If you
have any questions about the talk or just want to chat. Please don't hesitate to
reach out to me.