Hello, I am Federica Chufon. I'm a specialist solutions architect for
container technologies at Amazon Web Services.
Today I'm going to talk about how the Kubernetes
ecosystem has evolved to answer to more complex application
patterns from a networking standpoint.
So let's dive right into it.
Let's start with the easiest pattern,
which is the monoith how do we handle
internal calls and client traffic within the monolith?
Well, applications are on the same physical
and virtual machine into the monolith. Therefore we
use loopback interfaces to grant
communication. And how do we handle
client traffic? Well, if you want to be fancies
you could use load balancer or a proxy.
But this pattern, the monolithic one, is not
used anymore because of a number of reasons, as reducing
dependencies between applications,
enabling developer flexibility,
reducing blast radius and decreased time to market.
So we broke down, or a
pattern that is very common is to break down these monoes into
microservices. In particular,
you can containerize those and manage them
with, for example, kubernetes.
So in the Kubernetes context, how do we handle
service communication? Well, when you containerize
your application and put this into a Kubernetes cluster,
your application will talk thanks to the container
network interface. Some examples include
Amazon VPC, CNI,
Cilium and Calico CNIs.
Well, client traffic can also be handled by load balancers.
But when we are talking about application traffic,
Kubernetes ecosystem needs
something more and this is actually the ingress
resource that needs deployed into your cluster
and an application which is the ingress controller which
picks up the creation, update or
deletion of ingress. Kubernetes objects and automatically
creates updates or deletes load balancers.
Well, of course, breaking down your application
into microservices is only the first step.
The pattern that we see with our medium large scale customers
is to further break down applications into different
clusters or different areas of the cloud
to gain flexibility and for separation of
duties and security.
Well, so let's recap this a little bit. You have multiple
microservices which are spread across different clusters,
different areas of the cloud, and those are written in
different programming languages usually. So in
this context, how do we handle service to service communication and
client traffic? Well, we need to take
into account some challenges.
So first of all, how do
we manage network connectivity and traffic routing,
and how do we obtain visibility into service
to service communication? Let's say, how do we manage the
observability of my systems and how
do I ensure trust by automatic
security and compliance in my systems
and applications also tied
to the modernization of our application patterns
and architectures. We need also to modernize our
organization and really create a
culture of innovation by organizing well
our teams into small DevOp teams.
So those objectives needs to be
taken into account or were taken into account
from the Kubernetes ecosystem when deploying more
advanced offerings and answers to
application networking in Kubernetes let
me introduce a couple of concepts from Amazon Web
services. The first one is Amazon eks elastic
Kubernetes service. This is a managed Kubernetes cluster
from AWS in which we manage the control plane of
a Kubernetes cluster. In the slide you can also see Amazon
VPC, Amazon virtual private cloud. It's basically
a chunk of the AWS Amazon network
that we give to you and that you manage completely.
Resources like Amazon eks live in an Amazon VPC.
So again, how do we set up and manage the
ingress and service to service communications
while guaranteeing agility, control,
visibility and security?
Well, you could use again load balancers,
but planning for scale, you don't want really
to provision and manage a load balancer per service.
There are techniques with ingress controllers
that enable you to well share
load balancer across multiple applications,
multiple backends, but still when your application
scales massively or when you have stricter
requirements, you may need to adapt.
Let's recap. We have seen how networking
is handled in monolithic applications,
how Kubernetes answers to containerization
with CNIs and ingress controllers. So let's
talk about now how microservices
high handed by the Kubernetes ecosystem
and how the networking offering has
evolved to answer to the problems of having a distributed
system. Well,
Kubernetes project said,
okay, proxies are really useful
to manage networking in general. Why don't
we use them within a Kubernetes cluster as well?
In fact, there is a pattern which is called
to put this proxy as sidecar within
the same pod, sidecar to my container
that is next to the container which handles the application
and put these in each pod that
I have in my cluster. This pattern
is known as cycle proxy pattern
and it is basically a way to decouple the
networking and the application layer.
All the traffic that needs to go into
the application pod or container or
generates from the application container passes through the
proxy. This enabled me
some nebulas to have,
let's say, more flexibility between
our applications teams. Let's say that
we have a team that manages a front end
and that needs to talk with a team that manages
a back end, when the back end team releases a new version,
we need to actually change and point
our application code in the front end and point to
the new backend. Well, this is
not needed anymore. If we are using a proxy
AWS sidecar, because we can actually use
the proxy to point to the new application.
So inconsistencies are minimized.
We are separating, let's say business
logic from operation and also install
operation of installs, upgrades, et cetera are a little bit
more easier. And well,
again, one of our objectives was
to make our application observable.
Now we have a unified layer,
one of the proxy that manage our service
to service communication and gives logs which
are in the same programming language and in the
same way because it's actually the same proxy next to
each container of our application takes out a layer
of observability that is very important
when we are managing sidecar or application at
scale. But again we are talking about scale.
How do we manage all of this sidecar? Well,
much like in a Kubernetes cluster, we manage
our applications with a control
plane and well think
about having a control plane also for our sidecar
proxies and the control plane plus the
data plane which are the sitecar proxy themselves,
it is a service mesh. On the left side
of the slide you can see some examples of service meshes
which are commonly used by our customers.
Let's dive a little bit deeper into use cases. Well,
obviously traffic routing is something that we want to manage with
a service mesh, for example routing
from a version one to a version two. But also
there are some advanced features for routing like for example
prefix query parameters or specifying
HTTP headers.
Let's say that we want to protect also our application from
large spikes in traffic and we want to assure
a good level of services. Well, the service mesh
enables me to implement automated retries, secret breaking
and rate limiting into our applications.
Security is also one of our objective and you can enforce
that your application are able or not to talk either within
themselves or among theirselves
or to third party APIs.
You can also enforce that the communication are encrypted and
so reinforce Tls, for example at
the reverse proxy level, not at application
level. This can also integrate with third
party services to generate and renew certificates.
Not only Tls, but we can also
enforce service to service authentication with
mutual Tls.
Another use case is observability. We talked
about it a little bit, but basically the
layer of observability that I gain is that I can
also implement tracing within the proxy to understand upstream
and downstream dependencies and also I can understand where
the bottlenecks are and
identify patterns and understand service
performance.
Another common use case is multicluster.
So connecting together different clusters
which are placed maybe also in different vpcs
or different accounts and the
communication can be granted by implemented
in the correct way. Obviously a service mesh one
common proxy that is used within
meshes is envoy, which is basically highly
performant cloud native proxies. It's very efficient,
it has a really small footprint and
it handles well client side
load balancing, retries, timeouts, rate limiting
enables you to have observability layer seven traffic
and supports different for example HTTP
HP, two CRP and TCP protocols
and also it has rich
and robust APIs for configuration.
One service mesh that uses ongoing proxies
is istio. You can install ISIO into your cluster
using istioctl or istio operator,
create and manage the components like for example
mesh virtual service, virtual gateways, et cetera,
through istioctl and Kubernetes APIs.
There are different supported platforms on
Amazon Web services. You can configure and run
your mesh in Amazon EKS,
Amazon EKS Fargate self, also Kubernetes
on Amazon EC two and also it integrates
with Kali. Kali is a console for istio service mesh
and you can use it configure, visualize,
validate and troubleshoot your mesh.
Let's see how it is istio deploying to our
cluster. We have an is cluster. We want service
a and service b to be able to communicate. So when you
deploy Istio, we are actually deploying the data plane which are
again the proxies throughout the service
flows and the control
plane. The control plane is well a set of
pods which is ECP and it's not managed
by AWS. It lives into the clusters as
again AWS a resource pod. So service
meshes is really the answer to a lot of our
challenges, but well,
still some remain. We have
a lot of now sidecar proxies that we have
to deploy and maintain at a scale. This can be
challenging. It only integrates
with container based workloads. Let's say we are
using say a serverless service like AWS lambda
or Amazon EC two. This is not
really supported. And also before even thinking
about deploying a mesh, we need to have intervpc
networking that we need to actually
implement to grant connectivity across vpcs,
for example, and to enforce security.
So how can we answer
to these challenges? Well, let me introduce
the Kubernetes gateway API. The Kubernetes
Gateway API is a sig network project
that took the lesser learned from the ingress project
and implemented a new way of doing
networking into Kubernetes. We have different
objects that belong to the Kubernetes gateway API.
The first of it is gateway class. The gateway class
enables me to formalize basically the type of load
balancing implementation that I can use. Let's say
if it were ingress, for example, it would be a load balancer.
The gateway actually specifies
a point where the traffic can be translated
into the Kubernetes services. So how do I translate traffic
that is coming from outside the class, inside the
class and where this is HTTP
routes. Those are rules for mapping the request
from a gateway to Kubernetes
services, and the services are
basically the targets of our HTTP routes.
A nice feature to the Kubernetes Gateway API is
that it is role oriented and
we have finally a mapping between the Kubernetes
objects that we have in our cluster and a role
within our organization. There are different
implementations, like for example for the ingress,
we have different ingress controllers,
so we have different controllers for the Kubernetes
gateway API. You cannot recognize different icons
that we have already seen in our presentation, like for example istio
njs haproxy and a new one.
This is the Amazon VPC lattice icon.
Amazon VPC lattice is a networking service that we have
in preview and announced in our
previous Rainband Rainband 2022.
And basically this
implements a layer seven fabric
layer within the application VPC
fabric. So to say we
can enable service to service communication without sidecar
proxy, which are required, and much like
a service mesh, but without the
need of deploying sidecars. It works
across all the compute options, EC two KIAS
cs lambda, and enables
you to deploy complex
security, let's say architectures, because actually
it's really easy to grant or implement the
networking also across vpcs and accounts where before you needed,
for example to deploy transit gateway pin connections,
et cetera.
Let me give you an overview of Amazon VPC lattice
components. We have a service network
which is basically a logical boundary that you can
define across vpcs and accounts,
and it is used to apply common access and observability
policies. Then we have service.
The service is a unit of applications and it extends across all
the compute instances, containers,
serverless, et cetera.
We have then the service directory which is a centralized
register for the services that are
registered into Amazon VPC lattice.
And then we have security policies which
are identity access management, declarative policies
to configure access, observability, traffic management
and those can be applied at a service gateway
and or application or network level.
Amazon eks supports Amazon EPC lattice
and we actually have built a controller that when we
create Kubernetes gateway API object
automatically, the controller works and creates updates and
deletes lattice resources.
Let's see a little bit deeper how the controller works.
So we have for example an
object like the gateway which is deployed
and the gateway automatically will
once applied, the controller will automatically
create a service network and associate
the vpcs where the EKs clusters
live into the service network
that is. Now we have network
connectivity between the two
vpcs that you can see in slide,
much like as if we had configured for example a
transit gateway and attached the two vpcs to
it. Another thing that
you need is that, well now we have connectivity
networking that is set up, but we have
not defined how the traffic flow. To do so we need
an HTTP route resource. HTTP route
will automatically once applied create
services which are again the targets.
Well the targets the unit of applications that are defined
for Amazon VPC lattice.
In this case we have defined two services.
One it is local to our cluster and one which
is another service which we actually
imported, exported and imported from one cluster
to another. That is to speak, let me
grab pen. This HTTP root
will be applied, for example in the first cluster as a resource,
and we will have exported and imported
this service into this cluster so
that it is visible to be picked up from the HTTP
route.
Then there are other things from the HTTP
route we specify the gateway
which is tied to. So basically we are associating our services
to the service network. And again
we also specify how the traffic it is redirected
from the gateway to our
targets, which in this case are these two services from
one from the first cluster and one from the other cluster.
So you can see how now we have
grant in a really easy way, easy set up
cross cluster communication without even
needing to set up underlying, let's say networking
companies like Transit Gateway VPC, period, and then
deploying a mesh and deploying and maintaining a
set of sidecar proxies.
Thank you. I hope this session has been useful for you
understand a little bit better the ecosystem that we have within
Kubernetes and in particular within the answer or
integration from Amazon Web services to the Kubernetes
ecosystem, in particular the Kubernetes gateway API.