Hello everybody, today we'll talk about safety
and I will present you the concept of safety crowdsourcing.
I am Bruce Lanzaribev, I am the CEO of greed company.
And we'll show you the solution, and we'll show
you the business benefits of risk
hunting. When we talk about heavy
industry, we always mean that it's connected
with heavy risks. For example, these are two pictures
of metallurgy plant of NLF
refinery. And these enterprises are
huge, so the size can be 10.
Course at these size of enterprises,
the incidents are inevitable.
So if we look at some statistics for the United States
in 2022 there were
five and a half thousand of fatal work injures
by different types. And the number of injuries is increasing.
So why it's still increasing?
And what's the problem with the conventional risk management?
First of all, it's static procedures and policies.
So we build the list
of procedures and we always try
to comply with them without developing
the new culture. And this traditional safety
is based on periodic inspection. So the health and security officer
is performing his
daily routines and checking the checklist.
So it's very time consuming and we may not cultures
the unforeseen risks. And what
also I have to mention is that the
conventional risk management is based on past
statistics. We analyze incidents and improve the
policy, rather than identifying and moving proactive.
So it's a proactive approach to the safety, and of course
the limited employee engagement. The employees
are usually outside of the safety process, they have to
follow, they have to stick to the rules,
but they are not part
of this strategy. So what
we would like to achieve with risk
Hunter is the safety crowdsourcing.
What do we call the safety crowdsourcing? This is the process
when every employee is becoming
the proactive person and
he's involved into the safety, involved into
identifying new potential risks.
So our concept is based
on the bottom up motivation,
how we call it. So conventional risk management is the
top down motivation, and our concept is based on
the bottom up motivation. So we want everyone
to become part of the new safety culture and we want
to engage and focus people on
finding safety issues in the enterprises.
So the focus safety is first and productivity
is second. So safety is always
more important than current duties.
And this is the concept. So in practice we
have a technology platform that supports
this concept. It's called risk Hunter. And what's the
idea that everyone has the mobile application,
and if you spot the risk, you take a photo
and you comment, you assign it
to the category and send it to the risk manager. The risk
manager validates this risk. And if
he confirms that this is the real one,
then the employee who reported is receiving
the reward for that, the bonus points.
Well, we have been speaking a lot on
motivation in the system and we have
currently two motivation models. First is material motivation.
So when you reach certain number of points,
then you can exchange them for some tangible practices,
discount vouchers, certificates,
subscription to the online cinema and so on.
This is the material motivation. But what works better
is the non material or personal motivation.
Well, recent researches show that intangible
motivation works
better in long term. So that's why currently we focus
on the personal motivation more than on material one.
And we have the list of
personal pages, so you can reach certain
level within the department
after you get certain number of points and you
receive awards. So we want this
motivation to be the foundation of
our solution. So if you report, for example, 17 tasks,
then you can get the level one hunter
and so on. What is important
is the hunting season. So in our solution
we have the hunting season so that we can focus attention
on certain types of
risks. For example, in winter it could be
one categories, in summertime or
after rain it can be another one. So the hunting season allows
us to focus attention on certain
problems, lives, electricity risks, for example,
next two weeks we look for the electricity issues and then
we can focus and concentrate all the people
on problems within the company.
Well, hunting season is also connected with the gamification.
We have the competitions in the system, so different
plants can compete with each other and even
different teams within one plant can compete between
each other. So that
really drives the involvement and
more interest into the system. So we had some situations
when the people were really keen
to have the first place in the competition.
So that's the competition
spirit. And what's also important, that we can not only
give rewards for taking the first place,
but we can also can give rewards for passing
safety training. Well, for passing safety exams.
So it's not only about finding their risks,
but it's also about being prepared.
So it's the spirit of collaboration and loyalty of
stuff.
Well, of course,
in the risk hunter it's very important to attend
the training to properly identify the risks.
And for this we also grant the
bonus points for passing surveys,
for taking all the trainings.
And we integrate the risk hunter with corporate learning
system so that we can also integrate
the risk hunter into the learning process.
In the morning, when the person is fresh
and ready to work, we have the safety quests
so that you don't
forget the safety lessons
and that's every morning. We can have some random
tests, tip of the days,
and it's pushed by the notification
so that you don't forget to pass it. Depending on
the location, in the large plans, there can be different
risky places, risky locations. So we have a location
based safety brief. When you enter, for example, the warehouse
area, then you will get a video on
risks related to warehouse management.
And that's good for large
enterprises. But what's important
is that every reported risk has
to be mitigated.
And after it had been eliminated,
the person who reported it should get a
notification about the elimination
of the risk. Because if there is no feedback,
then the employees, they quickly lose the interest
in this application. So the feedback is the core
part of our application. And the risk manager
also has the mobile applications, so he can be
in the field and he can assign the task to
other people, to other workers, to fix something
or to prevent this
from happening in the future.
What's also important is the
statistics, so we can always see
the percentage of risks eliminated.
We can see which risks are trending,
for example, fall flung, hates or get
contact with dangerous substances.
So we always can stay on track and see how
we progress in making the environment safer.
It can be also aggregated by year.
So we have statistics on
the type of the risk, sleeps or trips,
exposure to harmful substances. And we
can always be informed on the
progress and on the. Of course, the high priority risks
should be eliminated first, so we can have the focus on
these kinds of risks.
And there are some examples,
real life examples. For example, that's the open engine,
and after it has been reported,
so we have the protective cover with a
sign on that, so that no one puts his hand into this.
And that's the steam coming out
of the pipe. So it had been fixed,
and now this is the picture after the
work had been done. Well,
what's the advantages of our solution? It's that
we involve all in place into the process.
We use the gamification and we ensure
the feedback, so every risk is spotted and eliminated.
And we have the history
of using this solution for three
years now. And for that time we have
registered more than 150,000 risks.
And out of them almost 600 are
extremely dangerous situations
which could cause the fatal injury or
death. So we also have the
statistics that the risk hunter reduces number of injures
by 25%. And outs of
this number of fatalities also go
down. So for the three years we have almost 50%
decrease in fatalities.
And so that's the last
slide of my presentation. So we are working
hard to improve the safety. And you are welcome to use
the gamification and use the concept in
your enterprises. Thank you.