Hi everyone, thank you for joining my session.
Today I'll be talking about how to secure your JavaScript
applications. Before we get started, let me introduce
myself. So I am Joshua Arvin Lat. I am the
chief technology officer of Nuworks Interactive Labs.
I am also an AWS machine Learning hero, and recently
I am one of the five winners who
were awarded the Digital Leader of the year award.
I'm also the author of the following books, Machine Learning
with Amazon Sagemaker, cookbook, machine learning engineering on AWS,
and then the third book, building and automating penetration
testing labs in the cloud. So without further
ado, let's begin. So there's going to be three parts in this talk.
So for part one let's start by talking about the
reality. So what do you
mean by the reality? So if
we have been building JavaScript applications, whether it's
in front end, in back end, using JavaScript for mobile applications,
maybe you think that if you were an amazing developer
or engineer, you would be able to automatically
secure your applications in real life, in real projects.
That's not really the case. Why?
Because once you get to work in an organization or in
a team, there's that reality that organizations,
especially right now, would definitely prioritize,
as you can see in the screen, the short term financial objectives as
well as the long term financial objectives. At the
same time, the overall goal is to make the clients and
customers very happy. So what
does that mean? What's the applications? The implication? There is,
there's that chance, a very big chance,
that we'll all be focusing on the features and less on
the engineering best practices as well as the security best
practices left alone compliance. So in
order for the team to be able to build systems
really quickly, a lot of the
other items that's in your pipeline, it's probably the
security checks, that's probably the other compliance
requirements. Those will be deprioritized
so that you'll be able to launch your product faster.
It happens to all companies, whether big or small,
whether you're in a startup, because right now a lot
of the leaders and managers would say, well,
there's nothing to secure if there's no business. So let's focus on the business first.
However, in reality you need to take care
of the security from day zero or day one,
because security is kind of tricky to include once
the app is already running. It's not just about adding firewalls
to an existing JavaScript application. You have to make sure
that the developers are already
aware of the different security implications and risk and threats
available so that when they build the system it's
already secure and hardened. In addition to that,
developers usually know a lot about
the best practices from the development end they may
know a few security best practices as well.
However, in reality most developers
have no idea how an attack really works
because for one thing, being a developer is already hard enough and
they have to learn a lot of things already. Right now,
if you want to become a developer, it will probably take you two months,
three months, six months or even a year of experience before you're
really able to contribute to more complex
projects. How about you spend another one to two years or
three years trying to learn how to securing your
JavaScript applications? So one of the ways to
help us understand what to prioritize
and what to do when it comes to security, one of
the more important things is for us to understand what
we call the cyber attack chain. So let's start
with a simple example. Right now a developer would
probably think that this is code which
has harmless lines
of code. In most cases they
would say oh, there's that evil statement there
which technically evaluates that expression and
that could be used to compromise the entire application. So if
this piece of code is part of an overall web application,
developers would say that's
risky. So before we go into that, let's first check
how this application works. Let's start by
entering a mathematical expression.
So you input one plus one and your application
behaves normally so it produces two. So amazing, right?
So your application is supposed to do what it's supposed to do. That's the bare
minimum requirement. However, most developers,
even though they know that using the evil statement is not recommended,
they don't know how their applications would be compromised
because it's not really part of their training. However,
somebody is just playing around and trying
to input different things in your application, they could easily
input something like this. And what would the output
be? It would create a hello
text file where the server
files are running inside the production
server. So very scary because
this well crafted input is used
by a potential attacker in order to perform something
which shouldn't be happening in the first place. The application
you built is just supposed to evaluate
a mathematical expression. And for some reason your applications
was used to misbehave or to do something which it
shouldn't have, which is in this case to create a hello text
file. Is it really that bad? I mean,
what more can you do with this example? What if
a potential attacker runs the following
command in a different server? So let's call that the
attacker machine. So the attacker machine is different
from the target machine. So the target machine is your production
server where this application is running. So again,
this is kind of simplified because the lines of code I've
added, they're basically just there as a standalone line of code.
In reality, that evil statement, that block of
code, may be part of a larger web applications.
So going back to this example, if the hacker
or the attacker runs the following command,
what happens there is the attacker machine
listens and waits for the malicious input to
be pushed to your vulnerable application.
So this time, the moment that that specific
block of code is invoked again, and instead
of entering or inputting a mathematical expression,
you input this instead and the IP address
is now replaced with the public IP address of the attacker machine.
So what happens here is that the
victim machine, the target machine, now connects
back to the attacker machine.
And what happens there is the attacker would now
be able to run commands as if it
was his or her own machine, similar to Ssh.
So very scary, because the moment the attacker has direct
access to your machine using something
called a reverse shell, then it's technically game over for that
machine. The next steps there would be for the
attacker to perform other types of attacks, maybe look for
other passwords, look for databases there,
download the data and use the data collected
to basically perform other malicious actions.
In other cases, it's possible for the attacker to perform something called
IAM privilege escalation. So if your application
is deployed in the cloud and the server where your applications is
running, there is a big chance that other attacks and
chains and sequence of steps would be performed by the attacker
after the initial set of actions. Again, it's a chain.
It doesn't end with this simple set of steps. There would be other more
steps that the attacker would do. So on your end.
It's important that you practice code review.
You have code review sessions in your team and you need to have
someone knowledgeable about these types of security
best practices. Because even if you guys know that
it's not recommended why we should not use evil,
you should be able to explain and demonstrate
why that's the case. Now let's proceed with part
number two. Let's now talk about how to secure machine
learning powered JavaScript application.
So right now there's a lot of innovations
and new solutions when it comes
to AI and machine learning. Right now
you've probably heard about large language models and
at the end of the day, these large language models would be deployed
inside a server, right? However,
in some cases when you have to build aipowered applications
or machine learning powered applications, you usually
no longer need to follow this set of steps. So when
you have the time, the money, and your organization has
their own data, they would be able to build machine learning
models. So you start with data collection, you prepare the
data, you do feature engineering, you perform a
bit of analysis, and then after model training
and hyperparameter tuning, you evaluate the model or models
and then you choose the best one and then you deploy.
So the moment you deploy the model, it's now usable
by other applications so that they
would be able to mimic human intelligence.
So for example, let's say that there's an image of
a cat and you uploaded that image
of that cat to a mobile application,
and then your mobile application pushes it,
let's say to a JavaScript server. That JavaScript server utilizes
a machine learning model to perform
inference, basically to predict if it's a cat or
not a cat, and then you return the response
back to the mobile app and then there you go, the user
would receive if it's a yes or a no. So the
input would be image and then
the output would be one or zero. So if it's
one, it's a cat, if it's zero, it's not a cat. So basically
that's how machine learning powered applications work.
In the past you would generally have to deploy
it inside a server using various different
approaches or techniques. However, right now
there's now an option to even deploy your machine learning
model in the browser. So wow,
right? So using javascript you would be able to deploy your
machine learning model in the browser.
So in the left hand side you can see that,
yes, you can deploy your machine learning model on
the server side, and then on the right hand side you can see that
you can deploy your machine learning model in the front end side.
So what happens there is the browser is able
to download your machine learning model from the back end and
then there from within the browser you
can do a lot of awesome stuff there already. So there's
no longer any more back and forth after the initial request
because everything is going to happen inside the browser.
So for example, continuing the example earlier about
that cat being pushed
CTo the machine learning model in the back end,
instead of that image being pushed
to the back end from the front end,
what happens instead would be the
image of that cat stays in the front end
and the machine learning model in the front end.
Also in the browser what happens there is
the inference happens in the browser and the
model responds whether it's a cat or not. A cat but this
time that request no longer reaches
the back end, the server, because the model is already in
the client side, the browser. So why do this?
What's the advantage of this approach? The advantage
of this approach is that, number one, you can work offline and
then there are no servers needed if the
model is in the front end, right?
Second, it helps with data privacy because the request from
the browser no longer reaches the back end, and there's better latency.
Also because there's no more back and forth from the front end
to the back end and back to the front end.
So in order for us to appreciate this further,
it's basically your favorite libraries and frameworks
in the front end combined with a
specific machine learning library. And here, these are just a few
examples on what you can use to perform this type of scenario.
However, before you do that, there are several security considerations
you have to research and think about before you
have this type of architecture. Because for one thing,
anything that is pushed to your browser can be
downloaded by someone who knows how to do it.
So let's say that you have a website and
it's used by a lot of users. What if the machine
learning model used and
pushed to the browser for that browser? Side inference,
what if it's downloaded by your users and they create a new
website using the same model? So again,
in most cases you would prefer the model being deployed
in the back end. However, in some cases, if you're really okay with
the security impact or risks, then that's
fine as well. So if you're doing a demo, if you're not
using data which is proprietary,
if you're okay with your model being downloaded, or if
you know how to further secure your model in the front end, then that's the
time you deploy your model in a way
that can easily be downloaded by the browser
and perform this type of approach.
Now let's proceed with part three, the last part.
In order for us to secure our JavaScript applications
again, in the previous examples we've focused more
on the back end part, and in some cases you focus more
on the specific JavaScript implementation.
But in order for us to fully secure our applications,
we need to be fully aware of how to secure
the libraries and library configurations as well,
the framework configurations as well. What I mean by that is, every time
we use a library or a framework, we need to be well aware
of the different vulnerabilities and risk involved with that
specific framework. For example, if you accidentally
forgot to enable production mode using a specific framework
or a library, what would be the impact. So again,
in addition to having a good understanding of the different vulnerabilities
for the language, it's important that we have a good idea on
what risk and vulnerabilities are also possible when
using this specific libraries and frameworks.
At the same time, when using libraries, be very careful because there
may be some malicious libraries as well and you don't
want your application to be compromised because there's some sort
of backdoor in that library.
So there are different tools available online,
whether they're paid or free, and you can use that to further secure
your JavaScript applications.
Also, when it comes to vulnerability management,
it's preferred number one for your organization or
for your team to utilize something like this. This is what
they call an automated vulnerability management service or
tool. So there are different tools available online.
And the great thing about this is every time there
are changes in a server or there are changes
in a container image, this automated tool
would automatically scan those servers
or containers and provide this output.
So this output is a list of the different risk and
vulnerabilities involved in that system.
So in addition to having that code review layer,
whether that's manual or automated, you can also have this
layer which makes use of an automated vulnerability management
tool. In addition to that,
when dealing with network infrastructure where your JavaScript
applications are hosted, it's important to
practice this network solutions. So with
network isolation, even if some
of your servers get compromised, hopefully not.
If some of your servers get compromised, the other systems
in the same network would be protected.
If there's network isolation in place, if you're
able CTO properly design the subnets.
If there's a private subnet here, if there's a public subnet here,
then the damage can be limited
only to a certain portion. So network isolation
helps a lot because even if the
attacker is able to fully compromise one machine,
the other machines are not automatically compromised
also.
So my question for you guys is how
about IAM privilege escalation? So for one thing,
how does this work? So the first set of steps may
involve your JavaScript application compromised,
and then let's say there's that reversal
and your attacker is able to access the server.
It has the ability to run commands inside that server.
Even if from a network standpoint the attacker
is not able to attack other servers because of network isolation,
it is still possible for an attacker to utilize
something which is called an IAM role.
So this IAM role is attached
to the server when it's deployed
in a cloud environment. So this
IAM role is called
differently in Azure, GCP and AWS,
you can just think of it as a configuration
which allows the scripts inside that
server to run cloud
computing actions or commands. So for example,
this security IAM role
allows the server or the scripts inside the server
to create a new resource,
or even to modify or delete resources from
within that instance. So the scary
thing there is what if that instance
has an IAM role
attached? CTo it, which allows any user
to run a script inside it which
deletes all the resources in that
account. So no matter how secure the
other applications are, the weakest link
will be the weakest link. That will be the source of
chaos from within that entire cloud account.
So there are different ways to handle this, and there are
different strategies to manage the risk and
potential impact of that kind of attack. But one of
the ways would be to restrict the IAM permissions.
Never give too much power or
permissions to a server.
So in the past you give permissions to a human,
but right now when you're deploying your applications in
the cloud, you can either give permissions to a human
or you might be able to give permissions to
a machine resource, which is in this case a server. So limiting
those permissions, or maybe not giving any
permission at all would help improve the security of
your application. So again,
securing JavaScript applications is not just about securing
the code, it's also securing where your JavaScript
applications are running.
So how about denial of wallet attacks when
it comes to securing JavaScript applications right now you
also need to understand the architecture aspect.
What if you have a serverless implementation
or architecture which uses AWS
Lambda and JavaScript to process web
request? So AWS Lambda is
a function as a service which
processes an event and provides a response
or an output. So if you have a web API that
can be your backend web server,
but behind the scenes you have a serverless web API resource,
and you also have serverless functions which processes each
of the requests. Having a good idea on
how the finance aspect works would help you, because if
your application is not able to process denial of service
attacks, well then you might encounter
a similar issue here where you might be surprised
that your cloud bill would be
amazingly large. When I say amazingly large, you wouldn't
be able to pay the bill at all because there's
too much request which force your infrastructure
to scale automatically. And then you have to pay a
lot of money because you pay for what you used in
a cloud platform. So this affects different cloud
providers and it's important that you're aware that this attack
is possible because it's going to really cost money which
would then close that cloud account.
So in order to protect against denial of wallet attacks
number one you need to be aware that that's possible and second you need to
be able to include in your plan and architecture how to deal
with ddos and denial of wallet attacks.
So that's pretty much it. In this session
we learned a lot of things. There were three parts.
The first part focusing more on the JavaScript code
and making sure that the developers are well aware on
how that JavaScript code can be used to compromise
the overall system and server. The second part involves
how to secure your JavaScript applications
which are machine learning powered and part
focuses more on the other aspects like securing the libraries
and frameworks used as well as the other aspects
like the infrastructure and the network
as well. So thank you again for listening to my talk
and hope you learned something new. Have a great day ahead guys.
Bye.