Okay, so, yeah, welcome everyone. Good morning, good afternoon,
or good evening from wherever you are.
And this talk is going to be about software composition analysis 101,
knowing what's inside your apps.
So just to give you a little bit of overview about
me, as jobing said, I'm an information security specialist.
I've been doing apps back and also devsecops lately
for at least over ten years now
in Upsec and Devsecops, like five years,
I've deployed multiple SaaS dust software
composition analysis solutions, right. Currently I work as a
cloud security research and kind of
integrating my application security skills with cloud technologies
such as different cloud services, kubernetes, Docker and
all that stuff. I also have a blog where
I try to share my articles at least once
a month and also there is all my contact information
and my previous talks. So videos or slides,
talks that I've given since 2011,
it's all there. So the agenda for
this talk, right, we don't have a lot of time. We have a little
bit, 30 minutes, right. So we'll try to cover what's
an SCA, what's a bomb, like a buff materials,
right? And what's an ass bomb.
Before we dive deep into what is software composition
analysis and how it works, I'll show you some
numbers, right. Why should you, as a developer,
right, as this event is targeted for developers, why should you worry about
that? Right. Why should be your problem and should be your
concern as well. And then we're going to talk about supply chain attacks.
And one of the main reasons that they happen is because of
open sources, libraries and dependencies that
can be compromised. And then we talk about best practices
and some software composition analysis tools. If we have
time. I'll do a quick demo here. So, yeah,
what is SCA, right. So if
you work in apps, you probably have heard about SCA by now,
but it's kind of a new term. At least when I joined UpseC over ten
years ago, people didn't talk about software composition analysis,
right? So we talk about has and dust and that was it,
right? And I think over,
I don't know, five years ago a little bit more that we started
talking more about it. But it's not a new thing, it's not a new term.
It's been around for a while with different names around like
library analysis, open source security, third party dependency.
Right? So there's different names, but now kind of these term,
I think was coined by Gartner is software composition analysis,
right. To analyze what components are part of
your software, your application and checking if
they have any public known vulnerabilities, if they are outdated, if there
is any risks for these business, even legal risks
regarding license purposes, right? So SCA is aimed
at providing the open source software with governance,
security and, and what does that mean?
Provenance, right. You need to understand whats sometimes you're using
libraries and code on your applications from people
that you don't even know that they can be on the other
side of the globe and sometimes they might not be trustworthy,
right. You might not be able to trust them and inject
or import that code into your application,
especially on enterprise applications, right.
So one of the things that software composition analysis
tries to address is understanding
the software bill of materials, right. And we're going to talk
about whats in the next few slides. So what
does it mean? What do you need to
perform a software composition analysis, right. So mainly these things
that you need to do and that's kind of given across the
board on major SCA tools. You need an
application manifest, right. Giving trucks on how the software should work.
You need a dependence metadata which shows what are the
dependencies that you have in your software and the versions of those dependencies,
right. And the last thing that you also need is
the vulnerability data source, how you're going to compare.
If the library that you have in your code is outdated or vulnerable,
you need to compare with something, right? And so that is the vulnerability data
source, which is a database of vulnerability information.
It can be private or public, right? The most common public
one is NVD or the national vulnerability Database.
But we're going to see that usually that's not enough. So yeah,
I talked about software bill of materials, right. But let's back up a
little bit. What is the bill of materials? Right. If you've
done any kind of research
on engineering or product design, you know that
a bill of materials is a list of materials that creates
a product, right? So let's say
if I have my chair,
right, whats do I need to make that chair? Like, okay, I need
my wood, I need my kind of these
seat, right? So I need foam, I need some
kind of thing to cover the foam and stuff
like that, right? So you know what you need, you know the quantities and
how much they cost usually. So that you know whats is the
price of making that chair so that you can add to that
for like, okay, what is the price that I'm going to sell it, right.
So it's kind of like that. So this is an example of a
bill of materials and with software, we have the same thing, so we
call them has bombs or software bill of materials.
And with s bombs they are not very different from
bill of materials in real life. They're a list of components
in a piece of software, right. It's usually okay.
Mostly the dependence is the libraries that I
import or I use in my code, right. So nowadays nobody
code from scratch. You usually have frameworks and libraries
that are made of open source and sometimes commercial
components, right. So SBom is very similar to the components
in a product, right. So when you buy a processed product
on your supermarket, you're going to have the ingredients. So it's kind of
the list of ingredients in a packaged food, right.
So that's the main thing that software composition
analysis tries to analyze and understand and make sure whats
those components are up to date are not vulnerable
and are according to the licensing that you need and you want
on your software. So there are some major resources,
these for SBom. There are some standards as well,
with everything. There's different standards right now,
but I think they are kind of the most common ones that
I tried to show you here. One of the
most famous ones is Cyclone DX, which is a lightweight software
built material standard and it just became a flagship,
a WaSp flagship product last month. Right.
So that's very interesting and I think it's going to be very helpful for
OWASP and the developers who use the OASP resources.
There is another standard called SPDX which is an
open standard for communicating software buff material information and
it belongs to the Linux foundation. Right. So that's
another common standard that's being used as well. And we
have dependency track. So you probably have heard about OAS
Dependency Check, which is a famous OAS project for checking
vulnerabilities in your libraries. But dependency track, it might
not be as famous as dependency check. Right. So dependency track
allows organizations to identify and reduce the risk of these software
in the supply chain. So it helps you track your
s bomb and track any kind of dependencies on your software.
Okay, so why you're telling me this, right?
Why me as a developer, if I'm talking in a developer
event, why you should worry about it, right.
So here I brought some numbers for you.
84% of the code bases had at least
one vulnerability with an average of 158
per code base according to the open source risk
analysis report done by synopsis, I think last year.
Yeah, last year. And another thing before
they compared in 2016, can average of 84
open source components per application was found
on the software that they tested. Right, and nowadays, like last
year, 2020, there is an average of 528
open source components, right? So it's a huge increase and
it's very hard for you to track and validate and analyze
all those things manually. Right? So you need a solution, you need
something to automate that for you and at least try to
cover outdated and vulnerable libraries in your code.
There is also a great study, and I think was presented by
earlier in this event from snake
talking about the state of open source security report, which is really good, and I
recommend you taking a look and it shows the number of new packaged
biochem per year. You can see right away
here that of course Javascript or NPM packages
are very high compared to the other ones,
but there's been an increase on packages and libraries and
it's hard to keep track of those, right. And you don't know the
provenance. So that's the problem here, because anyone can submit a
new package. So just like kind of like the
App Store or the Google Play, you can submit
a new application here, you can submit a package as well.
And people will start using if they like it, right? And they will start
importing their project, right? So if they don't know you,
if you want to do something malicious with that
package, once it starts propagating to many different applications,
that's possible to happen. Right? So that's why you need to keep track of those.
Okay, so I don't know if you heard about this and just
one more data for you to understand and probably try to
just kind of worry a little bit more
about this problem, right. This was presented
by Mark Curfe, which is one of the founders of OASP,
and he's also the creators of a
company called Sourceclear, which is now port of Veracode.
And he presented this code cocktail, right? So there
is many studies around that kind of the open source
security space on how much is open
source part of my code, right? And so there are some
studies showing that between 70 and 90% of
your code are made of open source, starting from
libraries, frameworks and everything. So kind of like ten
to 30% is your custom code, whats your developers make.
So you can see right away that the attack surface
of your application, it's much higher
on the open source and on the third party code than on
your custom code. So that's one more reason that
although yeah, you should worry about SAS and Dast,
but software composition analysis can
be really important sometimes and can coverage maybe
a larger attack surface depending on your software, on your application,
your code base. So that's
why I presented these numbers for you to be aware of that.
And there is another issue, and I think was mentioned earlier in this conference
as well, right? You have the direct dependencies,
which is the libraries and the dependencies that you import,
right, in your code, but there are some indirect
or transient dependencies and that's even a
bigger problem, right? So I have a library whats imports another
library from a third party code. And that library that was imported is the
one that's vulnerable or is outdated, right?
I can't update whats library until
my library that I imported directly gets updated and
calls the new version of that library. So that creates a major
problem here as well. And that's what I think is
these biggest risk in kind of the software composition analysis
space. And what
more important than to worry about web application vulnerabilities
than to looking at the wasp top ten, right? We're probably
going to have a new versions of the top ten this year, but still the
latest version of the top ten and the previous one, they all talked about
using components with non vulnerabilities, right?
So this is a major thing. Whats software compositional analysis
tries to address is avoiding using those components with non
vulnerabilities. If you all remember these Xfax
hack in 2017, it was because a library was
vulnerable. The Apache threats two library has vulnerable and
it got hacked through that library, right?
So it's very important issue and you need to be aware
of here is just to show you
that there is some similarities and of
course some differences between the software supply chain and the traditional
supply chain, right? And that's the reason
why not just your libraries and your dependencies, but your whole pipeline,
you need to be aware of and protect it properly.
So you have your open sources repositories,
your source code repositories, sorry, your build systems, right?
Your application repository like for your binaries and where you deploy
your applications as well. And all that can
be entry points for attacks and for compromises,
right? We all seen the recent SolarWinds attack,
right? So it was attacking in these build system of the SolarWinds
of the SolarWinds application. So that's also
an issue that you need to be aware of as well.
Here I have a catalog that
we've done through the CNCF, as it was mentioned
in the beginning, I'm part of the CNCF security tag team,
which means technical advisory group. So we provide
volunteer services as well, just like for OASP,
but we focus on cloud native applications. So like
Kubernetes, whats CD and helm and all
that, OPA as well. So all those applications,
we try to provide them with guidance and documentation
and also doing some security audit for those applications.
And in this kind of group we have
done some catalog of supply chain compromises.
So in this GitHub repo from the CNCF, we have a
list of all the major supply chain compromises
that affected either the source code or developer
tools or publishing infrastructure in the past
like ten years, right? So we have a lot of them there listed and
I updated this list recently. So I think it's pretty much up to
date with kind of just a
few recent events. But it's very important for you to understand that
this is a major thing. Your developer and your
infrastructure, your pipeline can be a target of those
attacks. There is also the software supply chain white paper
which we wrote recently and published this year.
It talks about not just securing the source code and your libraries,
but also the build pipelines, your artifacts and your deployments.
So it's very interesting for you to take a look and it's
available for free on the CNCF GitHub repository.
One last thing, whats I like to mention here is our supply
chain attacks are migrating to the cloud, right?
Since almost every company are migrating to
the cloud and even now during the pandemic, everyone's starting using
the cloud more often, either SaaS services or infrastructure as
a service, right? We need to be aware of that. So recently
our team at Trend Micro did a research on the supply
chain attacks in the age of cloud computing, right?
So here you have an example of on the
top there, the developer using the IDE in
their own device, in their own house or their own
company office, right? Yeah. These install the required
program, they set up the environment, they interact via these ide.
But there's many organizations where the developers
don't run their ide in their local devices, right?
So it's kind of the evolution
approach of the VDI, right, the virtual desktop. So you have
AWS, cloud nine,
I think now there is one for GitHub as well
and Azure has one. So you have their online ides,
right? So these are some risks on using those as well. And you
need to be aware of that because you're communicating and you're hosting
your code in a separate location and there can
be other flaws where attackers can compromise that
system and get access to your sources code.
One last thing that you need to be aware of,
and I think it's very important for supply chain attacks is the
US executive order, right. I know it's just happening in
the US, but it might affect other organizations that either have
customers in these US or supply software to the US.
Right? So it was published in May twelveth this
year. And one of the sections it
talks a lot about enhancing the software supply
chain security. So it talks about maintaining
accurate and update provenance of software code and components,
right. So it's basically talking about software composition, analysis and
software supply chain security to understand that. So if
you're an organization that sells software or
intends to sell software to us government, you need
to be aware of that executive order. You need to focus on supply
chain as well. Okay,
so there are many different tools and I mentioned some of them here already.
The has dependency check which is a free one.
It focus on NVD. It's mostly for Java and
net. If I'm not mistaken you have the retired js
for Javascript code and dependencies.
There is Nic which is free from open source and it's the sponsor
of this event. Right. And there's also many
different ones, commercial ones, one that we have
fraternity and Michael we call open source security,
which is basically a partnership with sneak to provide
their features in our platform.
Let's see how we're doing on time.
Are we good on time? Let me see. Okay, I think
we can do some demos, right? Let me try to share my screen quickly
here. Okay, so basically what
I'm going to do here is show you a
quick demo of sneak inside the
trend micro cloud one platform. It's basically the same
UI that you're going to see if you
want to use Nic as a platform for you to analyze your.
Yeah, and it's free for open source, right? Nick is free for open
source. You can add your projects directly from GitHub. So basically when
you log in, what you need to worry about
is configuring your integrations, right. How sneak is going
to look at your code and check your code repositories
to understand and to collect that
data to analyze the libraries.
So let me just close this, I'll do just a quick
demo before we move on.
So I'm going to add a project from GitHub and I have here all my
public repositories from GitHub and I know
I have a lot of repositories but it's mostly forks.
But yeah, I have here the OASP juice shop, right? If you're
familiar with OASP Juice shop, it's a platform for you
to learn about web application security has different vulnerabilities
and it's very user friendly for you to learn.
And it's developed in I think code and angular.
Right. So basically I select a project from my GitHub or
from any other repository, I can change
some settings here, pointing these, the dependency
is the files for checking the libraries and these versions,
that's not necessary. These basically, okay, add selected
repositories. So it's going to
add and it's going to start scanning, it's going to find,
depending on the language and the project is going to try to find where
is that located. Right. So where are the dependencies,
are they vulnerable? So it's checking with the SNC database,
which is even public, the database of intelligence of
vulnerabilities from SNC, it's public and you can see that.
So it quickly showed me the results here and we can see that here.
It analyzed, since it's a JavaScript or a
node project, it analyzed the packet JSON
file. Right. And if we check here we can quickly
see oh, there is a critical vulnerability here,
prototype pollution, which has a cvss of
9.8, right. So that's very critical and we need to
be aware of that. And that's in the package called low dash. And so
there is even proper sneak
id here and I think you can go to the
sneak database here to read more about it. Right. So yeah,
you can take a look here, there is a CVE,
there is a CWe, right. And there's the description of the vulnerability
here. So that's very interesting for the developer to know right
away what they need to do.
Right. And also here it shows when
the vulnerability was added to this project, to which version of the
package and what you need to do. You can also ignore here if
you want, right. And there's a risk code and all that stuff. So it's
very important for you to analyze those libraries
and see what can you do there if there is
a new version. Updating is
the most common thing to do. But you also need
to be aware of not breaking your application, right. So you
need to have proper testing, especially regression testing, to make
sure that once you update whats library,
you don't break the application.
Yeah, basically here the dependencies, and as I said,
the dependencies can be direct dependencies or indirect dependencies,
right. So it shows these, that there are some indirect ones
that are vulnerable as well and can be even harder for
me to fix because I need to rely on that one,
the top one for me to update that. Right.
So yeah, you need to understand that as well.
Yeah, basically that's the demo that I had to share. Just a quick
overview on how you can use a software composition analysis
tool and sneak is the one that I most recommend
using. And yeah, I hope you
enjoyed this talk and I'm available for questions later.
Ah.