Hello, let us talk about Metric collector and analyzer.
My name is Timo Pagl. I'm a Devsecops trainer
and strategist. I'm an open source fan and an
open knowledge fan boy and I'm
a university lecturer. In this talk I will provide
you now with an introduction. Afterwards we will
take a look at the architecture of Metrica and then we will
come to an outlook.
I am also the leader of the devsector Ops maturity
model and the question first
is I say why do you need security maturity
models when you want to enhance
the security in your area of influence? Then you ask
yourself how to enhance the security and there are so many
options you have that you need to think about how to prioritize
to understand the options. I like to categorize
in DevOps strategies. So how do
you harden your DevOps processes
and technologies? And then the
question is how can you enhance your security through
DevOps strategies? So how can you utilize the strategies which
are already there? For example, you can utilize a build process to integrate
security testing there or you're having information gathering
maybe with a stack like Prometheus
and Grafana which collection the different metrics.
So there you just need to adjust the metrics that you're getting
alerted when there is security incidents.
I regularly perform assessments and
these assessments are performed quarterly,
yearly or bi yearly. But as
a product team I want fast feedback for my
performed security activities to stay motivated.
So as a product team I want
to implement an activity and then get
feedback. An example in the area of security
testing is the meantime to
respond to vulnerabilities.
I might have performed
very well. Then I want to see it reflected in the
feedback. And in case I haven't performed very well, I also want to
get notified. Hey, it's currently not going as planned
and there are things which we can automate.
So the question is how do we automate
devsecops assessments?
And the solution is Metrica. In Metricca
we have manual assessments which we perform in
a YAmL structure and automatic
assessments where we pull the
information from various sources like
Jira, other security tools like
dependency track,
confluence, maybe even from
Azure active directory.
So there are various tools where we can get information from
the metric collector and analyzer.
Here you see an overview for it. So on the
bottom you have two different or three different YAML files.
You have activities per team and per application.
So some activities are per
application and some activities per team. So when you have for example a security
champion per team then this is team based
and the activity status is inherited to
the applications of that team. You have a one to n relationship
here and then you have maturity model definitions.
So on which level is a specific
activity? What is the threshold for that activity that
you say it is performed for an application or it's not performed,
that are the information we store in a configuration yaml.
But manual assessments have a lag. So for
example, when you do thread modeling, you document the thread modeling in
your tool, for example in confluence.
And afterwards you need to document it again in YAML,
or the product owner or the product team needs to document
it in the YAML.
In addition, there the collector comes into
place. The collector automatically collection from various different sources
like confluence, in case you document your threat modeling in confluence.
And then you maybe have a label on that page
called threat modeling. And on
the top you have information when
did it happen and who the participants
and very important, the application id. And then we fetch that information automatically
with the collector and afterwards both
sources. So with a collector source and
the different YAML files are getting analyzed by the analyzer.
And then we push that information to
Grafana security dashboard. And in Grafana
you might be able also to configure alerts, automatically alerts.
For example when a threat modeling is missing,
you might say I want to perform a threat modeling every quarter and a
team hasn't performed it within the last three months.
And you can send out a warning, hey, you should very soon
perform a quick split modeling so that
this process is also automated. Here you
see an overview of how
product owners or the team can handle the yamls
in the repository. So you have a repository and
the product owner maybe pulls the repository
or uses a web UI to perform changes.
So for example, hey, I read all the
needed security policies and I confirm it in the YaML file.
Then the product owner pushes it.
These changes to the repository create the pull request
and then a security architect could review these
changes, approves or denies it, and then
see changes are reflected in case the
pull request is accepted.
Here we see how the flow is for the thresholds.
So there is a trigger, for example the pull request.
Then we transfer the meter model information
to Java objects. We combine the
Yaml files and the collector information.
Then we check the threshold for that team in that
particular level, for example the mean time
to patch. Then we generate dashboards out
of it. The dashboards will be
already half thresholds which we
generate from the Java application.
So we want to stay independent from
the grafana. We want to be able to put any other
option there as well, any other data source,
for example the maturity,
the devsec option, maturity model itself, or even other sources.
This is a very big overview of the architecture.
So in GitHub we are building the whole application
so that you can utilize it in your organization and
with your data. We are also planning
to make the architecture
very flexible so that you can define,
so that you can have your own activity
definition. That's why we came up with
this class diagram where
we have the spring component, the date component and
the integer component with an interface.
And then the activity has all these
different types, so you can
combine these types as you like.
And in this case, the main developer here is
Rafael Vespi, who came
up with this diagram and is implementing be
very the YAML file should be very generic so
that you can have your own activity definitions per
application or team. You have the activities YAML and the
team YAML and you have the very
generic configuration Yaml, which is there only once,
in which you define what activities are there and what are the thresholds
and what are the levels for these different
activities. In the configuration
yaml, you have the application id, you have
the target level, and then for the activities, the level,
in case you have implemented the activity on which level
this activity should be performed.
And we're currently not having a structure for the threshold, but that will come.
Here is an example for the activities YAml. You have again an application id
and the different activities. We also want
to generate a schema so that when the pull request
happens you can, or the product owner can receive there
is a mistake in the provided YaML
file. I have to say it's
not a silver bullet. You always
have people and processes. You need to say as
a team you still need to perform these activities. You need to put it
into the YAML files. So that's all something where you need
to do a lot of cultural work.
And I recommend to use the collector
in the future rather than the YAML. So the yamls are there
for static things which you cannot automate easily, but everything
you can automate, you should automate with the collection.
As you have already mentioned, currently we are
in a draft status or the implementation phase.
Currently we can perform changes very easily. So in case you have any ideas
how to enhance this, please talk with me.
Come to the overslack channel,
to the DSM channel,
or if you like, you can also send
an email. Here are my information.
The access Switzerland is sponsoring this project and
we currently estimate that it will be implemented
by the end of 2023.
Thank you and see you soon.