Hello everybody, my name is Tomasz Manugiewicz
and today I would like to spend this 30 minutes with you talking
about CTO view on DevOps transformation.
Starting with the word DevOps, I would love
to ask you, what do you think about this word? What does it
mean for you? Usually it means two things.
The first thing that people say is that DevOps
is a mindset. What that really is. We'll dig
into it in a second. But on the other hand,
some engineers say that DevOps is a tool chain. We have
a lot of tools that we would like to use in our project,
and that's DevOps. So that's also right.
DevOps is actually the mindset and
the tool chain. So the way we think about tools and
others and our technology and the tools we are
using. Speaking of technology,
simplifying the process a little bit, we have development
activities going on. Those activities produce some jar file,
for example, and we put this jar file
deploy on the server and ask operations guys to maintain
the observed. That's the software development
in a very big nutshell, right?
However, when we dig into the details on
the development side, there are a lot of plenty
activities like architecture. We need to design
the software, we need to plan the architecture, then we
need to program, produce a code.
We need to make sure that our code is merged to
the one project. So we need version control systems.
We then deploy to various environments
and we implement logging mechanisms,
right? So that's the development piece of work that we do.
On the other hand, there is operations piece of work. So monitoring
our software, how it behaves, how it performs, and so
on, observing the logs that we implemented and patching
our software with the new versions and fixes.
All right. But in the middle there is magic
thing, deployment, deployment to staging environment.
We can have the UAT environment, so user acceptance tests,
we can have a pre prod environment, prod environment,
hidden product environment, even, or hidden pre prod environment.
Obviously in various organizations we
do it differently, but that's how it looks in general.
And now this middle section,
nowadays we replace by infrastructure as a code
approach, by containers, implementing Docker
or other containers, by orchestration mechanisms,
by configuration management, CI CD pipeline
logging, monitoring and so on and so forth.
And this part could potentially belong to our
development world and development team, or could belong to operations
team. And it differs from the company
to company. And that's where the DevOps
core of DevOps, DevOps heart is. I would say so.
DevOps for me is a development plus operations,
development people, programmers and
operations people coming together in
order to have efficient software, sometimes developers
needs to do, and they would like to do something from operations side
of things. Sometimes operations guys would like to do
something from developers. And those two activities
combined together is a DevOps for me. So that's why we are talking here
about mindset, because it's a
set of our mind, how we will approach our collaboration
together using those tools.
Obviously, everyone is talking about this kind
of this picture. Everyone is talking about those tools.
We use puppet, we use chef Docker, you've already mentioned
everyone is jenkins, right? And build pipelines and so on
and so forth. So that's not a tough thing.
We can learn about it, we have skills to
use it. We are curious about how it works as well.
So that's very interesting for us. What's difficult
is who will be using which tool,
what are the standards, how will communicate together and collaborate
together. And that's where this transformation
word comes into play. Because let's imagine the old monolithic
architecture of our system and old monolithic structure of our company,
right? In order to transform it to microservices.
This is not just only about transforming our technology
stack, it's about transforming away ways of working,
it's about transforming our cooperation, communication and so on.
So that's why we talk about transformation. Either it's DevOps
transformation, or agile transformation, or any other kind of transformation
is about changing the way we work. We used to
work, so that's why it's so important to know
and so difficult to implement.
So how to implement that? We have state a,
for example, the monolithic architecture and the system corresponding
with our monolithic organizational structure. And we have state
b, beautiful, shiny microservice architecture,
orchestrated on the cloud, everything is automated
and so on. So that's two space.
On the other hand, we have
people who wanted to work in a state
a. Some of them would like to also work
in a state b. But there are some people who
don't like change, and that's totally okay.
Pretty much every one of us have some difficulties in
changing our habits. So that's why
we have the state a transformation
to state B. And this is not just easy,
just like saying, hey,
from tomorrow we'll do everything in another way. We need
to do it step by step. We need to transform it. So in
the middle stage, we need CTO have something that we
were using before. So on the left hand side, you can
imagine the silos, for example,
like green and red rectangle,
corresponds with the two departments working
in the silos. And in ideal state in
the B state, we would like to have those people working together,
development and operations. So in the middle, we need
to break the silos a little bit, building trust
and having this third component, which is this activities
in the middle that we had this orchestration, deployment activities,
container activities and so on, as a shared
responsibility between those two departments.
Now, when those people from department Green and department Red
will establish trust, the shared
responsibility is possible. So there will be no blaming game,
or we would like to eliminate the blaming game. We would like CTO have
one group responsible for the whole software.
And that's actually three steps that Kurt Levin described
is unfreeze the organization, change the organization
and freeze. Unfreezing means that
saying, hey, we would like to change the ways of working.
We don't want to have silos anymore.
We would like to unfreeze it and prepare you to explore
the new ways of working. Then in the stage number
two, we change the ways of working and then freeze
again saying, hey, this is new ways of working. You see the benefits,
you can experiment with that. And that's our strategy moving
forward. So those three steps, this is the
Kurt Levin model, as I mentioned. So unfreeze, change and
freeze. This is typical behavior of our transformation.
So when we unfreeze, we create climate
for change.
We learn how to implement the change.
We teach other people, teach our leaders, we show them that the change is,
first things first, important. The second thing is very critical
for our business. And there will be benefits for the organization and
personal benefits as well for
the people engaged in this stage.
Then we enable the organization. So we provide all the tools
that we would like to have, all the knowledge, as I said,
all the trainings. We have a lot of one on one discussions with
people, showing them the benefits, explaining them the
need for the change. And that's the most critical process,
this enabling organization in the middle,
because if you will do it right, people will be ready
for this change. And then freezing,
meaning sustaining change. So once we
learned new ways of working, once we learned how to
together operate in, for example,
Jenkins, or how to use nagios and other
tools, we would like to keep it. We don't want people to
come back CTO, the other tool to the old ways of working and
old tools, saying, hey, this nagios is not so good. I would
like to use the previous tool I
was using, or saying, no, I don't want to be involved in this
build pipeline creation, because I'm just operation guy.
We don't want that. We want people, developers and operations working
together. So that change needs to be
sustainable and we need to provide environments to keep people
satisfied and keep people engaged to
have this change. So that's, this freezing part here
is just an example, but I guess that you already
are familiar with that, that we have obviously some
activities. I'm not calling those
phases because we are not in an environment
of waterfall anymore. Maybe in
some commands we do, but I would like to call it
activities. There is a coding activity, there is a building
activity, that we build software, there's an integration part,
there's a testing part. We release and software with
the corresponding changes and then deploying to production and
operating. So this is about first step is CTO have
continuous integration, then continuous delivery,
continuous deployment. And DevOps is one step
further. So having everything and
everyone working alongside together. So that's DevOps.
All right. And our talk today is about clevel view or
CTO view on DevOps transformations, how to
implement the change and how to drive the
change in the organization, how to transform this organization.
The question is, do you really want to know what's the city
of view of DevOps transformation?
I guess you know, you want to know.
First things first. You need to understand that there will be broader
context for you. And sometimes it will
be difficult to have this context because we, as a
specialist, as engineers, we are very
narrow in the focus. We have deep knowledge.
That's our advantage. That's how we earn for living.
We have very deep knowledge, technical knowledge, but our focus
and view is limited. And generalists
have a zoom out and have a broader view. They don't have any more.
So deep knowledge, that's why they hire you guys.
But they have the broader view on the context of the business,
of the environment, of the structure of the organization.
So that's the visualization.
I would like to show it to you, by the
way, I would like CTO recommend to follow this guy. He's very
great designer and provides designs such
like this. So I like CTo be inspired by
this guy. All right.
Talking about our activity, daily activities,
programming version, controlling deployment and so on and so forth.
What we've already discussed, that's huge part of
our life, that's huge part of our knowledge and our experience.
And at the same time we call it DevOps.
Right as I greet. But this is just part of
the organization. This is not a core of the organization.
Obviously, it might be a core, but this
is very small part of what's going on in our organization.
So we have DevOps activities, we have
agile activities that I'm not here to talk about agile,
but I also specialized in agile ways
of working, and it goes hand to hand
with DevOps. So we have DevOps and agile practices,
and that's about collaboration, about tools as
well. Agile is also about tools sometimes, but in
general, it's how we collaborate together, developers, operations guys and
product guys in the agile environment.
Right? So that's collaboration. And then in the whole organization we
have structure, as I said. So CTO guys need
to think with other CE level people about the structure
of the company, how we will be working together.
So that's the structure. With whom, how and with whom,
what will be the structure of our teams, what will be the structure of
our departments, how CTO break the silos and so on and so forth.
Then there is a strategy. This is more about how actually
the strategy is with whom, how collaborate,
but how to deliver software. How about our technology?
We'll be using Java or net. Are we going to go CTO,
the microservices oriented architecture and so on. So the strategy,
technological strategy for ctos and the business strategy
for executives, for CEO,
how to earn money for the whole company, for the whole business, to provide
you jobs, right? So that's the strategy piece.
And then there is the last but not least organizational behavior piece.
So what we will be doing here in
the meaning maybe not even about the product, but how
to behave in our organization, what are the norms,
what are the standards, what is our culture in
this environment, what is our language that we speak, for example,
that's a lot of different activities. So that's in
general broad picture of the whole organization.
So you can see that your technology part even is
key in the organization, is just part of it.
And the organization is going through change.
So we need to transform this organization from
state a to state b, if you remember. So all the people,
all the topics, all the aspects that we have already talked about need
to be transformed, need to change
and have this way ahead of the organization.
Actually, I see the two ways or two
buses, if I call it that way, the mindset
bus and the technology bus. We already talked a little bit about the mindset
of technology, right? So we need to change the technology and
we need CTO change our ways of thinking and ways of working.
So that's how our organization is going through the
transformation. We need to transform technology. At the same time, we need
to transform our mindset, ways of thinking
about ourselves. So looking again about the
structure, we can see the
interactions that's up there. There's interaction
between mindset bus and technology
bus. I guess that some of you already recognize
this pattern and this analogy to our computer
architecture. So if we think about organizational
behavior, this is an input to our mindset. So how
we will be behaving, what do we accept or what don't
we accept? If operations guys will be blaming developers
and developers will be blaming operations,
are we okay to accept that? Or we will say, no,
this is not our norm, we don't accept this rule.
We accept no blaming culture, for example.
So that's the input to mindset bus. But when it comes to strategy,
actually, when I was thinking about that, there are actually inputs, CTO, our mindset
bus and the technology bus, because it's about which
technology we will use and how to use it.
But also, this is about how to approach this technology
and what are our ways
of working together alongside with this technology.
If we have, for example, microservices oriented architecture,
how our teams will be speaking together, or even
more. And that's the next bit, the structure.
So this is the analogy for me to the memory,
the organizational memory, how we'll structure our
teams in order to make sure that the knowledge will
be stored in our organization and the
experience that we have in building. For example, microservices will
be stored in the teams, rather than just pulling people
to projects and dispatching them after the project.
So that's about structure. And at the end of the day, cpu is
our collaboration. So we have our
cpu here, right? Every single one of us.
But in the organization, there is collective cpu.
That's why organizations are getting bigger and bigger, because they need,
sometimes we call it brain power. They need the brain power to
think through solutions, to design the products.
So we need to collaborate together. More precisely, our brains
need to collaborate together to
produce the outcome. So that's how it works
and how it looks. And then there is
a trust that needs to be established.
And the technology bus, for me, it's cognitive aspect
of trust. So we need CTO know that
this person will deliver the solution,
that he or she has the knowledge, he or she has the experience,
and will prove that is able to deliver the software,
and then will trust this person. And also CTO
will trust this person and vice versa. If CTO have
to have some knowledge,
people needs to trust him or her, that she or
he will deliver the idea that
the strategy, technological strategy. And there is another aspect of
trust, emotional aspect of trust. And this is about more about the mindset,
how we approach other people,
collaboration with other people. Do we trust them?
If we are open with them, if we are honest with them,
we don't hide ourselves or keep a secrets. We are ready
to cooperate. That's emotional aspect of trust. So those two buses,
for me, is also about building a trust,
cognitive aspect of trust and emotional aspect of trust.
I don't have time today to talk more about building trust,
but as an engineers, trust for me was a little bit fuzzy
word. So I dig into the details and
created a special talk about trust. If you
are interested, I think there are some talks
out there online you can reach out
to and listen.
There's one effect connected with trust, the iceberg
of the ignorance. This effect tells
us that ceos or
clevel guys know just a little bit about the troubles
in the organization. They measure that this is
just about 4%. They know about just 4% of the problems.
Why is that? Because of the erosion of
trust. That 100% of problems are
known for people in the teams. Right. You know,
guys, what's going well, what's not going well. And sometimes
you share with your manager, if you have better trust with
him or her, you share more. If not,
you hide some problems. Right. Sometimes we
are afraid of talking about problems. So that's the challenge,
and it's going on. Right. So, to remove those
barriers, we need to build a trust to
bubble up the problems, not to be blamed by our CTO. We don't
want to be blamed. Right. But to solve that
problems. Okay. So now, looking from the CTO
perspective, what are their needs and what are the biases?
They have some needs, and sometimes the conversation
with CTO can be tough. I know, and clevel
guys, but this is because they have some
needs, personal needs, as all of us, and they have some biases
as well. So today, I would like to tell you something
about that for you to understand more. Clevel executives.
It is about needs.
Based on the Marshall Rosenberg research and
biases, notation is about this organization that I put
the link here. You can check. There are more
than 100 biases over there that people are biased.
And I chose the most suitable one for sea level guys.
So I divided into four sections as
we talked about organizational behavior, strategy, structure, the collaboration.
When it comes to behaviors, sea level guys
have a need of presence, of your presence.
They need to see the people that are engaged,
that are ready to support ctos,
and they are ready to build the trust with CTO, even though
there are sometimes tough conversation. CTO need
to build trust with you, and you need to build trust with CTO, so they
need your support. That's basically
it sometimes it's challenging. And why it's challenging because there are
some biases that CTO guys can be
led by. The first one is choice supporting
bias, seeing previous choices as a good. Let's imagine the situation when
you have new CTO coming into your organization, and she
was seeing good options and good
solutions in the previous company. So she will be probably
bringing these ideas to the table and seeing,
hey, it was good because previously I did that, it worked.
But right now there is a different organization or different structure
or different business environment. So that
is one bias, the other one is a conservatism bias.
As simple as it sounds, prefers PI or evidence over
the new information. So basically, sea level guys,
they are searching for evidence
in the data. So if they have the
evidence that something worked,
they prefer doing that way, rather than seeing
new solutions, new architectures and so on.
Obviously, ctos are more open to new
architecture and new technological stuff. But in general, clevel guys,
they may be conservative in that type.
Confirmation bias, seeking information to keep our internal
judgment. So if you would like to implement
microservices or go to AWS, we seek
only about that. Everyone is going to aws
and so amazing. But we may forget
about difficulties in the structure
piece. They are achievers, most likely
sea level guys. They are achievers, meaning they would like to achieve
something. They would like to discover. This is strategy in
a structure. So they would like to achieve something. They would like
to discover something. So they would like to build a strategy
to achieve and discover new horizons.
Right? And they would like to also know that
we know where we are heading to them as a CTO.
So they YC level guys produce strategy piece and roadmap
and so on. But I would like to also understand that you know
where you are heading to. And there are also
three. By assisted I
found impact overestimating of things because of its potential
impact. If we see potential impact
that they may have on the revenue, for example, we overestimate
the implementation of microservices, of getting
rid of our servers and moving to AWS.
Ostrich does. The funny name ostrich
by us is ignoring dangerous information, obviously.
So focusing just on solutions
that worked and with
a happy path. Obviously there's not that way that all ctos
will be forgetting about ignoring that dangerous information.
But that's the bias that can be dragged
into and overconfidence. That's very
frequent bias. Being too confident about our abilities,
too confident about moving to AWS in a year or
so. In the structure piece,
they seek consistency, stability, and clarity.
So they would like to have consistent structure in the organization,
stable structure in the organization, and clear
structure in the organization. That's why when you
have new executives coming in, they would like to make
this organization as efficient as possible for them.
And the biases that they can have at this stage. Clustering,
isolation, seeing patterns where there are no patterns. I had one
advice from my colleague. We had totally
two different departments, but just one word in the
name was the same. I don't remember even the word, but let's
put it strategic projects.
And one department, let's use that name.
One department was totally technical strategic projects development,
and the other was strategic projects project management.
And this person saw just strategic projects and
say, hey, we need to merge those two teams, right? Because it's
just strategic projects. So be aware
of this vividness. Focus on
the most easily recognizable data. So, again,
looking at the data, but focusing, you need to understand that ctos
have a lot of distractions and a lot of information they need to
have in their heads. So they seek for
clarity. And if they recognize the data patterns,
they will go under this one, even though the data
might be not correct,
framing, being influenced by the situation, is how the situation is
presented. That's the aspect of elevator pitch,
right? That we remember some examples in
Silicon Valley of the elevator pitches that were not so, that the
businesses were not so profitable, but the elevator pitches were so great.
So that's why we
need to avoid this bias. And the last one,
collaboration, group empowerment,
inspiration and situation and contribution and belonging.
So when CTO asks you to come to the office, because they have the
workshop for you, they seek inspiration from you,
they seek stimulation that you will ask questions to CTO,
you will collaborate, contribute, you will
be empowered group to inspire CTO, because CTO
is not just one person sitting somewhere and judging.
He or she would like to speak with you, and that's also about belonging.
He or she would like to belong to the group, because sometimes
he or she is perceived as a person somewhere else in the board,
and he or she may feel alone. So he
or she would like to belong to the group on the workshop, for example.
That's why people ask about coming to the office.
And the biases at this stage, mirror imaging,
assuming others will act the same as we would like to
or as we would act. This is more
in the group, right? False consensus, overestimation of
consensus within the group. If we don't have a trust and we are afraid of
conflict. Sometimes not so frequent, but sometimes
the discussions that should have happened will not be happening because of the
lack of trust and fear group thinking.
Choosing the option that majority of the group prefers, even though it's not the
best option. That sometimes that can happen even
in the executive team itself when more like
say, hey, we have six executives and five of them are
into one solution. But just CTO is seeing different point
of view. But it's difficult. CTO challenge
those five people and hello effect agreeing and disagreeing
with someone because of his or
her personality. If we are inspired by someone, we can also
be biased.
All right, so at the end, in a couple of minutes I would like to
give you a pro tips how to show up
in front of the sea level guys in front of the CTO.
Be docker but not this docker.
Be a container that have
a lot of information inside of you and can
ship those information to your CTO. Also organization
can be this container and the
transformation is very slow because
this container moves very slow. So you need to
be bond, James Bond.
Basically you need to be the person go to person for special
tasks. If your CTO trusts you and say, hey,
this, I don't know. Mike. Mike will
deal with that definitely. You will
win trust in the CTO and you will win
in the organization. Build trust within the crew and
the skipper. So build trust between your team and
CTO. Not having a blame game,
we have bad CTO and so on. Even though team
have this narration. Build trust with them, try to bring
them together. Know your coordinates
so create a map roadmap for
your team. Measure where you are.
Inspect and adapt. If you can improve something and
have alternative road meaning. Have alternative solutions.
If this solution will not happen, keep a full
steam, have the energy be energized and motivated
to help your CTO because CTO seeks for people
who will help him or her moving this organization.
Don't wait in the port, just be brave and be vocal.
Ask for meetings with your CTO and propose your solutions
and drive a tagboat. Not sure if you know what the tagboat is that those
small boats that moves those bigger
containers, bigger ships in the port.
Small tugboats can move huge ship.
With this tagboat you can stabilize the ship. You can normalize
the tech stack. Help your CTO
be involved in the technology in a typical technology discussion
as well. But also know your limitations of
your technology and don't just focus on AWS because this is AWS.
Know your limitations and speak with your CTO about hey, this is good solution
but you need to watch out for this and this and that and
look behind the horizon. This is the most important point
for our technology people, engineers. We need to look
behind the horizon of the business side. We are not just
here to code, we are just here to grow the organization.
So be the captain in your team. Drive the
group towards new destination. This is something
that CTO and CW guys seeks in engineers.
Not just coding, but thinking about the whole business
and thinking about other ships. So other companies,
if they can do what they do and how they achieve
results in the organization at the end.
I would like to leave you with this quotation. The wind and
the waves are always on the same side of the ables navigator.
So be brave and thank you very much.
It was a pleasure to speaking with you today.
Cheers.