Everyone, very warm welcome to the Conf 42 session
on empowering executives to embrace quantum computing.
This session is ideal for executives with little to maybe no
technical background and who are extremely interested
in learning more about quantum computing. My aimed in this
session would be to provide you with an overview of what quantum bidding is,
why is it maybe necessary for you to understand at this point
of time and if it is essential for you to
adopt this upcoming technology in your existing industry.
My name is Vardaan Sahgal and IBM, the software head at
Womanium where I also lead the Quantum Solutions launchpad
headquartered in Washington, D. C. Alternatively, I am also
an IBM Qiskit advocate and have a breadth of research experience in
theoretical software domains of quantum computing.
Talking about womanium Womanium is basically a nonprofit
organization based out of Washington, DC, US.
Womanium was started seven years back with the aim of educating
young girls and promoting more women in STEM and essentially creating
the scientific leaders of tomorrow. Till date, womanium has
helped students get trained in STEM fields by providing over
1100 scholarships spelled across a staggering
88 countries. Womanium has been actively involved in
training the next generation of workforce by education participants
in STEM fields from life sciences to engineering
to quantum computing, and has been the recipient
of various international awards along the way. For the past
couple of years, womanium, in very close collaboration with
a lot of us national laboratories, has been working on providing
training in all sorts of quantum domains, quantum computing,
quantum hardware, quantum sensing and even
quantum communication for that matter. As I mentioned before,
the main purpose of this presentation is towards a
nontechnical audience. My main aim in this session
would be to provide a bit overview of what quantum computing is
and why does it matter for executives level people like
you to understand this upcoming technology?
While I discuss quantum computing, I would delve
into some real world applications and real world use case studies
where quantum computing has already played a major role in defining industries
in the recent years. I would also highlight some very good
practices and some operations which you
should take while stepping into this overhyped quantum computing
industry. So stay tuned till the end of this presentation and
I hope you like it. So the first question is, why should
you be interested in quantum? After all, is it just
hype? But the very important
point is that even if you put aside the hype, I feel
that the stats shown on the screen right now should be more than enough to
get you interested. As of this year, more than $36
billion of public funding has been allocated towards the
research and innovation of quantum technologies across the globe.
You mind that this is a billion with the capital and Bolt B
and add to the private players working in the quantum
market, this figure grows even higher and
this humongous investments is bound to
make a very significant effect change
in a lot of industries. In fact,
according to a recent survey, 97% of the industry executives
already believe that quantum computing is bound
to disrupt the industries in the very near future.
A few decades back, quantum was just heretical.
It was just in textbooks and research laboratories. But now
it is very real and very much alive with more than
100 active quantum players in the entire ecosystem.
As expected, the tech giants of the industry were the very first
adapters of this emerging technology. But apart from that,
now we are actually seeing a lot of new startups with heavy
capital backings move into this domain. And not only
startups, we are also seeing a lot of pure quantum companies
going public, making it more and more significant
to actually work in the quantum industry. And gradually,
with the trend of huge investments, the traditional
non quantum companies are also slowly adopting this new technology.
Judging by the trend, the investments in quantum
are not stopping anytime soon. And with
the fast paced research that is going on, we can definitely see that
the early advantages quantum computing can be observed
in as nearly as maybe next four to five years.
Now that I have got all three at least interested in
hype about what quantum computing is, the next question should
be essentially, what is quantum computing?
And technically, I would love to dive into the fundamentals of
quantum computing and start explaining all about superposition,
all about entanglement, maybe what is Schorz's algorithm?
But honestly, I feel that you don't
need that pipeline, especially the executives present here
listening to me in this session. Because this
technical stuff, it comes at a later stage.
It is defined for a different audience. For you all
this does not matter or should not matter, because, okay,
let me ask you a question. You all use Internet,
right? Obviously you are streaming this
session right now online. So that answers my
question. But honestly, try to answer this. How many of you
actually know how the Internet works? Or maybe
for that matter, how does your mobile phone work?
Or maybe your laptop work? You don't know. And that
is okay, because we have been using classic computers for a long time
on a daily basis without worrying about the
underlying electronics. And the same should go
for quantum computing as well. Unless you're working at the
very bottommost level of research in quantum computing,
you should not be worried about what it is.
Instead, I would suggest that the interest should
be in the question of the high level stuff.
Maybe why is quantum computing necessary for my business,
or what are the advantages which I could get from quantum
computing? What are the tangible benefits which my
business or my organization could avail from quantum computing?
And continuing along these lines, I would like
to introduce quantum computing in a much more, I would
say, easier manner for you guys. And this
is, I feel, the best way to understand the tangible benefits of what quantum
computing is. Try imagining the problem of solving
a simple maze, a maze problem.
Now, if you try solving this particular maze problem using a classical computer,
it will intuitively just try solving each and
every part. It will try going from one part into the next and to
the next, and it goes on until it finds the
correct path. That is how the classical computer works.
On the other hand, if you look at the picture on the right hand side
of the screen, the quantum computers solves the maze problem
in a very different way. It is faster,
but in a different sense. It would be incorrect
if we say that quantum computers solve this maze
problem by checking all the parts faster
than a classic computer. No, it does not work that way. Even if
we say that quantum computers are just checking all the parts
in a more efficient way. Again, incorrect, because the
quantum computer is inherently built different. It is
not at all checking all the parts. It is, in a way, just changing
the rules of the game itself. Quantum computers,
using some, I would say, let's say, magical quantum properties,
can directly understand the maze and instantly
compute the correct solution. And again,
these so called magical properties might
seem a bit tacky to you right now,
and you might be wondering what these
are. How is this happening? But these are not important for you right now.
You could easily skip this for the time being, because these magical properties,
which might be very, very important for physicists and
maybe computer scientists, maybe researchers,
they might find this really interesting and very
important to know. But for you, at this executive level, this does not make
a difference. And now comes a very critical point in this presentation,
because I just mentioned to you that quantum computing can outperform classical
computers. So you are already thinking about
all the various possibilities of what quantum
users can do. Maybe quantum computers can
help make your daily tasks faster. So why
not just invite schrodingers cat to just do
your daily talks for you? Or maybe you
are thinking of finally colonializing
Mars, taking humans to Mars, setting up colonies over there using quantum
computers. Why not? It is faster than a
classical computer, so it will solve all our problems.
And maybe you are even thinking of making time
travel possible using quantum computers.
This is all nonsense stuff. But coming to the real stuff,
can robots actually rule over humans
using quantum computers again,
right? So this is all just hype.
All these possibilities are, I would
say, fantasizing about quantum computers. This is not what
is possible, even by a long stretch.
And job's side, I would sincerely ask or request everyone
to take a breather, take a few steps back. And yes,
quantum computing does hold a tremendous advantage.
Absolutely. But is it going to replace our loving old
classical computers? Quantum and classical computers
are bound to coexist, and they have very specific
domains where both of them will exist.
Quantum computers might have an impact in specific
industries, huge impact. But they are not like superpowers,
right? Sent from above, sent from the God itself
to help us just reimagine things on earth.
That is not. Quantum computers are, they are not magic.
They are still very much science. They are still very much bound by
the laws of the nature. So looking at the realistic and practical side
of things, I would say optimization and chemical
simulation problems are one of the clear winners in getting a quantum
advantage, especially in the near future. And this is closely
followed by quantum machine learning and cryptography use cases.
All these fields, because of their
interdisciplinary nature, very easily affect large industries
like finance, healthcare,
engineering, defense, and a lot of others. But at
the same time, we should remember that we are still in the very
early stage of this technology. We are facing
a lot of technical challenges in getting to a
quantum advantage. So although there are a lot of potential
use cases, we are still a long way behind
getting a realistic quantum advantage.
A study by McKinsey actually reports the various industry sectors
quantum computing could directly impact in the next five
to ten years. And just as I mentioned just before,
use cases in optimization and life sciences tend to be
the emerging frontrunner. But the important thing to note over
here is that, in fact, every major industry
is bound to get affected in some way or the other by
quantum computing. In the long run.
The potential of quantum computing are vast and
really varied. But let me now talk about
some of the specific industrial case studies to
try and give you a better understanding of the impact
quantum computing can have on the industries.
And one of the most promising applications, like I have time and
again, is organizations.
The traditional computers struggle to solve
complex optimization problems due to their linear processing
power, but quantum computers, on the other hand, can handle
these problems exponentially faster.
Companies could use quantum computing to potentially
optimize the delivery routes and reduce the traffic and
transportation cost. That is exactly
what Volkswagen has demonstrated recently. Using quantum computers,
they were able to create a very smart traffic management system,
which provided effective public transport station support
across the city. On a different note,
again using optimization, quantum South, a company based,
solved the optimization problem of distributing cargo
in an aircraft. Indeed a very interesting use case.
But the underlying fact is that optimization is a very broad term
and these kind of optimization problems can be very easily translated to
a lot of other industries. Optimization,
like speaking in layman terms,
optimizing anything and everything, eventually boils down to
maybe minimizing a cost function, which chain be performed better
using quantum computers. So I would say,
looking for a better workplace timetable for your
employees? Go quantum. Looking to improve your goods
delivery schedules? Again, go quantum.
And basically any kind of optimization or logistics problem,
go quantum. Or I would say at least try quantum.
Another example is of pharmaceutical industries where
using quantum computing to accelerate drug discoveries by
simulating molecular interactions at an unprecedented
level of accuracy, quantum computers
are able to simulate molecules and simulate molecular
interactions at a much more accurately than the
traditional ways which we have been doing so far.
This allows for a rapid identification of
maybe potentially new drugs to treat various diseases,
cure a lot of the medical problems which we
currently face. And this drug
discovery might seem to be a very industry specific use case,
which is no doubt being actively pursued by large companies
like Fujitsu. But the underlying chemical
simulations using quantum computing might
hold the key to unlock large opportunities in various
industries, because once we are able to simulate the
chemistry, even in its most natural form,
factory chemistry, food technology, material science,
even nanotechnology, all that gets changed.
And this change in various
industries at the same time could impact most of
the industries we know of today. Financial institutions
could also use quantum computing to optimize their portfolio
management systems and manage their risk analysis.
And one such example which I would like to highlight today is of Morgan
and case, which have been using quantum computing
to optimize their financial portfolios. They do this
by analyzing large amounts of data and running maybe some complex
algorithms and simulations on quantum computers to identify
the best investment opportunities, reduce risk in
their portfolios, and ultimately result in significant
cost reduction, savings and obviously improved
returns for their clients. Great, right?
Make money out of quantum and moving on to
the final, but a very important caveat. I will say
using quantum computing is its effect
on the existing security. Quantum computers
have the potential to be like extremely, extremely powerful
machines, but this unfortunately comes with
the risk of disrupting the existing communication and encryption
protocols. While honestly we are
still decades away from an actual quantum computing, being able to
hack into our existing security. But the best time to start working on
presents such a scenario in the future is now,
right? Id quantique led the movement towards
quantum communication protocols to replace the existing classical ones
last decade and since then, there has been a lot of improvements
on post quantum cryptography architectures, commonly known
as PQC architectures, to secure the data of today
from the threat of tomorrow. Companies like Sandbox
AQ recently demonstrated that PQC security systems
by pairing with software, yet another example
of quantum computing making a significant impact in the existing industries.
Yes, I mean with all these examples,
yes, quantum computers are the future.
But again, I would remind you to stay clear of
the hype. You need to get ready for
the quantum revolutionizing. But by staying well informed
and staying clear of all the nonsense floating
around quantum computing, it's very easy to jump on
the hype train. But that is a very dangerous part to pursue
because you have now understand what quantum can do. It is important
to actually get well educated about the same too. You need
to understand the underlying principles which majorly
govern the quantum technology. You need to understand what are the various risks involved.
You need to understand the scope of a quantum advantage which you might expect
in the future, which is all
necessary to eventually make you well equipped
to take decisions within your organizations regarding anything quantum
and this is where womanium can help in
the quantum sector. Womanium maybe host
an annual month long quantum workforce training
program, partnering with over 50 national research labs,
academic institutions and quantum companies. And this
program is specifically designed to make you
industry ready by providing you hands on training in
advanced quantum technologies. This is,
I would say an advanced quantum program. It is typically
long, it is very thorough, it is providing you in depth knowledge,
and typically it is suited for students or maybe professionals
who are looking to work at the technical side or maybe the research domain of
quantum computing. The registration of program is actually
open right now. The link should be somewhere down
below. It's basically womanium.org
quantum if you do not see the link down below.
And yeah, if anyone of the tech
side is viewing this session right now, please feel free to enroll
in this year's annual session. But you
coming back to you, the executives, the high level professionals,
you don't need to know all this technical stuff.
You don't need to nerd yourself out right now, as I
said before. Instead, for professionals,
for investors, maybe policymakers and industry
leaders like you, you need a different
type of education. And that is where we offer an executive education
course. Now, this course is delivered by industry experts
on your demand and is customized according
to your needs and requirements, right from the course content
to the course duration. Everything we
tailor make it for you, for your organization's need
for your specific requirements. So since this is
an on demand course, we conduct it on
a rolling basis throughout the year. If you are interested
in such a kind of course, please get in touch with us. I would love
to discuss it more. You should find my email
again somewhere below down here or maybe at the end of this presentation.
And yeah, please feel free to reach out and I would love to discuss
it with you. But the final thing which I wanted to discuss
the most is something which I'm really excited about, which personally
excites me the most, is the quantum solutions launchpad.
What is it? I'll talk about that in a moment, but before that
I'd like to talk about why did we have to introduce
such thing? Over time, we realized that quantum
computing is a very interdisciplinary
field and even with all the essential education at
the corporate level, companies are facing a very hard
time taking the first step
in quantum computing. And to solve this, we had to
introduce this quantum solutions launchpad where we help
and provide full stack quantum solutions
to get you
started on building your first quantum project for your organizations.
And again, all this is customized to your professional needs.
I hate to repeat that again, but if you're interested in any of these programs,
get in touch with me ASAP. Become I end I wanted
to take a moment and talk a bit more about what the quantum solutions launchpad
exactly is and why should you maybe collaborate
with us and join us. So as executives,
I feel it is very important to recognize that quantum computing
is not standalone solution, but it is
rather an ecosystem that requires collaborations and partnerships.
And that is a fact no one will deny, because the complexity
of quantum computing solutions and quantum itself is
such that it demands a multidisciplinary approach involving
experts in all sorts of fields, from physics to computer
science, mathematics, even life sciences,
optimization specialists, machine learning experts, all sorts
of things. So the first step would be to ideally build a diverse
team with all the necessary skill sets.
Tough, right? But with the quantum solutions launchpad, you get
access to a truly global remote quantum workforce.
We recruit the best talents from all over the world for
you so that you never have to worry about the logistics on maybe
onboarding different people with the right skills from all
across the globe. You don't need to worry about that because the team which we
select to work on your problem will be the best team tailor
made for your problem. Secondly,
because of a unique position in our quantum ecosystem,
we can provide you with an honest opinion. We can provide you with an unbiased
opinion of the various quantum service providers
that maybe you can find best
for long term collaborations. And this
would include all the industry technical vendors, all the
research institutions, all the other organizations that
help provide quantum services which
may be complementary to the project you're working on. You would
never have to worry about the technical details when you're
partnering with us of maybe which Quantum SDK
to pay for, which quantum hardware service to subscribe to.
You don't need to worry about that when you are working at the quantum solutions
launchpad, because we take care of that. We take care of all
the confusing hard decisions with input from
very good industrial expert team we have. We help you choose the
best quantum vendors suitable for the quantum project designed for
your industry. And all this
by being budget friendly. Since we are nonprofit,
if you remember, all the funds which we receive go back towards
student scholarships. And that is why we don't charge anything.
We don't want to keep anything in our pockets if everything we receive
goes back to training the future quantum workforce because
of this budget friendly approach that we have.
This essentially minimizes the risks involved for you as a company in
taking the first step and getting started with quantum.
That is what our partners love so much about us.
And finally the best part, you take away
the entire quantum project we develop for you
with all the IP rights and 100%
of the ownership, no strings attached.
Great, right? Yeah. So just to summarize it,
by partnering with the Quantum Solutions launchpad, you can accelerate
the development and the deployment of your quantum computing solutions,
while also mitigating the risk and reducing
the cost. Just to remind you and repeat myself
once again, my email should be somewhere down below.
Please feel free to reach out to me. Following which me and my teammates would
love to talk about any sort of collaboration opportunities
we see in the future. We would help you guide your business
into taking the first step in the quantum and yeah,
I guess that's it from my end. Thank you
for attending the session. I am.
I'm always open to talk anything about quantum.
Feel free to hit me up on LinkedIn or reach out to me by mail.
I'm always there for you. Great. Thank you
everyone. Have a great day ahead.