Hey everyone, how is it going? I hope you are all doing good. This is
Harika Chebrolu, working as a senior software engineer in Red Hat.
So in this talk we will be going to discuss about how AI
can be leveraged by energy industry to accelerate the smart green
transition. So the main agenda that we will be going to cover in
this session are the problem statement. That is what are we trying to solve and
why are we doing this then how are we going to solve this? Using training
and production ML pipeline and the sample solution architecture to
solve this problem. So now coming to the problem statement,
so we all know that by burning coal, gas and oil for our energy needs,
we are adding carbon to the atmosphere which is tapping
the solar heat control which
is contributing to the global warming.
And we also know that we are looking
for a ways to go green and protect the earth.
So I believe one of the most excellent ways to go about it is having
solar panels. Solar panels. So we
know that solar panels doesn't absorb heat from
the sun and it does not penetrate the heat into the buildings and keeping
the earth cool and also the building cool and
it will direct the sun rays away from the house. And we also
know that solar energy is very promising and
freely available resource which
will not be ended anytime soon.
So that's the reason we have the increasing attention on
solar energy as
a renewable source of energy. But the problem is
there is no proper knowledge and
viable information on installing the solar panels on the rooftops.
So that means the investors
or the policymakers and the electricity and
the railway department departments doesn't have the enough information to
come up with the viable solar energy investments
which are sustainable and cost effective.
Hence high potential solar investments are remaining
as an deployed. So along with it, the installation
and understanding the rooftop efficacy
is also a very cumbersome and time consuming
process and which will take at least one to two
day full day to calculate the solar protection of each rooftop
and which is increasing
the revenue of the solar economics.
This has resulted to the cost of sales
taking up to 30% to 40% of the total project
cost, significantly worsening the unit economics of
solar projects. So for this, if we come
up with the smart system that can help
to improve the integration of renewables in an effective way,
will solve all these problems and also it will
decrease the global warming.
For this we can detect the rooftops
and give the understandable rooftop classification to accelerate
the growth of the solar installation in a given area in order to
identify the potential of facilities solar installation depending
on the uncluttered surface area and direction, location,
surroundings, color, material,
et cetera. So we can consider these
data points as an input to calculate the solar
potential. And as an output we can give the optimal location
to place the solar installation to have the high
emission of, I mean to have
the high energy consumption but with
less carbon emission. So we
can provide this deep engine product, so deep engine vision product
to the battery owners or to the property owners so that
they can utilize this to
get the optimal location of the solar panels and also they
can decrease the investment on time and also on the money and
also with less carbon emission. So that's
what we are trying to solve in this way.
So for this we need a training and prediction phase
like every ML pipeline has. So in
this training phase we'll have the rooftops images data set
as an input which are completely unlabeled
and not preprocessed. So we will extract the
features of those images after having property,
preprocessing and annotating them and
removing noises and brightening the images,
doing all the image preprocessing techniques,
we can extract the features and after extracting
features we can calculate the available rooftop area
and we will send those data sets along with
this data to the training, to the
training phase. So here we can follow the batch
process. That means 70% of the data we'd be sending
to the training and remaining 30% of the data we can send it to the
testing. So after application of
proper training algorithm and after optimizing the
training data set incrementally,
we would get one trained model and we can validate
that trained model by the
use of remaining 30% of the data set. So this
will come under training phase and now coming to the prediction. So by
now we had a trained model already. Now we need to validate
or to check whether our trained model is
doing training property on the unseen data set. So we have
already unseen data set. I mean we have
kept this unseen data set aside. Now we use that unseen data
set for this prediction process.
So after running,
after running the algorithm or the model on top of
this unseen data set, we would get one energy variable as an output.
So through which we can estimate the optimal
location to install the solar panels.
So along with it. So we will
be getting this energy variable depending on
various factors which would get trained based on those factors
which I have already mentioned like surroundings,
material, available, rooftop area and the type of rooftop
and surroundings, et cetera.
So coming to the solution architecture, as I have already mentioned.
So we would be getting the rooftop data which was completely unlabeled
and dropped. Now we need to clean
that image data set for the algorithm to detect
the features properly. So for that, first we need to annotate the
data, like annotating the material, annotating the type
of rooftop and whatever is required
for the further process, we need to annotate them. Then after annotation
those annotated images data set would be going
to preprocessing and the noise remover stage where we do
all the whitening or the grayscaling and
removing the watermarks and all those things we'll be doing as
a part of the stage. So those cleaned images,
we will be using these cleaned images in the olact
segmentation model where we will segment the images
and also we will classify the images into these four types, that is flat,
heavy, industrial, low, uncluttered and existing solar. So we will classify
the rooftop as flat. If there is no equipments on
the rooftop, and if it is completely flat, completely plate,
we will classify the rooftop as heavy industrial as if it has
more equipments, more pipes, et cetera.
So if it has in that structure, then we
classify that rooftop as heavy industrial. So if
the rooftop has very few equipments, very few
pipes, then we will classify that that as low cluster. If the
rooftop has already a solar panel installed on it, then we classify that
as an existing solar. So after applying
the OLAT segmentation model, we would get the segmented
image as an output and we would be using this segmented
image for the further process. Something like calculating
the rooftop area, available rooftop area.
Sorry. And for predicting the material and
for the prediction of color. And we would be using all these factors
for the calculating of energy. So we can calculate
the available rooftop area using mask r
can algorithm or the grayscaling algorithm.
Depending on the images and depending on the accuracy, we can use
any of these algorithms and then we will calculate
the material and the color. So for the color we can use CIE 76
algorithm and for the material. So we would be already
allotating the data. For the material we
can use that label data and using k means clustering,
we can detect the material for the rooftop provided in the given
image. And based on these factors, we can calculate the energy
produced based on the few factors
provided, which would be provided by the electricity department
as an output, we would be getting an energy and we can
ingest all this entire model into
an engine or into some project. And we can deliver this product to the
energy departments or the railway and electricity
departments and they can use this model to get
the output based on which they
can decide the place where they can install the solar panels to get the efficacy
of the solar energy. Thereby we can reduce the global warming and
also the carbon emission. Yeah. So that's it from my end.
Thank you.