Hello, everyone. Thanks for joining. My name is
Jessica Wirt. I am a UX strategist or user experience
strategist at UX consulting firm Truematter.
We are headquartered out of Columbia, South Carolina, which is also where I'm
from. And basically our job at Truematter and
my job as a UX strategist is to make sites and
apps and Internet, whatever digital products easy for
real people to use them. So that sounds pretty simple in
theory, but it is a little more complicated
in practice. And I'll talk a little bit more about that in
a minute. But first, I'm really here to talk to you about
unicorns, as you might have guessed from the title of my presentation.
But I'm not here to talk to you about any old unicorn.
You'll have to probably go to a different sort of conference for that type
of thing. Im here to talk to you about UX unicorns.
There's a myth running around in our industry today.
A lot of companies hear about this fabled UX stuff,
and Im kind of poking fun at that idea.
But truthfully, a lot of companies hear about the amazing metrics
and results that UX is producing for their users and
for their competitors. And so they think, awesome, let's hire
a UX professional into our internal team structure,
and they're hoping to fix it for us. They're going
to do Ux for our company.
Now at Truematter, we jokingly call these new sites and
these individuals UX unicorns because
while they sound super fun and super magical,
they do not actually exist in practice.
UX unicorns do not exist because no
one person can handle all of the aspects and
experiences and disciplines involved in actually producing
excellent user experience all by themselves.
It inherently takes a team. So it's
great that companies understand that UX is valuable,
truly, and that they want to incorporate it into their teams,
but they get themselves in situations where they hire a UX
professional. They don't incorporate them in the correct
way because they don't really know how to. And so hiring
that UX professional doesn't actually end up producing the results
that they wanted to see and expected to see. So it
sort of youre the concept of UX for them.
That's because they're operating under a few myths.
Obviously, one of those myths is that UX unicorns do exist,
but at a more fundamental level, many companies just
don't understand what UX is. It's a
buzzword, even the acronym by itself.
I mean, who would know that UX stands for user experience on
its own. That's kind of confusing, right?
So because I know that some people watching things presentation
might find themselves in that camp, I want to talk about what
UX is, and I want to do that by talking about what UX is not.
First of all, UX is not a band aid. So it's
not something that if you have a poorly built,
poorly designed, or envisioned digital product,
you can simply slap on top and expect to see
the sort of amazing results that you're hearing about or might be
hearing about from other companies around you. So it's not a
band aid, not a quick fix. UX is also
not something that you can tag on at the end of a project.
It's not a last minute fix, just like it's not a quick fix.
UX is actually involved in every project where it
is truly thoroughly implemented and
thought of all the way from early discovery and definition
through implementation, existing and implementing any feedback
from launch. So there is no such thing as a
UX phase or quick UX tag on to
make surface level changes. It goes far beyond that.
And of course, UX is not something that a single person
can do all by themselves. Now if it's not something
that one person can do alone, obviously that implies UX
always takes a team. And really, if we think about
it, it's not just that UX takes a team, it's thats
producing any truly excellent digital product is going to
take a team. So I want to talk about what
a fully fledged products teams actually looks
like. I want to talk about the five disciplines involved in
a fully fledged project team.
And a lot of companies are familiar, a lot of individuals are
familiar with at least some of these disciplines. But if some
of them sound a little bit nebulous or far off to you,
don't worry about that, because I'm about to explain to you what exactly each
of these individuals or people in each of these
disciplines actually does.
Im also, just to clarify, these are not every
single person that's involved in producing a digital
product. These are the hands on, day to day people
that are doing that sort of grunt work,
if I can call it that, as one of the people that does that sort
of thing. So I'm not talking about business analysts,
scrub masters, project managers, marketing, sales. All of
those people are obviously incredibly important to the ultimate success
of a product. But I'm talking about those
hands on, day to day people because that is where UX expertise best
lives. So if you're familiar with some of these disciplines,
great, I'll go over them in a second. But another youre thing to
understand about UX and how to incorporate UX
expertise into a team is that, yes, you have these five
core disciplines of a product team. Within each of
these disciplines out there in the great wide world, there is a
smaller group of people that are considered UX professionals.
That just means that as they go about their daily tasks
within this primary discipline, they're doing everything from
a user experience standpoint. So I'll
give myself as an example. My job title is UX strategist.
That's what I do. It's obviously a strategy position. So I'm thinking about high
level product success and users at every turn. But I
come from a content strategy background, so I'm
also considered a content strategist. But because I'm a
UX professional, I'm sort of couched
under that discipline. And that's how most UX
professionals are. And that's truthfully where you'll find
the most value in hiring a UX professional is someone who comes
from a specific discipline but also really knows UX.
So let's talk through each of these one by one, starting with developers.
You probably know about these people extremely important.
They build for product users and use cases if they're
developers, that are also UX professionals. So UX
developers or UX people in each discipline think a little bit differently
than their counterparts that are not UX professionals. So UX
developers also guard against extra features and functions
that users don't actually need, and they really
build towards usable patterns for experience,
consistency. All of that helps that end user.
In the same way, visual designers that are UX professionals think
about layouts and styles for how humans actually operate
and take in information online. They are always considering
interactive behavior as it relates to design,
so they work closely with other members of the product team in
order to do so. And they're thinking task based
design at every turn because that communicates how to actually use
the interface, not just tone or style, but how it is used.
Content strategist you may or may not be familiar with. These are
the people that come from writing backgrounds. Some of them come
from, honestly, all sorts of backgrounds.
Psychology, marketing could be a lot
of different things, but these are the people that are thinking about
presentation of information and actions for how humans
actually digest words online. They're thinking about the right words
to guide users to the right task. So they work super
closely with visual designers in that regard, and they're
thinking towards reusable content patterns that support design
and development. User researchers
this is more of a traditional UX role. As you might think about it,
they're different than market researchers or other type of resources because
they are truly honed in on the user at every turn.
They are observing real people using products in real life.
They're designing and conducting activities leading to valuable
interactive input. So in layman's terms,
they're actually talking to individual end users and conducting
activities with them to gain that valuable information.
They're using task based tests with users to see what
is and is not working. These are the people
that really uncover all sorts of fun,
unexpected things when it comes to UX,
because across the board, people do not use digital
products like you might expect them to. Of course, there are best practices
within the UX community and within the digital product community.
Yes, but people surprise us all the time. That's why
user researchers are so pivotal to a product team.
And last but not least, you have information architects.
These people areas also more of a traditional UX
role. They are thinking about organizational structures that
make sense to real people. They are functional,
or rather, they are thinking of functional but human understandable
interfaces. And they're really bridging the gap between technical
requirements and user interactions. So because
they do that, they really do bridge the gap between how to structure
and build a product for
those end users in a way that's going to be intuitive to them and
make sense at every turn.
So that gets us to our final fully fledged
product team in each of those disciplines.
Obviously, it's important to have people that
are specialists in each of those disciplines. Yes,
but in a truly ideal state, each of those
disciplines would also represent someone
who is a true expert in UX,
or at least has a functional, working understanding
of how to incorporate UX best practices into their team.
Now, what you'll notice is that obviously an entire group
of professionals, whether or not they are UX professionals,
far outweighs what any one single,
even magical being can do all by themselves.
So why do so many companies still think that
UX unicorns exist?
My take, it's either because they don't understand
what UX is, which we've talked about already,
or they simply don't understand what successful
user experience looks like in practice. So I want to give you an
example of what that looks like. I'm going to show you the before and
after of a website for healthcare
organization that we've actually worked with in the past. At true matter,
the before will probably seem familiar to some of you.
I'll go ahead and show you that.
Yeah, it's a big sites here, lots of links,
an attempt at organization, but obviously this
digital product could not support it. It was not in
any sort of organized cms so
it needed a lot of work. This clearly needed a massive UX overhaul,
so that's what we gave it. So I'm showing you the after version
on mobile because obviously that's what we're focused on here.
But you can see all the way from high
level organization in this navigational structure
down to the simplicity of the design on the screens,
the content strategy,
just high level statements, high level micro copy or
extremely valuable microcopy.
Functionally everything is vastly improved from
that before. This is what user experience produces.
These are the kinds of results thats you can see in your
digital product with UX know how incorporated and
it produces metrics too. We've had companies
see 45% increase in site traffic,
65% reduction in maintenance over time,
which is just massive. Everybody understands how critical that is.
And this one's fun. 465% increase in
mobile use from a before and after for a
site super similar to the example that you just saw.
That is what a fully fledged product team
with user experience know how applied at every
turn in every phase produces.
But what about money? Of course, what about money and what
but stakeholder approval? If you don't
have the budget and approval to actually
incorporate UX know how into your team in every single individual,
that's okay. There are still things that you can do and that involves having
a single UX professional. Now if you're thinking,
isn't the entire purpose of this presentation to convince me that I shouldn't
hire a single UX professional, you're sort of right.
You don't needed to hire a UX unicorn. You needed
to hire a UX professional and use their know how and their
skill sites to bolster the strengths that your team
already is producing with the disciplines that it already has.
So it's not that you can't hire a single UX professional and be successful,
you definitely should if you have the budget and approval to do so.
It's that you have to go about incorporating that UX know how
in the right way. So let's walk through those steps.
It starts with identifying your gaps. Before you ever write
a job description or look outwardly,
to hire a UX professional, you need to understand
your current product team's strengths and weaknesses thoroughly.
So let's look at an example. Let's say this is your product team. You have
Romeo and Juliet. We won't ask any questions there.
Let's say Romeo is a front end developer and Juliet is a
back end developer. This is what a lot of product teams actually
look like, obviously, especially development teams.
So out of these five key disciplines, you only have one
area covered. That's not good, but you can work
with that. That means when you hire a UX professional,
when you actually do go to write that job description, you should target
hiring a UX professional that has a background in one of the
disciplines that you are missing from your team right now.
Now when you complete this steps and you're sort of thinking through,
okay, what do we have? Who do we have?
Make sure youll analyze untapped potential on your team.
If you have especially a lot of individuals on your
product team thats are in a single discipline,
look for any underlying skill sets or skill
sets thats you can bolster really people that
you can direct to sort of COVID one of the other disciplines
if you have that available to you. So let's say someone
on your team is a developer and this is kind of an odd scenario,
but maybe they areas also a visual designer or they have worked as a visual
designer in the past, they have a skill set there or
there's something you can do to be able to give them a little bit of
education, train them a little bit so that they can cover
that discipline. Do it. Because when you go to hire
a UX professional, that means you just have one more discipline already
covered. You don't have to worry about it. You don't have to
look for someone to cover it. So once you analyze
your gaps,
you needed to prioritize those gaps based on upcoming products needs.
So obviously, if you only have developers on your
team and you have all gaps in all of those other disciplines,
youre going to need to do some prioritization based on
what you have coming up. You basically need to ask the question,
okay, based on the projects that I have coming up,
who do I really need? What discipline am I
hoping to have to have to do this? Well,
for example, let's say you know your team is about to build a ton
of forms. If you're full of developers,
if you have all that developer knowledge, that's going to be a walk in the
park to actually create those and build them out.
But look at all of the copy that you have here. You need people
that understand structure and how to write a form so that you get
effective responses. So maybe the UX professional
that you go to hire is a content strategist or an
information architect by trade.
Maybe for another example maybe
you are doing some sort of patient facing application
for a healthcare system like we talked about earlier.
So there's a lot of design involved here and
it's probably going to be pretty important to understand the types of patients thats
are coming in and going to be using this and filling that out.
So maybe the UX professional that you hire is either
a visual designer or a user researcher. So that's
sort of how you practically go about targeting. Okay,
which of the gaps should I really focus on? Which discipline
do I truly need to hire someone in? And if you can make
thats person a UX professional, it's a win win situation.
So the next step is supporting your new hire. And I
say that knowing that there's a steps that I'm skipping pretty much
entirely. You actually have to find the right person and hire
them. That's actually the easiest step of this entire process.
So I'm not going to cover it very much, but if you
have specific questions there, I'm happy to answer them. You can find me on
LinkedIn and just reach, but I can pass along some articles or some know
how to help with that. Supporting your new
hire is probably the most critical phase of this entire
process. This is where a lot of companies misstep
and start treating their new hire like a UX
unicorns. You treat your new hire like a UX unicorn,
they will start to act like one. Which means they
will run away into the magical forest of LinkedIn and you will never
hear from them again. They'll quit. You don't want that.
You obviously can't afford thats for your project budget,
timeline and sanity. All of the above.
So don't treat them like a UX unicorn. That starts with where
you place them in your organizational structure. If you
leave your new Ux hire out in an island by themselves
outside of youre existing team structure,
everyone is going to look at them like some weird
UX person, which is how most people already view UX professionals.
And that's fine, but that's not going to help you get anywhere,
practically speaking, when it's time to start incorporating UX
knowledge into your actual product decisions.
So instead of doing thats, always, always put
your UX professional inside of an existing team
structure. Like I said towards the beginning, that's where they
belong. They belong doing that day to day discipline specific
work. They're just hoping to do it with that UX
focus and with users in mind at every turn.
Now, beyond actually placing them in your structure,
immediately involve them in that day to day product
work that can involve even reviewing what
other people have done for UX best practices,
sharing some of that know how and that's really the last
step to making a new UX hire successful.
When you only have the budget or the go ahead for one person, you have
to use what they know and use their skills to share UX knowledge
with the rest of your team.
But you have to be realistic at this phase. Just like one person
cannot handle all of Ux by themselves, one UX
professional cannot turn your existing product team into
a group of fully fledged UX professionals.
Maybe if you have ten years, sure.
But one person is not going to be able to do everything
required for their job and train everybody in all of the UX
best practices. Provide them the experience. That stuff takes
time, so they're not going to be able to do that. But what
you can do and what you're aiming for is a UX happy team.
Your single UX hire can share enough of the best
practices knowledge for UX, the practical
decision making, they can weigh in, they can review other
people's work. Creating a UX
happy team, all thats means is you have
a product team where one person is a UX professional but
everybody else is doing their best to incorporate UX
best practices and think about users and that will
make a world of difference. That is what progress
looks like. It's not your ideal state, but it's good
enough to start getting you some of those amazing results only
if you do not treat them like a UX unicorns.
So in order to do that, you have to make sure you follow the right
steps when you're hiring a UX professional. Identify your gaps,
prioritize project needs so look at
your gaps and prioritize the person in the right discipline
that you actually need to hire. Then support them by
putting them in an existing team structure and
from there share the UX know how from that individual to
the rest of your team.
That just might be enough to get youll the budget and the
go ahead to hire another UX professional. At which point you
would of course just go back through the process again. Continue sharing
that UX knowledge. Continue relying on your entire team,
not just one individual to come in and save the day.
But even if you don't get the budget in the
hire for another UX professional, at the end
of the day, progress still looks like
a team of individuals all collaboratively working towards
one UX goal. And that starts with one UX hire
that is not treated like a UX unicorns and
that's about all I have for you today. So if you're interested in user
experience, you want to learn more both about team structure and from a
more basic perspective of what the heck is ux?
Because I get it. What the heck is ux?
We have additional reading@truematter.com
slash ideas. That's our blog. We just put but educational
materials so that people can learn about ux.
That's where you'll find the post thats sparked
this whole presentation. Ux unicorns do not exist.
If youre from a little bit more of a technical background or someone that
you work with might benefit from understanding how developers and
UX professionals work together, we have an article specifically for that.
And we have additional articles on mobile use.
So what's the coordination between UX and mobile?
All sorts of stuff. Design any discipline or
area that you're interested in. We have more there other
than that. Thank you.