Hello everyone. Today we're diving into the fascinating world of data
storytelling, leveraging the magic of
oracle analytics to make it happen.
So before we move on with our topic today,
a quick introduction about me Uncle Aze
and analytics principal consultant with Ritman Mead.
I've been in the industry for almost two decades now.
Almost been quite fortunate throughout my
technical journey to have gained exposure to various technologies
starting with mainframes and
when came a time to choose my path, I chose Oracle
and have been having an exciting ride ever since, starting with data engineering
and switching to Oracle analytics as my major focus
area since 2019,
when I'm not working or speaking in conferences, I would be busy
in my full time passion as a mother of my eleven
year old daughter, also finding time alongside to explore
my journey as an artist, which kind
of works wonders to keep me recharged. So I'd
be happy to connect with you all through any of my social handles
which you can access via the QR code here to discuss anything
analytics and also art if you are interested.
Alright then, a bit about my organization
Ritman Mead is a global oracle data and
analytics consultancy. We are oracle partners
and have been thought leaders in the industry for more than 16 years.
In addition to our reputation as core
experts in anything data covering data
integration, engineering, data management,
data visualization, reporting and also data science,
we are also quite popular with our technical content with over
2000 technical blogs published related
to all these fields. Happy to be here.
My topic storytelling. Now why
do we need storytelling? Imagine for a moment that
data is not just a collection of numbers and charts,
but a vivid narrative that captures your
imagination and holds our attention.
Now that is the essence of data storytelling. It is
an approach that transforms abstract data
into meaningful narrative. In today's world,
we are bombarded with information
from all directions, right? Each day we
create an immense amount of data. But how do we
make sense of this avalanche of information? How can we extract
value from it rather than feeling overwhelmed?
Storytelling is the most powerful way to put
ideas into the world today as we all know
it. For thousands of years, it has been an integral
part of our humanity. Data storytelling
is our solution to this issue.
It's a method of turning dry statistics into engaging
stories which resonate with people in the current
business world, with exponential growth in data,
volume, variety and velocity.
All these collected and combined data may hold tremendous amount of
potential value, but not an ounce of
value can be created unless the insights are uncovered
and also translated into actions or business outcomes.
So you can all imagine how in the current
world and with all these technical advancements happening around,
there's been a huge shift towards more self service
capabilities in analytics and also bi. The pool of
people who are generating insights has expanded
beyond just analysts and data scientists now, which is a
good thing. But the new breed of data tools
which are available is actually making it easier for people across
business functions to access and explore the data of
their own. So that is definitely a good thing. But what is
happening in the other end is that this is also
leading to an unprecedented number of insights in
which are going unutilized. Unless we
can improve the communication, the way we communicate these
insights to our stakeholders,
we'll also see a poorer insight to
value conversion rate, which is a
key issue. By framing data
within a narrative structure, we not only
make it more interesting, but also more impactful.
A well crafted story just communicate
the information properly or impactfully,
but it can also evoke emotions, spark curiosity.
It can hold audiences attention far better than
raw data ever could. So that is why I have brought this
data story from history here to discuss, because 1855,
the Crimea war time, Britain was fighting a
battle with both Russia and deseasis.
As a nurse, how do you think Florence
Nightingale can convince an army to invest in
hospitals and healthcare instead of guns and ammunition?
What she did was telling her story with data
in her most famous visualization, as you can see it on screen,
the rose chart of deaths. It demonstrated
through the color scheme and patterns that
a reduction in hospital deaths would lead to thousands of lives
saved. This collection and process of visualizing
the underlying data was also a revelation to Nightingale,
and when she communicated this to the army, the visualization
helped convince the british army to make sanitation a priority,
which saved lives in the process. Soldiers death had fallen
sharply after the government sent out a sanitation committee in
March 1855, which cleaned up the hospitals drinking
water and ventilation. So what does this tell you?
Data helps find opportunities and resolve misunderstandings.
A well crafted story can evoke emotions,
spark curiosity, and hold audiences
attention far better than raw data ever could.
Being a navigator who charts a course through the vast
sea of information, identifying hidden patterns
and connections, or insights that might otherwise
go unnoticed when effectively done.
This enables informed decision making.
And by integrating storytelling with data,
what we are actually doing is bridging
the gap between data experts and everyone else.
Data stories influence people's thoughts and actions at critical
points in history. There's been so many other examples too,
if you look back, which has made an impact on the world
around us, and that is the true power
of data storytelling. If you don't communicate
your data clearly, your audience might be like those blind
men here in the story, in this old story parable,
if I can call it so, each person is touching a different part of
an elephant and coming up with their own ideas about what it
is. The sky feels the trunk, it's touching
the trunk. It's a snake tail.
Seems like rope for this linemen. And the body
is felt like a wall, right? So they basically, they are
all guessing based on their limited view and experiences.
Without the right context, it is easy
to misunderstand the full picture. Context matters.
So here is something interesting from a study at USC.
Researchers found that people with brain damage in a part of the brain
that handles emotions had a really hard time making
basic decisions when given choices.
These folks struggle because they couldn't use their emotions
to help them decide. Now, this shows that emotions
are super important in making decisions quickly and effectively.
So when we share data, it's not just about throwing out
numbers. We need to connect with our audience emotionally
to help them understand and make good decisions. And that's where good
storytelling with data comes into picture.
By making our data relatable and
providing the right context, we help our audience really
get it and act on it. It's also power.
Gives you the power to influence. Let's see an example
just to prove my point. Now, imagine you're trying to convince
your team to invest in a new project. You could just show
them a boring spreadsheet or some data,
or numbers, like how you can see in here we have the schedule
type, productivity score, and satisfaction rate for
two kinds of two schedule types, which are compared
against the traditional and flexible schedule.
Now, this is one option or one way of sharing
your information with your audience. But instead,
you could also craft a narrative. Now, you start with
a relatable problem, add some compelling data points
that highlight the issue, then show how your project
is the perfect solution. Now that is a
good way of building your narrative,
an effective narrative. So by the end, your team isn't just
nodding along, they're excited and also ready to take action.
Now, that's where the power of influence through data storing
telling comes into picture. It's all about connecting the dots in a way
that resonates with people. You're not just presenting
the information, you're guiding your audience to a conclusion, making the
data meaningful and memorable. When you tell a story
with your data, you're not just informing, you're inspiring. And that's
how real change happens. So here in this visual,
as I said, it's just a plain table showing
raw numbers for productivity scores and satisfaction rates.
And probably a narrative that can go along with
this data which is shared, is that the study shows
the flexible schedules have higher productivity scores and employee
satisfaction rates compared to traditional schedules.
Now, this approach is lacking what engaging
visuals, and also there's no storytelling element in it which,
which makes the data come to life.
So this simply presents a raw data without context,
without emotional appeal or even a narrative
structure, making it harder for the audience to grasp the
significance and connect with the information.
Now how does this look? Now this is a more visual
narrative which also has
given or highlighted the key points or key
message behind the visual that we have in here.
Stressing on the key points, also using the color coding
to bring, to give the audience extra understanding.
With just one look here, we are able to understand what
the numbers, which are important, and also the
positive and negative aspects of the comparison with red and
green color coding, which is, which are bolded,
right? So it's just the way you present the
data, which kind of makes it very easy
for your audience to grasp it all at just one
glance rather than, you know,
giving them the plain numbers and letting them guess the
understanding behind based on their own perception that actually
underlies a lot of risk. They may not really get the
point that you're even wanting to communicate.
So your weapon, that's where Oracle analytics comes into
picture. So Oracle analytics is your comprehensive solution,
offering a robust suit of features that cover
every step of the analytics journey, from connecting to data
modeling, preparation of your data exploration,
visualization, even storytelling and collaboration
with other counterparts. It's all here in
one integrated platform. But what sets Oracle
analytics apart? Let's take a look. Firstly, it caters
to everyone in your organization, from it and data
engineers to citizen data scientists,
executors, business users. No matter your
role, Oracle analytics has something for you now. The embedded
machine learning brings advanced analytics capabilities to
every user, whether you are a novice or an expert.
And with both centralized and governed reporting and
self service options, you can trust that your data is consistent
and reliable, no matter who is accessing it.
So basically, Oracle analytics abstracts the complexities
of your data sources, the query languages, making it
easy for even business users to dive into
analysis without getting bogged down in technical details.
And let's not forget about data security.
With built in trackable data preparation and enrichment,
there's no need for risky data exports or reliance
on Excel spreadsheets. Now, when it comes to
deployment options, Oracle has you covered for
those migrating to the cloud. Oracle Analytics Cloud OAC is
a solution and built on OCI Oracle
cloud infrastructure OIC offers the benefits of
cloud native analytics without the need for on premises infrastructure.
But if you prefer to keep your data on prem, then Oracle analytics
server is the answer. When studying about the
importance of context, it is crucial to develop
your understanding of exploratory and explanatory analysis.
When we do exploratory analysis, we may need to test
hundred different hypotheses or look at the data in hundred different
ways to find the core message that you want to
communicate. There's a specific story you
may want to tell. So on a high level exploratory
analysis which kind of marks the first starting point of your
of creating a good data story, it involves
understanding your data well, highlighting interest,
testing different hypotheses which could be underlined
will be to connect to the right data sources of your choice from
cloud or on Prem Oracle analytics
applications. When you use them OAC or OAS,
it allows seamless connectivity to all major data sources,
be it in cloud or on premises
or PAAS application. You can also connect to data sources with
rest endpoints and analyze the data.
For example, connect to SAS or PAAS applications or government
data such as weather, spatial or census data without
compromising on data governance. The connecting to data
via rest endpoints enables you to analyze data
from many transactional SAS or PaaS
applications without having to understand the internal
format or structure of the data. So that's the advantage of
it. You can see on screen the Oracle analytics
cloud interface, the application home page
in here. So I'm going to quickly show
you how easily you'll be able to start with
your data exploration with the help of Oracle analytics cloud
for creating your data story. So to
create a new data source or connection, it is as easy as
accessing these options and
create connection gives you create
a connection on top of any any data source that you can think of.
As you can see in here, even the rest API connection
is possible and what you just need is
the connection credentials when you map it, the wallet.
So whatever connection credentials, if it is handy
then feed it and it's just a
quick way to connect to all your data sources.
So once you create a connection, you will be able to create
a data set on top of it. Therein. We have to choose the
connection which is established and then
select the table or the schema, the tables or
even say if you have a spreadsheet, data that you want to analyze on
top of. Just need to drag and drop the file in here so that
you'll be able to access it into the interface.
So for our analysis,
which I want to quickly demonstrate, I am going to access an existing
data set which is having the sales
data. I thought this would be interesting
to access. Sales super stole.
Let me go back to the home page and take it from
there. Sales this way I'm searching could be different.
Yeah, we do have the sales superstore. So I
click on the sales superstore data set and you can see that it
has taken me to the
workbook. So a new workbook is created on top of it and you
can see on the right hand side it is already giving you,
even if you, even if say I didn't have any understanding about the
data set as a user and I'm trying to find a
grip on what exactly is the information stored
in there. You can see the auto insights which are
loaded in the right hand side which is generated based out of the machine
learning algorithms running in the background.
So we are getting a good start of understanding
of the data which is residing and
there could be a lot of visual analysis which is readily available
for you, which you could directly use for
your data story. So if I just click on plus
you can see automatically the canvas is loaded with the visualization.
Let me try to bring this heat map as well.
And likewise I'm just randomly adding
some of the analysis which I thought we could include
in the story. So I'm just pulling few
ones in here and you can see that automatically.
It is all adjusting the position, the layout,
and so the interface is by
default capable enough to do that. And if you
want to do any data preparation for your data, now what? How do
we access the data editor? So you click
on data, you click on the edit button there
and you can soon see that the data is loaded in
here. So once we import our data sets or create
connections and access our data sources, we'll be cleaning the data
by removing say duplicates or handling any missing values to
ensure accuracy, even we can do any
transformations on the data as relevant. So Oracle analytics also gives
you the power of machine learning algorithms, recommending possible
data enrichments that can be applied in just one
click. So you can see the recommendations are listed in the right hand side.
And so currently the
data set which is loaded, you can see the preview pane in here,
gives you an all full on high level understanding of the data,
how exactly it is varied, and if
at all there was any missing value or null values, we would actually be
intimated or notified by red color code.
And if you want to do any sort of data transformation
for any of the columns, like for example the sales. Let's see.
So all these transformation options are readily available
for you, which will be if when applied, it will be added
as a step in the left hand side. You can keep a track of the
steps that you're adding as your transformation steps.
Just to give a quick demo, if I
say rename the sales column in here.
So if I say it is sales sales
test. So I'm just testing the renaming option
to show you how the steps are added in the left hand side you can
see if you don't want that step to be applied,
you can even decide to remove it at later point
in time and it will be reverted back. So likewise any sort
of transformation you will be able to work
on in this transform editor and the recommendations
is another interesting or very, very useful feature
which is powered by machine learning. Now say if I click
on any of these fields which I'm interested in
now, this is a location field. Now see the enrichment, the data enrichment
refers to. If you know, it gives you the capability to add
information based on existing data which is not already there.
If it is meaningful for your analysis,
it is just one click away in here. Like for example,
now what we have in here is the city information,
the country, state, province, I think we already have
it in here. But say, if we were also interested in
understanding the population of that city to see,
you know, how much is our range in terms of sales already
and how much more scope. If you want to evaluate that or get that sort
of an insight, then I just clicked on
the recommendation wherein it asks to populate or
enrich the data with the population and you can see that it wants
in just one click, a new column has been created,
named accordingly, and all the population
information is also loaded. So this is how
for each of the kind of data that you have in here,
suitable recommendations,
if it is valid, it will definitely be available
for you. And as a user say, with less technical know
how, this is really going to be handy to,
you know, add more relevant
features to your data, data set that you're analyzing
upon. So once you're happy with your data and all
the transformations and cleansing is done, you can create a
workbook out of it. So I'm going to save
all the steps which has been added, primarily the column
addition. And now you can see that that new column
is also loaded in here in.
So if you go back to the initial workbook that we had created and
go to the visualize bar, we already had the auto
insights in the initial when it was initially loaded.
That is our starting point of analysis, for example.
This is likewise if at all you want to make any change in here,
it is as easy as removing or
dragging and dropping the see the
corresponding fields and you will be able to see
how the data is immediately. The changes are reflected in
here. Now just, you know, randomly showing you,
if you're not sure like where, which exact position to drop it,
you can even just drop it into the visualization area
and it is smart enough to group it accordingly
for the given visualization style and for
your data stories. Suppose say you only know some key
fields which you are interested in. Like for example in
here we have, we are interested in understanding more about
profit and sales
and discount and quantities are some of the key information I have
picked up here. And you're not very sure what kind of visualization
will really serve me good here to get a good understanding of
the data or the patterns or insights. So what I'm doing is I'm
just selecting it and bringing it to the
canvas area. So you can see this green bar kind
of guides me, the positioning of the new visualization
which will be created out of it. So I'm just in selecting
a smaller portion in here in the middle of both.
So you can see that automatically a pivot is
created out of this information. And if
you want to change the visualization into any
other kind which you think could help you better,
you will also be able to just select it
accordingly and all those information will be available or
the changes will be reflecting right away.
Also, for your visualization or analysis,
the exploratory analysis that you're doing, if you want to add any
filters, you will be able to drop in the
filter fields, the filter bar in here,
or if even, you know, visualization in itself
can be acting as a filter, you have use this
filter option to create or use visualization
to be a filter for all the other visualization that you already created
so that you, you're doing your analysis on the basis of all the
factors. Like for example, if I'm creating,
if I used or apply the user's filter for this visualization,
which I did, I can see the tick mark in here. So if I click
on any of these data points, or you
can see how the visualization
is loaded, which changes accordingly based
on the selection made in one visualization. So many such options
are available for you. Oracle analytics includes more than
45 different built in visualization types. And for any cases
that require unique or specialized visualization,
you will also be able to map
new visualizer custom visualizations from the extensions
visualization extension that is available for you. So these are all like
custom visualization which are in addition
to the inbuilt visualization types which you
have. So creating visualization helps you represent and
analyze your data patterns, find insights,
show trends, display distribution across timelines
or geographic region. So this is the advantage of it.
So automatically the interactive elements we had
a quick look at. We also saw the built in visualizations
extensions I was just showing you here. The custom visualizations are nothing
but the extensions, extensions which we have embedded
and also one click machine learning power.
Now if you want to show say a trend analysis, now this is a time
series data. We have the timelines compared against.
If you want to add some statistics, you know
which, which is created with the help of the
machine learning algorithms, it is just again one click
away. Say if you want to add a trend line for
this visualization for each of the
index value, what, how exactly the trend line or the
trend has been is established with the corresponding
color code. Also now say
if I am taking the trend line out and say if
I want to add some other statistics like outliers.
The outliers did not work because it needs additional
information. So let's go back in the interest of
time. I'm just quickly showing you some
option which we can definitely apply on top of the line chart here.
Let's take a look at a data story which is built out of Oracle analytics
taking the same data set that we have seen so far, the sales superstore.
So in here you can see that what I'm trying to do
is check out complete analysis
of different dimensions of the sales data for the superstore.
And starting with the sales overview, I have given
a map view which is always quite attractive with respect
to visually full attention of the audience and
give it one glance understanding
of which specific stage
the sales has been higher and where it has
lower or minimal, and which region there has been
good business. So all these understanding, you are able to
see that with a quick glance in this map view.
Also to support if you want to filter out any
particular info sales information
I have given the filters for city category, order date,
product name and ship date.
Additionally have included the tiles
in here with the major sales profit quantity
and discount figures for bringing
the attention. So I also added
some conditional formatting in here. If you look at
manage rooms, if you want to say
you want to conditionally display
some icons to show whether the sales has been positive
or negative, let's say if you are going
to have a sales of 500,000,
then if your organization it
can be considered as a positive state,
then we could just conditionally format it
further. So I have added the conditional formatting
and you can see that the icon is also giving the user
an additional assurance that it is all as
expected and in green. So likewise,
conditional formatting can also be effectively utilized to
pass on a data message. Going further sales
performance across time so I try to ask
the question about how the sales performance has
been across time period and visually analyzing the answer
to the question.
As you can see here, we have taken the timeline
between February 2017 to December 2020
and try to understand how sales has been varied
across this timeline. Also added a reference
line to show you and average sales
performance. Additionally have included
the trend line in here, the gray colors
you can see it will give an understanding to the audience whether
the trend has been positive or negative. So these are all
ways to visually understand how exactly
the sales performance has been. I want
to further ask a question about per product sales
performance. So that is why this visual analysis is
brought in here. And as you can see,
then we add the product name and the sales
to the bar chart, the horizontal stack bar chart
which I used here, which is quite ideal when you have
a long label for
the x axis. So because all the product names has been in here, this,
this really gives a very clear visual view of the
entire data. And also the sorting is applied
based on the sales figures from high to low. So that is also giving
one quick glance understanding of
how this shear speakers have been performing
for each of the product. So the filters in
here is handy for doing manual analysis
because for each of the product type, we have
all product category and subcategory separately we have
separate performance data. So what I've
done is manually analyzed based on my categories
of category selections. And I
have demarcated all the sales
highlights for each category so that I'll be able
to report it to the management easily.
So these are nothing but annotations which we have seen, how we created
and further. So this basically
I have, what I have given here is all the positive data in which exact
category and subcategory products have got the best
sales. So that's, that's what we have in the notes there.
Now I am also trying to study the
profit for each product category.
So at this point in this visual analysis, I could
say that there were some losses incurred specifically under
the category of office supplies and
also furnitures. So that's color coded
as you can see in the label here, and the maximum loss
has been incurred under the category of furniture and
subcategory of tables of around eighteen
k dollars. So I
am now trying to go in depth to understand
the figures around, you know, these categories
and subcategories, as you can see here. So if
I go to furnitures, you can
see that the tables, the loss
incurred numbers have been set in here and I can match it
against the quantity and sales figures compared
to the other subcategories as well. So specifically
for the tables,
we are trying to understand why or what
exactly has happened in here. So I need to just
rename it to tables and furnitures.
So you can see how quickly we
can able to do all these.
So furniture stables is the loss allowances. What I'm
specifically doing here, and based on the comparison
between the quantity, sales and discount data for furnitures
subcategories, I want inference. I have finally
decided is that for tables,
as you can see, the quantity sold and as well as
the sales figures are not really
that less comparatively,
however. So yeah, the table is coming here. So when
I'm selecting the table in one visualization, you can see that
it has been highlighted in the other visualization. So this is a brushing
concept that is playing out here.
So what inference I have from
this data is that probably the higher discounts for
tables, which is leading to the loss scenario, even if
the sales figures and the quantity sold are
comparatively higher than many other subcategory of
products. So, discount figures compared to
its price pricing are marked as higher than approval limits and needs to be
controlled in future. So this is my final inference or
the main tagline for the data story,
which I have to take to my management now
if I'm going to present the understanding
or all these visual analysis, I'm pulling it out to the present
layer for final refinements before my store
story is presented or shared across.
So you can see that all the canvases are pulled out
into our presentation layer. It is being
loaded one after one. And right now I'm happy
with the order which has been given
for the initial four
canvases. So I want it to be intact along with
the notes which I have added now, just if at all. I didn't
want the notes to be in there. I always
could, you know, turn it on or off with the
property adjustments in here, the raw and allisons
for the longs I am trying, I don't want it
to be shared across with the manager. It was just for my
understanding, which I had done so I'm going to hide that in here
and going to settle with these canvases
as active. So just to test it out if
I'm going to play it. You can see how exactly
this data story is going to be
presented to the external stakeholders.
So all the selected five active canvases
are in, you can see in here in
the bottom bar. So the audio has been
intact and also it has taken
out the loss analysis
canvas, which I did not want. And interactivity
of your data storyboard
is also quite the same
as how we saw in the visualization layers. Data points and tooltips
are giving all the information about each of the data points
as you hover your cursor around it and
even we can see all the nodes. We wanted it
to be there for the management to know and visually the
color coding and the sorting orders. Everything is looking
intact with respect to giving a clear messaging to,
as to what is the exact scenario
in our sales analysis and where our
focus area should be to avoid the losses.
So that is the data story which I have shared
as an example here with the help of Oracle analytics.
So this gives you a good understanding of in what all
ways you will be able to use the application.
So not in scope for this discussion
in today's presentation. However, it would be
good to highlight that there's lots more that you can do
with the help of Oracle analytics in
terms of analysis or predictions
or sentiments, you know, sentiment analysis,
specifically about any product feedback, etcetera.
So there are ways in which we can create
the data pipelines, what exactly we call it in our client.
It's a creation of data flows, which is quite powerful
if you want to do even more complex data transformations.
And also, as I said, the sentiment analysis,
it's just a matter of creating or pulling out the right
steps and,
you know, just save the data flow and execute it and it will give you
the final output in the form of data set,
or even you can save it into the database if
that is what is preferred. The same capability
can also give you the power to create,
train models, evaluate models performance,
and finally apply it to live data for
doing predictions or classifications or,
you know, anything which, which requires further
more complex and sophisticated handling.
With machine learning algorithms and models also
playing part. So, so much can be done.
And in the interest of time, we just try to
give an overall understanding of some of the
capabilities, some of the major capabilities, which are quite
important in terms of data storytelling.
And that is where we
stop with the demo for today.
So that was just a quick demonstration to just give you a feel of
the application and the ease with which you will be able to
interact and use all the sophisticated options
that you have. So based on your requirement, you will be able to pick
and choose and get here your data
speaking to you and your audience so what makes a
great data story? Once you have done all your exploration on your data.
So the first thing that you have
to take into account is identifying
your audience. So once you have a clear understanding of who
specifically your audience is, then you can talk to them and perhaps do
additional research, find out what they most care about,
what their goals are, what they currently know, what decisions
need to be made, and what additional knowledge might help
them make the decisions that will help reach
their goals. So knowing your audience will always help you know what
data to look for and include in your analysis.
You might use quantitative data such as about revenue change over time
or number of people impacting. Or you might use qualitative
data such as processes, systems, additional related data.
So all these data sources can be very easily blended
into your analysis workbook when it comes to Oracle
analytics cloud or oracle analytics applications.
So what is relevant?
So audience, once is taken care of, the relevance is the
next feature which we need to be careful of.
So this means that content needs to fit with the audience's
current level of knowledge and it needs to help them reach a goal
of some kind. So maybe your audience is internal,
like a presentation to leadership about the need to invest in a specific
strategy or tactics. Or maybe they're external, like a campaign
to persuade customers to try out your solution. So either way,
think about what matters to them. And the best stories speak to
people, and the more specific the person or the audience is, the better
outlining the story arc.
Once I have my data, I explore some possibilities and
with my story arc in hand, I can think about what sort of design,
layouts or compositions might work best. I want to get a better
idea of what will work visually so that I often sketch out
by hand some layouts and compositions. So this gives you
also an understanding of the
narrative that you want to stick to, since traditional story
art with a beginning, middle and end.
So that is what we are all used to doing. So for data stories,
this usually means you need an introduction to the topic
before you dive into the data. You also need to conclude
with a specific call to action. Now this is another thing that makes a
data story distinctly different from a straightforward report.
Also, if your audience is not an expert, it's important to use
plain language when you call out your
final inferences. Right, and intentional
visuals. What does that mean? It means whether to use
photos, graphs or charts. The visuals you use should help your
audience easily to understand what the data means above.
All, the visuals you include should be appropriate for the
data well labeled,
and the labeling options or formatic
options are definitely easily possible with oracle analytics.
And you also saw how we can add further notes,
annotations and even descriptions which I not show you. But it's
all easily possible.
It should be legible, whatever. Your visuals
should be legible and also not misleading. So great data
stories pay attention to details like use of color and
imagery, including considerations related to accessibility
and diversity. So it is possible with oracle
analytics that you can transform data into compelling
stories that not only inform but inspire action,
leveraging the full potential of the capabilities with them.
If you want to learn more with written and maid
so you can access our technical blog which is
quite popular among the community,
wherein also we have options for you to
learn from us through our bootcamps, which comes in
quite frequently, and a new course.
So whatever we discussed today were all like high level concepts
about data storytelling. Just a quick glance or
peek that I gave you
about the interface as well. But if you want to learn in detail,
we have a new course coming up which is data visualization for
data storytelling,
wherein we will be in detail,
taking you through different processes,
different techniques that you can adopt to formulate
your data story in the right and effective,
impactful manner. With that, we have
come to an end of this quick session.
Hope you learned something out of it,
and thank you very much for listening.