Jamaica real
time feedback into the behavior of your distributed systems
and observing changes sections errors in real
time allows you to not only experiment with confidence,
but respond instantly to get things working again.
Conf 42
Javascript thank you so much for coming to my talk today.
My name is Griffin Zahal at Kale and I'm excited to talk to all of
you about building a browser based metaverse with Babylonjs.
I am a developer advocate at Dolbyio where I work a lot in
the audiovisual space, including live streaming video production, post processing
of audio, and we're going to be talking a little bit about some
of the stuff that I've been working on and learning about as I've been
kind of going through this journey where we're going to be kind of taking a
look at 3d environment and game development all
within javascript. So let's talk a little bit about
the agenda about what's going on first. So I'm going to start off talking a
little bit about what is Babylonjs in the first place. Then we're going to
go into a couple of different examples where we're going to get started, we're going
to see some code, we're going to get building, and this is all going
to start with a hello world, then talking about some 30 assets and concepts,
and we're going to continue on further in areas like animating characters,
adding videos directly inside of our textures, adding live streaming
directly within our web based game environments, adding spatial audio and
perception, and then starting to wrap things up with some examples, learning more
in areas like that. So without any further ado, let's get started
talking about Babylon JS so Babylonjs is
a JavaScript based library for 3d graphics rendering. Traditionally this is in
the game development space, but it isn't limited to game developments at all.
It's used for proof of concept, you have 3d models and
it all uses HTML five and WebGL to kind of power everything together.
This is very good for cross platform game development where if it
can run in a web browser with HTL five and
Webgl, it can run Babylonjs.
So any kind of environments with the Internet connection or even
just having local files, being able to do it with a localhost server is going
to be able to run it and it is Microsoft backed. So a lot of
engineers who actually worked on Microsoft environments started
working on this where we've seen a lot of uses in education,
blockchain, data visualization and others among
the game production areas in the first place.
So what we see in the image over on the right is the actual Babylonjs
environment. So this is the playground that Babylon is
able to let you access directly within the browser. You can update the code
live and see the models change directly on there and see all the different environments
you're able to save them. And we're going to be taking a look at that
in a little bit. So here are some examples of
some stuff that was built on Babylonjs. We can see a
couple of big ones. So the top left over here has Minecraft
that was recreated directly in Babylon Js. I know Microsoft acquired Mojang,
so doesn't surprise me that much that it was built directly
on there. But we can see a couple of other ones like Temple Run was
built in Babylon. We have some shooter games
over here, some pachinko stuff going on. Space invaders recreated in a 3d environment,
which is pretty cool as well as some non game related things. So this
center right bottom one over here is a
map interface where people started taking a globe and kind of tried to
Google Earthify Babylon Js to be used in the web browser
as a proof of concept. And another one that's also really cool in
my opinion, is this lower right one over here is an
art gallery that somebody implemented directly in Babylon Js which kind
of starts talking about the whole metaverse vibe where especially in this remote
world where I'm giving you this talk remotely in the first place, a lot of
people are trying to kind of come up with ways for people to kind of
display their exhibitions live via the
Internet. And Babylonjs is kind of a foolproof one that doesn't require
use of very strong tools and hardware
that you need to kind of be able to render all this in the first
place. So let's start off with hello
world. And for this I'm going to go over to the browser and this
is a website called Playground Babylon Js over here.
This is what happens exactly when you load it. This is the hello world that
they give you from loading their playground. You have the code
ide over on the left and you have the actual 3d environment to play with
on the right. And this whole code mesh
is what you're actually seeing being rendered over here. This is an NPM package.
So of course you need to make sure that you're importing everything properly. But on
the playground it does all that for you in the background. So all
of the juice that comes from starting Babylon js
comes from this function over here. Create scene.
And create scene is how we're determining what we actually want to be
rendered how we want everything to be controlled. Every single
thing, essentially that Babylon is going to work with needs to be within this
function. So that we can actually establish the scene. So the first
thing we're doing is we're creating a scene. It's a basic scene object.
No meshes. Just letting us actually have an environment
to work directly in. And you can see that we're defining it by taking a
variable scene. And we're assigning it to a new Babylonjs scene. And what's
really cool about this is that because Babylon is a package that we're
able to manage. It will let you autofill a lot of these as you
kind of see fit. So these are known kind of modules that being to be
able to automatically put in. So new Babylon scene engine is going to use
the Babylon engine to create a new scene for us. And this scene is going
to be where we're going to be able to put everything directly on. Next we
have the camera where we're going to be able to determine how we actually
want to view the scene. As kind of the viewer
looking inside of this environment. You need to determine how
you're actually seeing it. So what we're doing over here is we're using Babylon
free camera. And we're using something called a vector three over here. And a vector
three is essentially the XYZ coordinates that are going to allow you to
determine where in the three plane of existence
we want the camera to be established. And is going
to be the origin. The center of it, it goes into positive. It goes to
negative. It goes into decimal values. So that you can place things exactly where
you want it to be. So you can kind
of see over here with camera set target vector 30 is
going towards the origin. It's a nice little kind of speedway
to go to that area. And we can kind of change the location
of all these things as well. So if we go back over to the vector
three over here and we say, I don't want this at negative ten. I want
this at negative 15. I can then click this play button over at the top.
And you're being to see we're zoomed out a little bit more. I can revert
it back to ten and click play. And we're back to where we started.
This is going to allow us to kind of play with
just where we're starting, where things are going on. But you don't have to
kind of play and rerender every single time you want it to happen. Where we
can use camera attached control over here. This function to
let us move the camera dynamically. So instead of having the camera
be a fixed object. We can determine its position
a little bit differently as we move along. So this one is
allowing it to be attach control canvas. True is attaching the
control of the camera to the canvas itself. So what this means
is that we can click and drag our mouse on the canvas. And that
is what's going to control the canvas. Based on the mouse movements.
We are moving the canvas to move the camera. So you can also
change it to move via the keyboard. Or if you attach a game controller,
you can use the joysticks like you would in that area. It's very dynamic
on how you're going to be able to make it happen. Next we have the
lights. And lights are very important because without lights, you won't be able to see
anything. Kind of think about it as the sun
in earth. Where if there wasn't for the sun, you can't see anything.
So this one we're using a hemispheric light. There's a few different types
of light sources. That have kind of different ways
that they radiate themselves out. Hemispheric light
is one of the more common ones. Especially if you're trying to kind of emulate
the sun where we're creating it. And once again, we are positioning
it on so directly overhead.
And we can also determine, say, want to
indeterminate area. So we can make it 00:11 rerender
and you're going to see the light now is at a slightly different position on
the sphere that we have over there. It is completely dynamic
and customizable. Where you can also create functions to make that change
along the way as well. So light intensity is going to
determine how much luminosity that light has. It's going to get lighter
and darker. Default is one. So we can change it back to one
from 0.7. And it's going to make it a lot brighter.
If you have actual color in that. It's going to make different saturation values
and all that. This is just a gray, uncolored surface.
And then we also have the shapes where we are
determining a shape right here, a sphere. So that we can actually
determine what it looks like. You do want to put in the position of everything
as well. It will default to the origin. But we can also determine
what the sphere is actually being to look like. So sphere itself,
the object has some subparameters that we're going to be putting directly into
it. You'll notice that all these different things are
going to give you a name, it's going to give you a position
or some other sub options. And then it's going to tell you which scene you
want to but it into. We're all putting it into the scene variable that we
started directly with at the very beginning. But we can also take a look at
some of these optional parameters. And if you hover over them, it's going to give
you a little bit of a hint about what it actually is looking for.
So the diameter two is pretty self explanatory. It determines how big you want it
to be. We can make the sphere bigger by making the diameter equal to five.
It's going to be a lot bigger. And we can revert it back
to two, make it smaller. But what's also very interesting
is that this is graphics rendering in 3d.
So you're going to have to determine how you're building this in the first place.
The number of segments allow us to determine how many kind of polygons
you want it to be made out of. Kind of, if you think about that.
So 32, we have a pretty realistic sphere.
If we zoomed in a lot, you would definitely be able to see some hard
edges instead of completely smooth and round surface. But we can actually
make this look a lot more blocky if we reduce the amount of segments.
So if we move from 32 to 16, we're going to start
be seeing a little bit more of a fuzzy outline. But we can also go
even lower to something like two. And you're going to be noticing it's
extremely blocky right now. And this is going
to be easier on the rendering engine, whether you have a sulfur or hardware
renderer going in and over that, and also allows you to kind of customize
a little bit about how things look directly in that way. But let's say
you don't want to work with sphere in the first place. Babylonjs does
have pre built objects that you might want to build directly in.
So instead of create sphere, I can say let's create
a cube.
That is not the function name. We can do create box.
That's the name. And that is going to allow
us once I correct the
text over here. So once we remove all the sphere
specific stuff going on over there, and we move all
the sphere to a box, we can then click play and we
will then get a box instead. Additionally, we also
have the ground section over here, which is just determining this
kind of rectangular plane over here.
That's just another object that we have over there that we're determining as the ground,
you can determine the size and the scene the same way you would with everything
else. It does not need to be a square. It can be a rectangle,
it can be a circle. It can be whatever you want it to be.
Now that we've gone through some of the introductory hello world that Babylon playground presents
us, we can go and talk a little bit about some of the introductory concepts
that we just learned about. So the main method that we have is create scene
where this is where we generate objects like our cameras, our planes,
our lights and our meshes. Where we use functions like mesh builder,
free camera and hemispheric light to be able to determine these objects
that we're placing directly into our scene. If we want to determine the
position where it's actually all happening within our scene, we want to use
vector threes so that we can define the XYZ coordinates of these objects
that are all relative to the scene. And then we have autocompletions given directly
within the NPM package so that if you're using an IDE like vs code that
supports them, you're able to get a little bit of help on actually building it
without needing to know every single function, revisit the
docs, cross reference everything and start all the way over there.
So with 3d assets and concepts, we're able to expand on these hello
world concepts a little bit further, where we can do things like changing the
colors of the objects, or we can even directly load files
where if you have an artist, for example, where you're building a lot
of these assets and models in a program like Maya,
where you have a professional actually working on them, instead of trying to create
a bunch of boxes and spheres and putting them all together for what you want
it to look like in the first place, you can directly put it in
with that mesh itself. You don't have to kind of worry about
needing to develop it all to yourself. We've been able to use the mouse camera,
navigation, and you can even do things like switch scenes directly within
the environment that you have. This also includes areas like
VR and AR experiences, which we'll get into a little bit. But first,
let's go back into the playground where we have this model that
we were able to download directly from the Babylonjs community,
where you can see it's this very detailed skull that an artist made. So instead
of needing to kind of put together all these different meshes, we're able
to just directly upload something and kind of use it as
we want, look around, kind of see all the different angles of it
and play with it in our own workshop. We can even take
a look at another example we have over here where we're able to take our
click and drag controls and make it even more kind of advanced,
where we can click and drag any of these different shapes and
move them where we want them to be. We have added color directly to them
and we're able to kind of expand the scene and the light to fit our
needs a little bit. This also includes some tools that are very useful for
the actual process of building, where if we click on this debug
section, we have a couple of new menus that we're able to take a look
at. We are able to see the scene where we can see all the different
materials that we've worked with. So we have all the different objects in these
kind of different colored ones where we can see the actual position. We can
see all these different class objects where we can determine textures,
lighting and all of that directly within a debug menu.
But if we click this gear icon in the inspector area,
we can also do things within Babylon like take screenshots,
record videos, make gifs,
even export these directly. So if you wanted to save this
object and load it somewhere else, you're able to do that directly
within Babylon itself. If we go over to the original playground
that we worked with as well, we've made some customizations. And one cool thing that
you can do over there is the save icon over here is
going to let you kind of create like a little demo thing where once
we save it, you're going to notice that we have a new
little hex code over here on the top menu, which is going
to allow us to save and reload this anywhere that we want. So we can
save this customization that we made directly to this workspace. So if I refresh
this page right now, you're going to be able to actually see this once
again exactly the way that we left it. And you can share this with anybody
you want. So if you've made some customizations, or if you've made your own custom
Babylonjs playground scene, you can share it with anybody that you
want in that scene. Or you can download it just the way that we shared
over here and be able to upload it as its own Babylon environment
in the first place. Going back over to talking about VR and
AR experiences, that's not something that Babylonjs prevents you from doing
any. It actually has a lot of built in support for VR headsets where you
can actually try out a lot of these different playground examples on your Google cardboard
device. If you have one of those still, and even has support for
WebXR frameworks, which is update and
replacement to WebVR, which actually means that you can develop games
and experiences in the metaverse for Oculus Valve Index,
HTC Vive headsets, and you can even check
out the documentation on how you might want to build that yourself. Taking a look
at what that actually looks like. We have the community demos
over here where we can take a look at some of the different meshes.
So this one for example, you can see the playground has its own hex
code that it's playing with over here. And what they are doing
is they have the textures that they are actually
importing directly from different web URLs. So you can see that this
asset is stored as a GitHub texture that they have in their
git, which is just being referenced via the Internet.
The beauty of HTML five, it works very similarly where if
you have a model you want to import with all the textures involved
directly in it, you can take a look at it. And here we
have a much more detailed environment where these textures
are very detailed. You can see we have a nice background going on that's
in a 3d space. We have a very detailed
bottle with a drop shadow, but you can see kind of the light source
is over here. This table is basically the
same thing we had with the plane over there. We're just taking a little
bit more detail and care into the objects that we're directly putting in.
And on the VR side, we have another example from the playground over
here where somebody took this car.
I think it's the DeLorean if I recall correctly. And they allow
you to do a VR experience as a sample. So you see this little VR
goggles button over here. If I was viewing this via a Google cardboard,
which I'm not, but you can kind of see where it's coming from,
you would be able to view this entire environment in that 3d kind
of space via that headset itself over there.
Of course, I'm not streaming from a VR headset, so you might
be a little bit disoriented the same way that I was. But it's very cool
to know that a lot of that is directly built in. And if we look
at kind of what's happening, they're using create default VR experience.
Looks like this is an older example that's a little bit deprecated,
where we highly recommend that you take a look at the actual documentation
of Babylon for the updated ways of doing it. Though this one does still work
as we saw before. It's just very easy for you
to take your 3d environment and directly put it inside of that metaverse.
So continuing on with our presentation, let's talk a little bit
more about the animation section of everything,
where we have a lot of static scenes that we've already seen.
Everything has been rendered, and we've just been looking around the render.
You don't have to keep everything static. You have the ability to use render loops
to modify models so that they are updating live without needing
to keep on rerendering your scene over and over and over again manually.
So this can be done with the scene on before
render observable, where this will do kind
of just a loop within the render function itself. So it's always looking for
some type of input or some type of action to determine whether it
should start or stop doing that new render. So this can
be done for moving characters. This is useful
for actually physically moving them, or making them do different emotes,
or have idle animations. You can assign this to key presses
within your keyboard or controller of movements,
mice, or even getting creative like head trackers,
you can attach it to any type of input
that your device would be able to recognize. It's fair
game for all this. So this example over here has
what we have going on with this model.
So you can see we already have an idle animation going on over here.
But I can use my keyboard to make her move,
turn, and I can even press a button to make her dance.
So this is all directly within one instance. You notice
that we're not manually rerendering anything. I'm not clicking a
play button over and over again. So it allows you to do exactly
what you might expect to do from a game in that same action where
everything is live, it's moving, it's not going to just be a static workspace
that we have going on over here. This expands even further
with using videos as textures where yes,
videos can be pre recorded, but still allows you to take
an actual 3d environment and then overlay video directly on
it. This also enables things like audio directly on it. And it's
all based on HTML five. So it works very similar to a typical video container.
But instead of a video container just being a static,
flat video, we use it as a texture for an object. So we
can put it directly onto a plane, we can put it onto
a cube, a box, a sphere, somebody's head. If we want to actually
emulate what somebody's head is going to directly look like where we
can put in different sections that you would be able to in HTML as
well. With playing, pausing and assigning
those two buttons that you can directly interact with as well on
the space itself. You don't need to assign everything to a key binding. You can
put it as a user interface component within your browser as
well. So we can see an example of this once again in this
workspace that we've already created where we have these couple of video
objects where we can open up a menu and we can see these different buttons
that we made where I can click on play and it should be able to
play the video for us. I think my audio is turned off right
now to avoid any feedback. But you can see we're playing the video and we
can also pause the video on demand, replay it, mute it. If there
was audio playing right now. Oh, there it is. It may not
even exist at all. You can pause it once again and
you can notice that if we look around the environment, we have it
showing on both sides of what is actually going on
in here. And what we can do is we can take a look about how
this is actually built. So I'm going to go into a vs code instance
that we have going on over here where we can take a look at this
main js kind of document that we have. So we
can see that we're just assigning a lot of different variables. But then we have
the create scene function that we saw before where we're taking
a look at kind of the typical things where we have the camera,
we're attaching the control of the camera, we're saying where the camera is,
but when we actually want to place the video itself, we want to make sure
that the video is properly in scale. So most videos these
days come at a 16 x nine aspect ratio, but sometimes it's too
big and it's going to take way too much power to be able
to render that. So we can scale it down by just taking that 16 x
nine ratio and then creating a scale ratio that we
want to either multiply or divide by so that we can get
the proper size that we want the video to actually be as
a part of the box that we have. Then for the plane options, we want
to set the height and width that we have already determined over there,
as well as determine the side orientation. So by default it's not
being to appear on every single side of a mesh. So we can use
this double side helper function from Babylon itself to actually
put it on both sides of that box and see it the way that you
would want it to be. Then we finally call that video mesh that we have
over here with video plane. Mesh is mesh builder. We're creating a plane
and we are putting in the actual objects and scene directly
in them, where we're then taking the video feed as
a local file we have and letting the video actually
be placed on side with some more helper functions over here.
So we're creating a video material and texture as the function over here.
And then we're placing it directly on side of that video object
that we have, determining if we want it to loop, if we want it to
autoplay, and then also adding pause functions directly
on there so that it doesn't kind of just play immediately as
we go on there. We just have it playing when we want to play it
by clicking the button itself. A lot of this is additional helper functions so
that you can kind of see it all happen altogether on that first place.
We are talking about the metaverse forever, and I don't think it would be that
much of a metaverse if we only had pre recorded videos. So let's
also talk a little bit about adding live streaming as video textures.
So Dolby IO live streaming allows you to be able
to stream live content in extremely low latency, where we are no longer
limited to existing video files. We're able to
actually broadcast videos in real time.
So you would do the typical things about acquiring an API credential
at Dolby, where you can get one for free, where instead of assigning the
source object to the video file, we can assign it to the stream URL
that we have received from Dolby, which enables real time broadcasting directly
in metaverses, which we've seen a lot of very good use cases for in live
events, concerts, lectures, the live
sports scene, auctions, kind of, it goes on
for a while. So we can take a look once
again at the sample that we have over here. And if I switch
from video to stream, you're going to notice that the videos
disappear. And that's because our stream hasn't started yet. Over at our Dolby
creating dashboard I can click on start right here. It's taking my live camera feed.
Hello, let's mute the microphone.
We can now see that I'm being streamed live in Babylon over here.
So it is the same feed. You can take a look. It is
using those same objects. But now I'm able to put everything directly
inside of the stream. I'm not sure how well it's going to do the
capture difference between the camera you see over on the
top over there and the camera that you see here in
Babylon. But hopefully it should be broadcasting pretty quickly
to you and we can take a look at how this is all working once
again in our code. This is the same exact file over here, but if
we go a little but lower down where we're doing things like
determining the GUI buttons and doing some parsing and
all of that over there. But what we can do over here is we look
at the stream button over here, we're able to then access the video
texture in a different way, where we're setting the URL equal to the
streaming URL that we have determined in our Dolby API key,
and we are determining that we want to switch the video texture
over to that. The magic happens in our helper
function over here in streaming js, where we're actually taking
in our credentials. Don't bother copying these, I'm going to rotate
them as soon as I finish this video. But we can look a little bit
further down in terms of how this is actually being done,
where we're setting the video texture and then we're adding the stream based on
the texture itself going on over here, where it's functioning essentially the
exact same as that texture video that we have,
but just accepting a live feed via a URL. Once again, the beauties
of using an HTML five interface. It is the same kind of
code as long as it's accepted in your web browser. There is no reason why
Babylonjs isn't able to accept it itself. So we're taking the token to
authenticate, and then we're changing the view appropriately and broadcasting it and
changing the texture appropriately, as well as doing some error handling
directly within there. So we can see an example about how
one of our customers actually has gone a little bit further than this with
one of the customers we have called Red Pill VR, where I'm going to
mute the video so that this doesn't kind of get too loud and
feedbacky. But you can see that they've taken our live streaming and
turned it into a metaverse based DJ experience.
We were able to see that they have the DJ actually being recorded
live, but they've implemented him into this metaverse
where there's an audience that's able to listen directly
live. So that if he, for example, is trying to engage
the crowd by saying, hey, how are you all doing? It only takes a couple
of milliseconds for it to actually reach the people on the other side who are
experiencing this live concert in this live event built directly
within here, as opposed to the couple of seconds it might take in traditionally based
creating, which I find to be really cool. And there's no reason
why you wouldn't be able to build a very similar experience within Babylonjs and
even incorporating the 3d headset experiences on there, so that
you might be able to actually see what's going on in as real time as
possible. So continuing on with the metaverse based
theme, you also have the ability to add in spatial
audio via Dolby as well, where you might want to add in live communication
within your game or your metaverse environment, which you can do
with an audio based SDK where you can add in real time communications.
I'm not going to be going over any code or experiences directly within
this, but just know that there are a lot of web
based ways that you're able to do live communications between different people. And putting it
directly in a game would be no different. The same way that you might experience
that in a multiplayer video game that you'd be playing with your friends.
You can add in different spatial audio areas so that you're
actually able to take the position of where you see somebody directly in
the plane that we have in Babylon Js and hearing
them from that direction. In that direction only instead of hearing everybody from
every different direction all at once, you're able to actually
more realistically hear people as you might in real life.
Once again, we have a customer example of this. If you visit Odyssey stream,
if you want to see an example of it, but just know that this is
just kind of typical, taking the positions of objects within Babylonjs and
feeding them into different sdks so you can actually see and hear
that relative positioning that goes on over there to
wrap things up. This is really just the tip of the iceberg
when it comes to Babylon Js, where if you want to
kind of see a workshop that we have done, you can visit Bitlymetaverseworkshop
for self paced workshop. If you want to go more in depth on some of
these experiences and actually kind of go further with all
of that. It's an open source GitHub repository, which I really highly
recommend you all check out. But also definitely make sure that you check out the
community resources like Babylonjs community,
as well as Docs at Dolbyio if you want to start incorporating some live
streaming or video communication directly on there, I'm going to
make sure to show off the Batlon JS documentation right now so
that you all know where it is, how to find it, and also just
kind of how to get started yourself. It's all just very well organized
and very useful where you can even see the examples
of the playground that they let you go and directly play directly with. So it's
not a traditional documentation. And you can also see the workshop that I
reference right here as a GitHub repository which you can then clone
and then run as an interactive kind of
documentation git repository that you're able
to play directly with and create your own environment right there. So thank
you so much for kind of listening and attending my
talk. Hope you enjoyed it. If you have any questions,
please feel free to tweet me down at the bottom you'll see my Twitter handle.
It is at being of the Griffin and I'd love to see what you build
in Babylon. If you have any questions or
if you just want to show off something, I'd love to see your playground links.
Please tweet those at me or just kind of say
hi. I always want to meet more of you. Thanks for showing up and hope
you enjoyed the conversation.