You on the road to conquering the world.
You need to regress or get in touch with your inner child
to make progress. I know what you're thinking right
now. Do I want to conquer the world?
Of course you do. And now you might be
thinking, but my inner child is pretty messed up.
Totally fair. Mine two. But your inner
child is also incredibly wise.
They know how to fall down and get back up,
how to be brave, how to play,
and how to explore and be curious. I'm rain
Leander, developer advocate with cockroach labs.
And today I would like you to use a child's
mindset for growth, to embrace your inner child,
to become the beautiful unicorn I know you are,
and yes, to conquer the world.
Who here knows how to ride a bike? Raise your hand
if you're in the Netherlands. You've known how to ride a bike possibly
since birth. But most of us learn at some point in
our childhood. Unless you haven't.
Unfortunately, if you don't learn how to ride a bike when you're a child,
it is infinitely harder to learn. And not because
our brains have shifted, but because at some point,
some shitty person laughed when we fell down.
And we develop this aversion to failure.
We don't want to fall. We don't want to mess up.
We don't want to be embarrassed. And when we're trying
something new, we wants to instantly be the
best. I've got news for you.
When you're trying something new, you will not be the best.
You are not a secret ninja if you have never taken any ninja
training classes. You will not win the Tour de France if
you've never learned to ride a bike. But you could,
as long as you get back up.
Because it is absolutely guaranteed that you will fall down.
You will fail, you will mess up, you will
make mistakes, and that is beautiful and
totally fine. Fall down.
It's part of life. And then get back up,
child. I am asking you to embrace your inner child today.
Maybe this analogy doesn't fit as well as the rest,
because bravery is not something we're born
with. It's something we develop. And from what I've
seen with a seven year old and a pair of four year
olds, children are not the bravest creatures.
Because becoming brave is hard. Sometimes it
feels impossible. Being brave
is not a lack of fear. It's moving
forward despite that fear.
But if it's overwhelming, here are some baby steps. Two.
Becoming more brave.
Embrace that vulnerability.
Admit you have fear.
Do it anyway. And when you fall down,
get back up. Nothing is
impossible. Every big scary monster or
dragon or problem can be broken down into manageable,
bite sized pieces. And the key is to start.
Listen to that fear inside of you.
Acknowledge it. Admit it.
Take a few minutes to make a plan and then do the plan.
Just in case you're one of those skeptics who doesn't believe
in the importance of play, I'd like to introduce you to
the National Institution for Play, which gathers research
from diverse play scientists and practitioners to prove
that play is good for your physical and mental health. It increases
harmony and effectiveness of relationship, it optimizes
learning and it encourages innovation.
How many here now want to become a play scientist?
When we're children, play is built into our daily
structure. But as we get older, there's less recess, no more
breaks, and fewer naps,
which is bullshit. These moments of play,
of engaging in activity for enjoyment and recreation
rather than a serious or practical purpose,
are instrumental to enjoying life. Two becoming
a unicorn and to conquering the world.
Now, sadly, I can't tell you how
two play. This depends entirely on
you. What you enjoy doing for fun. Do that
when it's not fun anymore, it's time to find a new fun
thing to do. Now, sure,
I can give you some ideas like baking cookies and
sharing them with me. But most
importantly, book the time on your calendar and
these go play.
It is absolutely possible to live your life sitting in
your room doing the same thing day in and day out.
But why?
Im so glad you asked. Literally from
birth, people are explorers, exploring surroundings,
environment, relationships, limitations,
potential. And what does this do? And how does that work?
And what happens if I do this?
To stop exploring is to stop being true to yourself.
And the key to exploration is to stay curious.
Curiosity pushes you to explore, yes, but also
to network, to solve problems,
to recognize and take advantage of opportunities,
and to lead a happier life.
But how? There are many
paths to achieve an exploration
can explorer's mindset.
Mine includes being curious,
listening a lot,
ask questions a lot,
avoid dysfunction, listen.
Embrace learning as fun. Develop a
beginner's mind. And please don't forget
to listen.
Here's a little secret. Come closer,
a little closer.
You are a unicorn already
this label unicorn is a euphemism for
being unique and fabulous and extra. And you.
And if Dr. Seuss is to be believed, no one in
the world is youer than you. And they're right.
All of the experiences you've had in your lifetime, your education,
your background, your ups, your downs, whatever brought you here to
this talk today at this conference, no one
else has that reality. Your experience,
your truth, your existence and
understanding. That is what makes
you a unicorn.
The neat part about all of this is if you follow those other steps,
you will conquer the world. It's inherent in
the steps. Be willing two fall down and get back
up. Be brave,
play, explore and be
curious. Be the beautiful unicorn
I know you are and you will conquering the
worlds. It thank you.
Many thanks to comp 42 python
organizer, organizers and sponsors.
If you have any questions, comments or just want to
stay in touch, feel free. I am rain Leander on most
media. Thank you so
much.