Good day ladies and gentlemen. I extend my heartfelt gratitude
for joining me today. My name is Akshay Bhat.
I am genuinely thrilled to be your guide on a fascinating journey where
we explore the profound fusion of GraphQl and Kubernetes under
the theme empowering Kubernetes workloads with GraphQl
while unleashing efficiency and flexibility.
So let's embark on this expedition.
Before we embark on this journey,
let me just give you a brief background of my
own past. I'm Akshay Bhat.
I wear many hats in the technology world. I'm a developer advocate
at Hasura, a regular speaker at
tech conferences. I'm a developer by heart
and I've been a serial tech entrepreneur and I'm a staunch
advocate for open source software.
I've had the privilege of being immersed in the world of technology for a number
of years and I've witnessed firsthand the remarkable evolution of
Kubernetes and graphQl.
My journey in the tech industry has been a thrilling adventure,
rooted in a deep passion for coding and a strong commitment
to fostering community driven innovation.
Beyond my work with Hasura and public speaking, I have ventured into
the realm of entrepreneurship. I've founded and co founded
several tech startups, each with a mission to solve unique challenges
using technology. And as an open source
champion, I actively contribute to and promote the
use of open source technologies, fostering a sense of
community and collaboration wherever I can.
Please connect with me on either LinkedIn or email to
discuss more. Now let's move on
to our agenda.
So today I'll be talking about,
firstly, sort of seeing the outline of
graphQl, demystifying graphQl,
elucidating its pivotal importance and illustrating its primary
facets. Then we'll make the transition into scrutinizing
the challenges that typically besiege Kubernetes developers.
Crucially, we'll dissect how graphql emerges as the
veritable solution to these conundrums.
Then we'll spend some time talking about the efficiency of Kubernetes
clusters and containers, and then we'll discuss why GraphQL
is a great complement with its flexibility. I'll showcase
some real world use cases and examples where this combination works best.
Finally, we'll explore a bit about Hasura and how it can be an ideal
tool when you're running GraphQL and kubernetes.
So let's look at the power of GraphQL,
right? So at
its essence, GraphQL represents a query language for
APIs. However, it's unequally. More than that,
GraphQL is can emblem of flexibility, efficiency and real
time capabilities. This section aims to unveil the bedrock
of GraphQL, its core tenants and its critical
attributes. So GraphQL is a specification for
how to talk to an API. It's typically used over HTTP,
where the key idea is to post a query to an HTTP endpoint
instead of hitting different HTTP endpoints for different resources.
GraphQL is designed for developers of web
or mobile applications, essentially HTTP
clients, to be able to make API calls to fetch
exactly the data they need from their backend APIs.
Before going further in understanding GraphQL, it's useful to get
a sense of how GraphQL is actually used in an HTTP client.
When we talk about GraphQL versus rest APIs,
let's say we are fetching a user's profile and their address.
In a typical rest scenario, you would essentially
be querying or requesting various endpoints
for different resources, different endpoints for different resources.
So the core of rest API involves around resources.
Resources are identified by URLs and request type, it may be get,
post, et cetera. However,
if your API server was a GraphQL server instead,
this is what your API call would look like. As you
can see, you're querying for a user
and you're querying the iD, the name,
the address and the street, or even let's
say the name of the hotel or the city. And you get the response in
a very similar JSON kind of format as your
request is right.
And also we
are changing the way we think about API calls. So instead of making different
APIs calls to different URLs to fetch data,
what we're doing is instead of getting a resource,
you post a query that describes what data you want.
You think of the data your API returns as a graph.
This allows you to make ad hoc queries to
a single URL endpoint that returns data based
on the query. And in the example above you
can see that we fetched for a particular user and
their id, all that. So the query you send as
a data in the post request has a structure and syntax.
And in GraphQl we have mutations and subscriptions.
I'll tell you how it looks like GraphQl
queries look very neat as you can see, and they are easy to read because
the shape of the query is very similar to the
data that we actually end up getting with.
So now let's look at some of the benefits of
graphql. Number one,
we avoid overfetching, so we avoid overfetching
more data than we need because we can specify the exact fields
we need, we can prevent multiple API calls
in case you need more data. You can also avoid making
multiple calls to your API. In the case above, you don't
need to make two API calls to fetch user and address separately.
Lesser communication with API developers.
So sometimes to fetch the exact data you need, especially if
you need to fetch more data and want to avoid multiple API calls,
you will need to ask your API developers to build a
new API. With GraphQL. Your work is
independent of the API team. This allows you to work much faster and
focus on building your product instead of worrying about all the
backend stuff. And every
GraphQL API conforms to a schema which is graph
data model and what kinds of queries a client can
make. This allows the community to build lets of
cool tools to explore and visualize your API, or create
ide plugins that autocorrect your graphQl queries
and even do code Gen. We'll understand this in more detail. So essentially
it's a very self documenting kind of system.
So here is
a small chart showing how
GraphQL and rest API would
look like. So in rest API you have get for
the same you have queries in graphQL for
writing data, you have post in rest, you have mutations for
writing and updating data in GraphQL and you
have subscriptions for watching or subscribing to data which
does not have a very clear analogy or parallel
in rest APIs.
Now let's look at unleashing the
efficiency of kubernetes. Now that we have the foundation
of GraphQL laid, let's transition to kubernetes.
So Kubernetes is an open source container management tool that
automates container deployment, container scaling,
descaling and container load balancing. Also called as
orchestration. Along with automated deployment
and scaling of containers, it provides healing by
automatically restarting failed containers and rescheduling them when
their hosts die. This capability improves the application's availability.
Kubernetes follows the client server architecture as you can see
in this architecture diagram where we have the master installed
on one machine and the node on separate Linux machines.
It follows the master slave model which uses a master to manage
docker containers across multiple Kubernetes nodes.
A master and its control nodes constitute a Kubernetes cluster.
A developer can deploy an application in the docker containers with the assistance
of the Kubernetes master.
Kubernetes, while being a marvelous tool for container orchestration
confronts its fair share of challenges in terms of
API complexity and data retrieval. These are big challenges and
as the scale of the cluster grows, the complexity
of data retrieval grows more than linearly.
Right. But GraphQL,
as I found, was a solution and I've seen multiple use cases
where GraphQL was used to address these challenges. So let's
understand how GraphQL
solves these problems.
So first of
all, GraphQL solves the
data retrieval problem. So it's very flexible.
That sets apart graphql from the rest APIs is its
finesse in data retrieval. Rest APIs often lead
to the pitfalls of overfetching or underfetching data, causing unnecessary
data transfer and inefficiency. So however,
with GraphQL, we'll see how it empowering people
to wield data in a much more effective way.
The other thing is efficient resource manipulation.
It's not just confined to data retrieval, but also
if you want to do manipulation or updation of data mutations
are in. GraphQL are our trusted companions in this simplifying
the intricate tasks of modifying data within Kubernetes so
you can essentially update, create, delete resources
all within a single well orchestrated,
well constructed query. The other thing is real
time insights with GraphQL subscriptions, which is a very
core feature of GraphQL. It's a game changer in Kubernetes
scenarios. So real time updates can completely revolutionize
monitoring and management within Kubernetes.
And we'll see how this subscriptions
can manifest and how we can use them. Exactly.
Now let's come to Hasura and see
how in a graphql and
Kubernetes environment, it shines. So Hasura is a powerful and
versatile technology that serves as a graphQL engine and data platform.
It has gained immense popularity in the world of application development for
several compelling reasons, and it's an excellent fit for Kubernetes and graphql
environments. Some of the reasons are that it's
built on GraphQL. Number one, it's a GraphQL
score. So it's a modern query language which is modern query language
for APIs. With Hasura, you can create a GraphQL API
for your data with minimal effort. This aligns perfectly with the principles
of Kubernetes, which emphasizes container orchestration
and scalability, and graphQl, which optimizes data fetching and manipulation.
So it's a very good combination. The other thing is real time capabilities.
Hasura excels in providing this for GraphQL subscriptions
and this means that you can easily implement features like live
updates, notifications and interactive user experiences,
and in a Kubernetes environment where you might have a dynamic scaling and a
distributed architecture. Hasura's real time functionality seamlessly
integrates, ensuring that your applications remain responsive and up
to date. Hasura also simplifies
data access and authorization. It connects to your data sources such
as databases and rest APIs, and generates a
graphQL schema automatically. This means you
don't have to write complex boilerplate code for data fetching,
filtering and pagination. With Kubernetes managing
your containers, you can ensure that the data layer is scalable and
highly available. In Kubernetes and GraphQL
setups. Security is very important, so Hasura
also offers robust authentication and authorization mechanisms
out of the box. You can easily define fine
grained access controls and permissions for your GraphQL schema,
ensuring that only authorized users can access specific data
and perform certain actions.
Also the other thing is it reduces the time and
effort required to set up a robust GraphQL API, enabling faster
development cycles and easier maintenance. This is
particularly valuable in Kubernetes environment where agility and scalability are essential.
The other thing is it provides built in monitoring and observability tools
that help you keep an eye on your API's
performance, GraphQL API's performance and usage and in
a Kubernetes cluster with a big size where monitoring and debugging can
be complex, these observability features simplify
the process and enable you to productively address issues.
So in summary, Hasura is a great fit for kubernetes and graphql
environments because it simplifies data access and
enhances developer productivity and offers real time capabilities.
So let's take a small demo and see how things
look like.
So this is a documentation regarding how you can run Hasura
GraphQL engine on Kubernetes.
So this is how it looks like.
Essentially these are the many different attributes
and data that exists and you can query them with
GraphQL. And getting the data is very simple. You just
connect the database whether it's postgres, in this case it's
postgres and you can just track those
tables and the data is available.
For example here the orders and assignment table is
available directly here to query and you
can just run the query and fetch the data.
So this is some of
the documentation for the talk that
I used here. There is introduction to GraphQL, there is
deployment guide and also do check out the
blogs that I've written on this topic. I've written some on
Kubernetes and how you can deploy GraphQl
APIs very fast for very scalable
application.
So thank you for joining
this talk. As we near the conclusion, let's sort of recap
what we talked about. So GraphQL isn't a
merely a technological innovation, it's a paradigm shift that can
reinvigorate your Kubernetes workloads, elevate user experiences,
and kindle innovation. I urge each of you to embrace this opportunity
to experiment and discover how GraphQL and Kubernetes can transform
your projects. So while we looked at both GraphQL and Kubernetes,
we also saw how Hasura, as a powerful graphql engine,
plays a pivotal role in empowering Kubernetes workloads.
It simplifies the creation and management of GraphQL APIs within Kubernetes,
making it accessible and efficient. I implore you
to take a closer look and see the benefits of Hasura
firsthand. With that, I hope you're eager to take a
plunge. Feel free to seek out any clarification you
need on these and reach out to me to discuss more on these
topics. See you.