Thank you for coming to my talk with the title of enjoy typesafe
web development with Ada. Well it is not actually about Ada,
but I want to take Ada as a way to basically that
there is a lot of opportunity in using functional programming in the
JVM world, right. So I'm Mapuji, I'm from
Kulkul Tech and in this conf 42 series I wanted this
us about FP. Why is it very important and then
how it benefits you like Java programmer, right?
And the good news is I'm from Java island so
let me work to you about FP and the Java ecosystem,
right? Okay so I want to discuss about a lot of things,
but this is the outline, right? So one is I want to discuss about
what is functional programming really is and what are the benefits of
using functional programming, what type of FP languages and
if it's really awesome, what is the success I ever had
in the past. And I'll discuss about Elm and how I really loved
it. And I want to explore further about using
FPL language in the JVM world. And it leads me to the Ada, how I
use Ada as one of the example of pure FP language
in the JVM world. Right, okay so that's a lot of
jargon, but let me take you to a story, right?
So if you take a look to FP
programming or fastline programming, it is actually a very old
concept. It is created in 1978 by a bunch
of people and it is really old, right? And the good thing is,
although it is really old, the concept still holds true till
today. And this is very fascinating for me because it is such an
old concept, but it keep repeating and then there is a lot of value
in learning about it. It gets you become a
better programmer by learning it, right? And it will not be
like frontend development where they invented
a lot of concept last night. It is just like good old
concept, right? And there is a story when I playing with Elm in
the front end world because Elm is like pure FP
languages, people think that the number
of updates that met in the past few days is really
matters. And then the problem with Elm is Elm is updated
two years ago and there is no update since then. But it is very stable.
But people things that if it's not up there is stable
or it is like unmaintained. But the thing is
for Elmer is really stable, but for some other programming
language, I don't know, but sometimes in
FT world it becomes very very stable. Right? Okay, let's continue.
So there is a nice meme about code written in Haskell
is guaranteed to have no side effect because no one will ever run
it. Right? Okay, so what is actually FP?
So let me introduce you to John. John is a software engineer
and he would like to create a new web app. So he's writing
a web app and he grabbed his favorite language and
hint is it's Java. And he start writing,
right? And he's using a new tech stock,
it is using a new this, new that, anything and
whatnot. And it will take a while for him. And few moments
later, Tada. Now he's
having a working app and he scared
to create a pull request, right? So he made
that pull request and now the code will go through a series
of code review, right? But like
in any other code review, your spaghetti code will
not pass, right? And he got things, he got recommendation
to refactor the code from the senior guy.
And like any other code review, ten lines
of code, ten issue. But if it's 500 lines of code, it looks
fine. And the problem is John is
come to the former batch, which is ten lines of code,
ten issues. Tada. Okay. Then he
can reflect up the code. So he's tap tap, tap tap tap
tap tap tap tap tap tap tap, tada. All the sweat.
And he said, I finished refactoring the entire code. Cool.
Is the bug fixed now? Is the app
is still working? Turns out it's not. That's a problem.
What we can learn from here, the thing is developing software
is hard, right? The other problem is building reliable
software needs a lot of effort. There is code review,
there is unit testing, there is refactoring. And sometimes
software is just, there is too much detail in it. There is too
much details, right. And take a look in the refactoring.
Refactoring is good, I support it.
But sometimes it can be very complex.
So I asking can it be more simple? And next part is,
is it possible to make like refactoring? And all the effort
we have in the making of software engineering, more reliable,
more enjoyable maybe. And my suggestion is
so welcome to the functional programming. I cannot
guarantee you much, but it's been fun for me. Welcome to the FP.
And then I'll introduce you to what FP is.
So FP is like old concept. It's already there
since 1978. And turns out
like I said earlier, it can help you code better.
So one, it helps make your mind to
a see things differently. So when you code in functional
programming, it's very far, far different. So youll used to
work with objects or imperative
programming, you prepare some variable, you do things,
but in the FP it's the same, but it's a little bit different.
So now you see things differently and it
is affecting you when you do code now you be more
creative with composing functions. Now when you write
the code, youll model the code with different construct,
you model the code with a lot of function, you're composing it together and
hopefully it can help you to write better code by making
the code more readable. You can use a lot of concept in phasma
programming querying. You can do something like pipe operator
and things like that and it becomes very expressive.
And the good thing is if you are using a very
strict FP language, it can make your code easy to
change, easy to refactor, easy to maintain.
This is very, very integral part, and very important part
that I really love about FP is if you choose the right FP languages,
it can make your code easy to change and it's very enjoyable.
So you can create like the code looks like
something right now, but in the future if you learn new
things, you can refactor it and then make the code to be something else.
You can refactor, the interface is the same, but you can refactor,
but you can feel safe because if it's compiled it might be
working. So it scared better because now your code
is composed by function. Hopefully it is like pure
function. So you can take an advantage of concurrency
of you don't need to think about state anymore. And yeah,
this is it. So let's take a look. The quote from
Uncle Bob from the clean architecture all risk condition
deadlock condition. Concurrent problems are due
to mutable variables. See mutable variables and
let's take a look to the Eric Eliot quotes.
FP is the process of building software by compassing pure function,
avoiding set state mutable data side effects and
functional programming is declarative rather than imperative. And application that
flows through pure function flows through pure
function. Okay, so let's continue. So what is the benefit of
using it, right? It seems awesome. If you are using FP,
you can get the following advantage. Your code can
be achieving the holy grail of bugs free code because youll
have no side effect. If your code is compiled, 90% is
working usually. And you can take advantage of efficient
parallel programming because you are using immutable data. You don't need to think about memory
anymore, and you can take advantage of concurrent programming.
You can use nested function, you can use lazy evaluation,
things like that. It's very awesome. It can make you more readable and more
performance this way, but if you're doing it right. Okay, so there is a
couple of types of FP languages. So there is the
first part which is more into pure functional programming language
like Haskell, L. Mercury clean and so on and so
forth. There is another part of language which is impure functional
programming language like Scala, closure, f, sub okaman and so on and
so forth. There is also a lot of op languages or multi
paradigm languages like JavaScript, Ruby that's now trying
to adopt a lot of FP idea into the
language. And it's cool. It's very awesome I think.
And they should do more, right, okay, so what functional programming
success I ever encountered. So let's take a look to
my experience in building application using FP
functional programming. It is elm.
So if you take a look to the Elm website, you can see that
they claim that it is a delightful language for reliable
web application. And there's a lot of testimonials.
It is like a scam, I told youll it's like a scam.
So some people said it is the most productive programming
language I have used. Some other people said my
favorite thing is the feeling of joy and relaxation when writing
elm code. Others said using Elm I can
deploy and go to sleep. And some other people said just follow the compiler
errors and come out the other end with the working app.
So if you break things, you refactor like John and then
now you break things. Initially your code is like having a compiler
errors, but once you finish all the compiler errors,
99% it is fully working app, right?
It's very amazing, right? Yeah. And the other
feature it's provided is something that's really rare in
web UI or web development or friend development is
runtime exception. So if you take a look to the Javascript
error in the browser, you can open Google now and then go to the
web tools devtools, you can see that there is a lot of console log error.
Sometimes you open Facebook, it's the
same. You open Twitter, it's the same. There is usually some runtime error
happening there, but by using what is it? Elm,
you can basically minimize the error to almost zero.
So it is happening on NoRAD ink where they have almost zero
runtime error. They get it one, only one. It is because bug
in the compiler, but it is already fixed by now. So the
other good thing is if you see here, the compiler gives
you some very meaningful errors.
So in here it said this to in
call projects may be in, but drop needs the first argument
to be in. And there is a hint there, right. It's very
interesting and like I said before, fearless refactoring,
where the compiler guides you safely through your changes and
sharing confidence even through the most wide breaking refactoring in unfamiliar
code base. It's very awesome because whether you're renaming a
function or you make drastic changes in a code data type, you just fold
the compiler and by the end of the day you can get a
working app. And the other good thing is this
is something that really specific to Elm, but they have some
model on building reliable app, but this is specific
to them. Right. Let's just keep it. So the
last part is about fast and friendly feedback.
People now really interested in immediate
feedback. They need things now and then. Having a
compiler that's really helping youll to get that fast feedback is pretty
awesome and I think most compilers done
that, but elm make it to the next level by having a very
easy to read and friendly kind of frustration
friendly. What is it? Nice compiler errors
and you are talking to compilers rather than you
blame the compiler, right? It's very empowering.
And now I know I want to explore more about
Ada. So Ada is one of the pure
FP language in the JVM world and it is awesome.
And it is basically Haskell for the JVM.
So let's take a look at it. So why people are using Ada?
So EDA is there because it has a
very robust interrupt. So ETA has a strongly
type FFI or foreign function invocation or interface
that allows you to safely interrupt with Java.
And it has another properties which is ultra type
safety which it has a global type inference giving you a dynamic
language experience, but with a strong type hidden underneath.
Sometimes you don't need to put all the type annotation,
but youll still get all the advantage of very very
strong type system. And because the next part
is ETA offers wide range of strategy for handling and currency.
Like there is STM, there is mfas, there is fibers.
So it's very flexible. And let's take a look to the demo.
So let's go to the demo now.
Hopefully it is working. Okay, so ETA is updated
now I can now run Ada atlas
run and it will run through the app, it resolving all the
dependency and all that stuff and then downloading from
source. And then after that we can run it.
But while it's compiling the app, let's take a look to the code.
So this code is. You can take a look at it in
GitHub. It is very simple.
I create two applications. One is the Fibonacci
application, the other is the simple hello world.
We'll basically walk through it like one by one.
And the idea is,
it is mostly Haskell, right. It is Haskell code. The code
is HHS, which stands for Haskell. Right.
And if you take a look at it. So while
my code is still compiling, let's take a look at programming
languages. If you see here, in here, they want
to create, what is it? They want to create a very simple
hello word application API. And then what they can do is
basically they create a type API and then they can decide
that I want to create hello. There is a query params
and then basically it's returning a JSON value, right. And then
after that you can create some similar to
controller here, like controller. And then after that you can
basically returning an error there
if they didn't tell your name, otherwise it will basically
returning hello something. There is maybe, and there is the other one,
right. And it is running on the port 9000. Okay, so let's take
a look at the actual code here. I hope it is
already running. So in here it's still processing just fine.
Yeah. So the problem with Ada is, well,
I'm doing it. The problem with Ada is Ada is running,
having a lot of problem lately. So the maintainer
is not very active anymore. So the downside is
Ada is not really actively maintained, but it's pretty much stable.
It's pretty much stable. And you can use a lot of
Haskell packages here and then you can still doing a
lot of productive development in Ada. But I
think it is interesting idea to have Haskell with
the interact of Java. But the really good thing is what I
recommend using Ada is not for production application, but more like
youll are learning things, you can see things differently
by learning how to write things in Haskell, especially if you are from Java
world, you don't want to learn all the Java build tool,
but now using Ada you can use something like gradle
to basically running Haskell application. Pretty interesting,
right? Yeah. So while waiting you can go through all this and
then get a cheat sheet and then get a feel of how Ada
looks like. And then after that in here. Once we finish
everything, we can basically run the app. So I'm waiting here.
Okay, so let's check again on the docker we
have on the atlas. It is running now. And let's
take a look on our Fibonacci API. So it is
very simple. So we have application running on port 9000
and let's take a look at it. So let's open local host
9000 and we put Fibu.
Okay, so let's try, I have Fibonacci endpoint
here. If I call one it gives me
the Fibonacci number. If I put two I hit
two, if I have four it returns like five
things like that. Very awesome. And it can keep like
on and on and on as you wish. Right.
And things is just a very basic simple API.
And then I want to give you the one that exactly looks like this.
I can go here and then I can change the surfer
into surfer. Two, for simplicity I can go here
and then I will restart the machine building
executable compiling and then transit running.
And then in here we can get the endpoint hello and
then query param, right. So just hello
and then we can go query parame equal my
name and it should be able to tell
me my name. That's really awesome, right? Yeah,
so that's very basic example of Ada.
I'll make it larger. So the idea is we have
almost similar application like Haskell,
but you can do some java interrupt if you want. I give some
Java interrupt example here if you want to take a look further and
yeah, so that's the very basic endpoint I can
tell to you. So the idea is you can have very strong
type languages. So in here.
So the magic on the Haskell is it's basically
giving you this type, like this type
annotation and then basically everything should
match with this type annotation.
And then in here one of the interesting part is
the jetty surfer here where it's basically interoperability
with the surplus. Right. Very awesome. So the idea
is we are using surf and surfer, but behind
the scene there is some page that Eta giving to the
Haskell compiler, the Atlas compiler to basically using
some patch version of to instead of using
the actual serpent from the Haskell. So it's very interesting. Yeah,
I think that's it. I hope that you enjoyed the simple
demo I had and the
Ada don't side. So as I said earlier that the language is
not that maintained anymore. I'm not very a fit user
of Ada. So I'm not sure if it's like the language is not maintained
or it is already stable enough, but I think
that it is the later one because many packages
is not hosted anymore, I cannot install it and things like
that. I need to run the docker version to make it run on my machine
and things like that. So please think about it when choosing Ada
in your production and managing compatibility with Haskell
ecosystem is hard. So for example, if I were to run one
of the example from the app, I need to basically very careful in choosing
Haskell dependency. I'm not sure if it's from
the Haskell or from the Ada, but it is very hard to manage the dependency
and make the dependency working together. But yeah,
that's it guys, that's about Ada. So I hope you enjoy my
presentation. I hope that you can be a better John by
maybe learning more about FP languages in the future,
or you can also explore or applying it to your day to day
work environment. So if you are a tech lead or someone that
can basically influence a tech statistician,
you might as well take a look at some FP languages
instead of only the popular one. And I can
assure you that it's worth the effort because it
helps you open your mind and see things differently.
And thank you. That's my presentation today. I hope that you
enjoy my presentation. Talk to you soon,