You event driven architectures
problem do they actually solve? Hi and welcome to Conf 42.
I'm Bogdan Sucaciu and together we'll demystify event
driven architectures with Apache Kafka. I've been working with event
driven architectures a couple of years now. Currently I'm a tech
lead at Deloitte Digital, a digital consulting firm. And probably some
of you may know me from plural website where I teach about various subjects,
event driven systems being one of them. Speaking about event
driven, this is the subject that we're going to be focusing on today.
My goal is rather simple, to change your perspective about it.
For a long time they have been marketed as the solution
for real time or near real time systems.
But is it true though? I mean, we already have real time
systems that are not based on events. We create a new user,
we make can order, and so on. It's not like
I'm going to create a new user, go and grab a coffee,
and then 5 minutes later I can come back and finish my
order. In fact, only a couple of use cases really require event
architectures, and most of them are related to real time
analytics, fraud detection, sensor readings and
so on. But still, event driven architectures,
something else to the table, something much more powerful than you
expected. And to illustrate all of this, I'm going to use
Apache Kafka. Actually, I'm not going to be using on Kafka
that much. If you've already used Kafka, there is quite a big
chance that you won't learn anything new today. But still,
Kafka is an important piece of technology in the event driven world.
Why? Well, I'm going to drop some clues during the session regarding
why Kafka makes such a great option for event driven architectures.
Without further delay, let's get started. And what better
way to start with than one of the most powerful architecture patterns?
Demonolit. Yeah, you heard me right.
Demonolit is indeed an extremely powerful pattern due
to its simplicity. Basically, we have a
bunch of lines of code, and all that code is running
on a single process. Also, we often have a
database attached to it in order to store various data.
Most of the time is some sort of a relational database.
However, it has quite a major drawback,
scalability. And I'm not talking just from
an operations perspective like virtually scaling a process,
but I'm also talking from a team perspective.
I think we've all been there endless conversations on
collaboration apps about basically changing the color of
a button to pink. So working with monolith
is not really scalable or fun. So how can we
fix this problem? Well, some very smart
people came with the idea, what if we take this
big application and split it into multiple services?
It first started with SoA service oriented architecture,
but it was quite tricky to determine the right bounds
for the applications. So this tendency
naturally evolved into what we call today microservices.
Each microservice gets a different piece of the business domain.
This way separate teams can work on separate applications,
allowing to scale down or up the number of teams
working on these product. Exactly the same concept can
be applied to infrastructure. We can scale down
or up the number of instances only for the applications
we need to. However, there is a slight concerning
issue. As we all know, in software
engineering we don't have good or bad, right or
wrong, we have tradeoffs. So by using
microservices, we now have to solve a different set
of problems related to data access.
A lot of times microservices sound very utopic,
like each microservice can evolve independently
without having the need to coordinate with another microservice.
But I think we've all been there. Practice doesn't
transpose 100% from theory. Most of the time
we're using synchronous APIs such as rest or RPC calls
to exchange data between our services. Let's say that
one of our users makes a request to one of our
services. From there we have an entire cascade
of other calls that need to be done from one single rest
call. We may end up with 20 or even 30 other
calls. This happens because even
if each microservice owns a single piece of the business
domain, we will always need data from other domains to get
the full picture. Let's say we want to make a payment
transaction. It's not like we only need the credit card details.
No, we also need the name of our user or even his
address. And that is usually stored by a different
microservice. So in order to get the full picture,
we always need to somehow compose it by calling different
microservices from our architectures.
Sounds easy, but by doing this we are diving into a
new set of challenges, such as distributed transactions,
timeouts, dependency management,
coupling or even data ownership.
These challenges and many more others have been
introduced by microservices and by the fact that
we are now using distributed systems to perform our tasks.
And that's what event event driven architectures really
good at. They can easily solve distributed systems problems
by introducing new concepts and patterns.
But first, what exactly is an event driven architectures this
is these main talking point of my presentation and I haven't even introduced
it yet. Well, I was curious too, so I went
to Wikipedia and I found this event. Event driven
architectures shortly said EDA is a software architecture
paradigm promoting production,
consumption of and reaction of events. There are
some interesting words being thrown in there, production,
consumption, reaction and so on.
So let's find out what they actually mean.
To do that, we need to go back to our microservices to
keep things simple. I'm going to pick only four services,
blue, gray, purple and red. To make
things interesting. The blue service is using reSt APIs to
communicate with the purple and red services, and an
RPC call to communicate with the gray service.
Rest APIs are based on a request response type
of communication, whereas with RPC calls
we don't always get back a response. This flow
can also be represented in another way using unidirectional
flow of data. Now the blue service calls
the gray service and the flow ends. But when the
blue service calls the purples and the red services,
the flow continues and they will provide some sort of data
back to the blue service. This is interesting,
but we still haven't solved any of the problems mentioned earlier.
To solve them, we need another piece of the puzzle called
event stream. The trick is quite simple.
We now have two types of applications,
producers and consumers. Producers send
data to an event streams and consumers retrieve it
from the same event stream. What's interesting is the
fact that an application can be both a producer and
a consumer at the same time. Just like the purple and
the red services, these consume data from the blue event stream
and produce it into another. Now, if we
isolate only the producers, we can immediately notice
that there is only one producer type per event stream.
The blue service produces on the blue event stream,
the purple service produces on the purple event stream,
and so on. You should definitely keep this in mind when
you're designing your event driven architectures. You could,
for example, use multiple producer types to produce
to one event stream, but that will complicate a lot.
The consuming process. Then if we take a look
over the consuming part, we can notice that multiple consumers
can retrieve data from the same event stream.
Also, one consumer is allowed to consume data
from multiple event streams. So consumers are
much more flexible than producers in terms of connection
to different event streams. And by introducing
only one concept, we actually tackled multiple
issues. First of all, our applications are no
longer coupled since the event stream is meant to serve as a
decoupling factor and then data ownership is
already simplified. Each event stream stores one type of data
and any interesting party can easily consume it.
But what exactly is an event stream?
Well, an event stream can be represented by many things,
such as logs, topics, queues,
websockets or even reactive APIs.
Now I know that some of you may be thinking,
hey, how can a websocket be considered an event stream?
Well, if you come to think of it, websockets or even
reactive APIs are a bit more special scenario.
The event stream and a producing application have merged together
into a single entity. But if you think about the previous deductions,
we still have only one producing application,
and multiple consumers can connect to the
same event stream. The only difference between
a reactive API and a topic is that the
event stream and a producing application are two separate
entities. In fact, anything that you can asynchronously
subscribe to can be can event stream. Any tool,
library or protocol that can produce data in an asynchronous
manner can be considered an event stream.
These are, however, some fundamental differences between
these event streams types. For example,
queues, websockets and reactive APIs treat
event differently compared to topics and logs.
While using the first category, we can only react
to events, we consume them and then they are gone
with no option of getting them back. Topics and
logs, on the other hand, can persist those events and we
can replay them later on. This pattern is a
bit more powerful and we'll see why a bit later.
An important thing to remember is that kafka uses topics as
event streams, and under the hood it uses logs
to persist events. This is one of the main reasons
Kafka is such can excellent choice for building event driven
applications. Of course, Kafka is
not the only system that allows this. These are plenty of
other examples such as AWS kinesis or Apache
Pulser, which work in a similar fashion. But Kafka
has another ace under its sleeve, something that
kinesis and pulser aren't that good at, which we'll
see in just a few minutes.
So in Kafka's world, event streams are represented
by Kafka topics residing on Kafka brokers
producers connect to the Kafka broker in order to produce
data, and consumers have to do the same thing
in order to consume it. This brings some implications
to our way. We exchange data throughout the system.
Firstly, we're now dealing with something called inversion of
control, and it's quite a simple pattern.
While using the classic rest API approach, it is the
job of the producer to send these data to the consumer.
Now, the producer doesn't care anymore.
Its only job is to produce data to an event stream.
Actually, it's the consumer's job to retrieve the data by
subscribing to the event stream. So we are inverting the
control from the producer to the consumer. By empowering
the consumer to retrieve the data that it is interested in,
then we have can out behavior. Multiple consumers
can consume data produced by only one producer.
Talking about producers, it is recommended to have
only one producer type per event stream.
Just to make things clear, I'm referring to the producer type and not
producer instance. Multiple producer instances
can produce to the same event stream as long as they
are on the same type. And finally,
producers don't really know consumers. From an application perspective,
a producer is like hey, my only
job is to produce data to this event stream,
but I don't know who is going to consume it and frankly,
I don't even care. Consumers have the
same mindset. These don't know who is producing this data,
they only care about their connection to the event stream.
However, if we zoom out a bit from an architecture
perspective, consumers and producers are well known in
order to get the full picture of the business flow.
So going back to microservices, our main challenge
was data access. By adopting an
event driven architectures, we're actually solving it.
Our data is now really easy to access.
We just have to make our consumers subscribe to an event stream
and that's it. It's much easier to subscribe to one
or more event streams rather than making 20
or 30 API calls. But still,
just as I mentioned previously, in software engineering,
we don't have right or wrong, we have tradeoffs.
And the tradeoff for event architectures
is consistency. While using synchronous APIs
we have that strong consistency, and we're always sure
that we're getting the latest version of our data in
event driven architectures no longer have
that. Instead, we have something called eventual consistency.
In fact, the key to building successful
event driven architecture is understanding and
accepting eventual consistency.
We can't just simply take a synchronous rest API
and then transpose it in an event driven way. New patterns
require new ways of thinking, so such
attempts may fail due to the mismatch between these patterns.
In fact, not all flows are meant to be event driven.
In the real world, we will always find a mix between synchronous APIs
and eventing patterns. Now,
I've babbled a lot about events, but I haven't really said
what an event really is. Well, to do that
we need to have a look of our communication types between systems
and the best way to start with is a message.
A message is just some data being exchanged between two
different services a and b. A message
has a form, a body, but it doesn't say how the
data is being transferred. That's why we
need some more concrete definitions. The types of
messages can be determined based on when these action resulted
from the data transfer is happening. The first one
is command a. Command will always
happen sometime in the future. Even if we
initiate the action now, the result of it will
be perceived sometime in the future.
Also, a command is a directed instruction,
meaning that we know exactly who we are communicating
with. An example will be rest calls service
a, calls service b. A very important thing
to know is that the fact that we don't always receive a response
while using the command pattern. Sometimes we do,
sometimes we don't. The opposite of a command is the
query. Now, our service does not give instructions
to another, but it actually requests some data,
just like trying to request a database or a search engine.
Queries happen in the present because we are requesting the
current state of our data. Also,
one important fact is that we are always getting a response back.
Finally, we have events. Events are
a bit different compared to the other two. They represent actions
that have happened or have been triggered sometime
in the past. As you've probably noticed,
commands and queries require point to point communication service
a, query service b, while events on
the other hand are undirected, meaning that
anyone can consume events without the producer knowing.
Also can event producer will never receive a response
from its consumers. In fact, there are two types of
events that a producer can send. The first
one is called event notification.
And just like his name is suggesting the event producer
is informing its consumers that an action has
happened. I can actually give you a great example of
this pattern in practice. I'm not really sure if I
can mention their name, but let's say that one of the biggest ecommerce
companies has an extremely interesting use case on their homepage.
They are displaying some random items that you may
or may not be interesting in buying them.
However, at the bottom of the page they also have
a questions section. Do you know how they are
compiling those suggestions? Well, we tend
to move the cursor based on the direction of our eyesight.
If we look to the right, we also move the cursor to the right.
So if we see something that may attract us on that page,
we tend to hover these cursor over that specific item.
The moment we do that can event is being sent to their
questions service notifying that we have hovered
over that product. So as we scroll down the
page we probably hover over a couple of items.
Then at the bottom of the page we are getting suggestions
based on which items we have hovered over.
Sounds really cool, right? This is actually one
of the best examples of the event notification pattern because it
really denotes that eventing aspect. The producer
isn't interested in getting back a response, and it also doesn't
care about its consumers. All the producer does it cares about
is to send hover events to the backend system.
So how would something like this would look in Apache
Kafka? Well, we always have at
least two applications, a producer and at least one consumer.
The first step is to define the event stream, in our case a
Kafka topic. By the way, I'm using Java
here, but there are kafka clients that would work with many other programming
languages like Golang, Python and so on.
Then in the next section we have to define some
configuration. Both our producer and consumer
need to know how to connect to the Kafka cluster and what
serialization format should use. Next we
have to initialize a Kafka producer and a Kafka consumer.
Pretty straightforward so far. Now things start
to divert a bit. The producer has to create a producer record.
You can consider a record as an equivalent to an event.
It's just that record is the official naming in Apache
Kafka. A quick fact about records,
a record is composed of a key and a value.
Keys are used to identify events and values store
the payload of that event. On the other hand,
these consumer has to subscribe to the same topic the producer
is producing too. We can actually pass a collection of
topics meaning that our consumers can subscribe
to multiple event streams at the same time.
Finally, these only thing left to do for our producer is
to send that event to the Kafka cluster. I've talked
earlier about inversion of control and how it's the consumer
job to actually make sure it retrieves the data well.
The way this works in Kafka is by using these poll pattern.
The consumer will actively query these Kafka cluster in
order to find if there are new events to be consumed.
As soon as the poll method returns, we are free to do whatever
we want with those events. However,
the poll action only happens once. That's why we
need to wrap it in a while. True loop the end result
sounds like a broken record. Hey, do you have new events for me?
Do you have new events for me? Do you have new events for me?
If the broker has new events in the event stream, it will pass
them further to the consumer. Let's actually see
how these code would look in action. So I have
four terminal windows. On the left I will be running a single
producer. On the right I will be running not one but three
different consumers. All three will do exactly these same
thing. They will lock the consumed event. In practice,
these would actually consume the events in different ways.
Starting with a producer, we can see that it's producing
messages containing an incremental number as the key and
a random uid as the value. I've used
a while loop to make sure that an event is generated
every 1 second. Now let's start the consumers.
Firstly consumer one, then consumer
two, and finally consumer three.
As you can notice, all three of them are receiving the same events
almost at the exact same time. Just try to think about
how much code it would take to write an application that
does the same thing using synchronous APIs.
Of course we would get some added benefits like strong consistency,
but if we don't really need them, it's fine.
The next type of event is event carried state transfer.
I know it sounds quite fancy, but I think it will
be quite easy to explain it using an example.
Event carried state transfer is all about the changes
that occur in the current state. Let's take for
example, the address changed event. A user changes
his or her address through a user interface.
This is a change in the state. Now our
producer needs to send the address changed event to the event stream.
But how much information should that event contain?
It should contain only the new address,
the old one and the new one. What about the
user information? Let's say we want to go minimal
and pick only the new address. That event is produced
to Kafka, which is then picked up by the consumers.
Only then we realize that one of the consuming parties
is a tax service that requires the oral address as well.
Uhoh, what can we do in this case?
Well, that service can query back to the source system and
get the missing data. Do you notice the
problem? Because we haven't passed enough information into
our event, we have now introduced coupling between
our services. That's why when you're designing your event
model, take into consideration that all consuming parties
should avoid querying back the source system.
One other problem that we frequently encounter while using microservices
is the distributed source of truth. Our data doesn't reside
in a single place, but it is distributed across multiple
data stores. So in order to compute the results,
we actually need to query multiple databases,
and it's quite tricky to do it the right way.
Sometimes we may be tempted to apply some workarounds,
like copying parts of the data from one database to
another. But this also poses some challenges.
How can we make sure the data is in sync? How can
we make sure that the moment we compile our result, we have the latest
version of the data? A lot of effort would have
to go into writing, deploying and maintaining
some database synchronizers. We are now working with distributed
systems, so we need another way to tackle this,
a more efficient one. And these is these event
sourcing comes into play event sourcing is
probably one of the most powerful patterns, but it is
also one of the most demanding. It all comes down
to an event log. You can think of an event log
as a ledger where we keep various actions that have happened.
For example, let's think of a bank account.
When we open that bank account, we start with the initial
amount zero. Then money is being deposited
into that account. First we have a transaction of 500
and these another transaction of 200. Finally,
we have to pay for that new tv and $300 are
subtracted from that account. So event sourcing
works by always appending new records to the log instead
of updating an existing row in a relational database.
If we want to compute the current amount, the only thing
we have to do is to replay the log and go through all
the transactions. By doing so, we can easily obtain
the current balance of our bank account, which in our case
would be $400. These is how event sourcing
works. We always build the current state by replaying
all the events from the log. You may think that these pattern
is rather new, but we're actually using it for
quite some time now. To give you an example,
Git is actually an event sourcing system.
We always retrieve the latest version of our code base by
replaying commits from the log. So why is this
pattern so powerful? Well, it solves our data access
problem. Let's say that we have three applications that
need some data. In the Kafka world, these would be some
simple consumers that subscribe to a Kafka topic. Just a
quick reminder. Kafka uses log files to store events.
That's why it is such a powerful option when it comes to
event driven architectures. Cool. Now let's
say that two events are produced to the event log. The only thing
the consumers would have to do is to consume those two
events. They can be stored either in memory or any
persistence layer. By doing so, we are building
a socalled materialized view. We are building a
current state based on events.
If a new event is being produced, the consumers
will pick it up and update their materialized views.
But this doesn't happen in an instant. There's a slight delay
between actually appending the event in the log and updating
these materialized view. That's why we have to accept
eventual consistency. We know that at some point
in time our data will be consistent,
but we don't know exactly when.
Now, not everything goes perfect in production and
things may fail. Let's say that one of our data stores goes
down and we lose all our data. But that
is totally fine. Why? Because all the other applications
are not going to be impacted. If new events
are being produced, the other applications can consume
them in their own rhythm and update their materialized
views. But what about the application that went
down? Well, we can simply bring back an empty
data store. Kafka consumers also have the ability
to rewind and consume events from the past.
That means we can start consuming from the beginning of these
event log and recreate the current state.
I always like to end something on a positive note. So what I want
to say is that the game is on. We are actually witnessing
a transition period and we are all part of it. A couple of years ago
microservices were really popular and everyone was talking about them.
Right now the same thing happens with event driven system we
are changing our systems to adapt to a new mindset and
event event event driven architectures. Step of all of this I would like
to thank you for joining this session and don't forget I'm available
to answer any questions that you may have. Feel free to connect with
me on Twitter or LinkedIn. I'm always open for interesting discussion.
Thank you again and I hope I'll see you next time. Have fun.