No, wafs don't use a web application firewall, and when you
should anyway. I'm Joshua Fox,
senior cloud architect at Doint International and please contact
me by email. This is remote and I always like to
talk to my audience, so please reach out.
I advise customers in Google Cloud,
AWS and Azure. I'm certified in all three and I'm
also a Google developer expert, which means I travel
the world talking about Google technologies. But I'm not a Google employee.
And in this talk I will mention a few different web application firewalls.
We at Doit support our customers who are digital
cloud natives. We give them advice in the clouds
and we offer them software for analyzing costs,
reducing cost, understanding the cloud systems,
and we also resell cloud services,
sometimes at a very nice discount.
This talk is based on an article which you can see at the end.
I'll give you a link to these slides and a QR code so you can
read the article as well. But the talk goes into more detail.
The scenario is that the chief information security officer
is shouting about the vulnerabilities in your web application.
Very worrying, and nobody knows what to do.
Quick, we need a solution now. So somebody says
WaF and the CEO says, yeah, go ahead,
let's protect our system. That sounds
like an easy solution. What is
a waf? It's a service that tries to protect your web
application. And later on I'll get into detail on how
it does it and what it tries tries to do.
But first, let's talk about some drivers for getting a web application
firewall. The biggest one is a hacker attack
fire drill. The system is under attack,
data going out. There are data being encrypted by an
attacker. We have to do something fast.
Another reason is similar. It's a penetration test. This is a hacker
attack that you paid for. And I have seen this
happen when I've hired penetration testers and
I asked one of them, would you like a password to our system
to go into it and see what vulnerabilities there are? He said, well, let me
try. Without a password. Within ten minutes he was tap dancing
through the database. And so I sent him to another business
unit because it was really scary what was happening to our business unit.
Yeah, that's right. Same thing. The state of the art is
not good. This is always motivated
with urgency. And the problem with that is
that quick and dirty solutions tend to stay that way.
And that means that not only do you never get a proper
fix for your insecure system, but your team doesn't get a fix.
You do not develop the expertise as a team that you need
to keep your application secure. Another driver
for WAF is outside requirements, which often expresses itself
as an audit. You have to fulfill the audit,
whether it's because of a government regulation or the customer says
you need it in a request for proposals. Maybe a partner,
maybe the cloud provider itself requires that if you want to
sell together with them, or a
standard certification may require a WAF. Well, can't argue with that.
They demand it, you're going to get it. Although that's not security.
And another thing that isn't security is a security
blanket, something to make the CEO feel warm and cozy.
Because we have the WAF, so we've protected our system.
That is the most dangerous driver for getting a
WAF. To understand what a WAF is supposed to
protect against, and often does, let's look at some
potential threats. The top ones to look at are
called the Owasp top ten. Owasp is a standards body,
and the reason they list ten is because in reality there are thousands
of possible vulnerabilities, tens of thousands depending on how
you count it. Nobody can handle all of that, so they give you
ten to look at and to learn. And we'll
review a small fraction of that here, as well as some other threats.
I created a demo. This is live running system
at knowaf dot joshuafox.com and with waf dot joshuafox.com dot
I'm going to walk you through it here in my talk
in slides because it helps us focus on the key points. But if you want
to play around there, you can. Now I'm the attacker and
I'm going to create a game for the innocent victim. This is
actually Scrabble, and the name I choose for
myself is pretty strange. Script Alert hacked you script,
that is JavaScript, and I'm going to
make that JavaScript run in the browser of the innocent victim. In an actual
hack it would steal your cookies, steal your password,
but this is the standard example used to keep it simple. Once you
can run arbitrary JavaScript in the victim's browser, game over.
This is the architecture. One server can be reached
through a load balancer that does not have cloud armor, or through
a load balancer that does have cloud armor from the same browser.
Two different routes, actually, two different subdomains with and without protection.
I made the code unsafe by taking the code in the lower
right, which wraps up the person's name in a
div. So when the hacker sends a chat message to
the innocent victim, the chat message will be rendered safe
by escaping it. I'll show you what that looks like later. Then I
broke the code on the upper left. The attacker's
name is just going to be rendered onto the victim screen and
execute it. Whoops,
hacked you. That's JavaScript running in the victim's browser.
However, if we access the system through the WAF,
it will be blocked. So again, I try to create a game and I make
my name into a script and boom, access is
forbidden. So that's nice, but it's
kind of a crude weapon to just break a
request in such an ugly way. If you're sure you're working
with a hacker here, well, I guess that's good, but I will explain later
why this is a cruder system than you would really like.
Another example of an attack is SQL injection,
famous comic strip where the mother gets a call
about her son and her
son's name is Robert. Quote parenthesis,
semicolon, drop table, student, semicolon, dash, dash,
and little Bobby Tables has been
entered in the database of the school and they've lost all
the student records. Why is this?
Well, if there is a bit of SQL like this
where the first and middle name are inserted into the database,
then it comes out like this. After you put that weird name
in Robert, quote close parenthesis.
Everything after the is a comment and therefore is ignored.
But this drop table students will be run.
Not good. The entire database table is dropped.
Another example of an attack is distributed denial of service. That's where
they pound your server with so many requests that it can't
handle it anymore. Why distributed denial of
service? Why multiple attackers?
Because if it's only one attacker, then your one
server can probably handle it. It's one on one.
Your server can probably handle the load. But if there are hundreds
of attackers pounding your server with requests, it might
crash under the load. The worst type of
threats are application level in your application,
broken access control, incorrect authorization
of page. So what if
you have hundreds of pages, hundreds of PHP's,
jsps, and some of them have
not correctly defined who's allowed to see them
or search. Pages are often very vulnerable this way
because if you're letting your user search in some gigantic mess
of text, and then of course the search results include
snippets of text, do you know where those snippets came from?
Is each one of them authorized to the person who was searching?
But hey, let's toss in Oauth to protect against those threats we mentioned earlier
and many others. How does cloud armor work
how does it protect your system? Here's a sample architecture.
There are end users on the left, and cloud armor attaches to
the load balancing, which importantly decrypts the HTTPs.
That's necessary for cloud armor to look inside and see if it appears to
be a threat. Cloud load balancing then sends the request onwards
either to a backend on Google Cloud compute engine, which is the case
from Aida Scrabble, or it could be kubernetes or many others,
or even outside of the Google cloud. It only
sends on the request. Of course, if it doesn't block the request,
you define the control using policies and rules.
A policy is a collection of many rules arranged in order of priority.
The ones with a lower priority number have a
higher priority. They're going to take precedence over the ones
with a larger priority number. And here's
what the rules look like. Each rule has a match condition and action.
Action could be deny the obvious one. If you see a threat,
allow once you've created a rule that says this
certain particular string really isn't a threat, so let's allow it,
or just log and do nothing else. And the
match condition is often a regular expression,
but it can be many others, which we'll talk about.
It could be an IP address blacklist
or whitelist. Think about your firewall in Google Cloud
or in Amazon. That would be an access control list, a security
group. Or you can block certain IP addresses,
but here you're doing it in the WAF, on the edge so
it's faster blocking before the request even gets
into the cloud. And also the more sophisticated tools
for defining blocks of dangerous IP addresses.
You could block entire geographies. If you only sell in one
country, you might want to block every other country to just say, well, I don't
want anyone from that country. It's not even a question, let's exclude them.
Or a scan of HTTP content, often with a regular expression
where you look for those scripts or other dangerous strings.
Please use the pre configured rule sets.
So Google Cloud armor has some for SQL injection, which I showed you earlier,
cross site scripting which I showed you, and many,
many other potential types of attack. Some smart people put
these rule sets together and they are complicated,
complicated rule sets. You can then
configure them with sensitivity. You can either
say let's be hypersensitive and block, but then you risk some
false positives. You might block something you don't want to,
or let's make it at a very low sensitivity just to get the worst,
most dangerous looking ones. But then we risk false negatives,
but you can make that trade off. I showed you a minute earlier,
SQL injection. It's way more complicated than that.
Each one of these here is a definition from OwAsp
of a different type of SQL injection attack.
The second one, common DB names that detected well, you saw
the database table students. I don't know how common
that is, but the good people at OWASp determined that
if database table names are in there, if database names are in
there, it's more likely to be an SQL injection. And there are hundreds
of these. And in each one of those there are
signatures. I am not expecting you to read
this. In fact, I'm showing this to you to show how complicated it can
be. That is a regular expression as you can detect.
Don't try to read it right now unless you're smarter than me and tags
severity many other definitions of this signature.
Now you can write your own rules if you want. So in this case
we're looking at the user agent header and looking for WordPress
case insensitive in that we might imagine that
a hacker is trying to break into WordPress so we write that rule.
I would suggest that you use the rules the experts wrote
at a far greater degree of sophistication, which addresses false positives
and false negatives better than you probably will be able to.
But when it comes down to it, the WaF won't protect
you. It will not bring you the security you want and
need. The first reason is that you may be blocking your own application.
Here's an example. You have a software engineering forum. People are discussing snippets
of JavaScript. Do you want to block those? Well, I once
entered a bug in a bug reporting
system. There was a security bug. It involved
a JavaScript for cross site scripting and my request disappeared.
I couldn't even report it. Well, of course there was looking
at my report about cross site scripting and blocked it.
So you can't just block these things because they look
somewhat dangerous. And it's not just software engineering
forums or bug reporting systems. Anybody could write some string that looks
a bit like an attack string. You get
false positives in certain cases. If your application is badly
written. Some applications pass JavaScript back and
forth from client to server and then execute it. That is bad.
But if your application is already written that way,
your product manager is not going to like it when you explain why you're blocking
your own functionality. Or more simply,
if your application has hundreds of text fields and unvetted
code written by perhaps unskilled developers.
Or it could be nothing wrong with your system. But the rules are imperfect.
You saw how complicated they are, and they might miss something,
and they might label a request as
an attack when it is not. Job zero is
a secure application. That is your job. You must have
somebody on the team who is responsible for security. Doesn't mean everything
is secure, but you can go to that person and ask what's the situation,
what are our main vulnerabilities? And then every team member must have
some degree of training. After all, you take care of performance
in your code, you take care of usability. At the same time, you have to
always be thinking of security. I can't define
how to secure your app in a few minutes. It is a complicated,
a very complicated profession. But here
are a few simple ideas. One is to escape all strings, so the
top string, as you know, is a potential attack. The lower string
will still be rendered visually as the top string,
but is no longer interpreted as JavaScript.
Or there's a function in the react framework,
dangerously set inner HTML.
Yes, the react team was very worried that you would use it. They're telling
you not to use it. When developers are under stress and it seems
to work and the other one doesn't work,
they use it and they will insert,
let's say, JavaScript without escaping.
You can try sanitizing, which means deleting anything that looks like
an attack script. But I told you a minute ago,
why deleting those all could create false positives.
The only way to handle this is with a security mindset. It must be
in your mind and in the minds of your team members at all times.
That's what they're paid the big salaries for. Let's take another
example of false positive DDoS. So we're looking
for big spikes which probably indicate an attack.
So here we see that there are gigantic numbers
of requests that come all of a sudden on a low traffic website. And maybe
the DDoS system should block it. But oh
no, that is the Australian Open tennis match. And if you
block those spikes, you've blocked the only reason the website exists all year.
There are ways around that. First of all, by planning in advance and turning
off the DDoS protection. Perhaps another is to rely on advanced
machine learning driven features which do exist in
the wafs. IP addresses also
can bring false positives. It's just a number. Do you
know who's using it? Maybe the numbers behind an NAT and shared by hackers
and non hackers. Does your product manager want you to block even r1
customer who in a b two B situation might get very
angry to you, get very angry that the system
is blocking them. Do you want to block an entire country
and completely deny yourself customers from that country?
One way around this is with a dry run, so you can set the WAF
to preview, and then even though the action is in principle
deny, you will only get logs like this log.
This is an abbreviated log and it will basically say
we would have denied the request. And you can look at that and say
oh, we really shouldn't have denied it. My code is awful.
It passes JavaScript on purpose, or we have to accept
that JavaScript here, or we have to change our code.
And therefore you will not endanger yourself with
those false positives. But the problem with preview
is uncertainty. I have seen teams turn on the
preview and wait for months in which they're paying a lot of money as
they try to figure out if given strings that trigger the Waf are really a
danger, not a danger, and they are scared of blocking
because they don't know their own application backwards and forwards. So this is
not a cure all. But in addition to false positives,
you could also have false negatives. They just let the attacks through.
Reg exes, as you learned back in college, are limited as a language. They cannot
catch everything. Besides which,
they have to be fast. Remember, every web request is being scanned by potentially
hundreds of Reg xs before it even gets through. And for
that reason also, only a few kilobytes can be scanned by these
reg xs. And that means that any attack after those kilobytes
will simply be let through. But the worst thing
really is broken access control.
If you left some of your pages open to unauthenticated users,
to all authenticated users, or to the wrong authenticated users.
If you left them open to write for users who should be only read only,
the WAF is helpless. It doesn't know what you
intended when you wrote your application. And the attackers
can shift around too. They can change their IP addresses using a
VPN or whatever. They can also change the country they appear to come from,
and they can change the attacks. Tiny string changes may
get through the regular expression while still carrying an attack.
They are smart, they are human, they are always scheming,
and the WAFs have predetermined rules. There are new machine learning
systems that are flexible, but they are not magic either.
Well, what if you leave yourself some flexibility?
The Wafs do offer that you can configure the policies.
You can exclude a rule from the policy because you think it's
making false positive detections exclude a field, not scanning
a field. But then remember, you're not scanning the field.
Raise or lower the sensitivity. You can create your own rules.
That looks good, but I suggest you
don't do that because the experts have already worked
on the tough balance between false positives and negatives, and if
you try to reduce the false positives, you may be increasing the false
negatives. You don't have a very special
case you think you do, but in fact these attacks
are most often widespread across the industry.
On the other hand, if you have some deep hackers,
then probably nothing you do is going
to help. If state level hackers are
coming in, your tweaking is not going to make the difference.
If you do have a very special case in your code because your code does
something weird, probably you need to take a good look at your code,
not tweaking the WAF rules.
But the WAF is not just imperfect, it may make things worse.
Remember, it looks at your decrypted messages
of each HTTP request. It has to to
see what the risks might be. What if the waf has a bug? The biggest
risk though is complacency as the
temporary becomes permanent as you don't learn new skills.
I compare a WAF to a jewelry store with giant
holes in its concrete walls, and then the jewelry store owner
puts a chicken wire fence around and says, well, it's not perfect, but at least
we have a fence. Yeah, maybe you should be looking at those
big holes in your concrete walls. Besides all
that, the WAF risks performance because it has
to run those rules on every single request. The more rules
to run, the more of a risk to performance.
If we talk about the cost of a system, we should also talk about its
cost. And I'm not going to talk dollar amounts. You can look
those up, and plus they're different wafs. But generally
in the basic form, you pay for each rule you define, each policy
you add, or for a very, very large number of requests.
As with many things in the cloud, so long as your systems
are still under test, so long as you haven't gone viral, these costs
are negligible. When you go big, you can get
an enterprise system in which you pay a monthly fee and not pay
on demand. There are variations of this and pay
perhaps a lesser amount if there are massive amounts of resources going through.
The real risk is if you commit to pay a monthly fee and then
find that there are so many false positives and negatives that despite the risk,
your product manager tells you to back out, then you are paying a lot.
I've said all these bad things about Oauth. What is it
good for? If you have external requirements, like I
mentioned, you have no choice. Then it's not a security choice,
it's a compliance choice. Go ahead. If you
are running a third party app, perhaps a commercial system
where you cannot alter and fix the code, perhaps open source where you don't have
the skills to fix the code, then you can put the WaF
in front of it. You still risk complacency. The WAF isn't magic.
Another use case is central supervision. So you have a security
team in a big company. It hears about a new threat CVE,
like the famous log four j, and it steps into action and
uses the WAF to block it, meanwhile shouting very loudly at
the product team. Now the immediate
response should be, you know, is the product team really going to fix
it? But in this case we're seeing the WAF
as a monitoring tool. And if we choose deny,
allow or preview, then that's actually
to help the central team understand what's happening, temporarily control
it, monitor it, and not just tune the
protection per se. It's part of a process across a large organization.
Another reason to use the WAF is if you absolutely know what you're blocking,
you know there's a hacker coming from a specific IP, or you have a
business partner and you want to whitelist your IP addresses and let no one
else through, and you've chosen not to use a normal firewall. Just some examples.
When you know what you want to block the one go to
feature. So here it's pretty straightforward.
I do recommend OAuth. There are other services
that could come in useful. You can pay to have a human team
on standby from Google Cloud, from Amazon and so on.
You can get event services where you see the attacks as they
increase over time. Let's say they come in waves where
they provide third party IP address lists, for example
for tor nodes, and where they adapt
the protection using machine learning in a more flexible way than
in the basic services. Regardless, if you
are going to do a WAF, let's say for ddos, do it now,
not doing a fire drill. I suggest you
prefer the WAF offered by your cloud service provider,
Google Cloud armor, AWS Shield and so on, because the HTTPS
is probably being decrypted at the load balancer
in typical architectures. So you don't want to decrypt
it in two completely different vendors and
they offer pay as you go. Some of the other vendors do too. But the
importance of pay as you go is that your ramp up period may be far
longer than you expect. In summary,
the minuses of of are first and foremost complacency
that you will not put the resources on it, you will not develop the skills,
you will get false positives and block your own application.
Product managers are willing to take risks or false negatives,
and you'll let the hackers through even though you paid all that money for Oauth.
And they do add risks and slowness of their own.
However, the pluses are that they're easier than do it yourself.
You don't need to change your code and essential tream
can control and monitor and understand
security through the WAF. There are also advanced features
that you probably can provide yourself, like the machine learning driven
adaptive protection or DDoS protection.
In conclusion, security is job zero.
Your job in your app. You cannot hand off responsibility
to anyone else, but there are some cases where a ref is
relevant. You can see my slides here bit
ly waf don't waf
dont. Or you can scan this QR code and
see the slides. And we are hiring. I love my job,
so please email me there whatever you want to discuss.