Jamaica. Make up real
time feedback into the behavior of your distributed systems
and observing changes, exceptions.
Errors in real time allows you to not only experiment with confidence,
but respond instantly to get things working again.
Close.
Hello, everybody. Welcome to my talk. Also, welcome to comfortitude
Chaos Engineering. My name is Kennedy Torkura.
I am the cofounder CTO and c two admitigant, the continuous security
verification platform.
So this leveraging, I'm going to be talking defeating ransomware attacks,
attacks with security chaos engineering. My Twitter
handle is up there, and feel free to reach out to
me to ask questions regarding my talk.
I'm very passionate about this topic, and I'm always wishing,
I'm always available to talk about it. All right,
so firstly, let us look at ransomware.
Right, an overview of ransomware attacks. So,
ransomware, what is it? It is basically a type of malicious
software, which is actually called malware,
that threatens these publish or blocks access to
data or computer systems, usually by encrypting it
until the victim pays a ransom fee
to the attacker. So what ransomware does is
it's similar to what kidnappers do in the
physical world. They kidnap people and
then they ask for some kind of ransom which has to
be paid before they release victims.
Similarly, this is the same method that the
ransomware attackers employ, with the difference that these time
around, these attacks, actually happen in the digital
space. Now, let us look at some statistics about
ransomware attacks that have happened in recent years.
And what we have here in this graph. These pie
chart is actually gotten from the Zofos report,
one of their security reports for last year. And we can
see these, that actually there is 79%
of ransomware. And this
pie chart actually explains the amount of incident
response that they carried out, because this
is a managed security provider. So they kind of offer services
for other companies because of their expertise. And according
to the report from last year, most of
the incidents, response activities that they carried out were
in response of ransomware attacks, 79%.
That is really high. Also, there are a lot of
statistics online if you check about ransomware in the
last one year, 18 months. So what
we see from sonic wall is that there is
148% increase of ransomware
between Q two of 2020 and Q two of 2021.
A lot of ransomware
attacks. Also, we see ransomware attacks,
about 190.4 million ransomware attacks,
just as at q three of last year.
The same from sonic wall. There is also an interesting
report, actually, this is from the FBI. The FBI in
the United States specifically, these have received complaints
just in the first half of last year,
2084 complaints about ransomware
and of course, talking about finances. This time around,
according to cybersecurity Ventures,
victims will pay a total amount of about $265,000,000
because of ransomware by 2031.
So these are just some statistics
about ransomware, how prevalent it is, how it is expanding, how it
is becoming a very huge problem for
enterprises and even people. And it just goes to say
how important it is for us to begin to take
care of or to begin to prevent ourselves from becoming victims of
ransomware. All right, now, we already looked
at some of the impacts of ransomware, but here I
just want to highlight on five main impacts of ransomware attacks.
Of course, the first is financial loss. As we have seen,
there's a lot of loss of financial.
Companies have to pay a lot of money to the
criminals that are behind these ransomware attacks.
There's also data laws because oftentimes,
even after paying ransom,
the agents, the malicious people behind ransomware attacks, they do
not return all the data. Sometimes these don't even return.
They don't even hand over the encryption keys or even if these do
that, these are reports that the victims are
never able to recover. All the data that got missing,
got lost as a result of the attack. And of course, these is also
reputation damage. Okay, so the reputation
of a company is badly smeared. If they
fall victim to these attacks, they have
to do a lot of communication tactics,
firstly to their customers, to their investors, to the public.
They have to apologize. And it's a bad reputation
for a company. And they have to spend a lot of money, a lot
of resources to be able to repair this reputation
if they are ever able to do that. Legal implications
also, this is really huge nowadays,
especially for companies that are in Europe, we got the GDPR
and usually what around somewhere, as we'll see later on,
is a culmination of many attacks.
Right? The attackers go through multiple steps. And it's
often the case that some of
these attacks actually expose data, as we have seen.
And it's often the case where it either directly
violates regulations like GDPR,
or it's also the problem where customers of a
company that is a victim of ransomware actually take
the company to the court. They take the company
because sometimes ransomware impacts their
own activities. It makes the customers lose money, it makes
them lose resources, and they take the company that
provided a service to them to court and becomes a legal case.
And of course, it disrupts business. Right? In Germany
here, a few months ago, a company called Mediamact,
which is one of the biggest online retail shops,
they were attacked by ransomware. Now, this ransomware
actually made it impossible for
PoS systems to be used in
the shops so the people could buy,
they could not actually pay for services for products these
bought. And this disrupted a lot of business activities. So ransomware,
one of the biggest impacts it has, which we feel immediately,
is the fact that was a company, your business is disrupted,
you cannot serve your customers, you cannot go about your normal
activities. It's a big pain.
All right, now let us look at the steps,
right? And as I said before, ransomware is
a combination of multiple steps. In fact,
before a ransomware becomes successful, it means
the attackers have carried out multiple
attacks against the infrastructure, against the victim.
And in the end,
they are able to kind of identify that material,
they're able to identify that resource that is very critical to you,
so critical that they can place a huge amount of money
and you're going to pay. So what
I'm showing here on the screen is about a specific ransomware
called winter two. And this,
Rama, is actually a ransomware that targets windows operating systems.
And usually the infection vector is through RDP.
And they actually also use phishing
attacks to
target their victims, which might be employees of a company, they might
be normal individuals. And they're also distributed using
ransomware as a service, which is another
factor that has made ransomware to become very rampant
these days. Because what ransomware as a service does is
it lowers the entry barrier for people who want to conduct,
who want to use these attacks because they don't need to have, again,
the technical capabilities to develop ransomware.
These don't have to write it from the scratch. They just go to the
service provide of ransomware, which are usually available
in the dark web. And they go there and buy the tools and
they even offer them services and they buy it at a cheap
rate and they are able to use it. So the
important thing about this slide here is just to show the attack
can of Wadrama. So Wadrama, as I said before,
starts with an RDP brute force attack, and then
the next thing is it scans for connectivity and
also for new targets. The interesting thing in step three there
is you see that the ransomware itself, tons of
security controls, so it has the capability
to identify that you're using maybe some firewalls or some
antivirus devices or any software
that might detect its presence, and it switches it off.
It does another network reconnaissance to kind of understand
your network, to understand your keys to the kingdom,
to understand what kinds of resources are more critical
to you. As a victim, based on that,
it might move, literally, it might move from one resource to the other,
from one network to the other. And other things, as you see
in step five that might occur is credential
theft. So they begin to see your credentials.
They want to gain root access to certain resources
in your network. They place a backdoor so that they can
actually, if at all, you detect them at this point in time
and you flush them out of the system, they leave backdoors
which will enable them to come back to your system
along the way, you see, they also have con miner
to mine bitcoins in the victim
system. And the last step, which is step eight,
is where they actually ask for ransomware.
So you can see that there's a lot of work that they have to do.
There's a lot of security loopholes that they have to exploit along the
way. Eventually, they arrive at a
place where they feel confident enough that they have verified a
resource that is so important that
they can place a high price tag on it and they can
force their victims to pay
for this resource to be returned
or to pay for the decryption key of
the resource. Okay,
so we have looked at ransomware, and now how
about these cloud. Okay, so do we have ransomware that happen in the cloud?
There is a lot of misconceptions about ransomware in the cloud,
and we're going to be looking at some of those ones. Firstly,
what we have seen in recent years is that ransomware has
actually, the attackers, the perpetrators of ransomware attacks,
are now beginning to target cloud based systems,
cloud infrastructures, cloud native systems. And why
is that? Well, one of the major drivers of this change of
tactics is the Covid-19 pandemic.
All right, so Covid-19 has come and we are
still in the pandemic. Hopefully, we are out of it very soon.
However, many companies have realized
that they have to transform these infrastructure.
They are undergoing the digital transformation and they are moving
to the cloud because these cloud offers for them most
of those facilities that will help their systems to be
agile, to be elastic, to be robust.
One of the major problems about moving to the cloud,
amongst many other challenges that people face when they move to the cloud,
is the fact that especially for companies,
for enterprises that have both on premises and cloud systems,
the line between on premises and cloud systems
actually is blurred. Right. It is blurred because some
cloud service providers make it so easy for
the on premises and the in cloud infrastructure to
connect. And so this connection becomes
a good bridge for attackers to also leverage. And they
can actually leverage such connections to
easily attack or to move, move laterally from on
premises systems to cloud based systems.
The next thing is misconception. So one of them that I have heard about
is the cloud is immune to ransomware,
right? The cloud is not immune to ransomware.
Cloud is not immune. These cloud offers in the cloud,
these is the shared responsibility model, which is one
of the models that is not well understood by most customers
or most people who migrate to the cloud.
Right. As a user of the cloud, you got your
own responsibility. You have a lot of things to take care
of, especially everything that is referred to as
a logical security measure. You got to take care of it.
So because of that infrastructure
like object story, like x ray buckets on AWS,
a lot of the security measures that have
to be put in place are a responsibility of customers.
And we will see an attack in the next few slides that
actually shows how s these buckets are
being targeted and being used, have been targeted
during ransomware attacks. All right,
so one of the key things I wanted to take from this
slide is that the implications of ransomware in the cloud
could be worse than the implications
in traditional or on premises environments.
And the major thing is because firstly,
most cloud resources are misconfigured.
According to Gartner, 99% of cloud
resources are going to fall to attacks because
of misconfigurations. So there is a high chance that attackers
are going to get access,
they're going to get privileged access, are they going to leverage it,
and they're going to get access to resources
that they can use for ransomware. All right,
so what are the countermeasures that are in place now?
There are a lot of countermeasures that have been put out there
for ransomware. A lot of them are written
provided by the cloud service providers themselves. There are
also countermeasures that are provided by different security vendors
or security organizations.
One of the important things, as we have seen, that ransomware is a combination
of multiple attacks, is that you have
to enable a defense in depth security
architecture. Your security architecture has got to be layered.
It is a layered security system that can actually
detect or proven ransomware.
So what we see on this slide,
these is basically a very nice way of
describing defense in depth. We see that
one of the first layers of ransomware countermeasures
is training and awareness. Right. You have to train your employees.
They have to understand the basics of cyber hygiene.
They have to understand that they are targets to things like
phishing emails, and they
have to avoid the temptation of clicking links
that seem malicious. So basically,
there are four main types
of controls. When we talk about defense in depth,
there are the preventive controls, which include things like
firewalls, authentication and authorization, identity and
access management systems. These are also the detective
controls, which actually detect malicious activities in
your environment that might be indicators of compromise
regarding sims and login systems.
Then we also have recovery controls. Right? Recovery controls
are those controls that will help a compromised
system to come back to life to resume
its normal activities. And what are these controls?
These include things like backups, disaster recovery
methods, incident response,
and of course, I've already talked about security awareness.
In summary, most of the ransomware countermeasures
fall under these four controls.
Now, you might be wondering, okay,
what has this to do with security chaos engineering?
Right? And I'm here today to tell you that security chaos
engineering is one of the robust
or one of the best ways you
can actually prevent yourself from becoming
a victim of ransomware attacks. Now, security case
engineering is the identification of security control failures
through proactive experimentation to build confidence in
the system's ability to defend against malicious conditions.
Right. And we're going to be looking a little bit into it.
We are in chaos engineering conference. So I
want to believe that most of the audience already are sort of used
or have heard of chaos engineering.
Chaos engineering. Security chaos engineering, actually,
it implements most of the techniques or
the methods or the approaches of chaos engineering.
However, this time around, the focus is on security. The focus
is on security attributes, on confidentiality,
integrity, and availability.
All right, so let's look at how
security cares engineering is what it actually means.
So basically, in security career,
the first thing that you do in security case
engineering is to define your hypothesis. In these case,
you're talking about security faults. It's about injecting security faults
into your infrastructure so that you can verify
if the security controls are functioning was you expect
them to function. All right? And this infrastructure
could be code, source code, could be things like docker containers,
could be cloud infrastructure, could be kubernetes clusters.
In the end, you're actually conducting those
security faults so that you will perceive
or you will verify if your preventive
controls, like the ones we just talked about in the last slide, if they are
working as they should work. And because this
is security, at the end of the day, there are three main things in your
infrastructure or in your security architecture that you
want to prevent, right?
You want to make sure that the security attributes, which are confidentiality,
integrity, and availability are not violated.
Any violation of these is a security breach. It's a security
problem. It might lead to cyberattacks,
it might lead to a lot of problems. So at
the core of security chaos engineering is for the protection
of the attributes of security, which are confidentiality,
integrity and availability.
Now let us look at an example scenarios of
a ransomware. In this case, it is a bucket ransomware attack.
Now, during a bucket ransomware attack, the attacks
basically, and there are various ways this
could be conducted. The scenario we're going to be using today is just a
hypothetical one which might happen. So in these case,
firstly, the attacker creates a user called Bob.
And after creating these user, that user,
Bob tries to get access to an EKS
cluster, a kubernetes cluster on Amazon Web services. By the way,
these scenario is typically based on Amazon Web services
and actually could be applied to even every other cloud service
provider since they have similar.
So. Well, Bob tries to get access to the EKS clusters.
He's able to get access to it. He compromises
one of the clusters, a pod in the cluster.
From there, he gets to understand that this pod
is actually looking towards an s three bucket.
And this pod is actually either dumping
information or retrieving information from an s three bucket. And it's able
to understand that that s, these bucket actually has information that
is very critical, maybe things like credit card information or
Social Security numbers or
it could be anything that is very delicate for the company.
And so the next thing it does is to move forward,
take over the bucket, encrypt it, request for ransomware.
And that is more or less the lifecycle of
a ransomware attacks. Okay.
What's interesting for us here is, well, in this scenario
could be actually a security chaos engineering experiment
that you're conducting for your AWS infrastructure.
And what you're going to be looking for, firstly, is in
the first step of this attack,
let's call it in this attack actually, where a
user is created, you want to understand,
okay, the detective controls that have been put in place. And this could
be like cloud security posture management systems. It could be like the
AWS config. These are security controls
that should identify when
unauthorized access is carried out
or these should actually identify unauthorized access. They should
identify when people who are not supposed
to create new resources are creating new resources like
a user. And this is something that you will expect
these kinds of tools to detect in
the next step. As we discussed, the attacks
went forward and got access to an eks cluster
and then went forward to compromise one of the pods.
Right. And from a security standpoint, you're going to be interested
to understand whether these activities that
were done by the attacker before he successfully
compromised a pod, if any of the Kubernetes
security controls detected this
exploitation, if it was detected,
whether threat detection tools like AWS guard duty
or security hub that are actually supposed to detect
the range of activities that will be
conducted,
understand, by an attacker to be able to
really conduct this attack.
Okay. And now we get to the point where the attacks
actually compromises the s, these bucket.
And even in this case, these are a lot of activities.
Like I said, for the attacker to identify
that this bucket has sensitive information,
there is going to be a lot of reconnaissance, there's going to be a lot
of probing attacks,
and these are attacks that should be detected.
These are specific commands against an s three bucket that
should be deemed as malicious. And you will
expect also, again, that things like the access analyzer
of AWS that kind of identifies when access to
resources are suspicious, you expect it
to kind of fire up an alert or from the security
hub and such tools.
Yes. And we finally get to the point where the
attack is successful. And as a victim, you're already asking yourself
whether to pay or not to pay because you
already saw the request from the attacker for a ransom,
right? And this is the point where incident response is actually
triggered. Incident response in most cases is triggered
at the end, after the attack is almost
successful or is already successful after these ransom has been
requested for. Of course. And these
is the point, again where things like backups are, people begin
to try to trigger their backups to bring
their system back to life, to resume their business activities.
And you want to ask whether are your backups even accessible?
Are they usable? Are these already corrupted?
Are they run books that you use for incident response? Are they
even accurate? Are they functional? Are they updated?
Now these are questions that are very interested, very interesting
from a security chaos engineering experiments.
So how do we even run these experiment? So there is
a concept of game days, which are specific periods that are set
aside to conduct security chaos engineering experiments, right?
So game days are usually used by DevOps,
by sres, to conduct experiments that
kind of test how robust or their systems
are, how available they are, how they can respond to incident
response. But security game days this time around
are with a security focus.
I will not go into details of the components
of people who should attend this sort of
security game days, but essentially you're going to be having your security team
there. You're going to be having maybe some sres, anybody who
is actually part of the security incident
response mechanism or lifecycle.
You want that person to be part of the game days, part of the security
game days.
All right. Now you might
also be thinking about what kinds
of security activities should constitute or are
good candidates for security chaos engineering.
And there is a very good resource that was released by
Amazon Web Services called these ransomware risk management
on AWS using the NIST cybersecurity framework.
And in this document, there are a lot of possibilities.
These are a lot of recommended practices that should constitute
either prevention, detection, or recovery from ransomware.
Agreed again, that these are very specific to Amazon
Web services, but again, they are similar
resources that you will find in other cloud
service providers. So what are these things? There are things
like, we have already mentioned some of them. Things like checking if
backups are already in place,
whether they are well configured, corruption testing,
deny listing, looking at things like your EC, two security groups,
route 53,
if all of these AWS resources
are well configured to prevent or to detect
or to even recover from ransomware.
So go check these resource out
and I'm sure that you're going to have
some good insights as in where to start running
your game days from.
One important topic I want to talk about here is about continuous verification
of runbooks, right? So we all know that runbooks are extremely
helpful for security incident response and also
for even normal incident response. Basically,
runbooks carry these compose
of certain steps that are written that
can be executed in an incident response scenarios
and which helps these operators to actually be a little
bit help the operators to be a little
bit proactive. Now,
runbooks are very useful. However,
security incident response in cloud environment introduces a
lot of challenges, right? And these challenges kind of impact
or kind of limit how efficient runbooks can
be. All right. One of the challenges is because in
the cloud infrastructure is constantly changing.
Infrastructure is not static. Therefore,
this means that runbooks also cannot be
static. Runbooks have to be updated periodically,
as often as possible. And also these
runbooks have to be aligned with the
current state of the infrastructure.
And this is very important because security teams, they gain
confidence by exercising runbooks.
All right, before I conclude, I just want to highlight about some relevant
resources. Since I come from an academic research
background. During my doctoral
research, I did a lot of research about security Chaos
engineering. And some
of these papers are already published. And if
want good materials that will support your security chaos engineering journey.
Yeah, these are some nice materials that will help you.
And I also had a chance to be one of the contributing authors to
the first book on security chaos engineering.
And this was released last year. I was very lucky
to be invited by Aaron Reinhardt and Kelly Shortridge.
And this book has also very good content around security chaos
engineering.
All right, so this is the last slide. And,
yeah, just to mention some important points again.
Firstly, ransomware is a real threat.
Cloud environments are not immune to ransomware attacks
they can suffer from, and there are attacks that happened in
real life. Also, security chaos engineering
provides for you, means that you can verify your security
posture. And this includes ransomware. Right. You can use security chaos
engineering to check whether you are
resistant to ransomware attack, to check
if whatever measure that
you have put in place to either detect
or prevent or even recover you from ransomware.
You can actually use security chaos engineering to check
whether those controls are working as you
kind of expect these to work. All right, so thank you very much
for listening to my talk. I am readily
available for you online or on Twitter to
answer your questions around this topic. Have a nice conference.
Right.