You. Hello everyone, my name is Mohammed
Azmil. I'm the founding engineer of imesh. Since past few years
I've worked on various cloud native applications ranging from high performance backends
to blockchains to full stack apps. With imesh, I help
enterprise adopt Istio into their large scale production workloads.
I'm very thankful to Con 42 for having me here,
and today I'll be discussing on ambient mesh, which sync is the new
sidecarless and faster istio for zero. Trust a
bit about imesh. We formed in 2023.
We offer enterprise grade istio support, and we also offer
a dashboard called Imesh Dashboard, which you can use to
monitor your istio workload with a mission to simplify and
secure your microservices in the cloud. In today's
session, we'll be having a look at understanding what is istio service mesh?
What are the limitations of the existing service mesh, and we'll
be understanding what istio ambient mesh is all about. What are the security
and other benefit that it comes with. We'll be having a demo as well
where we'll be using istio ambit mesh with mtls. We'll be
applying l four and l seven authorization policies, do traffic management
and do observability with open source tool that come with Istio,
and a lot more. So we have quite a lot of meshes to cover,
and I'm sure it's a tongue twister for you as well. So buckle
up. And here we go. So in istio documentation,
you can find that a service mesh is a dedicated infrastructure layer that
helps you add capabilities like observability, traffic management and
security without adding them to your code. So for someone who
is not aware of service Imesh, it's basically a layer. It's kind of like a
pluggable layer, which you add while you're deploying your workload so that you
get observability, traffic management and security out of the box.
Let's have a look at istio service mesh architects, the one with the sidecars.
So as you can see, there are two major components to it, one being the
control plane, another being the data plane. So the control plane, which is
essentially istio, is responsible for injecting sidecars to all
the workloads when a namespace is enabled for istio injection.
So if the namespace is enabled for istio injection, all the pods
are going to be deployed along with a sidecar,
which is nothing but on web proxy. And this on web proxy is
the central point where you do traffic management, observability and mtls,
all those things that istio provides. Now, once the sidecar is deployed
to a particular servit, it internally intercepts the traffic.
Whatever is going to the service is now going through the onboard proxy and
then to the service. This is the traditional istio servicemas
architecture. Istio also provides ingress and egress gateways which
are envoy proxies themselves, but later on that once we go to
the demo. There are various limitations to the sidecar
approach, the most pertinent one being the sidecar itself.
Since each of your workload needs to be injected with the sidecar, it results
in modification of the pod spec and it redirects the traffic within
the pod. Also, if you have a massive workload like 4000 or
5000 pods, or even more, even the
lightweight sidecar, when it is deployed on such a massive workload,
causes a massive resource utilization. The traffic capture
stb processing, which are very computationally expensive, are done all
at the sitecar level. It manages l four routing, l seven
routing, l seven observability, l four observability
there's quite a lot of going on, and if you have to update the sidecar,
then good luck. You have to restart the entire application. There is no
midway approach that you can update half of the sidecar
and leave the rest running in an older version. The service first protocol
is also a massive issue with the current service. Mesh architects
with the sidecar as it impacts the permissive mtls and it's very
tough to work with and it doesn't even work properly for
nonconformant HTTP implementations. How about
we break it down? Instead of one sidecar dealing
with l four and l seven and doing everything in between, we separate the
concerns using two different layer, one for the l four secure
overlay, another for the l seven processing layer. The MTLS
tunneling, simple authorization, TCP metric logging
and routing. All of them can be taken care at the l four level,
whereas in the l seven layer you have rich authorization policies, metrics,
logging, routing and everything that you need. The ambient mesh
does exactly the same thing. It takes care of l four and l seven responsibilities
differently. There are two components to it. One is the
ztunnel, another is the waypoint proxy. Ztunnel,
short for zero trust tunnel, helps you to securely connect and authenticate
your workloads in the mesh. It is extremely lightweight as it
does not do anything related to l seven processing. All it does is
provide mtls and l four authorization. Waypoint proxy,
however, is the one providing you with l seven capabilities and
it is not mandatory to deploy waypoint proxy. You can deploy it
on basis of a namespace or maybe even service account depending on
your l seven use cases. So ztunnel, if it sees that
there is a waypoint proxy, will pass all its traffic through it so that the
l seven policies are being evaluated there, and it
again goes back through the other ztunnel to the respective workload.
And you can see that waypoint proxies are nothing but envoy proxies themselves.
And ztunnel is a different application which is written in rust,
making it very performant. Waypoint proxies are like
simple kubernetes pods which are deployed in a particular namespace. So if
your traffic is higher you can easily scale them up or down, which is
pretty easy. Let's understand what is HTTPs
connect tunnel ztunnel uses this to communicate with other ztunnel
and waypoint proxies as well. It uses Hbone,
the HTTP based overlay network environment, to encapsulate
all the traffic that is coming through the ztunnel into a single port which
is exported, as in this case that is port 15,008.
You can see the Ztunnel might be listening at port 84,
three and other particular ports from a particular
workload, but at the end of the day it's kind of encapsulating everything
in the Hbone and exported through one single port.
As a result, the ztunnel doesn't has to manage a lot of
connections with the other ztunnel or waypoint proxy, making it very simple
as there is only one port which is exported and the entire
traffic is kind of going in this kind of packet as you can see below.
So this clear encapsulation provides better interoperability
with load balancer infrastructure. It also works well with the existing
envoycar, the istio sitecar mesh. And as a
result we also have a better support for server first
protocols for your MySQL and other databases where the server
kind of makes the first connection. Now let's understand
how secure Ztunnel actually is. For those of you who know
Spiffy, the secure production identity framework for everyone,
it's similar to the workload attestation process. So here
you can see the sleep pod is trying to interact with the Echo
server on a different node and everything is going through
ztunnel and then a waypoint proxy and the communication is happening.
So in between we have SvID, which is spiffy, verifiable identity to
verify a particular service here. Since the spiffy
says sorry, the Svid says that it's from NS NS
one SA sle sleep. We know that it's coming from the sleep service
and then it has to go to the echo service. And this is how the
Zetaner goals from where to route the traffic. So what's happening
is for generating the certificates for a particular service
or particular workload. So istio is the one that acts
as the root ca. You can configure it to use a different root ca,
but istio in this case acts as the certificate authority.
Zunnel here assumes the identity of a workload which is running
on its node, and it acts as a node agent
in terms of spiffy. It then sends a CSR request to
the istio control plane on behalf of this particular service
to get its identity back. Istio control plane then signs
it and returns the X 509 certificate to the ztunnel.
Here istio control plane is kind of acting like the spiffy server
which signs the certificates for a particular workload, and this is how the
entire certificates are being managed in the service mesh.
Now let's have a look at ztunnel in action. This is not the actual demo.
We'll be having a demo further in the session. This is just to see
ztunnel in action. And as shown in example here we have
a sleep pod which is trying to talk to an echo server in a different
node. This is a local kind cluster and I'm using two nodes here
which I'll simply use TCP dump and listen for port 80
and the port 1508 which is the hbone port and
the same thing here as well. I'll be doing that and if
I run this I get the response. And also
here you can see the traffic is not encrypted.
We can see the request body and the entire response zero trust
adding spaces below. Now let's install istio and enable the namespaces
to use the Istio ambient meshtio
CtL install set profile
ambient. We'll be having a look at all the configurations and
all add in the session. This is just to show ztanel in
action. Let's give it some time to install everything
and once it is done we just need to label the
namespaces with istio IO
dataplane mode
equal ambient so that the ambient
mesh, the namespaces are kind of in the
mesh. Now I'm running the same thing.
We are getting the response back, but if you see here the entire traffic
is encrypted. You're not seeing anything that
we saw previously, and these are
kind of the logs for the different ztunnels and all communicating.
But every traffic here is encrypted.
So yeah, this, you can see the ztanel in action and how it
does mtls. It's just pretty easy. It works out of the box.
Now, what could be a better time than this to discuss the benefits of ambient
mesh? We trust saw Ztanel in action, and this is as easy
as it can be. So the first benefit is that
it can be used without modifying an existing workload.
It is a non invasive method of using the service mesh.
You don't have to modify pod spec or do any internal traffic
rerouting in a pod. I just labeled the namespace,
everything was working, and once we go to the demo, we'll be able to see
it even further in action. There is zero downtime.
You don't have to wait for any sidecar to be injected and running so that
you can say that hey, my service mesh is up and running.
It is very minimal in terms of cost because
you're not deploying sidecars for every particular workload. So that
makes it really cheap, both from the cost perspective and
the resource utilization perspective. It is interoperable
with all the sidecar based istio, even non istio workloads.
So yeah, this is kind of like the
best solution of istio you could ever imagine.
Okay, without any delay, I'll be jumping straight to the demo,
since after seeing ztanel in action, I'm sure you might be wanting the whole
picture. So let's hope everything goes well.
So this is my cluster setup for the demo. I'm using aks cluster
with two nodes, and this is the node specification,
as you can see. And I'll be using the Istio version of 118
three. So the way this demo will progress is that
we'll be starting with this particular architecture, and we'll kind of keep adding
bits and pieces to it. And as you can see, there is just one
namespace in node one and another namespace in node
two. Each namespace is going to have sleep and not
sleep pods. However, the echo server in ns one is just one
deployment and ns two. It has two versions,
v one and v two, for us to understand traffic management as well.
Now, we'll quickly go over the configuration for these deployments.
So here you can see we have two files, resources ns one and resources
ns two, responsible for kind of deploying
various workloads in different namespaces. So I am
defining the namespace here, and I'm also labeling it with Istio
IO data plane mode ambient, so it is taken into
the ambient mesh when you install it. So right now we won't be
having any istio. So whatever you install here, it's simply going to kind
of be there. And then I have service account for
echo service and I'm using service account for the waypoint proxies,
that's why I'm creating it. There is an echo service and then the deployment.
Same thing with sleep server and not sleep. There is a service
account, a service and a deployment. The only thing different
in resources ns two is the namespace, and the Echo server deployment is
having both v one and v two here.
So now we'll quickly install the workloads.
So all we have to do is apply those two files,
ns one resources, ns one.
Here it's creating the namespace services,
deploying everything switch for some time,
and we'll also deploy ns two. And done.
Awesome. So let's see what we have. In NS one.
We have our echo server, we have a not sleep and sleep pods,
the services, the deployments, everything is up and running.
Let's go to ns two. And we do have two
echo server here, one for V one, another for V two.
So everything up and running here as well. Let's have a look at the
pods and see if they are deployed in the right nodes.
The namespace two is running on this particular node,
one and ns one.
All the workloads would be running in the node.
Now moving to step two, what we'll be doing is we'll be installing istio,
and in this case I'll be installing istio with the ingress gateways as
well. In the trailer you had seen just the ambient mesh
istio, but here we'll be needing the istio ingress gateways.
So yeah, let's just copy the command
from here. Oops,
this much? Yeah, I'm lazy. I'm just copy
pasting commands. Oh, my bad. What did I do?
Command not found. Yikes.
Looks like demo gods are not with me.
Let's give it some time. It's going to take some time to install
istio. Core has installed. We have the istio D here,
the CNIs ingress gateways, everything is going to get
installed. We'll be having a look at the istio namespace as well,
to see what all things it has. So once
it's done for injection, okay,
cool. Get ns. We'll be having an
istio system namespace, which is by default.
And let's see kubectl
get all steer system.
Okay, maybe I need to reduce the size
a bit. Yeah, so here you can see we have the Steocanis
that are running on different different one for
each node we have the ingress gateway, we have the control brain,
and we have a ztunnel which is running on both the
nodes. We have the ingress gateway as well. And if
we have a look at the pods, you can see
one ztunnel is running in this particular node, another ztunnel is running
in this node. So we have installed Istio successfully
and well after that
we'll also be installing the gateway APIs.
We'll be needing this ahead in the demo.
Since I've already installed that in my cluster,
I won't be running it. You can simply use this command to install it.
This is just to install the Kubernetes gateway
APIs. Now since we have installed Istio,
let's install Prometheus, Grafana and Kiali. All the observability tools
here as well. So I don't have the ML files
here, I have it in a different location. So I'll simply be
going there Opensource 18.3
and then we can simply copy paste the command.
However, I don't recommend copy pasting it from PDF anyways.
You'll be having everything in GitHub. I'll make sure I'll add a proper readme
to it as well so you can use it properly.
Okay, Prometheus is installed. Let's install Yali
and Grafana as well. Awesome. With this
we have installed istio ambient mesh and all
the related add ons to it.
Now let's go ahead. Now in the next step we'll be labeling
our namespace so that it is ambit Imesh enabled,
which I've already done in my configuration. So if
you haven't done it, or maybe you're using a different namespace
which was pre created, you can simply label it like this. Now let's test
it with the Kubectl exec command and see if it's working
or not. Okay,
and while we are here, we might also need to execute
into the Z tunnels as
well, so I'll be doing that.
Before that, let me paste this command and format
it so it works.
Let's log the ztunnels cubectl log.
You can see it's kind of having all the
xds and all service discovery and all is going on.
Okay, what was the other pod?
Cool. So we have these eternal logs printed
here. Now let's run this command.
Nice. We are having a response back. It's coming from
v two. And yeah, in this case it might come from v two. V one.
We are not doing any load balancing stuff yet,
so let it come from wherever it is coming.
Yeah. Now we are having it from v one. And you can see it's
logging all the inbound and outbound proxies. This, you can see,
is basically the kind of Ip of this particular
services, these ztunnel services.
And we have the logs here as well, that it is having an inbound consumption.
We have a residue printed here as well. So we know from where the traffic
is coming. So, yeah, you can see the Z tunnel
is actually working pretty fine here.
And maybe if I do get
SVC system.
Okay, let's see what we have next.
We have already enabled ambient mesh. And next we'll be
having a look at the authorization policies. So we'll be doing two things
here. One is that first, by default we'll block all the requests.
And in the next, what we'll be doing, we'll be specifically
allowing ns one sleep, ns one to talk to
echo ns two. Now, let's have a look at
the configurations at first. So this is the deny all l four.
Basically, if you create an authorization policy here,
I'm just giving the name of the authorization policy and which namespace it belongs
to. So then you can see that if you don't
provide any specifications to it by default, if you simply create an
authorization policy, it's going to deny everything. So let's
see that in action. I'm going here.
Cubectl, apply f, deny all
l four and just created the authorization policies.
And. Yeah, let's sde
if that works.
Copied the command here. So here we're trying to
talk from sleep ns one to echo server
ns two. And we'll be getting a command
terminated with exit code 56. So this is the
policy is basically blocking us to do that even in the same namespace.
If I just want to talk to echo server one,
it's still going to block it. It won't allow anything, any, any communication.
It won't allow. So now let's have a look at
how to enable communications for NS two. Echo server in
NS two. This is the configuration to
it. Sorry, this one. So again, similar to
the deny all one, we are creating an
authorization policy and we are naming it as allow inbound to echo
ns two. You can name it anything you want. And the
namespace as well. We are giving here,
and in the specification, we are simply giving the
match label for the app, which is echo server ns two, and we
are giving the rule. So this action could be either you can allow it,
you can deny, it depends. All of these you can see in the istio
documentation regarding the authorization policies. It's pretty clear there.
So here you can see from, I'm just giving a source.
And in opensource I have to list the principle. So here I'm listing that.
Okay, you allow only the request that is coming from sleep
account ns one. This is very similar to the SVid you are seeing.
It's saying that in local cluster from NS one, just allow
sleep service one to kind of send requests to this guy.
Anything else would be blocked. So let's apply this policy.
Cubectl apply f,
allow communications from Echo ns two,
Yaml once it is applied. Now if we
go back and we try to communicate from NS one sleep to
echo server in NS two, this should work and this
should give us the response back and we have it.
And now if I try to do the same thing with not
sleep, which is in NS one, it would give an error
to me. And even if I tried to do it with sleep,
which is in the same namespace as that of Echo server, that is ns two,
it won't work. Right. So different exit code it is
giving. You can refer the documentation for this. But yeah, on the whole, the L
four authorization policies are working great here. So as
we can see, it is blocking the traffic and it is doing all the things.
Now, next we have got allowing traffic through the ingress gateway.
So this is, we have seen that we are communicating through the,
you can say we are kind of exec into the sleep pod and then we
were just writing curl command to communicate. Now what we'll
do next is we'll allow Ingress Gateway, which is the Istio
ingress gateway, to communicate with Echo NS one,
the Echo server in n namespace one. For this we need to apply the
Istio gateway Yaml file, which is the standard istio gateway. If I
simply go there and you can see in the configuration
I bills, just increase the font size a bit. You can
see we are creating a gateway.
Again, it's just the Kubernetes gateway type. The only selector is this
istio ingress gateway. Okay. And then we are
saying that for port 80, just allow from all the hosts.
So this is pretty standard gateway configuration.
Same thing with the virtual service, the istio
virtual service that we have seen up until now with the sidecar ones
as well. It's just giving a name for a particular namespace.
I'm specifying that use this particular gateway, which is gateway NS
one that I've made here. And all you have to do is route
all the traffics to the NS one service.
I need to apply this file. So if I
go here and I do kubectl, apply f
istiogateway yaml,
it's going to apply everything. And you can also
do it, you can just get the gateway right.
We have applied Gateway NS one, and also the virtual service,
it's associated with this particular gateway. And this is
the external ip for the ingress gateway. Now let's
copy and go over to Google Chrome and see.
So right now you'll be seeing that the connection error is happening because
remember, we applied deny all. So yeah,
it still won't allow the traffic until you enable it externally.
So there's another file which is simply saying similar to what we saw for
the Echo NS two that allow all the inbound
traffic that is coming from the Istio ingress gateway.
Now, istio ingress Gateway itself has a service account, and this is
just what we are referring to right now. Let me apply this
file communication
to echo NS one. And once the authorization
policy is applied, simply go ahead and refresh it.
And now you can see I'm getting everything. You can also see I'm getting
the envoy headers here. So yeah, nice.
We have an external gateway is to ingress gateway, and that is
working well with the ambient mesh workloads.
So moving ahead, we'll be having a look
at the l seven authorization policies. We'll see how to
generate the waypoint proxies. How do you apply waypoint proxies?
So what we'll be doing is we'll be restricting the
sleep ns one to echo ns two communication to only get request.
We won't allow any post or delete or any such request.
So let's first generate the waypoint,
and before using there you can also
get the authorization policies, whatever you applied using the get authorization policy
command in Kubectl. In this case, in NS one,
I think only two were applied, one for the inbound from the
istio ingress, and another was the denial.
Now let's have a look at how to generate the waypoint proxy. You can
use the istio command. X stands for experimental
waypoint generate nns two
and s, which is not the service, but the service account,
which in this case was echo server service
account ns two. Let me quickly verify
it. If that's the case, yeah, eco service account. Okay. Not the
server. Nice.
Okay, so this, as you can see, it has
generated the standard Kubernetes gateway API, yaml. You can see
the kind is gateway. The only difference is that you have an annotation
which specifies that this is for which service account.
In this case, it is for echo service account ns two. And we
have the name here as well. It's just taking the same service account name and
putting it as a name and namespaces. Ns two,
in specification, we are specifying that the gateway class is istio waypoint
and just a listener for the hbone. For the Hbone.
Okay, so what I've done is actually you
can directly apply it from here as well instead of generate. If you hit
apply, it would still work. So what I've
done is I've copied this over to a file and I've just changed the gateway
name so it won't be confusing because we already
have the names similar to what we had in the service account name.
So let's apply this file instead. Again, it's a standard Yaml
file. You can apply, it doesn't matter.
Waypoint proxy, yaml enter.
Nice. We have created the gateway.
Okay, now let's have a look.
Cubectl, get gateway.
NS two. See, we have an echo service.
And to gateway, the class is istio proxy. It has
its own address as well, which you can see the gateway
name and the istio vapor and proxy. But let's
also get the pod in ns two.
Now you can see there is a service, the waypoint
proxy pod here as well, which is running.
So as we had seen, that waypoint is just a pod.
It's nothing different. It's just a pod that is running.
You can scale it as and when you like.
Let's just log it and see what
is happening there. Pretty standard on
web proxy logs here. You can see nothing fancy here.
Anyways, so we have deployed that. Now let's again
try to query the ns two.
Echo service is ns two with service
one. So right now, I haven't applied any l seven policies
yet. We simply have the waypoint proxy and we are just
doing the curl command now. Trust, see what happens if
I run it. So previously we had already applied the l four
authorization policies to deny all, and then we
allowed the communication. But since I have applied the Waypoint proxy as well,
I am getting an RBAC error here saying
that access is denied because right now we have the Waypoint proxy,
but we are again not allowing what things we need to do.
So the default is basically it's getting access denied in
this case. So in order for us to allow the get
request, we can make another policy authorization
policy. In this case it is going to be an authorization policy
for l seven. As you can see, I am having a gateway name
associated with it, and in this case I'm using the same gateway
name which we had used in the case of waypoint proxy.
So this authorization policy would be applied for that gateway.
We are allowing the request and the rule is
simple. Whatever was previously there from the
source and the principle is basically this. And two here stands
for what kind of operations are we going to do? You can again refer
to the documentation for further kind of in depth
guide as to what these configuration would do.
And in this case we are simply using operations and saying that,
okay, allow, method, get. We are not using anything else.
We are allowing that from this particular cluster
to echo server, just allow methods, that is get request.
Let's apply this file Uctl apply f
allow get request to echo ns two.
Now it is created. Now if I try to do the same thing,
I'm getting a successful response. Let's try it with post
request. And we are getting an access denied.
Cool. So this is working. This is the l
seven network policies in action,
as you can see. So this was a very basic
example of how we would apply the l seven authorization policies.
So similar to what we have seen in l four authorization
policies. If you don't provide a spec selector by default, it will block everything.
We have already seen that since we had not applied anything.
And in this case also if you don't apply anything
in operations, the two is basically specifying what all operations you
want. So if I simply comment this out and I don't apply,
it will allow everything that in this case we are restricting
only to get, it will allow get postponed and all those things in context
of this example. But since we are restricting to the set
of operations as methods get only, it will
only apply the get request to kind of apply
the get request to pass through. Now. Next we'll be
having a look at traffic management. So we'll
be doing canary release here we have already seen from sleep ns one.
We are able to query echo ns two with the get request. Now we
want that. Okay, the 90% of traffic should be ending up at v
one and the 10% at v two. So to do
this we'll be applying a canary Yaml file.
So as you can see, this is pretty standard.
You can see whatever you would do in istio with
sidecars a virtual service that is applied
on a particular host. In this case, this is the host of Echo server which
is in ns two. And in route destination, we are only
saying that, okay, for subset V one, make 90% of the
request approximately go to subset V one for this particular host.
And in the other one we are saying that, okay, for 10% of
the time take it to subset V two. Now the definition of these
subsets are there in the destination rule that we
have set here. The destination rule is again applied on ns
two and it is selecting echo server service ns two.
I haven't applied a full qualified domain name here because it's in the same namespace.
So I'm just showing this example that yeah, it would still work without the
FQDN. Okay, so in
subset V one we are simply selecting echo server app ns two and the
version of the app which is v one. And in V two we are simply
selecting echo server app that is ns two and the version
which is v two. Pretty standard. Basically if you
apply this to the sidecar enabled service mesh, it would still work,
nothing different. So now we are going to do kubectl
apply my f canary.
Yaml. Let's wait.
Nice. Let's see kubectl get
destination rule. In ns two
we have the echo service one and also the virtual service.
Awesome. Now let's test it. So what we'll be
doing is so we'll run
a command which will send 100 request from the
sleep of NS one to the echo server of NS
two. If I can,
oops, I can properly format it.
We should be good to go. Yeah, let's run it.
It's going to take some time because it's going to fire 100 kind
of requests to this particular service.
And as you can see for version one,
I'm just doing a grab to get whatever version it is
there. In the logs, we can see that 91 of them have this echo
server deployment ns two version one. And if I simply change it
to version two, we'll approximately get ten
requests. In this case. Okay, it's 16.
That's still fine. Again, it's not going to be a perfect division of
percentage. It will try to approximate it as much as it can.
So we are seeing here different number, and you can see the variation
is quite huge. So, okay, now let's see,
what exactly was it sending here? If I simply do
the standard curl command instead of any grep or
anything. So let's see what we are actually picking.
So we already have a hostname that was being printed and
for different part it's going to be different. So this is what the grep
was doing and we are simply counting the occurrences. So in this
case it is again version one. Let's run it again.
It's version one. Again version one.
Since 90% of request is going to version one, we are most likely
to get this. So as you can see,
canary releases is working well. You can play around, do whatever
kind of 50 50, you can do a blue green or whatever
things you could do with istio. You can do the same
thing with istio ambient mesh, and it's nothing
short and it's pretty performant as we can see right now.
So after traffic management, let's have a look at the observability and
debugging capabilities of istio similar to that what we are
seeing in sidecar. We'll get the same things here as well.
So I'll be using. Let's go to Prometheus first.
Istio dashboard Prometheus.
So you can see I'm having all the istio related matrix
request total. Yeah, I'm getting everything
you can see from destination service gateways.
This is, by the way, the ingress ones here.
Also you can see the app was issue ingress.
You won't see a lot whatever we have done, from the curl to
the ns one, which we had tested previously
before applying the deny all, because those are some of the TCP metrics.
The L seven ones would come from envoy itself.
So in this case, ingress gateway is envoy. So that's why we are
having L seven capabilities. And the waypoint proxy itself
is an envoy proxy. That's why we are having all the L seven
metrics from there as well. However, all the L four metrics
were there. Once you apply the ztunnel, you'll be
getting all the tcp consumption opened, lost total,
all those counts. Everything would be there. So the matrix,
as you can see in Prometheus, it's working great.
Let's have a look at Kiali as well.
If I go to graph and I'm
choosing last one, r maybe.
Okay, I'll first. Okay,
so now you can see in sleep ns one to echo service.
We are already seeing the traffic flowing to version one
and version two. The green ones are the previous ones which
we had deployed before the service mesh was there.
So this is just the general ones, whatever that has been captured.
Once the service mesh is here, you can see that in the.
If I go to app graph itself, you can see everything is
in blue, is kind of tcp encrypted. Okay,
where is this version app graph? Right.
We had some of the failures as well, which is being captured here.
So yeah, pretty much everything is working in the observability section.
Let's have a look at Grafana as well.
I'm going to the available dashboard. You can however choose to create
your own dashboard. Go to the control plane dashboard
and see what kind of metrics we are getting.
So we have a cpu usage and we have our endpoint
listener pilots. Everything, whatever we had seen
in the istio sidecar version, we are getting everything here.
Let's go to some other dashboard, maybe the mesh.
Okay, what's there in the mesh one? Yeah, some of the information
related to mesh, how many authorization policies we have applied,
what interval and all those things.
So yeah, we also have the service workload request
and all those things, whatever was captured here. So you
can also do pretty much everything what you were doing with istio related to observability
here. So yeah, that pretty much sums it all.
So apart from observability, we can also
use istio CTL to debug our proxies.
So let's have a look at that. So you can use
istio CTL proxy status to get the
status of all the proxies deployed. So in this
case you can see especially the envoy proxies in this case,
which is the waypoint and the ingress gateway, they all
have the endpoint discovery service and ecds
and all those things, they are synced and all the information that you can see
you're getting. The ztunnel, however, is not an envoy proxy.
So all of these things are ignored. You can also
use istio proxy config to have
a deeper understanding of the consumption of these particular
envoy proxies. If you just go to the help section, you'll have
a list of all the available commands that are there and you
can use it to debug your proxies. So let's try
something like proxy get all.
So we'll be retrieving all the configuration for this specific envoy
proxy. In this case we'll be using the Echo service one.
And make sure that once you're giving the name of the pod,
you also give the namespace after the dot. So this is how
it works. So let's see what we are getting. We can see
that we are getting entire overview of all the
full qualified domain name services it has, what port they listened
on, or what is the direction of the traffic. Also what
virtual services you are using for this particular inbound.
So this is a pretty handy tool for you to debug,
and it also gives information about the root ca as well, as you
can see here. So you can also play around
with this, and istio CTL is a very powerful tool
for you to debug as well.
That's all for the observability and debugging. Okay,
so if you have been this far, then good job. So we have successfully
added ambient imesh to our cluster, and if
you have any questions related to it, feel free to reach out
to me on LinkedIn, or maybe even just create an issue in the GitHub
repository that I'd shared. So thank you everyone.
Once again, thank you to conf 42 for having me. This is MD
Azmal signing off.