What if you could work with some of the world's most innovative companies,
all from the comfort of a remote workplace?
Andela has matched thousands of technologists across the globe to their
next career adventure. We're empowering new
talent worldwide, from Sao Paulo to Egypt and Lagos
to Warsaw. Now the future of work is yours
to create. Anytime, anywhere. The world is
at your fingertips. This is Andela.
Hello, everyone. Thank you for joining my talk. So I'm Jerve.
I'm going to talk today about successful. Go for successful,
successful microservices architecture. Few years ago, when I joined my current
company, the team was working on we
had almost monolithic architecture and they
were using a programming language
called Scala. So then we
decided to make the transition using go and
building a proper microservices architecture software.
So the aim of my talk is not so
much about praising go or the
microservices architecture, but it's more about talking
about the journey and what
we learned through that journey.
So very briefly,
about myself. So I'm Jerve. I'm a senior
software engineer. I'm based in London.
The company I work for is called smart numbers and I
joiners them in 2019.
So we are a software company specializing
telecommunication. So we deal with things like
fraud prevention, call management, telecoms migration
or mobile solution and so on. So if you want more detail,
you have the website there, the link.
Myself, I'm part of the fraud prevention team.
So I'm working on fraud prevention products. So as you can imagine,
we have quite a weird and
strong constraint because we're dealing with telephony,
especially latency. So we'll come back to that a
few times through the presentation.
And if you have any question or
any comments or feedback for me, you have on the
right for you, I think. Yeah, you have on these right my twitter,
and you also have the link to my YouTube channel where
I'm trying to teach go the basics, giving you
tricks, tips, teaching you design patterns and these
kind of things. So that's for me. So now let's
dive into the subject. So,
microservices, obviously, I said a few minutes ago
that I don't want to spend too much time in praising microservices,
but I'd like you to understand what's a microservices
architecture and also what are the caveats
of using one of those.
So to set the scene properly,
I'm going to have to compare it with a monolith architecture.
So no disrespect for a monolith architecture.
So it worked very well for a few years it
still work in certain eases, but now the trend is
more into microservices for some reason,
for agile and so on. So the
cliche of a monolith, so you have a monolith on the left.
So usually a monolith is like a gigantic mono
service, years and years of code accumulated.
It's using a single database with a horrific schema,
difficult to migrate. And this kind of stuff, it's usually in
a single version control repo into a single GitHub.
So it means that you have to have a strong discipline in using
GitHub. Like you have to use branches and you have to do rebase,
you have to do commit, pull requests and all
this drama. So usually it's
quite difficult to extend and maintain, and it's not
such a nice dev experience. So as
opposed two that we have on the right,
successful, successful microservices architecture, the name suggests,
instead of having this mono blockers, we have multiple
services communicating with each
other. So usually a microservice is like an autonomous,
meaningful service representing business
unit. They can have these own
database and they are in their own GitHub.
So the advantages of that are
that they are easily testable on their own. You can upgrade
these on their own. So if you want to upgrade a component, a library,
on one service, you can do that and it won't impact the
other services. Your schema
is simple because you have tinier databases
and if you have let's say
four colleagues in your team,
and it means that they can work independently on four
different services in different repo without stepping on each
other toes. So you have quite of autonomous.
So it usually translates into a faster
release deployment or a better dev
experience overall.
So that's on paper, that's on theory. But obviously I'm here to talk to
you about the caveats of this pattern.
So I took a screenshot for you about
a screenshot of our microservices.
So we are using AWS, Amazon,
Amazon Services. So this is x ray, which is a
monitoring tracing tool. So the dots
represent services and databases or
any entry points. So you can see visually
straight away it's complexity.
So here we are introducing a lot of complexity between
the services in term of communication.
And we are also introducing what we call cognitive load,
meaning that it's a lot to take on for one
single person or for a team, as in if you have
100 services, it's not
humanly possible to remember what each single service is
doing or responsible for.
Then secondly, you are increasing the
overall latency of your those architecture.
If you're not careful, it's simply
because you can have a service calling another service calling over
multiple services. And as
I told you, I'm working for a telephony company. So if a person
is trying to contact emergency services,
you can't wait forever to process the call. And then
lastly I mentioned that it was easily extendable,
maintainable, yes and no. Because if
you have a service sending a request,
two another service and you want to change, you want to
remove or you want to add another
property on those request response.
It's quite a bit of gymnastic because you don't want to introduce
break and change and you might not aware if you change the response
of one service you can think about these service
consuming it, but then you might forget others. So it becomes
really complex. And it's even more complex if you
have multiple environments. Like you have a dev environment, you have a UAT environment,
you have a pro environment, you want to propagate this
chain smoothly without breaking anything. So it's
quite a lot of scheduling. Also maintainable?
Yes and no, because I
said earlier, they are upgradable on their own.
That's true, but let's say you are using a common library for each
single of them, and that library requires
a security patch. If you have 100 services,
you're going to have to propagate those patch
security 100 times, unfortunately.
So obviously any programming language could help
solving mitigating those problems or would have those problems.
But the goal of this talk is how do we make the
most of go to tackle them? Right, let's see how we can use
go the most efficiently possible.
So our first challenge was three
years ago when we had call start problem with
our serverless functions with Scala.
So a serverless function is a programmatic function where
your cloud provider takes care of hosting,
managing and provisioning your infrastructure, and then
you just execute your code.
The problem with that is when
you want to invoke your function, your cloud provider has to
download your code and then start your new execution environment as shown on
the diagram. So this existing time is your call
start and, and then your code executes.
And the duration, the length
of a call start depends on three factors. So first
one is the language. Unfortunately some languages
take longer than others, these the package size.
So it depends if your language is natively.
Once compile is natively more voluminous
than others, and also if you're using bigger dependencies
or more dependencies. So obviously if you're using
more packages or dependency, the longer is going to be your
cost because you have to download those dependencies
and also doesn't matter
here in our case, but it also depends if it's in a private network
or not. I'll put a link for you here. It's only
about AWS, the Amazon services about
call starts. It's a really good article.
So the problem we face and what we saw,
so we had awful call start with scanner.
So Scala is part of the JVM language
family, so it compiles to Java
byte machine, Java code byte machine,
sorry. And so we had call
start of one to 2 seconds and then our code executing.
So that was not acceptable for our
constraint, our product, because you can wait forever
for a call to be processed. And you
can imagine in that scenario that we had a
scala function calling another scalar function. So it means that you
could hit a chain of call starts,
which is a really awful experience for the customer.
So then we makes a trial,
we tried a Golemba and it was
much much better. So we had a call start of millisecond and then
your function execution. So that
makes sense because go binaries are really
lightweight, so therefore the provisioning,
when your cloud provider is downloading your code it's
much quicker. So then that's why the consists
are much much tinier with go.
So that was a first success for our microservices,
especially for the latency. So we decided to make the
full transition to Golang basically.
Second point is Golang is
quite a well supported and popular language. So it seems
a bit simple and trivial to say that,
but it does have an impact. So let me explain because
it's quite a well known language now and it
was already three years ago. So you often have
sdks available. So we use aws, but it's available
for Google and for Asia and
other probably. And as
we had to make the transition we had to
write services from scratch.
So for instance we had to write HTTP server,
graphql server, we had to write test to generate mock mocks,
we had to encrypt, to hash, we had to talk to a database,
we had to services as request response. So none
of us had experience in go and
we had plenty of tutorials available, a ton of tutorials available,
which made our life really easy.
So then yeah, these ecosystem was and
still is extremely alive.
And we have a supported community and it's a living language,
it's really well used. So it
means that the services we wrote three
years ago still beneficiate from updates, from improvements.
It's a bit of a teaser, but we had a
few months, a couple of years ago go modules
for these dependency management we had generic
like a few days ago, so it really does help
in building high quality services.
So my next points is quite a bit
of a continuity of my previous point,
but more in detail. So go is quite
a well designed language. So here you have all the standard
libraries built in when you download go,
I think it's worth mentioning because all of that, as I
said, is inbuilt. Like when you install go, you have all
of that ready to be used and you don't have to download
any external dependency or this kind of stuff.
So worth mentioning, you have the crypto for hashing
or to salt or the secret and this kind of stuff,
you have these encoding library for JsON marshalling and marshalling.
You have the amazing errors package,
very simple but really effective.
Have the formatting library, you have the OS library
for manipulating files,
you have string manipulation, you have the sync library for the
existing group, the Mutex and these kind of things.
And you also have the really good time library,
really well built. So a
bit of comparison here you have
for instance JavaScript. When you want to use TAM, you have to download
external library like moment or momentum
or date or date fn
or something like that.
Also the testing framework. So the testing framework
is actually a better example. So when you want to test
your code with JavaScript, you have a ton of libraries,
can't really remember, but you have mocha, you have
Chinese Sinan, you have cypress perpetual
js. It's not uniformized,
it's not like inbuilt. Whereas in Go, if you want to
write go and you want to test your
code straight away, you have a ready two be
used library dependencies management.
So we started with an external tool
called depth. But fortunately enough in Go 1.13
the dev introduced Go modules,
or Go mod, called Go mod. So it's just fantastic
tool which just work. So you
can add a dependency, you can download them, you can initiate a
file, it's just proper dependency management
available to you when you download go. So that's fantastic.
All right, some libraries worth mentioning,
obviously you could use only standard
libraries to build your pieces of software,
like you could write from scratch a
library on your own to generate graphql server or this kind
of stuff. But turns out that you really have good library
out there, really well maintained, really well tested,
and it really helped us in our journey to build high
quality services. So the
first two are testing libraries. So Gomega
and Ginkgo. So these are matcha assertion library and BDD test
framework. And these, the third one
is really important because when you're writing microservices
you have a lot of common parts
used by your different services.
So then the solution for that is to write common
library that you can share between your services.
So those kind of libraries are
codec serialization
framework or these kind of things. Or they can be
models to share between service to ensure that you are using
the correct request, the correct contracts
between them. So you want to do that
smoothly. So you have to have a tool
which can properly distribute
tag version your library for that. So Gorilla releaser
is a really nice binaries builder then.
Lastly, I thought it was worth
mentioning this GraphQl server generator.
So it just works out of the box and from
GraphQl schema it's generating
a full server ready to deploy. So it
really smooth the experience, the dev experience and really help us
to deliver value quicker.
A very quick special mention to Golan. So Golan is
an did. It's part of the Jetbrain family.
So you probably know Intellij.
I know that ids are quite controversial,
but if you're familiar with the Dreadbrain
ids, you can go pretty quickly with Golan, with all the
shortcuts and stuff.
So the learning here about the tooling is because you
have so go is well
built and you have really good libraries
available. So the tooling is really excellent. So that makes the dev
experience really solid. And for our microservices
it means you build faster and you build with high quality.
And overall it's just really enjoyable to write go at the
end of the day. All right, so my last point
is quite an interesting one. It's about the
new joiner experience. So for
a person new to go, or maybe his
or her first language or second,
Golang is quite easy to learn. So you have very few keywords
and the syntax is quite explicit.
So just in a few weeks you
can already understand and you can already contribute
massively. Two, the team. So that's
really good. And also even after a few
years, if you still have appetite for
challenges, you can always find subjects,
topics to deal with, like garbage
collection, or understand how the concurrency model works, all these kind
of things. So in
our team, just a few months after embracing the
Go universe, one junior member of our team did
a presentation. Two, the whole engineering department about go.
That was a massive success.
So at the bottom I put two links, two resources that
I like, I'm time to comes go back
there to just check some pieces
of knowledge. So the first one is a tour of go and the second one
is go by example. So Golang is really
beginner friendly. So it's immediately rewarding
for them. But also from the mentor side,
as you can build a solid base and you can consolidate
very crucial and important concepts like
solid principle, clean code, and you can also build
on that eases even further concepts.
So for our microservices, it means
that for a junior point of view,
you don't spend much time on struggling,
on learning a new language, but you can also focus
on the overall architecture and try to understand the
place of a service in the whole fleet of
services.
All right, so now I'd like to just
contrast all those advantages with some limitations.
So the very first limitation
with go that we face was how to organize
our folders and packages. So on the left you have these
traditional organization, the old fashioned way,
MVC model, view controller. So we started with
that. We had a package called controller with all the controllers.
Then we had a package called services.
Then we had all our services and was gigantic
package, not so much meaningful, and so
on and so on. You had views, models,
and we just agreed on
a better organization, which per context. So context
here does not mean go context.
So context is more like a logical unit,
like you have on the right, the order context,
where you have everything about order and then
everything about customer, and so on and so on.
And we also found out
that having too much level of nesting didn't work
either. So what we tend to do usually is
to have only one level of death, like you can
see on these, right? Or at most two
level of def, of nesting. Sorry.
So it really help us by organizing
those packaging in meaningful context to
identify common packages and extract them as common library,
or to do not misidentify them.
Do not extract something where it's not necessary.
And then the tooling did the rest, as I told you, with that go
release library, the second limitation
we face. So here, it's not necessarily impacting
our microservices, but I thought it was worth mentioning.
So the first caveat was the pointer
problem. So I'm going two, take a really
controversial shortcut here. But usually you
use pointer if you want to mutate something or
if your struct is too heavy to be passed around.
So in that case you use pointer.
So then we had a few problems with that. So first is
like, it's a bit daunting for someone who
has never seen pointer in his or
her life.
So we just took the decision
to avoid punters
like the plague, basically. So we try to
do it more in a functional programming way.
So let's try to avoid mutate things, and let's
try to do not use pointer in our struct if it's not
necessary, because we had a bit of a drama where
we had a pointer, a misuse,
and we broke prod once, so that was terrible,
so we didn't do that again. And then about interfaces.
So sometimes the concept of implicit interfaces are
also called the typing. It's quite difficult for a beginner to understand.
So about the future,
what else could we do with go in order
to have even better successful Microservices
architecture? Wrote a tiny user story there. So as a Go
software engineer, I want to write infrastructure in
go, deployment pipeline in go, my task runner
in go, and even writing go to generate my documentation.
So then I don't write awful yaml.
So here it's a bit of a joke,
yes and no, because go
is such an efficient language which brings so
much high quality to the services that
you'd like to have that resilience, that kind of quality level
for everything around. So that would be the dream.
Second point is about protobuff. So protocol
buffer. So we are a bit late in the game,
so we don't have that implemented at the minute
in our architecture.
So protobuff is about serialization
of structured data. As you can see, you can do
it in go. So here
it would help, we believe it would help to propagate
any changes between our services, because it can
do validate schema validation and these kind of
fancy things. And it's also very lightweight and very
efficient in term of latency. So that's something
on our to do list.
Another things on our to do list is the generics.
So just a few days ago go 1.18
did release these generics, finally. So it's ready to be
used. So who knows what we're going to found.
So in conclusion,
we saw that successful, successful microservices architecture, really good pattern,
but unfortunately you have to be careful about two points. So the
first one was these complexity between your services,
and the second one was the latency that you
could introduce in your services. So then we
also saw that go was really helping to ease those pain points.
So first one was excellent performances,
the library binaries, the language speed,
and then you have the tooling available because
it's quite a popular language, you have a lot of
good tooling available, a lot of tutorials and so on.
So overall providing a
really good developer experience.
And then who knows, maybe there will be even more
go features in these future to even make the
experience better.
So thank you for watching. Hi,