I'm Tommy Kay, head micro frontends department at Leaky and Frontend
house and podcaster known from micro frontend house series on
micro frontend house channels. Im going to take you into the journey
through the world of the micro frontends. Let's start with
the agenda. We are going to speak about software architecture.
Monolith approach, distributed approaches, micro frontends.
What? Why my winit. And at the end, we will quickly
summarize everything what I was talking about.
Are you ready? So let's do this. The software
architecture is about the whole system. Fundamental organization,
which includes components, relations between them,
infrastructure, environment and set of rules and
design patterns used to manage the system. Right.
It gives the directions to the development teams of how to
build, scale and maintain the whole system and
make it meet the business expectations.
Such set of the principles and tooling makes the
required work more predictable and efficient as
all of the team members know. Why, what and how?
One of the examples from the software architecture area is
a wellknown monolith approach. It issues that all of the requirements,
solutions, functionalities and data are encapsulated
under a single application. I believe most of us worked
with applications like that. And good example are rabionrails
apps. Okay, so basically rabionrails app encapsulate
the frontend layer, the backend layer, the database layer,
and it's everything closed under the single solution,
right? Okay, cool. So let's discuss the pros
and cons of the monolith approach. It encapsulates all the problems
and solution under the single application. On complexity
growth, it's hard to scale. Security of data
storing and communication is much easier. It has
a reduced palette of used technologies, lack of modularity
and easy to start development. The other type of
the architecture area is a distributed approach.
Let's take a closer look on that. Okay, so let's assume we
have a couple of different functionalities and integrations to
cover. We can build a single backend application,
the monolith one, or we can split the monolith into
separate microservices. Each of the microservices will be
responsible for the particular functionality like payments,
authorization, payment, treatment process and
stuff like that. To make the communication easier,
we can connect all the dots under the communication hub.
Let's call it gateway. The good example is Graphql
federation that is mostly based off the distributed
approach. The process conf 42 distributed architecture
is high performance under a big traffic and it's
really easy to scale. Increased response time depends on the
number of the nodes to process the request. High complexity
at the beginning of implementation. White palette of
available technologies, hard to debug and analyze
and hard to pros security for the whole system.
Does it make sense? So let's move forward. Now it's
the time to introduce the micro frontends.
What are the micro frontend house?
Mostly they are the adaptation of the distributed architecture
for the web applications. Right? So the assumption
is still the same. Create the small micro apps that resolve
the particular problem, expose each of the solutions
and use them wherever needed. One of the main
wins is the really great modularisation and technology
agnostic attempt as each of the module
can be realized with the different technology and
with the different teams. As we can see on the diagram,
instead of creating the monolith app that would include
all of the modules within its source, we did create a
separately micro apps like schedule, video, call,
user profile and notifications.
Cool. So those apps are used inside
the shell app and the shell app is basically
our API gateway that I have presented in the distributed
approach definition. Right? Cool. So the shell app connect
all of our micro apps and expose the single entry
two the end user. From the user perspective it will be just
the single app. But under the hood there would be
the combination of smaller blocks that are composed to
get the main app. Each of the module can integrate with
the microservices directly or indirectly, or with some single
API or with any data source, any data
provider we want to include inside our
architecture, inside our platform. The shell app also can integrate
with the data providers and then expose this data to
the micro apps. Depends on the case. Let's take a look at more advanced
usage. One of the options is to choose the distributed approach on
both front end and backend. And yeah,
you're probably right, it might look complex and certainly
it is. It fits well when there are a lot of
different functionalities, modules, views,
widgets and business logic to be covered and
scalability is one of the key requirements. We can
easily add or remove modules and compose new
apps within existing modules. Or add new modules.
Two. Compose the new apps. Yeah, there are plenty of use
cases and there are plenty of things that we can do with
the microapps approach. What are the pros and cons
for the micro frontends architecture? Each module is a separate self
contained app with on ecosystem. The key is to provide
the good communication between apps. Modularization makes
it easy to scale. Shell apps is responsible for integrating
all the apps. Each micro frontend has own API
integration. Independent development teams can collaborate
on the front end app easily performance optimization
opportunities. As we saw on the diagram,
creating the micro frontends architecture is complex
and it may be hard to set up and start implementation.
We can use one of the popular micro frontends frameworks
like big single spa webpack five and module federation
open components, et cetera, et cetera. There are a bunch
of different tools that covers the micro frontends architecture
and the micro frontends boilerplate. Two,
let us start implementation much faster.
Personally I did use bit and it makes the
whole job perfect and I recommend to take a look on
their documentation and also take a
look into their tutorials like they explain everything,
everything how to deal with the micro front end within your
favorite technologies. Mostly I was working with the react
and this tool makes the whole job
and it was really really easy for me to implement a different
app and connect them under the shell app. So yeah, I highly recommend
to take a look and enjoy. But yeah,
let's move forward now, it's time two, answer the question why
we might need that. The huge plus is that the separate development
teams can work on different areas of our platform,
each specialized in a different technology. For the company,
it means that the project teams can be composed of the mixed
skills developers and help to better
allocate the resources and employees. So for example,
one of the team that specializes in the react can work on the schedule
app that is realized with the react. The angular team
can focus on the video call app and someone who is
perfect in vanilla js can work on the Shell app with
just compose all of our apps right? Another use case
where the micro front end might be helpful is where there is
a need to migrate from one technology to the another.
Instead of doing a revolution and rewrite the apps from
the scratch, the development teams can adopt the distributed
approach and switch for example from angular
to react step by step. So following the
rule, make an evolution, not a revolution. It makes
the whole migration easier and more predictable.
And what's more important, teams can experiment with the product
by exploring different technologies and solutions
and pick the best one without rewriting the whole app, which as
an outcome saves time and money. One of the benefits, thanks to
the micro frontends'architecture is that we can easily
compose the new apps by reuse of the currently existing
modules or adding a new one. The same video call app
can be reused in the patient or doctor app or
in ambulance driver app, but the key is to
expose the right communication interface to be able
to inject the data and expose other handrails to lets
us integrate with this micro app much easier.
Now, let's assume that your client knows that he wants to build
three different apps, but based on the similar branding and similar
UI, right? So instead of creating the presentation layer
for each of the apps, we can extract the reusable blocks
and create a reusable package that can be utilized within
our apps. Okay, we can add storybook or
any other tool that you like to use to document our components library.
And as an outcome, we receive a good foundation for something
that's called design system. With the micro frontend,
House can easily put all things into the order and manage the
whole infrastructure in cleaner and more understandable way.
We discussed the theory for the micro frontend. House discussed
some examples, but as you can see in the presentation,
some big players also trust in the micro frontends architecture.
So those players are like Zalando, Microsoft, Leroamerlem,
Starbucks. And I believe it's also worth for you to check it
on your own. Choose the technology with the surgical precision.
With the micro frontends architecture, you can easily build scalable
apps that are composed from the independent modules.
Pick the technology that responds to the business problem and gives
the most optimized result. So that's it.
Thank you for your attention. I hope that you have enjoyed the
whole show and the knowledge I have shared with you
will be useful and and see you next time.
Bye.