Thank you very much again,
honor to be here. I am Alejandro Mercado,
currently living in Mexico City.
Well, I am going to talk about a little bit about
githubs and observability. Let me share
my presentation,
my deck. So the
name of my talk is observability,
the key to unlocking it ups.
So this is
a little bit about me. I am
the dev now doing DevOps living in Mexico City.
Also proud member of the DevOps Institute as ambassador for
Mexico, GitLab Hero and Dev Network
advisory board member. So there is my link.
If you wish to connect,
be my guest. So well, I would
like to start with this slide
to mention with this warning that this talk
is an holistic approach by
reference to the whole. So I don't
just want to talk about some specific topic,
technical issue, pretty deep.
If not, I would like to talk about to
see that the forest instead of the whole tree
or just one tree. So I would
like to start with observability.
So observability is. Well,
there is not a single definition about observability,
but observability is a management strategy
focused on keeping the more relevant and important and core
issues at or near to the top of an
operations process flow. The term
is also used to describe software processes that
facilitate the separation of critical information from routine
information. So seems
like a little academic definition. So maybe
when we contrast observability versus monitoring,
we have a better understanding of what
observability is. But I
would like to, or some companies like to
explain observability with these three pillars.
Metrics, traces and logs are the three pillars
of observability. So you can
think of an observability in these three components.
It's like the secret sauce. When you have this data,
you can be proactive and
you can observe your systems well,
it can also refer to the extraction and processing of critical information
at the highest level, architectural operation systems.
As I said, when we put
in contracts with monitoring,
when we talk about monitoring, maybe you have
been there diving in
a locks, ocean, so tons
of lines.
It takes a while to get real
and important information about what is going on with the system.
So that's why we have these new tools.
Actually, in most cases when
we talk about monitoring, it's because we are doing
a post martin analysis. So this is the main
difference between observability. Observability is
to be proactive, is to have this information to
avoid that the system crashes or to
have some problems. And even
then the user report the issue
or the problem we already know about it because we have
this observability running end to
end. So monitoring
tools passively gather information, most of which turns
out to be insignificant or we don't get
the real important information. So this can drown
operations, personnel and even AI tools in
data versus observability that
actively gathers data to focus on what's relevant,
such as the factors that drive operations,
decisions and actions.
So in this site is observability and
why it is important because we are going to
see proactively our systems.
These new terms is not that
new, but a lot of companies are adopting
Gitops because it represents some advantages.
So Gitops in
a pretty brief definition, GitHub uses
git repositories as a single source of true
to deliver infrastructure as code.
So single source of true is
the key definition.
So you can see this image, this is Githubs
in a nutshell. We are going to have
our desired state in
a couple of manifest.
Well,
I have to say that these
GitHub tools add a
control plane to kubernetes. So we
have this repo, this Git
repo. It can be GitHub,
GitLab, any repo, any repository that you have,
it doesn't matter, but you have the manifest in
this repo. This manifest
is the source of true for declarative code.
So it's going to do a reconciliation when
you are committing and releasing your
code. This is the CI CD pipeline. So you are
running a series of stacks resulting in the
update of the runtime environment to
match the source. So if there is discrepancy
or a difference between the desired state and the actual
state of the system, it's going to
do the reconciliation loop.
So submitted
code checks the CI process well, the CD process checks
and applies requirements for things like security,
infrastructure as code or any other boundaries set for
the application framework. All changes to
code are tracked, making updates easy while
also providing version control, shoulder roadblock
be needed. So well,
this is GitHub's blue subservability.
I would like to recommend
to take a look of this image. So you have the desired
state and the current state, and in
the middle you have the reconciliation loop.
I think that this is the
key or the middle or stone of GitHub.
So we observe,
and if there is a difference between these
two estates, we adjust.
So that is why observability is key for Githubs.
We can do GitHub's observability.
So why GitHub is important and web companies are
adopting Githubs because we have several
advantages from other release managing
strategies. We have improved security and
compliance, increased collaboration and productivity,
decreased manual oversight,
faster deployments and increase reliability.
And by the way, there is this site that
I totally recommend to take a look. You can
enter to open HTTPs opengirups
dev. So you have this initiative that
it sets like the principles of what is open.
So open Gitops is a set
of open source standards, best practices and
community focused education to help organizations adopt a
structure standardized approach to implementing
GitHub. I highly recommend
to take a look of this site. So it's not
about the implementation or tooling,
it's like a neutral vendor site.
So the principle of GitHub,
this principle I have to say are
extracted from the site. The principle of GitHubs
is that it's declarative, so you
don't do imperative command lines.
So it's based on
manifest files, like I said in a previous
slide. So is a clarity a system
managed by GitHub must have if desired state expresses
the clarity is know Yaml is
nowadays everywhere is versioned and
immotable. That means that the desired is
stored in a way that enforces immotability versioning
and retains a complete version history.
So it's similar like when
developers make commits and they have
this versioning and can do rollbacks,
it's pretty like the same. That's why it is GitHub,
it's pulled automatically. So it's
pulled because there are another paradigms that are pushed.
In this case, GitHub is pulled automatically.
So the subware agents automatically pull the desired state
declarations from the source, so it pulls the
desired state.
Do the reconciliation loops with the actual
states. And if there
is a mismatch it's going to do the
healing. So it's continually reconciled.
So subway agents continually observe actual
system state and attempt to apply the desired state.
So that's the
way that you can have availability
system. And it's, it's very easy to maintain
even if you have a lot of, I mean if you
have 100 of pods and your kubernetes
cluster is too big,
this tool even have some nice graphical
user interfaces that you can handle the state
and see if something is wrong,
you can apply the reconciliation.
So the demo,
there is not no show
me code. This is what developer says.
So there is a lot of tools that
are applying the GitHub paradigm
like fluxd wear harness,
Jenkins codefresh that actually
uses Argo CD wave.
Well in particular I'm going to do the demo
in Argo CD. So Argo CD is a
declarative GitHub's continuous delivery tool for kubernetes.
So remember it's a controller plane
running on kubernetes. It's another control plane running kubernetes so we
can handle the
releases. So at this point I'm going to show
the site. So there is a
pretty cool training.
If you go to codefresh IO you can find
some training. So I will highly recommend
to take this training
because our folks of coldfresh
already did the setup. So it's already
there. It's pretty easy just to follow the instruction
that as you can see in my browser we
have all destructions
just to follow. I will just
show one of the
lessons, that is just to show them.
So it takes a little bit to prepare
the environment.
Okay, so we have the
environment. So as I said, go to this address
learning cutfresh IO. So it's pretty
handy, pretty useful. You can learn about ArgoCD
from GitHub fundamentals to some
more advanced topics. So it's pretty cool because
as I said, we just have to follow the instructions.
The first task is to fart this
repository that we have on GitHub.com.
So we
have already,
I can show, I have my,
this is the.
So as you can see Argo
CD is already installed.
You can handle GitHub with the
command line interface, writing commands,
but you also have this nice Argo CD UI.
It's like pretty nice,
pretty useful interface that you can see what is going on with
your Kubernetes clusters and suffering is ramp.
You are going to see here in red,
some pod is failing or if we lose
communication you are going to
visually see immediately.
And of course you can do something to try to repair
or to do a rollback or to do something.
So we are going to do a new app.
The application name is whatever you want demo,
the project is default,
the repository URL is
the certification
examples acting as without the git
and the path is simple app.
The cluster is the default that we have
to know. You must need a Kubernetes cluster already
installed that thanks to
our fault from cutfresh we already
have there and the name space we can set
up the default.
So you can leave these other arguments empty
for now. So,
so that's it. You can click on create.
So at this moment we are going to have our
first application running on kubernetes and
based on GitHub so you can
see the application is out of sync.
If you see the yellow indicator
is out of sync. So you can sync
manually. But the idea is that you are
not going to wake up every morning to
sync all the Kubernetes cluster.
So it can be set up automatically.
But for demo purposes I just wanted to
sync it by clicking this
button to synchronize, you know, remember the
desired state with the actual state.
So if there is a difference, a discrepancy
between the two estates, it's going to
throw an error. So it's
processing.
Of course in the simple app you
can take a look of the manifest, because maybe you are wondering
about well, what is going on in the deployment
is using this manifest.
Of course the deployment is pretty simple.
It's just an
application, trivial go web,
an application in
go in the go programming language. So we
just have one replica. Maybe if I
change this state and do
the synchronization again, it's going to throw an arrow because now
I am telling that the desired
state is two or five or twelve. So this
is just a pretty simple deployment file,
JaMl. So you have this
container that is running a pretty simple application.
And the services, the other JAML
is just exposing the application in
the port 80 80.
So nothing too complex, but I think it's pretty
illustrative. So it takes a little
bit to get the
synchronization.
But as you can see in this learning environment,
we also have the shell. So a lot of these
activities or tasks, we can also
do that in
line. By line, I mean entering the commands.
It totally depends on what you prefer. So when
you have this nice interface,
maybe you want to take advantage of that.
I just want to see if
the deployment is already done because
I think it's a little bit slow.
I don't know if it's my connection.
I have my deployment, my simple deployment,
but it's not ready.
The pod is not available yet,
so we
have to wait to the.
As you can see that the view interface is
pretty nice. I think it's pretty handy.
If you have some problem, you are going to have this health
status you can see in this side menu bar.
The first is the sync status. It's unknown synced
when it's green and out of sync.
Well in this case the status is processing
the synchronization. But as you can see here in the health status,
if something is going wrong,
you are going to see it pretty,
visually, it's going to put in red
the frame. So maybe
you can do the rollback and you can do the rollback here
in the Argo CD user interface or
in the command line, it's totally up to you.
Of course I didn't show that,
but you have to install the Argo
CD in the Kubernetes cluster.
And an easy way to start Argo CD is
with the helm package manager.
I am going to go back to my slides waiting
to have this already synchronized.
But well it's just
to give an idea of what we are talking about.
So going
back to my presentation,
well if we can get any conclusion of
this, well there is a lot of operations,
there is the evolution of operations and it's
quite a bit a lot of
operations. So this is kind of fun because
we started with Ops following DevOps,
Devsecops, devsec ML
Ops, Triceratops, that this is the joke. But there
is another Ops, no data ops, GitHubs of
course, AI Ops, no ops and you
name it ops. So it's
mean. But for sure GitHub
is important thing. So you
can see that a lot of companies are adopting the
Githubs way to do their releases and to manage
our Kubernetes clusters. So definitely
GitHubs is currently in the stage of its germination.
I mean it's starting,
it's going to grow for sure. So you
can see the numbers.
So totally a good investment of your
time. If you are already doing DevOps,
the recommendation is just to learn another tool.
I mean it can be tough
because you're already handling a lot of tools,
but GitHubs is going to be part of.
Sometimes people
ask about if this is going to replace DevOps.
It's not a replacement, it's a companion.
Gitops is neither better nor worse than DevOps.
It's not the correct approach.
Gitops without DevOps does not have a future.
So you need DevOps to
do Gitops. The scope needs to be changed and
directed at 14 investigation and how the approach can add
DevOps is just a cultural thing. Also GitHub is
part of that. So it's unlikely that GitHub
will become something bigger than DevOps,
it's complement DevOps, I would like to
say. So if you take something of this
brief talk, the four takeaways will
be you cannot do Githubs without observability.
You know, observability is important to have all
the time, to observe all the time our systems
and git is the single sort of true for the
system intended state. While observability provides a single
sort of true for the system actual state.
The third one is internal observability allows the GitHub's
controller to identify configuration drift.
External observability allows operation, staff and other systems to identify
changes in the cluster. So cloud
native observability, as I said, is a new
skill and task you must add to your DevOps
for sure. So thank
you very much. This is all for me.
So thank you very much. And I am going
to be around here. This is my twitter. If you want to contact
me, be my guest.
So thank you very much.