Everybody, you welcome to my talk. And my name is Akwemiko Dsu
and I'm really excited to be doing this with everybody right here.
Really excited to be having this talk today because it's my first in a
very long while and here I am doing what I love
to do again and find it really exciting, very interesting
stuff to do today.
I'll be talking about something really cool, but before then I'm
super excited because this is my very first talk in the past
one and a half year already, and really
excited to be doing this in this kind of event. I mean,
conf 42 Engineering Chaos 2024.
Very excited to be doing this with everybody alongside the other amazing
speakers doing this. And I really want to give a
round of applause to everyone who organized these events and
making things work out together here.
So here in this talk,
it's going to be fascinating and it's really
great talk for people love to use react
and then explore so many different technologies that works around
react and different tools
for accessibility with react and all that kind of stuff.
Yeah, I think this talk is for you if you're looking to
put out something real good for creating
stuff seamlessly, I mean, react application seamlessly.
So yeah, we would love to
now get into the next part of this talk.
And yeah, here's just a bit information
about myself. My name is Okamiko, I'm just 18 years old
and this is something I've been doing for, I mean,
keynotes speaking. It's just been something I've been doing for the past
four years. And I am
just 18, like I said. And I have
been a devil practitioner since the past four years already.
And one X IBM champion for developers in 2021
of the youngest at the point, and also started
coding at the age of eleven. Then I transitioned into devil at the
age of 14. But I really do write a lot of
code. I'm a very big fan of react next and
I'm a very big fan of them. And these are technologies
I use in my day to day life. And I
really do not have a life outside of tech, as people say.
I mean, my friends tell me I don't have particularly
a life outside of tech, which is something I think I find very interesting
because this is what really keeps me fun. And yeah,
you can find me on any social media core of Lagos
is in the Andu Koda of Lagos and on LinkedIn. You can check
me open. And yeah,
I'm nigerian and I'm an unemployed devil. So if you're
potentially looking for a devil I can be one
for you to hire. So yeah,
let's get into the main stuff for today and before
you get into this talk, before listening to this talk, I mean there are
definitely some things you have to know and these are really
important things like crucial stuff like you need to know before or
while listening to this talk. You need to have a basic
knowledge of JavaScript, how to use JavaScript, and not
just how to use Javascript but architecture and all those kind of stuff
like how it really works and just the basic things.
And you also need to have some experience with using react
libraries like Chakra Ui or CSS libraries
like Chakra Ui, Towind,
buluma, all this kind of stuff like everything, not essentially
everything, but you can just pick one to work with because in
mysmuild you can use any CSS
library to you can work with any CSS library,
literally. And also Javascript
libraries like react in this context. You need to know how
it works, how to use this, because it's really essential
to be very honest. And that
takes us to the next thing which we have is the key points from
this talk. Like what are you going to learn from this talk? I mean in
your head you may be wondering, okay, what am I going to take off this
talk, what am I going to do after listening to this
guy and stuff like that? But first thing is
you're going to learn about the architectures of
Mysmail, how it was built,
where everything runs on like the basic
components that makes up mytmail, just everything entirely
like on the interface or like the
visual development environment which I call
the studio. And also you'd get to learn what you
can actually do when using mighty mail.
Like what can you build using mighty mail and all that kind of stuff.
So yeah, that is really all about this
in this context. And yeah, let's get to
the next. So I mean you may be wondering, I've been talking about
mighty mailed. Mighty mailed, mighty mail. What is mighty mailed?
What is really mighty mail? So mighty mailed is
actually visual development tool for
building react applications seamlessly.
Because in this context you don't have to write code, it's what you build is
what you get. So what you really have
to do is just do your things on your own and just
drag and drop edit the components, this and that.
That's all you have to do when you're using Mightymeld. So it's actually used
by react developers or I mean
people who don't even have prior experience using
react. So it's brought so much
accessibility that even if you understand react or even if you
barely even understand react, you can actually use it because it
doesn't need you to understand all
that code and stuff. But I mean, you need to understand the framework you're
working with. You need to understand that 100%.
And so you don't just make mistakes. So here's
the next thing. These are just the basic things that makes up Mightymeld mail.
And now we're getting our hands really dirty into the entire
architecture of Mightymeld mail because there are three things that makes up mighty mail.
And let's just find out. First is the studio. The studio, I call it
the visual development environment. And I mean, you still
get to learn a lot about that in this talk. The next is also describe.
And in this context we're talking about describe as one of the major
parts of Mighty Mail. I mean, with the scribe,
it's just the main part of everything, India architectures and
also the envoy. Envoy is also very essential,
but not as essential as scribe is in this context.
And yeah, like I said, first thing we'll
start with scribe. Scribe is the art of
the entire, like Mightymeld mail architecture. Because without describe,
communication won't flow well. Without describe, so many
things won't work well. And I mean, scribe is
in control of, it's just in charge of code generation
and updates. When you make a component, when you drag and drop a
component and you try to edit and all that kind of stuff, it's all undescribed
to actually edit or, sorry, it's all undescribed to actually make so many
updates locally and do all that kind of stuff. Then next
it's just the main parts of the project, like adds
communication with the envoy and sends the communication directly
to the studio. So everything is all on scribe in terms of
communication and the main part of the project.
Now we have envoy, which is literally like very
one of the most crucial parts. But I don't think as crucial as
scribe. But when you're talking about architecture, you don't leave any
part of architecture behind because you
don't leave any components behind, rather because you have like
three different things in this context and one can do without one and one can
do without one. But what I'm just trying to say is scribe, in my
opinion, is what I feel like is the most important
out of the three. The envoy also provides like
mysmail plugin and all that kind of stuff, but it's
also really essential. And without this, you can't even launch
your application. You can't manage your application very well because this is actually in charge
of all these things. And without the envoy, you won't actually see so many
things working well. You won't see so many things working well in terms
of like the mytemail plugin. Without the envoy you don't get the mysmail plugin.
And which, if you don't have all these things, you can't launch your
application. Your application will start well, it won't start at all.
And yeah, that's just the basic thing about the envoy.
And so next, let's just get
our hands like a bit dirty, not even a bit dirty, but I mean
very dirty, but not for too long. So thank
you. So here is just some more explanation
on the studio and the envoy. Sorry, and describe an envoy.
And of course, the envoy is literally lightweight
because it has a lot of responsibilities in it, but it was actually
compressed, it was actually compressed to be lightweight because of so many responsibilities
on it. Right. I mean, the hand boy just make
things real seamless for its users and provide
great user experience and developer experience for its
users. I mean, it was compressed to be lightweight. And this actually works
directly with the scribe to send communication directly also to the studio.
And this scribe, as I've always said,
serves as the functionality of the entire project. Without the scribe, this is
not working. That is not working in terms of the functionality and in
terms of code generation and this and that, everything is not really working.
So scribe's communication
with envoy actually relies on just two things for the communication.
It relies on HTTPs and secure sockets in this context.
And these things are just used for the communication
between scribe and envoy. Right, in this
context. So that is just it. And like I said earlier on,
this envoy has something really attached to it, and the only thing
attached to it is the browser API,
which is directly in the plugin and all that kind of stuff.
But let's just move into the next part. And as you
can see, the studio is what I literally call like the visual development
environment. And without this, you are not seeing anything related to
my email. And to be honest, in this context,
this is the only thing you interact with as a user, right? This is the
only thing, basically you interact with as a developer,
a person trying to use mightymeld,
this is the only thing you interact with. This is where you get to drag
and drop edit all these things, but it actually sends some
communication directly to describe for code generation,
for the code update and all that kind of stuff. I mean, some people actually
see my email as a code generation too, but it's not exactly a code generation
two. Don't misquote them. Sorry, don't misquote like the fact that
it's a code generation two at all. It's not even a code generation two
or anything similar. It can only be, right. But it
is not because it provides a different service,
it provides a different thing. If you want to use it as
a code generation too, you can, but that's
not the aim, right? So this is
just everything literally about the studio. It helps to send
all the things to scribe, like the updates to scribe and then scribe
provides the updates right in the code base locally.
Right. So what it just does is the operations and it requests
to the LLM which tries to update the code.
So that's just really everything about the studio. This is just where you have
everything done and right in the studio, you can see the browser, you can see
everything. You can see your
layout of your application and everything, right? That is just everything
literally about the studio. Now, this is
the mighty melt plugin. The mighty melt plugin is attached,
right to the envoy. And without this mightymeld melt plugin,
trust me, your application is also not running because
this is actually something attached right to the envoy. And without
this, you don't get to see so many things you see on this studio,
for example, like the browser and everything, because everything just
works with the browser API. But yeah, there is just a couple of
information about this Mytmail plugin. I mean, the Mightymeld melt plugin is
attached to different technologies. I mean, you can use this in next,
you can also use this in reacts.
You can use this in so many, you get
to see them at the end of the day. So it just lets
you do so many things and get all the features you're looking for in my
email and everything.
Basically, envoy provides this browser
API, right? So everything is all
on this mightymeld plugin. And it's
just actually insane how this plugin works. But without this,
your application is not even starting. So next,
Mightymeld melt plugin. So now you can see like the SWC,
SWC remix, react and everything. These are
just technologies you can actually use with react.
You can actually use in Mightymeld mail.
You can have your mighty mail plugin embedded into certain technologies.
You can actually have all these things really working with.
So you're adjustless technologies.
So next, Mightymeld mail just lets you do
a lot of stuff without writing a
single line of code, like just lets
you do this do that without even
writing a single line of code. And it's actually insane how it works.
It's insane. Very insane how it works.
But it's just the greatest advantage. And this is why
I think people really do miss core, like Mightymeld mail as
a code generation, too, which is not. But yes,
that is just really everything about Mightymeld mail and its entire architecture.
So you can feel free to connect with me on YouTube,
okomikosta, Twitter, or any other social
media platform. Core of Lagos, using the Andrew core of
Lagos and LinkedIn. Of course,
my name Opemipo Disu. And if you're looking to hire me, you can
do so. Thank you
very much for watching my talk and joining in. So I hope
to see you, I hope you get to see me in
my other talks. And thank you very much. And have a nice one.