Hi everyone, my name is Pablo. For a quick background, I used to
be have a developer, but then I kind of moved to the dark side.
And currently I'm taking care of several teams of developers
and DevOps at CBapoland. And today
I would like to tell you a story about generations and generational
differences and how it all applies to our industry.
Here's our plan. We'll start with some general information. So what's
the concept around the generation? What are the different
generations? What's the thing with differences? Is it
all just mess or is it really true? I will give you
some theories about that. And in the second act, we'll move to
particular generations and we'll see about those differences.
Also, a disclaimer. There are a lot of memes about
generations. We have those boomers and those millennials
that are barking at each other. So this is kind of mammical
topic. So most of those memes are kind of offensive.
I was trying to bash everyone equally.
But be advised and just keep your distance or
we will all die. For starters, let's look at
movie, quick movie that will show you a difference in how people
born in different decades would react to hitting themselves
in a frame of the door. Let's look at that.
Okay, we have some idea about this.
All right, so let's move on to general information.
What's the generation or demographic cohort?
Do those differences even exist? Or they are just
myths? And what are the theories about this?
The idea of generation or demographic cohort
is the ideas. We understand it. So boomers,
millennials, those ideas, we know it is kind of connected with a western
world. What is a western world? Well, it kind
of changed over time. Like, for instance, Poland was initially in the eastern
bloc and moved to the western bloc.
In general, there's an idea that we can kind of segment
the population to those cohorts that are roughly
20 years long. And the idea is that
when we are young, when we are up to 20 years old,
the events that take place, the technology that is
currently developing that we are using shapes us.
Of course, we can adapt at later ages to that,
but mostly the impact is during the first 20
years of our life. You can
find some references to early
ideas, early topics around that. Up to 100 years ago,
Karl Mannheim was working on that in Germany. You can
find some sources dating back to 1952,
53, something like that,
because that was when works of car were translated
to English. And I can see some pictures here. So some, let's say
milestones of in technology, but also global events might
be wondering what's up with this boat there. So the
idea is that the boat is kind of like
a shotgun over the fireplace in the first act.
If you see the shotgun over those fireplace in the first act,
then you know that somewhere at the end of the story, somebody will take this
shotgun and fire from this. So we will get to
those boat and we will be proving at the
end of our story. So stay with me.
So, in order to be on the same page,
what is the meaning of those particular generations? This is
the image taken from Wikipedia. A little bit enhanced. On the
right, you have ages of particular generation,
right? So alphas are currently several years old. Then we
have generation z, which is roughly ten to 26.
We have millennials, which are 27, 26 to 42,
more or less. We have generation x, which is 42 to 58.
Baby boomers, 58 to 77. We have the silent generation,
which is over 77 years old. By the way,
disclaimer, don't be attached too much to those numbers because
they vary depending on the source. Sometimes it's one,
two, three, even five years into one
or the other direction. So this is more or less the consensus,
but it's not always very strict. So, regarding the
geometry of this picture of this trapezoid,
we have the date of birth. Then we are going to
18 years old, or starting the productive
period, let's say. Then we are going roughly to 60,
and then the shape is proving to 70. So the end
of the productive period, of course, we would like to live out a little bit
more than that. So in reality, there should be, say a tail
at the end. But this is in general to give you more or less understanding
of the timeframes of particular generations.
So, to visualize how it looks in a population.
So, for example, this is a population of Poland, probably would be something
similar in the western countries. So we
can see that we have this red peak of baby boomers just
after the end of born, after the end of
world War two. Then it's dropping into the
x generation, then it's starting to rise
again. We have older exes and
younger millennials around the second baby
boom, then it's dropping again. We have generation Z and
generation Alpha. We would expect to rise again into
the third baby boom. However, we have some changes
currently in, say, approach to having children.
Not many people want to have a lot of children, so it kind of flattened
at the end. So how this relates to an
article, technology industry. So here we have two examples.
Start with a software house in Poland.
We have a distribution of people.
What's kind of striking is that most of them are generation
Y. So millennials, roughly 80% are
millennials. We have a little bit of generation z on
the right, the green color, and we have a little bit
of generation x on the left, the orange color.
Then the second example is a software house, or rather consulting
company from Netherlands. It looks similar,
a little bit different. We have, say,
the dominance of millennials, generation Y. We have
a little bit of generation Z, but we have much more of generation X
and just a few of boomers at the far left with
the red color. The reason for that is that because the
industry started a bit earlier, Netherlands, and also
this particular company is more consulting.
It's more on the consulting side. So they rather hire a little
bit more senior people. So there is not too many people from generation
Z. But just to give you a general overview, most of
the people in it currently are millennials. Generation Y.
What's the idea with those myths and facts?
If you google for generational differences, you will
get a lot of materials saying that, hey, boomers are like this,
millennials are like this, you should do this or that in order
to handle them. On the other hand, if you google for
generational differences myths, then you will find a lot of
articles saying that this is all bullshit. Everyone is equal. We shouldn't
discriminate based on age or the generations.
And now the question arises, which one is true?
Probably the answer is something in between,
right? If you look at the price from last several
decades, you can see the pattern that the younger generation,
which was the baby boomers, maybe in seventy s, then generation x,
then millennials, generation z, this younger
generation, agoistic, those mid generation, they want everything
to themselves and don't have respect for
their elders, et cetera. And it kind of repeats over time,
right? Each younger generation is kind of treated like the same.
If you look at some scientific papers,
you can see a lot of articles on the generations,
conflicts that arise like 3000 years ago,
2000 years ago, some ancient athens, some medieval times,
France, in United States, in Africa, all over
the place. So all over the place, those different generations kind
of clashed against each other. We have this idea of
generational narcissism. So we kind of assume
that our generation is the best, right? Those younger
are immature, they don't know how to live. They have no
respect. Those older ones kind of stopped
progress. It's difficult to talk to them. And we kind of in the
middle. We are the best generation. You can see the quote that was found
over 3000 years ago on the clay tablet.
And also, if you read little bit of research, especially over
20 or 30 years. You can notice that usually we
have four generations on the work market. And it's usually divided
into two halves. We have two younger generations and
we have two older generations.
Those younger generations are immature. They don't
know their life, they have no respect. Older one are kind
of like the last adult generation. So usually the younger generation
from those two oldest. So currently it would be the x generations
are described as those last adult generation currently research.
But if you look like 20 years ago or something like that, the baby
boomers were the last adult generation and the exes were those
still immature and generation without respect
for their elders. So it is kind of shifting.
The perception of generation is shifting with time.
To make matters more complicated, it changed as
we age, right? So our personality,
based on, let's say, the genetic lottery, what kinds of genes
we get, what is our neural system,
and also how we were raised for the first 20 years,
say the most forming factor. So most
of our personality forms up to 20 years ago, 20 years old.
However, over the next roughly 30 years
or something like that, from 20 to 50, there are also
some changes. So as we age, we get
more conscientiousness, so more orderly.
We have those life figure out more or less. Let's say
we are more agreeable, so it's a bit easier to
negotiate with us. Maybe we are even getting a little
bit of naive if we speak about older people.
On the other hand, our openness is going down.
So we have our schemes, our approach to doing
things, and we are not that open to new experiences.
Our extraversion usually goes down, right? So if you are 20
years old, going for a pub crowd is a great idea.
If you are 40, maybe you should get a little bit more
sleep or something like this.
Also, our neuroticism goes down. Neuroticism is
the measure of how uncertain you are about the external words,
how afraid you are, what is the level of your emotions,
strong emotions, stuff like this. So as we age in general,
we are tending to get more stable. So our neuroticism
goes down. We can say that,
we can describe it that with age, just stop to
care that much about what others think about this. And it's
kind of healthy to an extent, of course.
And to make things even more complicated,
there are other factors at play. So international differences
is one thing, but also we have cultural differences. So depending
on where you were born, whether it was United States, Germany,
Japan, Poland, anything else, you have a different baseline of
behavior. And those cultures differ in many dimensions.
And probably the most important thing is
individual difference. Right? So we have this personal
preferences, how your nervous system was formed over the
first 20 years of your life. And those is the most important factor.
And just somewhere in the background over those two,
we have also general differences that
have some statistical impact. But you know how it is with statistics.
If I go for a talks with my dog,
statistically we have those legs.
So use it a little bit. No, the idea is that
the whole point of this chapter is that there are some statistical
generational differences, but we have to use it with caution.
Right. Don't use it as a hammer labeled millennial
or boomer and just use it on everyone. In the same way.
I think it should be rather used as a delicate tool
in your people skills arsenal just to have this
understanding that there are some differences, but don't rely too
much on them. Let's move on the second act of our story.
So we talk a little bit about our particular generations
and how to deal with them. General.
So we start as a framing device. We start with the silent generation.
So those are people who are currently over 77
years old. So probably you won't put
as many of them as in our industry. They are
mostly retired by now, with some exception.
Old ceos or some people in corporation don't
just stay there forever. Wouldn't like to focus too much
on them just as a framing device. But I would like to give you
some examples from our industry. So we have Sir
Gordon Moore. So the famous Moore's
law about the power of processors growing over time.
And also co founder of intel. We have Margaret Hamilton,
who was writing a software for Apollo spacecraft and also
did a lot of research papers. We have Donald
notes, who is called the father of algorithm analysis.
He's still writing this book about the art of computer programming started
somewhere in the 60s. We have Barbara Liskov.
So from this name we have Liskov substitution principle,
the solid acronym. But she also had a
lot of contribution to the scientific field of computer science.
We have Alan Kay, who is known for
working on the first graphical user interfaces even before Microsoft
and Google and decided to borrow them. And also he is
the inventor of the small talk language.
We have Brian Kerrigan and Ken Thompson, who worked on Unix,
wrote the first book about C C
language. Ken Thompson is also an author of
Go language. And we have Larry Ellison, who is one
of the founders of the Oracle Corporation. So those are
all people from the silent generation and
move on to the baby boomers. So baby boomers
born just after the World War II. So currently
age between roughly 58 77.
We can kind of call them the analog generation. So when
they were starting to work, we were using pen and
paper, not computers. But of course, over time they migrated
to digital technology as well. Some differences
for baby boomers. So we had a cold war in the full swing.
So we never knew if you wouldn't be obliterated by the atomic
bomb blast. At some points, we had the landing on the moon.
Technology wise, the television started to be widespread,
maybe more in western countries, not necessarily
in Poland in particular. In eastern countries, on the other
hand, we have this growing communism with
the Cold War. If you ask Americans, they would
probably say that assassination of JFK was kind of the event that
impacted their life. And computers
are basically just starting to be used, right?
So they are rather used by scientists in white coats, not really
in mainstream business yet.
So what's the approach to baby boomers?
So baby boomers kind of like the face to face conversations.
They have the high power distance, meaning that if you have some formal
title, such as manager, maybe even a doctor,
you are being granted the respect out of the box value
structure, hierarchy, loyalty. Often they worked their
whole life or a large portion of their life in a single company.
They also value hard skills, right? So what you can do
technically what you are skilled at, not necessarily soft
skills. So how smoothly you can talk and stuff like this.
If you want to make them happy,
you can put them in some formal position of power.
So give them some formal title, such as senior just
manager, et cetera, and give them some opportunity to
mentor younger colleagues and show
them the business and stuff like this. Some example of baby
boomers. In it we have Biann Strozrop,
the author of C Plus plus, we have Steve Wozniak.
From Apple, we have James Gosling, the author of Java language,
Bill Gates. From Microsoft, we have Guido von
Rosso, the author of Python language, Tim Cook.
And from Apple, we have Anders
Heidezberg, who is the author of C Sharp language.
And we have Jeff Bezos,
the bookseller and also the virtual machine seller
Amazon. So let's move on to our next
generation, X generation,
born after 65, so currently roughly 42
to 50 air, 58 years old. The name
came from the unknown. X is the unknown. So world
was changing quite fast, new technology.
We didn't really know how this generation
will turn out. There was a book,
the X generation. There was a song,
the X Generation, and kind of somehow stuck. We can
also call them digital immigrants. So it's
often the case that when they were young, the world was more analog.
So pen and paper. And only after some
20 years or something, they started to use computers,
or maybe not even yet computers, but let's say more of
an electronics and digital world. Sometimes they are called
latchkey keys. So because of the social changes,
parents tend to work a bit longer. And those were
more divorces. So there were more single parents. And often
children have to come back to an empty house. So they had those
key around at their neck, and they have to open the
doors themselves. In those United States,
you can sometimes see the name, the MTV generation and
the current research, you can see the name that they
are the last adult generations. Those generation
younger are still not adult yet.
This is about generation. The idea about generations X.
What were the influences of Generation X?
So, in Poland, we had the martial law
in 1981. In general, the dissolution of Soviet
Union at the end of the Cold War,
the disaster in Chernobyl, 1986. Most influence
on the Eastern Europe. They have some first computers,
like Commodore, Atari, Amiga, stuff like this.
Pop culture is coming to Eastern Europe, the western
culture regarding cell phones, it's still rather a thing
of. Maybe some executives or directors
are using those brick like phones that we
have here. I saw the walkman that was quite popular
at those times. So how to deal with Generation X
then? So exers tend to be very autonomous,
right? Sometimes it's connected with the statistical upbringing.
Like if they needed to get back alone to
home, they kind of develop those sense of autonomy. So they
want to do stuff on their own, not necessarily
with the team or other people. They're quite focused
on results. So they want to know where
they are currently, where they are going, how fast, what are
the tools at their disposal, and kind of have the ability to
measure the progress. They still kind of feel
this authority to people that I hire in the hierarchy,
but not as strong as baby boomers. They still like a
little bit of. To have a little bit of rules and procedures around that.
They're quite focused on the career. So often they say that,
hey, I'm a manager, I'm a software developer,
not that I'm a pava or John or any
other person. So they are kind of prone to
burnout, like if you are a manager or team leader or
just a good colleague, it's good to look for those symptoms if
they are not really working too much, too hard on
the path to burnout. So be careful with that.
Some examples from our industry. We have Michael Dell,
the producer of computers and hardware.
We have Satya modela from Microsoft. Currently we
have Rasmus Lerdorf, who is the author of PHP language,
Linus Torvald. So first, Linux and Git, we have
John Carmack from the gaming industry, Quake of Stein,
doom, stuff like this. We have Elon Musk, let's say,
from Tesla and SpaceX,
and currently being a great manager,
or Twitter or X, or however it is called. Now we
have Larry Page from Google, or Alphabet
rather. And we have Jack Dorsey, who is actually the
founder of Twitter. All right, so let's move
to our millennial Austin, born after more or
less 1981. So currently 27 to
42, more or less years old. Why the
name? Why? Kind of stems from the fact that
millennials like to know why they do things like those.
It's not enough to tell them to do things. They need to know the reason.
And it's better be some sensible reason.
Sometimes they are called 90s kids.
Disclaimer here, 90 skits is not about being born
in the SE, it's about being kid in the.
If somebody was born in 1999 and says
that he or she's a 90s kids, you can a little bit
frown upon this. Milayas are also sometimes
called digital natives. So usually computers were
quite widespread when they were children.
Computers, but not really on Internet or online
presence. So they are a little bit more used to technology
and to the digital stuff. What are some other influences?
So we have the first Internet when millennials were young or in their
teens. So we have this great example
of dialing attempt with a modern. We have a globalization
in full swing. So more countries are joining NATO and
European Union in general. The cold war is over and
war seems to be quite at peace. We have this
30 years of globalization and global peace, which is currently going
maybe to an end because the
situation is quite not very stable at the moment. But while millennials
were young, it was very peaceful. We have some first social
networks on Facebook. Gigi was a communicator,
those messenger in Poland specifically,
we have some first really accessible smartphones
that were really kind of more interesting than whatever we have now.
Smartphone is basically the same as another. If you
ask Americans about some experiences
of that time, we'll probably hear about 911. This is
kind of like a point between millennials and
Generation Z, because the oldest Z generations,
people from Z generations were around four years old when 911
happened. So they usually don't remember that. If you
remember what you were doing at this time, you are millennial or
older generation, some other electronics.
So we have a discount here. Computers are quite popular, as I mentioned.
And the economic crisis was also after
2008, 2009 had
quite a lot of impact on lives of many millennials,
especially when they were starting to look for a job.
It was not that easy back then.
So how to deal with millennials? So millennials are probably
the most educated generation so far. For instance,
in Poland in 1990, there was 300,000 students,
but just 15 years later, there was over 2 million.
So millennials like technology. There's this term,
helicopter parents. So often it was the case
that parents of millennials were helping, going into the chopper,
getting the chopper into the helicopter, flying to their
chill, to help them in some difficult situations. So millennials are maybe
statistically not that autonomous as
the X generation. They like to work in teams.
There are also the first generation who really appreciated
the life work balance. So they are not really working to
work, just to life. And it's good to have some life besides work.
So they are not that keen to do
overtime compared to excess. Again, on average,
they have much lower power distance. Right. So my boss is rather my
body. Not necessarily very formal approach.
And they're generally more flexible than an earlier generation, more geared
toward teamwork. They like to spend some time
on their personal brands. It's often the case that they are freelancers,
because it gives them more flexibility to work at whatever hours they
want. For instance, they are more open to changes,
they are more direct and general, more open to
new experiences. Some examples of influential
known people from millennial
generation in technology so we have Ryan Dal,
who is the author of Node Js. We have Zankimik,
who is the founder of TikTok. Daniel actor,
the founder of Spotify. Mark Zuckerberg, probably most well
known person here from Facebook. Mela Iparkis
from Canva, those designer software,
Patrick Collison from Stripe, Whitney Wolfhardt
from Tinder and Bumble,
and Yvonne Spiegel from Snapchat,
so we can move on to our next generation.
Traditional Z is mostly just entering the work market,
at least older of them. They are between ten and
26 years old, sometimes not very creatively
known as post millennials. Snowflakes, that's the term from
sometimes can be attributed to like a snowflake server
in it. So every server has a different configuration. Also every member
of those nation, those unique individual are different.
Sometimes called zoomers, the playworth of boomers,
three c's. So connect, communicate,
change, and we can call them the online natives,
because the Internet and those online world was there since
the beginning, since they were born. They are used to be online.
They are used to is that everything is basically to
be found in the Internet, some influences,
right? So probably the greatest influence for
generation Z was the Covid-19 pandemic. So there was those remote
schooling, maybe finding the first job remotely. The world
kind of has shifted around generations
that are used to having this technology at
the fingertips of smartphones. With all those access to all
the knowledge of humanity. Basically we
are kind of nearing those end of 30 years
peace period right after the end of Cold War. So currently
the geopolitics is getting tricky. We have some contenders
for the world order as we had after the World War II.
And times are not very stable.
We have some next social
network. So Snapchat, basically, when I was doing this presentation,
when I was doing some research, I found out that Snapchat is no longer,
let's say no longer those newest social network,
and it's still stuck on a Facebook level. So TikTok is more.
Also, what's important for generations is that they are more
focused on environment, more environment conscious. So we see that
over our previous decades,
basically what happened is that the climate was changed,
right? We have this extreme weather phenomena.
Currently, the current generation is more aware of that.
It's kind of important matter for them compared to
some earlier generation. Of course, again, on average,
statistically, we have a great polarization
currently, political polarization. So we have those people to
simplify, people on the left, on the right. And it's even more difficult to
talk between those two groups compared to years ago.
And it's even more fueled by social media because there's
controversy. If there are different bubbles, there's a
lot of discussion, a lot of hate speech, et cetera, generates a lot of traffic
and ads like that. So it's not helping us. It's getting
difficult. And we have technology that starts resembling
magic, basically, especially after, especially last
one or two years with the advances in AI,
it's a kind of different world. So how to deal with
Generation Z then? So Generation Z is even more
educated than the previous generation. We have a
lot of knowledge at our fingertips because basically whatever
you want to learn, if it's a front end framework
or how to cook some meal or how
to do your tie, you can find a tutorial on YouTube somewhere
there. So just need to look and grab for that.
Generations Z is used to globalization and diversity.
So they have friends all over those place, basically online,
different countries, people are different. And it's kind of natural for them.
They're very individual. They have a very
different approach to different things as
compared to previous generation.
As of workplace, the workplace is no longer some
subplace where you have to go to make money. It can be fun.
You can cheer in there. It's kind of more civilized.
Also, generation Z kind of looks for
the greater cost in their work. So basically,
if the company is doing something else
besides earning money, like takes care of the environment or
some local communities, et cetera, it's more attractive for
generation Z. Some kind of
gamification at work or in the recruitment process might
be helpful. Generation Z is also even
more entrepreneurial than previous generation because they
have a lot of tools to monetize, right? They are used
to social media. You can create some content, get those money
from that. If you have some hobbu where you're buying some not
very typical stuff, maybe some paintings, some figures,
stuff like this. Maybe you can set up a small shop and sell
some access that you have. It's quite easy right now.
For generation Z, the quick feedback loop is important.
Again, probably it might be something connected with social media where
you write something and then you get some reactions and comments. So if
you are a team leader or a boss, you shouldn't be waiting one year
to give any feedback to number of generations. It should be
shorter, quicker, some appreciation, like just even liking
some message on work teams or stuff like this,
it's helpful. And for Gen Z, the hierarchy
flattens even more. So if you are a formal boss,
well, it has some meaning, but not a lot of meaning.
In fact, you have to earn your respect to be respected by
Gen Z. It's not just a formal title, formal hierarchy.
And you might expect that I will give you another eight people
from the next generation that were influential. I was trying to
find them, but it seems that it's just a little bit too early.
There's a lot of Gen Z people that are running some very successful startups.
They are just not that big.
So that we know which one of them, we really
have some kind of impact on our world.
So maybe when I will be doing this presentation in five years, ten years,
then we'll see. I hope I will be adding some
people here. And our last generation,
I won't be focusing on them too much because they are just few years old.
Don't know yet how they will approach the work.
They might just assume that, hey, they can install some application on
a smartphone, because before they are able to walk or something.
So it's going to be tricky. We still have several years
to prepare our workplaces for the generation alpha.
We'll see. I promised you
a boat that will be rolling a boat presentation.
So here we are as a boat. Let's do
an experiment in mind. Experiment with different generations. How different
generations would approach being told to roll
the boat. So let's start with boomers. We have a captain.
We have a crew of boomers. The captain says,
start proving. And the boomers would say,
okay, boss, this is enough. If you
take the X generation, we have the X.
We have those, captain, we have the X crew. The captain
says, let's roll. The crew might
say, hey, wait, captain, what's our target?
Where are we going? What's our speed? Do we have a device
to measure our speed? What's those direction? How fast should we go?
What's the deadline? So how fast should we rowing? If they get
this information, it will be much easier if they have this control
and those sense of target. Let's move
to millennials. Let's assume that we have this millennial screw.
The captain says, we are rowing. Millennial would
say, hey, hold on, captain. Those is an engine on this boat,
right? So why should we roll manually? If we can just
start the engine and get some rest, right?
So perhaps the captain would then say,
okay, we are in some kind of special
ecologic zone. There are different type of animals. We need to keep silent.
We cannot use engine area like masurian
lakes in Poland, for instance. You have to use those if
there is no wind on your boat.
And, well, it makes sense. From Milan,
they know the reason why we should do this, in order not to disturb some
wild animals. All right, then we can roll in silence.
Okay, and what about Generation Z? So basically,
let's say the captain says we are rowing. And what would those
Gen Z member say? Hey, what are we
proving towards the right island?
Is the island called profit the right target?
Maybe we should also visit some other islands, like environment
or local communities or some other just
causes. And this is something that would
make Generation Z more happy, not just earning
money for the company. All right, so those is our trip
in a boat. So in the end, I was telling
you about different stuff that different generations,
let's say, put emphasis on, right? Some of them likes this,
some of them like that. But in the end, if you look at this,
basically all of us need some kind of stability in the company.
We want to have some leader that knows the direction.
We like to be a little bit independent. We like to see the result of
our work. We don't want to spend the whole life at
job. We want to have some private life. We enjoy some kinds of. A little
bit of flexibility. We are a little bit individualistic.
It's nice to have good atmosphere in the job, to get
some feedback, to have this feeling that we are
doing some greater good, not just earning money and
of course getting respect from others. So basically all of
those things is important for all of the members of different generation,
maybe with a little bit of different emphasis.
So we can look at this tale about generation, but this
is basically like a story of evolution of
our. Those slide was
blurred on purpose. Don't worry. It's from the book reinventing
organizations by Frederick Lalou, who is describing,
let's say, different types of organizations, how they evolve over
time. And most of those types evolved over not
that many, like last hundred years. Many organizations
are at different levels, and we can see that those organizations
put different emphasis on different stuff.
And those different generations
kind of invented some parts of our workplace for us.
And currently you can take advantage of all of that.
All right, so we are nearing to an end, so called those last
slide. So this QR code
actually leads to my LinkedIn profile. You're very welcome to
join my network. I'm inviting you,
if you like to have some. Excuse me about
that. If you want to add some notes from
this lecture or you would like to look at the
slides again or some recording from different instances of this
talk, I have it all on my blog, which is called how to train your
Java. It's not about Java anymore, don't worry.
It's mostly about general software and people work. If you'd
like to reach me in private, ask some questions, you are very
welcome to do so. Take care of
yourself, take care of people around you, and thank you
very much for your time.