Thanks for tuning in and welcome to this talk. I am Abhishek Gupta, a developer
advocate at AWS where I work on a bunch of things, but containers,
databases and golang happen to be some of my key focus areas.
And I am joining you today from my home here in New Delhi, India.
So why am I really talking about deleting or removing Yaml?
To be very, very honest with you, I have nothing against YaML.
I have tolerated things like XML in the the past. So I guess YAML
is fine. But I'm a developer, I like to write code and
the last time I checked, YAML isn't really a programming language.
But if you think in terms of kubernetes, YaML is
the king. It's like this lingua franca, so to speak. So if you look at
existing tooling like helm or customize, or even
if you're writing manifests by hand, it's all Yaml.
So although the talk says removing YAml,
it's more about circumventing it or pushing it behind the
scenes so that it's not in your face all the time, so to speak.
So yeah, in the next 20 to 25 minutes or
so I will talk about this tool called CDK for Kubernetes.
CDK. It's in short, and it's an open source project which
is part of the CNCF or the cloud Native Computing foundation.
And in very, very simple terms, cdks is a framework using
which you can define and model your kubernetes, Opensource and applications.
So I'll give you a verb and tour of how you can use cdks
with the Go programming language.
So I want to start off by talking about how would you
typically use something like CDK. So conceptually it's actually
quite simple. So as you can see here is a very, very high level overview
of the workflow. So if you kind of start off
by bootstrapping a project, you write some code to
define your Kubernetes application and then you ask
CDK eight to convert that code into YAMl.
Right? And once you have that YAml manifest, it's really
up to you as to how you want to use it.
Every CDK application consists of what you call a tree of
components, and these are also called constructs. So you combine
basic constructs like a deployment, or a service
or ingress, or a persistent volume and so on and so forth,
and combine that into a chart and a chart
is yet another construct in syndicates. And finally,
one or more of such charts can be but inside
an app or an application. So an app is the
root of the tree in the entire hierarchy,
right? So what I'm going to do is switch over to my ide. Now enough
of slides and we'll spend some time looking at some code,
just playing around with things and trying to make sense of everything, trying to
make sense of what cdks is and how it works. So let
me do that. All right,
awesome. So in addition to actually being a framework,
CDkates also provides a very, very handy CLI.
So what I'm going to do is use this CLI to bootstrap a very
simple application here just to get things going right. So I
hope you can see this.
So I'm going to create a new directory and
change into that. Simple as that. And then I'll kick things off.
All right, so what I'm going to do now is use the CLI to bootstrap
an application. So say CDkates, which is the CLI
init, initialize an app. And I'm using go
here as a programming language. So I'm specifying go app here.
So I started off with an empty directory and
just invoked the CDK CLI and asked me, hey, give me something
to work with, right? And what it's going to do is come back to
me and you'll see that soon. So it's going to spit. But this
very, very simple, yet very useful starting point
from where I can build on stuff, right? So here
it is. This process is done. So if I were to open this main go
file over here real quick. And if you look
at this function called new, my chart, what this does is
create something called a CDKs chart object.
Okay. And if I were to scroll down a little bit and show
you the main function. So this
actually encapsulates or this chart is
within this app, right? So in this
app there's just one chart. And right now this chart is actually empty.
But I'm going to add some code here and we'll define a very, very simple
sort of hello world Kubernetes, our favorite Nginx deployment here.
So in the interest of time, what I'm going to do is do some copy
paste and then walk you through that code real quick.
So let me do that and
I'll just update some of the packages here because they
are not quite right, but yeah. All right,
awesome. So just focus on this part of the code right here.
So even if you've deployed a very sort of
simple Kubernetes application in the past, you have some experience with
that you should be familiar with what you actually see right now. So things like
labels or selectors or deployment,
or a container here, an image and so on and so forth, just like you
would define a yaml manifest, right?
But the big difference here is that now this is in the form
of code. This just happens to be go code. But CDKs also
supports Python, typescript and Java as well.
So while this looks pretty simple,
and you might feel like, hey, this is enough, I'm good,
but trust me, things are going to actually get pretty verbose when
you start building serious stuff using these simple primitives.
So what I'm going to do now is actually containers with this Nginx
based example, but show you how to improve this a
little bit. Right? So in order to do that, I'll switch over
to a different project here, which I have for you.
Now, if I were to open this main go file right
here. Now this is going to look
very, very similar to what I just showed you, but at
the same time it's different. So what I'm
actually doing is using the CDKs plus API, which is much
more natural and intuitive. So if I scroll up a little bit, if you
see, this is the package which I'm using, which is called CDKs plus.
So what I do here is define a deploying,
add a container to it. And if you notice,
I really don't need a lot of boilerplate code here,
things like defining selectors or labels. And then
finally what I do is expose this via a service.
So all this is go code.
And to convert this into a manifest, I can actually go
ahead and use the CLI. And to do that,
I'm going to hop back into this terminal right
here and use a command called cdks
synth. Okay? So what this will do is this will
generate a manifest in a different folder called deskt.
So if you see this is right here. Now, if I were to open
that manifest for you, just to show
this, as you can see, I just have a
deployment, very simple deployment with pod spec
and all the usual stuff, right? The selectors and the labels and
the containers image everything, all the normal
stuff, which you would typically do if you would define it
manually, for example. And if I were to scroll down, you would see the service
as well, which happens to be of the type load balancer here. So just like
we defined in our go code, that's exactly how the
yaml sort of got manifested, so to speak.
Right now. Now that you have this Yaml file, it's really up to you.
Of course, in terms of how you want to use it. So you can obviously
use Kubectl and do all this manually, but actually integrating
this into your existing Gitops workflow is something.
It's an obvious choice and that's a very interesting topic. But to
be honest with you, I don't have time to cover it in detail.
So let's go ahead and keep proceeding.
So any Kubernetes demo is incomplete without Nginx, right?
So let's actually go ahead and deploy this thing. So I'm
going to go back. So I'm actually using a local Kubernetes cluster
here. Just happens to be a single node kind cluster for the purposes
of this demo. So what I'm going to do is just apply this Yaml
file. So just apply the context of this disk folder. And as you can
see, the deployment and service have been created. So if I were to go
ahead and check as to what's going on. So if you see that
the pod is currently in the container creating phase.
So in the meanwhile we can go ahead and check our service.
And you can see the service here as well, the load balancer
type, it has been created. And if I were to go back and
check the pod again. Yeah, so it's in the running status now.
So if I wanted to try and access this NginX deployment for
the purposes of this demo, I'm going to just use port forwarding
here on port 1990 and go
to my browser here real quick and
cool. We are able to have this simple demo
up and running and access our Nginx server. Great.
Now while this Nginx example was very
simple, of course. Right. But now I'm going to move on to something a little
bit more involved. So I'm going to show you a WordPress stack
that has a MySQL database along with the WordPress application itself.
So in order to do that, what I will do
is I'll switch over to yet another folder or
project which I have. So if I were to open the code here and
scroll up a little bit. Now if you notice here we actually have two charts.
One is this new MySQL chart and the other one is the new WordPress
chart. Okay. And as you can see, there is a lot going on here.
We are defining all sorts of Kubernetes resources like secrets
and deployments and of course containers. And also notice
persistent volumes and persistent volume claims. Right.
And the same applies to the WordPress chart as well.
So pretty awesome. This is good, right?
But let me repeat this again. You do not want to
write these things over and over, say by
multiple teams within your organization. What you can
actually do is write this as a custom construct,
a custom cdks construct, and then it will
be usable as an artifact.
It's a very simple reusable artifact which other teams can utilize.
So let me show this to you as well. And for that, as usual,
I'm going to hop into another project quickly and
show you how a custom construct works.
So if you pay attention to this
function, call right here. Now imagine, imagine if someone wanted
to stand up a simple WordPress cluster. What they
can do is simply go in and use
the custom construct, just like any of the out of the box
ones which you use like deployment or a service and so on and
so forth. So this new WordPress stack function actually
encapsulates the process of creating the components
for a WordPress stack. Now if I were to dig into this a little bit
and go into what this function does, and notice, the first thing you should notice
is it actually returns a construct,
right? It doesn't return a chart, okay? And whatever
you see within this function now, it's very
similar to what I just showed you, right? I showed you two different
charts. One was for MySQL, one was for WordPress.
This function sort of encapsulates everything, all that process
and provides this AWs, a single
go to sort of artifact which other developers, other engineers
within your organization can use. Right? All right,
cool, this looks good. So let's go ahead and deploy a WordPress
cluster. So as usual, what I'm going to do is use this simple command
cdks synth. It's going to kickstart
the process of creating the YAMl manifests.
And what I can actually do is go ahead and create
this. So what I'm going to do is actually watch the pods in
the background while I,
excuse me. So I think I was a slight
typo here.
All right, so I'm going to watch the pods and at the same time apply
the context of this chart. So let's see what's going on here.
So yeah, our pods are getting created. They are in the
pending state right now. But while this is getting done,
let me show you the manifest which was actually generated. That should be pretty
interesting. Yeah, so you
see here just the usual stuff. Everything which we had
specified in the form of that function. So we have a secret
here. We have a deployment for MySQL
database for WordPress. We have persistent volume
claims we have a service, all the usual things which you
would expect, right? But imagine you had to write all this by hand.
It's better to define this in code and then ask a tool like cdks
to convert that into YAml. Right? So the same applies to
the WordPress deployment as well. So I have a deployment object and
a service which is of type load balancer because I need to access my WordPress
application publicly and so on and so forth. Right.
So let's actually go back and see
what's happening. All right. So awesome.
So I think things are ready. What we can
do is actually check our persistent volumes and
volume claims as well. Pv is up and ready. And what about the
PVC? It is bound so I think things look good. So we are right to
try this thing out. So as usual I'm going to do some port forwarding
here just to test things out and I'm going to access the WordPress
on port 80 80. So let me go back to my browser here
and just change my port real quick.
Let's see how this goes. All right, so what you see now is actually the
landing page for a WordPress website,
something which I can create from scratch just for demo purposes.
I can show this to you as to how
you can sort of play around with this WordPress application. So I have set up
my website now I can just log in using the credentials I had
just set. Yeah, so right now you're seeing a
WordPress application on Kubernetes using CDK. So this is the
admin console. Yeah, I can go ahead add a new
post life from
conf fourty two. So far so good
I guess, and publish this post.
And I can actually now go back to the website itself, exit the admin console
and yeah, this is my WordPress website.
Cool, nice. So far so awesome. Now you can go ahead and sort
of keep playing with this WordPress website, maybe try things like deleting the mySQl
deployment and just fooling around with things to see how it
behaves and so on and so forth. So I'll leave that as an exercise to
you. And what I'm going to do now is take a
look at a slightly more advanced use based and this is
about how to actually use crds with
cdks. So crds actually if you're not familiar, it stands
for custom resource definitions. So custom resources are
actually a part of the Kubernetes extension API.
So just like we have pods and deployments and other
native objects in Kubernetes, you can define custom ones as well.
And it's the custom resource definition API that actually makes
this possible. So although CRDs and their implementations are
relatively advanced, and obviously I'm not going to cover that in
this session, but at the end of the day you have to understand that
they are also defined as YAMl manifests. But with
CDK eight, what you can do is import existing crds
or custom resource definitions and simply use them as
API in your code. Okay, so let me show you an example
of a project called Strimzi. So it's actually a Kubernetes operator
that helps you run and manage Apache Kafka on
Kubernetes. So I already have the crds involved. So let me
quickly go back to that project as well and
show you how that thing is. So like I said, I have
the Strimzi crds already installed. So as
you can see here, there are a bunch of crds, but the ones which I'll
be using are for creating a Kafka cluster and a Kafka topic.
So I'll just be using two crds here. So Kafka
topics and this core Kafka cluster CRD.
Okay. All right, so what I'll do is first
import these crds using the syndicates
CLI, okay. And I'm going to reference the crds directly from GitHub,
as you will see very soon. Oops,
typo. And as you can see, I'm doing a CDK, it's import,
and this is the location for the CRD, the Yaml file itself.
I'm referencing the one directly from GitHub, and this
is going to go ahead and import this. This is for the Kafka cluster
CRD, and I will also import the CRD for
working with Kafka topics. So as always,
I have referred to this CRD right here
directly from GitHub, but doesn't really matter as long as you have access to this
Yaml file. All right, so if I go ahead and check the
imports folder here, you'll find something interesting. So we have a couple of directories
called Kafka streams IO and Kafka topic, underscore blah blah blah.
So these are slightly verbose naming, but the important
thing is that now what you can do is use
these crds as API, like I said earlier. So if I were to open this
code right here and show
you this function called new Kafka Chart, which happens to return
a CDK's chart, what is it really doing? So it's simply using
that API, the one which we just generated to define
or specify a new Kafka cluster.
And it has a zookeeper as well. So as you can see, I have provided
the version, the number of replicas or the number of Kafka
brokers, the configuration for the server and so on and so forth.
Okay, and how would I actually use this if I were to open
the main go file? You will see that all I'm doing is encapsulating
this chart into an application,
a syndicates app, and yes, that's pretty much all I need to
do. Right? So to create a new Kafka cluster, I'm going
to follow the same old, the usual workflow.
So I'll first do a syndicates synth. It is going
to spit but Yaml manifest.
So if you see here, if I were to open this file here again,
this is the custom resource definition for Kafka
cluster using strimzi, right? So everything which we had specified in
the code is here. The version, the number of replicas and the configuration and
so on and so forth. So simple as that. Now I can go ahead and
apply this manifest to the cluster so that it can
go ahead and create the resources required for this Apache Kafka
installation on kubernetes. Okay, so to be
very honest with you, this is actually going to take a bit of
time. So if I were to check this right here.
So as you can see, I have all the resources in
the Kafka namespace and the cluster
operator. This is something which I had, like I said, I had already
deployed the crds as well as the strimz operator. So as you can see,
this is already up and running. Of course, otherwise nothing would work.
And right now what's work in progress is the zookeeper
pod and the related resources. Okay,
I already have zookeeper service created here,
so let's see how this goes. If I were to check this again
as to how things are going. Actually, you know what, let me
do this. Get pods.
Okay. So I can see that all these pods are up and running.
So what I'm going to do is just wait for some
of these resources. Excuse me, I didn't mean to type that.
My apologies. So let's see if everything
we need is here. So let's
see. Yeah, so some of the resources
are still actually getting created.
Now sort of once everything
is created, you should actually see a sort of success message
from this command.
We'll give it a few seconds.
Awesome. Okay, so as you can see,
our Kafka resources, the Kafka cluster on kubernetes is
up and running. Now we can actually go ahead and test it
using the good old Kafka Cli the producer and consumer
Cli. So let me go ahead and do that. So I'm going to first
get the value for the bootstrap server. I'm just going to simply run a bunch
of commands and show you how this cluster actually works.
And what I'm going to do is initiate the
producer here and
I'm going to start the consumer in a different terminal first the
bootstrap server, and it,
and I can actually go back here and produce
messages. Hello, oops.
Hello conf 42.
If I can type cube
native, let's see what's going on on the consumer side.
All right, awesome. So we are actually able to receive these messages.
Hello Con 42, cube native. Awesome. So this is great,
right? So what you just saw, it's a very, very simple example,
I do agree. But then if you think about in the larger,
in the bigger scheme of things, you were able to actually write code,
actual go code, to define a Kafka cluster and
then use that to convert that into a CRD specification
or yaml to define your custom resource definition and then apply
that to your Kubernetes cluster. So with that said,
what I'm going to do is switch back to my presentation.
That's pretty much a wrap up in terms of the demos at least.
So let me switch back
real quick. So that's pretty much
all I have. I mean this is all I could cover in the space of
about 20 odd minutes. But just to give you a quick
recap. So we covered the basic syndicates API
and how to bootstrap a project and write a Kubernetes deploying.
And then you saw how cdks plus provides a much better
developer experience in terms of a very natural and intuitive
API. We then explored how to abstract away WordPress
as a custom component and then use that on demand to
spin up a complete WordPress deployment on kubernetes. And last but
not the least, we looked at some advanced stuff where we
imported a custom resource definition as an API and then
used that to kick off a Kafka cluster on kubernetes.
So really what I'm hoping for you is
to think about this concept of infrastructure is
code as opposed to infrastructure as code. So what you saw here
is actually a code first approach using the programming languages
we are familiar with, which we leverage day in, day out, right?
So if you want to learn more, there are lots of resources you can refer
to. And I've actually been writing up a series of blog posts.
So yeah, check that out. I think I've finished about
four blogs and a couple of them are still left so
it's a pretty lengthy series but I'm hoping it will be useful for you.
Of course you can read up on the Kubernetes excuse me
the CDK's documentation AWS well and there are a bunch of
examples on the CDK's GitHub repo and of course then there
is the API reference as well.
One last thing before I let you go, I would really really appreciate
it if you can provide your feedback. We really want to hear from you
how your experience was and we always look for ways to
improve so all you need to do is scan this QR code or go
directly to this URL if you so prefer. It shouldn't take more
than a minute to be honest with you so this is very short and sweet
feedback so I would really appreciate it if you can help us with
your inputs. So thanks again for joining and enjoy the
rest of the conference.