Hello friends. My name is Ala Shiban and I'm the co founder of a startup
called Klotho, enabling teams to write universal backend
code that runs anywhere. I led teams in the visual studio
at Microsoft and more recently led the cloud services.org
at Ride Games. I'm going to walk you through the state of infrastructurefromcode from
code in 2023, starting with what is infrastructure
from code? How does it compare to infrastructurefromcode as code
and the leading approaches and tools in the space?
Infrastructure from code, or IFC, is a broad term around
tools that analyze application code to infer the cloud resources
the application needs, and then creates and maintains
them without you having to manually define them. What that means
is that the tools are able to take application code with some
or no metadata, process it, and create a deployable
cloud version of it. What does the name mean and how is it different from
infrastructure as code? Infra as code or IAC
refers to tools that allow developers or cloud engineers to describe
infrastructure. You write templates or actual code,
terraform, pulumi or similar, that describes lambdas or kubernetes clusters,
IAM policies, API gateways, how they interconnect
sqs or Kafka queues and is loosely aligned with using
these resources using an injected configuration
or environment variable. And while the name infrastructurefromcode from code sounds
similar, it means something quite different. It refers to tools
that automatically infer the needed infrastructure components
from application code. Here's an example from one of the tools.
The application code is a plain Python app that
uses the Redis SDK and fast API web framework.
And once the tool is run on that code, it generates an API gateway,
a lambda to run the code, an elasticache instance to back
the SDK usage in the code that includes vpcs and
policies. The things that are needed to make this deployable and runnable.
And depending on the tool, you're able to swap out technologies without
changing the application code. Nowhere did it say Lambda. Looking at
it from an aspirational point of view, what these tools enable is
writing universal backend code that runs on different target platforms
with varying runtime characteristics, different clouds,
different underlying services on prem, different architectures,
and they're able to adapt as requirements change.
What problems does it solve, though? How rich would you be IFC? You got $1
every time somebody promised you a tool that lets you focus
on the business logic and not the infrastructure. And if you've been in the
industry for long enough, you've seen this never ending cycle.
VMS service oriented architectures microservices,
containers, mesos, serverless, and now kubernetes.
Focusing on the business logic comes with a really expensive asterisk
associated with it, because there's a lot that goes into building back ends,
lots to learn and set up. This list wouldn't surprise you unless
you look at number 14 that's not usually there, and the list goes on.
Research we've conducted shows that only 63% of engineering capacity
in midsized companies is dedicated to feature development.
Because of this and related enabling efforts,
and then requirements change and you're asked to be
able to run the application on a different cloud,
AWS, azure, GCP, add fault tolerance
or multi region support, switch from something to kubernetes,
integrate the serverless code with the existing architecture, or maybe
split that growing service into two, or actually combine
those three into one to save some cost. And that new service that Hema is
building needs GRPC for even lower latency infrastructure from
code aspires to enable universal backend code,
developers only write application code, and infra platform teams
set tech standards and ensure feature teams adhere
to them. They work together, but independently.
There are four dominant approaches to realizing this aspiration.
In the SDK approach, a custom SDK is introduced
that developers use in their code. The IFC tool would analyze
how the service code interacts and uses that SDK,
and then infers the infrastructure from that. Introducing a custom
SDK makes inferring usage from code more predictable
and tailored to work well for the scenarios it was designed
for. But it also means the SDK is always one
step behind in leveraging new underlying cloud features.
The use of a new platform specific SDK requires developers
to learn and make use of those libraries. However, they have
the potential of unlocking unique capabilities only they can offer.
This comes at a cost of sacrificing the breadth
and depth of features that popular community driven libraries
may offer. In the programming language approach, a new programming
language is introduced that is cloud centric. They introduce language
constructs that would otherwise be difficult to do in existing programming languages.
Interactivity or distributed computing constructs cloud be more
readily implemented or integrated into the language,
making the process simpler and more intuitive for software developers.
There are a few tradeoffs with that approach, though.
Software developers have to commit to learning a new language, which means
that they can't reuse the expertise they built over the years with existing ecosystems and
tools. Starting a new programming language also means that you have
to start a new ecosystem for that language or have stellar
interoperability with supported and interoperable languages.
That has failed in many occasions but also succeeded in others. Like with
typeScript, there's an organizational cost as well where you need to hire people with
that expertise in mind, and it's much easier to finding developers that
know Golang, Python, C sharp, Java. The annotations approach
relies on encode annotations, which either leverage the
existing programming language constructs, open source libraries frameworks in
the code, or expect more metadata inside of the annotations themselves.
Those tools have to depend on static analysis to an even
greater extent because they don't have a custom SDK or a purposefully
crafted programming language that has those constructs
built in. For example, in the node JS world is to annotate an event emitter
with a pub sub capability, turning it into a distributed mechanism
for passing messages around. But from the developer perspective,
developers are still interacting with an event system.
This would then be backed by SNS, SQS, Kafka.
It doesn't really matter, because that becomes the implementation detail of
the IFC tool. The trade off, however, is the expanding need for
the tooling to understand existing and growing sets of libraries, languages,
design patterns, clouds and underlying services. The dimensionality
of the problem becomes potentially too large and not having
an SDK to lean on or complement it. The temptation to
grow the annotation system until it becomes a full
fledged DSL or language is ever there,
which requires developers to then understand the annotation system
and processor, and often work around it manually when it breaks.
The last one is more of a hybrid between a few of the approaches.
You could have an SDK with some annotation systems to simplify that process,
or annotations that have more metadata in them, but expand existing
programming language interfaces or some variation on that
spectrum. Here's a list of the dominant players in this space.
We'll compare them based on these dimensions, and we'll talk about why they're important.
Starting with the license there's a strong desire from the developer operator community
to have more open source tools, which gives you a degree of certainty
about its future, all the way down to being source available or
closed source. As you can see, many of the solutions are already open source,
although a few who are generally more a SaaS offering
are either closed source or source available programming languages.
One or two languages. The majority support one language,
with a couple that focus on multilanguage support and
a few that are introducing their own languages. What is the developer interface?
Different tools and startups are taking the SDK approaches. Others are leaning
towards the framework or language approach, with security. Most startups
and tools are leveraging the fact that they have this reasoning in
static time about how the applications are constructed
to generate policies based on the dependency graphs,
so you get least privileged permissions through IAM or similar
policy engines without have to manually creating them.
Infrastructure as code support is important for teams that already have platforms and either
want to introduce IFC into the existing platforms
or integrate it into an IFC based workflow.
It provides infrastructurefromcode teams the ability to customize and
tailor the output to the organizational needs that they have,
reusing a lot of the terraform or infrast code templates they've
already generated. This ties into configurability and not the high level one
which most of those tools have configuration for. But how do you configure
the lower level pieces? Do you use custom configurations or
specifications, or do they allow for using infrastructure
as code as the mechanism to configure the generated resources,
bypassing any for a spec hosting model. Some are PaaS
only, and you get the same trade offs of having a PaaS versus IAS or
a self hosted solution. On the other end, it's completely
self hosted where it generates IAC or the elements for
you to deploy, and some do both, backing technologies like compute
or storage. Some support on demand computing or serverless
versus always on compute like Kubernetes. Then there's the next
layer of technologies that the IFC tools
target. Some are proprietary, especially ones that are more
closed source or SaaS versions. You don't know what they're using
behind the scenes. Others are preselected, meaning it's a specific
stack that they use as part of the implementation. For instance, API gateway
with postgres, DynamoDB, Kubernetes,
Lambdas, GRPC, and sQs.
Others are adaptable, meaning that the technologies are interchangeable.
Technology can be swapped out for another being able to switch out
GRPC with Linkerd or lambdas with kubernetes
without affecting application code. Cloud portability support
most support one cloud, others are prioritizing multi cloud
support. Here's a matrix with the distillment of all the IFC tools
and the characteristics of each. You can find it on Cloud dev,
IFC, and many more resources there. How does this relate to
existing infrastructurefromcode and platform teams? What we see happening
is that the infrastructure teams will continue describing more
custom and organization specific infrastructure as code
or terraform in the cases that they matter, and then provide an IFC
tool that translates developer code to cloud
versions of it that is integrated and deployed with the
tooling that the infrastructurefromcode team set, and by having this IFC tool
in the middle, it allows them to ensure and enforce policies across
the company based on teams or organizations or individuals
or types of technologies. The infrastructure from code, movement or
approach wants to help you break free from the cycle of the mundane to
work on challenges that nobody else is and only you can.
So check out cloud dev IFC to find all the resources
and tools. Try one out and join us on discord and continue the
conversation. Have a great day.