Hi everybody. My name is Moshe Zadka. My website
is cobodies.com, where you can find every way of reaching out to me, known to
humankind. And today I want to talk to you about Pyo three
and how Python loves rust. I want to start with the acknowledgment
of country. I live in Belmont in the San Francisco Bayer
peninsula, which is the ancestral homeland of the raw
Tusholoni people. Let's start by talking a little bit about
rust. What use it, why using it
might be a good idea, and how to use it.
What is rust? Rust is a low level language which
supports zero cost abstractions, abstractions that don't have
any one time cost, and it is memory
safe. This combination is pretty rare, and that's what
makes rust useful. So why
is this combination useful?
Well, sometimes, as they say,
algorithm needs to go vroom, right? Performance is useful.
However, the algorithm often runs on untrusted data.
We really like it, even if the data is bad, even if
it's bugging the algorithm. The way it
comes about is not harmful, right? It doesn't say
open a security issue.
The prototypical example that you want to keep in mind when
you think about trust is low level parsing.
Let's say that you need to parse some new weird
low level format. Your parser will probably have to do with some
untrusted data. You can't use
a higher level library because this is new format. So you have to go byte
by byte, which means you want something that can give you the performance of
reading something byte by byte while still keeping safety in mind
and giving you the zero cost abstractions to make sure that your
code still is readable and easy to debug.
So for my example,
I'll use counting as kind of
my low level parsing example. It's a nice third
example that will show us a number of features in rust and how to use
them for Python. So in this example,
we need to check if a character appears more than x time,
not to say how many times it appears. We just need to see if it
goes above a threshold value. That's an interesting twist.
And that means that we can't use a lot of other things that
might be super useful in general for counting,
but will, for example, read the whole file,
even if we only need to check for three
appearances, and those all appeared in the beginning.
We want to enable resetting counts on spaces
and new lines. Again,
this is the example, so you can think of like a
use case, right? We want to see is there the word that includes x
more than the character more than x time, or if there's a line that
includes it more than x time.
Again, this is not very complicated to implement,
which is what makes it a good example, and does have enough
nooks and trannies that we'll be able to use it to kind of get
into some of the interesting parts of interfacing between
Python and rust. So it's really
just interesting enough. So let's
start writing some rust code. The first thing we know is that we need to
support three options. Reset on new
lines, reset on spaces, and no reset.
So we make it an enum that would be probably the equivalent to
what we would choose in Python to make it as a three way num.
And now we have the structure that kind of keeps the parameters
of the problem, right? So you want to
define the character, we want to define the min
number and what is the reset.
And in our example we just have one method has
count, where you give it some data and
it checks if it has a count.
In order to make the code a bit more site friendly,
I've moved some of the implementation
into a separate has count internal function that won't
be exposed to Python later on. Spoiler alert.
But that makes it easier to kind of fit different things
on slide. So the function takes
a counter, it takes the data,
and it returns a boolean, and it
loops over the character. It will update
the current counter. You'll notice that I
define current count as a mutable. That's mutable.
And when I pass it, I pass it as a mutable reference,
which means as the changing site. I can tell that this
is a function that might update current count as well as
get it as an input. And if it returns Boolean,
then I can stop. I know that I already have enough
count, so I can stop. So now we
need to implement that count,
and we do maybe reset,
which might reset if we
encounter a reset character. It maybe increments
if this is the right count character, and if
it sees that the current count is bigger
than the minimum number, it returns true. I do that by just having the
last expression equal true. So the way Ras
interprets a semicolon separated
list of expressions is by evaluating them in order and
returning the value of the last expression, which in
this case is a boolean, saying whether we've exceeded the
current count, maybe reset.
Use a pretty fun feature of rust, which is
the match. So in this case I match on a tuple. The tuple
is the character. And what is the reset
and if it's new line and the reset is new
lines reset, or if it's space and the reset
is spaces reset, then I reset the count, and otherwise I do
nothing. Every function in rust has to return
a value, but in this case the value is the empty tuple,
which is always the same value, which is the empty tuple.
Maybe incur checks if the character
equals to the target character, and if so, it increments the count.
You notice that here I direct the current count,
and you'll also notice that again, both in the calling site
and in the function.
I take care to note that current counter
is a mutable reference, right? Which means that
it will always know that it's a mutable reference at every point.
And the important thing is that this is not a default. And so if you
don't see that, you know, for example, in this case, that counter cannot be
changed because that's not a mutable reference. So again,
I wrote this code both to fit on slides. This is not necessarily the best
practices. I didn't format the code according
to the best formatting guidelines, again with the ideal that it
fits into a slide and be reasonably readable. Here, the API between
the functions is definitely not ideal. Even the higher level
API is not what I would choose in other cases. But this is
enough to have working code. It's not really
bad rasp, it's just not an ideal rasp, but it's nice
to see it on slides. And now we see how that code,
right? So again, in kind of our imagination,
that code was kind of mostly written or pre written before we start,
but we have to understand it so that we can properly wrap it in python.
So now let's go to the wrapping parts.
There's obviously a few ways to wrap it, but using pyro three is
really nice, because all we do is add annotations
to the Ras code. We don't have to write any python code or any kind
of glue code. The only thing we do
is go inside the RAs code and add proper annotations,
so it's purely in line. And which means that as the
code is modified, it's modified together with the wrapping code,
we start with like include. This is the rust
equivalent to import statement. So we use a Pyo three prelude,
which imports a lot of stuff that we'll use on later.
And now we have to decorate the reset
enam a little bit. So we say this is a pyo class,
which means please expose it to Python, and it
can't be exposed to Python unless it implements clone or
copy, and these are basically things that we
would need to implement ourselves, except in waste. Often when you
want to say copy it the obvious way that you would have
copied, and clone it the obvious way that you would have cloned it.
There's a specific way to spell these things, and that's what derived
clone and derived copy means. It means there's
only one reasonable way to copy that. There's only one reasonable way to clone
that. Please just write the code yourself, don't make me do that.
So Russ will happily do that for you. The counter
is a little bit simpler. All we need to do is just wrap it with
a PI class and the implement. We wrap
with PI methods and we add a new method called
new. We didn't have to have it for us because we could
create a new counter object directly from rust. It wasn't
hidden. But in our case we do want to
make it exposed to Python, and that means that we need to expose a
constructor to Python. So we expose the
constructor to Python that takes the parameters and sets them in
the structure. And with all of that
done, we just tell the module to
include the counter and to include the reset and
we return ok. The question marks means that
if there's a problem in adding either class
that will raise an exception. Well, it will return
an incorrect PI result, which in Python, when it's unwrapped
will raise an exception saying I had a problem initializing that.
And the okay means don't raise an exception, it's fine.
Now the tool to use for all of that is maturing.
So maturing develop is the equivalent of
PP install minus editable. It installs it inside the current
virtual environment, and you'll still have
to rerun it because it's fast and not Python, but it
kind of more or less automatically keeps it up to date.
And when you finally want to upload a wheel to
pipe PI, you use material and build it will give you a great wheel.
And by a great wheel I mean it will be cpu specific.
So if you want to support more than one cpu,
you need to build it on more than one cpu architecture. And obviously
Linux Macs and windows will need different wheels, but it
will provide you a many Linux wheel, right? So that's all taken care of you
just by using maturin without changing hard. And once you
have either the wheel installed or you install it via Maturin for testing it out,
you import it just like any other module,
you create a new counter. In this case I
created a counter that does the new line reset method.
And if I count something that has three c's in it,
then it will return. True. And if
I count something that has three c's in it,
but there's a new line between the first two, then obviously it
resets on the, after it sees the
second c, it resets on the new line, and so it never gets a three.
And so it gives me false. Right. So now we have fast
code to implement the desired algorithm.
So what do I want you to take away from this?
Using rust in Python is surprisingly easy.
If you already have the Rust code, you decorate it.
If it's someone else's rust code, then you have to thinly wrap it
in your own layer of rust and then decorate that.
Obviously these two languages are very different from each other.
Rust is very high performance.
I didn't put any measurements here because that was beyond the scope of
what I have time to talk about. And also, there's many ways
to optimize rust, but even in
this case, implementing more or less equivalent code in Python would
be much, much slower. It's safe, right?
I looped over characters. I potentially
could have done pretty complicated things. There was no way that this
code could have an out of bound error or a
memory issue or something like that, because I
wrote it on top of high level abstractions that are safe even
though they don't have any runtime cost,
but just have a learning curve, right?
You saw, I have to understand stuff like mutable
references, and if you do slightly more complicated
things, you start to have to understand bow checkers and lifetimes
and a lot of fun things like that. It's not trivial,
and that makes it kind of awkward for prototyping. If I want to quickly change
how to function interface, I also have to change the type information.
Python is almost the opposite. It's very easy to get started.
Supports really tight iteration loops, but there is a
speed cap. You can optimize Python, but at some point you write
into pretty hard limits. But if you combine
them, you get the best of all worlds. You can prototyping in Python and then
move the performance button next to rust and the stronger
together you can do development
and then you send it off to be deployed
and you reap the benefits. So I hope that
will help you your own projects. Thank you so much for listening,
and I hope you enjoy the rest of the conference.