Hi, hello everyone and welcome to my talk. Today I'm
gonna talk about security by testing and how I
try to improve the security of my go projects just
by writing more tests. Before starting the
talk, I will give you a little introduction about myself.
So, my name is Alessio Veggie. I'm a software
engineer, full time cat food opener for my furry friend.
And jokes apart, I'm passionate about reading and
taking long walks on the social media. You can find me
on GitHub, LinkedIn, Twitter and so on
with this unique account and this amazing avatar.
So let's start the talk first concept to
know is about code coverage code coverage is
a metric that can help developers understanding
how much of their source code is tested and
how much is not. It is mostly used when
writing a unit test, but not only
related to them, and it's expressed
as a percentage.
Let's go a bit more in depth with code coverage. With Golang it
was first time introduced in version 1.2,
April 2013, if I remember well, and this
support was specifically for unit tests. Here's the link
to the announcement. And the story continued
after almost ten years with version 1.20
with a new grid support for the integration test.
So this means that combining the unit test with
the integration test coverage, the coverage
percentage of our projects sensibly increased thanks to
the last feature. During this time. Also, the go
community introduced some nice tools, like for example the
go to cover that gives you the ability to see
the to render the source code with its coverage in
an HTML page and so on. So that's,
that's what happened. Another important
concept is about Secomp profile.
First of all, Seccomp is a security feature that resides
on the Linux kernel and the second profile is
basically list of syscalls that you can use to
put them into a rule and attach this rule
to a program by defining if these
syscalls could be executed or not by the program itself.
So it works as a firewall for system
calls. Additionally, it is extensively used in the kubernetes
ecosystem, especially when you enable the second
default feature flag. So this means that
all the workloads that you are going to run will be,
will be attached to this default profile. That is
a default second profile that have inside
the most dangerous syscalls that you should never use in
your run. Let's see
now, the main idea that I had during the tasks,
so the main thought that I had was to create to
generate a second profile as an artifact
at the end of a test pipeline.
Why specifically the test pipeline because in
the test pipeline, we are testing, as much
as we can, our test our code through the
test that we write. And depending on the percentage
that cover our, our source code,
we can rely on them for a security profile.
So if we are testing the 70% of our code,
the syscalls that we are going to extract on the
test pipeline will be reliable for the 70%.
So that was the main idea. Additionally,
this second profile could be used in different
ways. The, the most common that came into
my mind was to use it through
an init container. When we deploy our application,
the init container basically injected the second
by downloading it from the artifact
registry and store it into the Kubernetes
node in order to allow the application container
to load it and run with it.
And there's the example. So the init container basically download it
and store it under Barlib Kubelet second,
and then the container, in this case the NginX container
for example, uses the security context second profile
of type localhost by referring to the second profile
itself, but with the localhost profile.
So now that we have the main concept in our mind,
let me explain you what was the step that I
followed and how I tried to achieve this goal.
So in this image, you can see basically
a call graph of an example
program. So having that
in mind and having all the tests that are
rendered can basically understand what is missing and what
is not. So we have a general overview about the
potential syscall that you are missing if you are not testing
the binary. So in
order to extract the syscalls from the test with
the integration test, that was the easiest
part. What we have to do is to build a binary,
provide some script to check for the expected result,
general scripts for the integration test.
An example that I really
appreciate is the test script suite.
And basically we can run our binary
by using strace or pair for whatever you want.
So in this case we can extract, we can collect
all the executed syscalls from the binary
by testing all the possible branch that
the executioner has. So this was the first part,
but it was not enough in my opinion, because we were
missing the unit test that are such a big part of
the test pipeline. So how I tried to extract
also the syscalls from the unit test, first of all,
it's quite simple to say, but it was a bit more complicated.
First of all, the gotest command,
we have to think that the gotest command compile and run the
test binary all at once. So when we run go tests,
we are basically compiling the test and then automatically
run with the same command. At first glance
we couldn't do strace of go test because
we were going to hook, we were going to trace
calls that were not related to our specific test,
but syscalls that were included in the go test command
that were out of school. So what we could do
at first I thought that we could for example compile
only the test binary without running it using go
test, but running it separately. So if we basically
type gotest c, we could compile the test
binary and run it by ourselves.
The problem in this case is that even
doing strace about of the test binary,
we could include some noise that are not related to our
specific function that we are testing, because for
example we can include some function that
load some test data from, from the,
from the environment. So as in as an example we could
open a file, read the file content, and this
syscalls will be collected by strace.
But we don't need that, we should try to find a way to
avoid this kind of noise. My personal idea,
I don't know if it's the good one, but it
seems to work, at least in some cases. But the
main idea was to create using a BPF to define
a trace point that basically start tracing the syscalls.
When a probe that is attached to the function that
we want to trace inform us that the
execution of the function started and we can stop the
trace point when the uert probe inform
us that the execution of the function is finished.
So we have a range of
time that we can rely on in order to
collect the syscholes that derives from our
function. An additional information is that Arpun
was based on go BPF at
the beginning, but then I moved to Libpfgo
and I will explain later why I took
this decision.
So let's see the juice part. So in order
to run harpoon what we have to do, we should basically
build the test binary first as we were trying to
do before. So just typing gotest c
followed by the package pop that host
our function. So in this case we are going to
build the test binary. So as a result we are going to have a
binary that will execute the test where
our function is located.
Consequently, we have to extract from
this binary the symbol name of the function that we
want to trace. So in the example
I typed the myfunction.
So myfunction is the function
that we want to trace and we are using objdump
since followed by the name of the binary test
by graphing for the function name.
In this case we are going to find the symbol
of the function name. So as you can see in the example below,
so we are doing objdump to test binary
of mine. It was an independent project from
this talk and we are graphing for the function
interface exist. So interface exists is a
function that I've created in my personal project,
a go function that we can find on the binary on the
test binary with the following name. So GitHub.com
allegra 91 forwardctlash packages
iptables dot interface exists. So once
we have the symbol, the symbol name of the function,
we can use arpun in order to extract the syscalls
from the binary. So by typing this command arpun
fm to specifying the the symbol
name of the function followed by the command
for the test binary.
So as I explained before, what is going to
happen with arpun is that arpun will take the elf
binary. So binary test and we'll attach
a u probe and a u ref probe to the main dot. Do something
in this case, but whatever is the name of the
symbol or of the function and will,
after it attached these probes to
the function, will basically run the binary
and the trace point will be informed by the u probe and
the u rh probe about the starting and the xd
and the end of the function itself.
So in this limited range of time we are going to extract the
syscalls. And here it is
an example. So by typing arfun fn
followed by the function, the symbol name of
the function, followed by the command of the test binary.
So iptables test.
So here's the list of the functions that are related only
to the function in interface exists.
Let's see now the worst part of this of this project,
everything was looking nice, but at some point I
realized that not all the things were working properly.
Main thing that was not working properly was that the u rat probe sometime
was not informing the program that the function
was returned. What was the problem? Basically the
Europe probe overwrite the return address of the probed
function with an address of a trampoline. This trampoline is
basically pointing to our EPF program.
So once the EBBF program
is executed and after it sends the instruction
pointer should restore tool to point to the next instruction.
But this thing doesn't happen all the time,
since the stack in the go binaries dynamically
changes due to the garbage collector, for example.
So this kind of behavior could
cause the program corruption.
So I had to find a way
to solve this issue, and luckily for me I
found this workaround on Internet.
So the workaround consists in starting
from the fact that the U probes could be attached
to a specific offset. So we don't
need to attach the U probes only on the symbol function
names, but we can do the same to a specific offset
in the function, in the binary function. So in
order to simulate the URET probe,
what you what we could do is of adding for
each rEt instruction that is inside the function,
a uprobe that basically simulates the functioning
of a UART probe. So instead of attaching
one single u ret probe in the function, we can
add the one u probe for each ret instruction
within the function that we are tracing,
and the rest of the function is the same.
So benefits of moving to lib bpf go
so at the beginning when I introduced arkun,
I mentioned the thing that was based on go bpf, that is
a library from the iovisor organization
and that is using bc under the hood.
So now I decided to move to lib bpfgo,
mainly because libpfgo gives you the ability
of attaching the u probes to specific offset,
and this thing was not supported by go bpf.
So we can basically simulate the functioning of our
UART probe by attaching the U probes
to the RET instructions, thanks to Libbypfgo.
And the use of LibfDo makes the project
even more distributable, easily distributable because
the LibPF Go is a library that is a wrapper of
Lib BPF. So Lib BPF gives
us the ability to write the program
with Cory. Cory means compile once runs
everywhere. We don't have to build the binary every
time we run the application as we did before with the Go BPF
that was based on BCC that needs GCC
as a dependency to do this thing.
So this time we can simply compile the binary the
first time from the pipeline, for example, and then
distribute the entire program through
the repository.
So the talk is almost finished. I just want to
point you to some links that helped me a lot
understanding this problem and links
from which I learned a lot. I also want to
thank some people that helped me doing this
project. Thank you for your attention and I hope
you enjoyed the talk.