Hello and welcome to my talk. My name is Prasav, and today
I'm going to talk about a different side of the could language, one that
will hopefully inspire you to search for the artist within yourselves.
While preparing for this talk, I thought a lot about how to approach
the subject. I could just sit and talk about
art theory for hours, but no one would stay here and listen.
I could also just dive straight into coding. That wouldn't make
it quite either. Beyond the basics, much of
the real creative work is just sitting alone and trying things for hours,
failing and trying again and over and over and over again,
trying different things, until they suddenly click.
So I figure I could just tell a story instead,
one that approaches the subject through the prism of my own experience.
A story that, interestingly enough, starts at the
end. At the end of our story, there has a book,
an actually different kind of book. It had none of
the usual suspects in it. There would be no web servers,
that there would be no networks, no containers even.
The book wasn't even supposed to teach the goal language.
Instead, it was more meant to inspire people to try
new things. Interestingly enough, it was also the first quote
unquote product that I released after jumping into the unknown waters
of solopreneurship at the start of this year.
And yet, this book is only a byproduct of a long journey.
Therefore, it's the journey that the rest of the story will focus upon.
It's a story about finding new sources of inspiration, about picking
up the goal language later in my career, and last but not
least, about rediscovering the joy of programming through
the language. My story with graphics began in the early 2000s.
Like many kids at the time, I also wanted
to make video games. So I started with can Pascal,
but quickly realized that those weren't really helping me make the flashy
stuff as fast as I wanted. So somewhere around that time,
a new language called processing appeared. It caught
my attention, and I immediately started playing with it. Processing was
born at MIT. It wasn't meant so much
targeting professional programmers,
but more towards non experts, especially people with an
artistic background. This was really the first time
that I saw a language that was meant two really
help people deal with graphics and such. So processing took
the basics of Java, but it really simplified them. It also came
with a really nice library that was helping
people to work with graphics. Many of the processing works
would occupy just a single file. They were called sketches at the
time, and one of them would look something like this.
So actually, this sketch on the left is
one of the first sketches that I wrote in processing, and later
on, it was the one that actually inspired me to write the book.
As you can see, there's really nothing too
complex and fancy about those sketches. It's essentially just a
few lines of code that would, at the beginning,
would just a nice color palette
from a source image, and then would use those colors to
basically randomly spread rectangles around
in various degrees of opacity. And this would create this
nice sort of overlay effect. But most of the processing sketches
are something like that. They're quite simple. My obsession
with the language even met me later on with one of the forefathers
of the computer graphics field, the german guy called fidanaki.
I was a student of his during my masters, and it was
about that time when I really started reading more deeply about the
philosophy behind those randomly scattered squiggly
lines. But in a typical fashion,
life took over, so I had to move on with it.
I jumped out of university, and I made the career
as a Java developer. It was about until late
2018 when I was introduced to go as actually a part
of a job switch. This was a pivotal moment,
and probably one of the few moments that was
going to define my future trajectory. I has so hooked
up on the simplistic nature of the language that I started using it
for other things. Has. Well, at some point, I figured I
could just grab my old processing sketches and translate them two
go, would that work? And the answer is
yes. And as people say, the rest was just history. One thing
led to another. But how does
generative art really relate? Two law. To go into
that, I will first have two define what generative art really
is. And that's a difficult subject
by itself, because you're probably about to find as many
definitions of generative art as there are people dealing
with it. And of course, none of them would fit the context of
the goal image. So I had to come up with my own explanation.
Allow me to share it with you. Generative heart is a
balance between procedure and randomness. It's the result of
simple steps multiplied many times over a complex
organism of tiny actors interacting sequentially and
concurrently with one another. Think about it. A lot of this actually
applies to go, doesn't it? Actually a fun fact, this animation
on the right was completely made with the goal language.
I think it really exemplifies what I mean with
this definition. It's a bunch of tiny actors,
each of them taking simple and seemingly random
steps. But in a combination, these lead
two the breeding of new behavior, of complex behaviors.
And this is one of the postulates of generative art as well. It's like you
don't have to write complex code to achieve complexity. You just have to
write simple things and multiply them over and over and
over again, stepping on the product of the previous
step, essentially. All right, let's look at some of the basic building blocks
that the go standard library provides as well. As is usual
for the go language, you're provided with only a bare set of basics.
However, these basics are so well designed
as it is usual for the language, we're provided with only
a bare set of basics. In fact, most of the
code types can really fit on one slide. It's just these three
interfaces that you see on this slide that you need two
know about, and you can pretty much say that you know most of the
graphics fundamentals provided by the go standard library.
Those basics are extremely well designed. They hold
a minimum set of requirements, and that's it. For a type to
qualify as an image, for example, it only needs to implement three simple
methods, the same for the color you can think of.
Those has essentially as the reader and the writer interfaces
of the graphics domain. It's really this idea of composability and
swapping that makes this whole thing so easy
and so interesting. As we'll see later, this allows for other
libraries to build up on those basics. All right,
let's look at one example. I think there's no better
way to speak about composition than the concept of image filters.
A filter can be an image too, wrapping its source in itself.
If we implement all the methods that satisfy the image interface,
we could then use our filter in any other place that accepts an image.
Another example, cutting a circle out of an image.
I think this was actually featured in
the Go documentation tool. Again, we can achieve
the same effect by wrapping can existing source and telling it
how to render each pixel. Unlike the previous example, here we
selectively play with the opacity of the pixels and not
just the color hue and saturation. So in
a way, we achieve the creating of the circle by saying
any pixel that's not in the circumference of the circle will
have an opacity of zero, essentially meaning that it will
be completely transparent. This leads to the perfect
circular cutout we can see on the right hand side. Implementing all of
those things by ourselves will be an overkill.
Thankfully, there is a number of great libraries out there that provide
us with what we need. Thanks to the composability and lack
of deep abstractions. Those are also extremely easy to integrate or learn
from. I could say perhaps one of the most widely used
libraries when it comes to drawing 2d graphics
in Go is called GG,
and it's really simple to use. It's one of the main
libraries that also feature in my book, and it's been
essentially an indispensable tool in my work ever since I started
working with graphics and go. What I really like about it
is the fact that it has the same procedural
API and look and feel of many of
the functions that exist in the processing programming language.
So those who have played with it would
expect to find the same basic primitives to work with,
essentially shapes and rectangles and
fonts and basic image filters and such.
It's extremely useful, and I can totally
recommend using it. All right, before we
go into a short demo session, here are a couple of notable mentions
that didn't make it into this talk. The first one
is webassembly. It's something
that I've dedicated the whole bonus chapter and part of
my book, and it's something that I
would definitely want to expand further upon, and we
might have a slight chance to see this into the demo. Although I'm
not going two go into the code, I'm still going to show you
how webassembly can be useful in
producing graphics generators for the web. For example,
the second thing is genetic algorithms. It's something that I'm currently working
on, and it will definitely be one of my
sources for future content for expansions of
the book, and why not future topics for talks.
So definitely expect to see more to come
in the next year or so. And the third one
is a book recommendation. I have to say it's one
of the few books that I would definitely recommend for people
wanting to start with graphics engineering programming ego.
The book is called the Nature of Code by Daniel Shipman,
and it's actually about processing,
but it's so well written and so easy
to follow that many of the things would be easily sort
of transferable and applicable to go.
And I should say there are a lot of interesting concepts
going back to math and statistics and sort of
different fields also, like talking about different aspects of the graphics and
art. So definitely something to check out.
All right, so the next portion of this talk will be a
demo session in which I'm going to show
one of my early sketches, and in parallel
I wanted to demonstrate how go applications
can be compiled to webassembly and drive interactive applications
on the web. Let's jump right in. One of the subjects
that I at least wanted to show in the demo. Unfortunately,
it's quite a complex topic of its own,
so I'm not going to be able to talk so
much in detail about it is the
compiling of go applications to webassembly and using them inside
a web browser. So at least I wanted to show how I
took one of my sketches
and basically put it inside of
a website. So what this website here,
and this is the URL, what this
website here does is it allows anyone to just go
there and generate graphics,
basically randomly generated graphics of
their own. So I can definitely advise anyone to just go there
and try it. It's completely live and I
will make sure to put all the relevant
URLs and addresses inside of the
slides. So without further ado,
I just wanted to start rendering and in
parallel move to my other demo because this might take a little bit of time.
Right.
Okay. Loaded the wasm file and
it starts drawing. So we could be able to see some results
in a couple of, not more than a couple of minutes.
In the meantime, I wanted to
switch to a very simple sample sketch. It's actually the sketch that
I'm speaking about in my book,
and as one can see,
setting up the whole sketch and the sketch itself,
they're not really complex. They shouldn't be complex at
all. Actually, I just wanted to show you
a sample output of the sketch. So this is what it's supposed to render.
It's essentially a reinterpretation of the
processing sketch that you saw above, but with a
little bit of addition. And since I actually
like playing with random color palettes
most of the time, I don't even start with predefined images
of my own, but actually source random images from the Internet.
And one of the things that I wanted to show you is how I do
that. Not many people know, but the popular
image sharing service unsplash, it has an API
and it allows people to essentially go
there and say, give me a random image.
In our case, we don't even want to book at it, we just want to
use it as a color palette source. Then once
we have this image, we essentially create a
sketch, and I will go in a couple of seconds into
what this sketch entails. We give it a bunch of parameters,
which I totally understand that not
everyone will really understand what they mean.
Sometimes I don't either. These are just
meant to essentially
drive the generation of every next step of every
next iteration. So as you can see there, some of
them will stay the same throughout the whole destination
width, destination height, or others are essentially
what the initial alpha of the rendering
is, and minimum edge count
and maximum edge count of the polygons that we're drawing and
stuff like that. So with that done,
what we do essentially is we
go through a bunch of iterations. That's one of the things that
make generative art what it is. It's essentially a bunch of iterations
on top of simple steps. And on every iteration, we call the sketch update,
the sketches update method. So let's take
a quick look into the sketch itself. Again,
super procedural. Nothing too fancy, nothing too
complex. It's setting up a
canvas under the hood using the library that I mentioned,
Gg. It's extremely helpful for allowing
us to set those things and draw primitives
on top and mix and match with varying opacities and
stuff like that. It's extremely simple and nice
to start with. And then the actual update method is also
not super computer. What's happening is unlike
we draw a random pixel from source,
transpose it over to the destination using
this super complex, super complex formula
of just finding the corresponding pixel into the destination
and essentially saying, draw a
polygon depending on the
configuration, with a certain number of edges at
this location. To make things even more interesting,
I added these two parameters.
So one is like this stroke inversion threshold, which says
well beyond a certain size, since these
polygons are expected to get smaller and smaller over time,
start adding something like a border, so that
the smaller the polygons are, the more sketchy they look like. So it
looks like a graphic. So one is this, and the other is
basically the one
that's called stroke jitter. Again, something that
I invented. It's completely up to
the people who create the sketch to come up with naming
conventions that sort of mean something
to them. So the stroke jitter will just say, we don't want
this particular color to appear in
that exact spot based on the source.
You can just as well add a
little bit of a randomness to it. And that's what this stroke jitter
will do. It just go through,
we'll just say, take the pixel and
give it a varying amount of distance
from the original source. And yeah, on every
iteration, we'll make sure to reduce the stroke size, and we'll also
increase the alpha so that we create this sort of effect of reducing
the polygon size. And at the same time,
I'll just explain it as building up or
sort of a kept effect of
the drawing. So without further ado, I'll just say,
let's go and try it. And as I was
saying, based on the fact that it loads a completely
random image, I have no clue what
the actual output will look like. So this
will be a bit of a surprise for me too.
One thing you'll notice is that the
smaller the polygons, respectively, the smaller the brushes at
the end. It will get progressively faster
and faster until eventually just finishes in a
couple of milliseconds. So let's see the output.
All right. Completely different image.
Not sure if you like it or not.
A bit dark to my taste. Maybe we'll just, you know, we'll just generate another
one, but it will basically follow the
same pattern image.
Few more iterations and beyond the thousand,
it will speed up.
And there we go. Black and white. Interesting.
All right, now let's
switch back to the browser and see what we've.
Okay, this is a new sketch. It's based on a concept called Perla
Noise. It's very well explained in the Daniel Schiffman book,
and it's something that I want to definitely emphasize
more on in future talks and in future chapters of the book.
So, as you can see, this one is also
quite nice.
And essentially, this sketch follows a
similar approach in that it will etc.
A sort of a random image from the Internet, and we'll
use it as a color palette, but instead of
randomly distributing polygons and triangles and whatnot, it will
just use a concept called perlin noise to
imitate randomly
scattered brushes. So, yeah,
again,
this looks quite nice to me, but I leave it to
the interpretation of the viewer at the end.
So, yeah, with this beautiful
picture, I just wanted to say thank you once again for
choosing my talk today and definitely looking forward
to seeing more and more people taking
the goal language for a spin and seeing what else could be
done with it beyond the usual aspects of
its application. Thank you.