You. Hello. Hello everybody, and thank
you for my session. My name is Radhu, Radhu von Foleya and
for the next 40 minutes we'll talk about security.
We'll talk about security best practices inside
Microsoft Azure. There are a lot of things around us,
and sometimes it's very easy
to lose between different information or finding the
right one. What I want to aim in this
session is to share with you some things,
some lesson learns and best practices that I identified
that are relevant and can have a high impact
on your own projects that are running on top of Azure.
Some of them you might know, some of them you might know, but because
of lack of time or team
capabilities, you might not
put so much effort on them. And I would like to highlight
what are the top 13 security
best practices that I consider relevant
and fit very well in an application
that we are building. We are running on top of Microsoft.
On top of Microsoft Azure. Before going
forward, I would like to share with you a code
of Gibran that I think that is very relevant.
If you reveal your secrets to
the wind, you should not
blame the wine for
revealing them to the trees.
In this context, we must be aware of that.
The most important thing, the most relevant thing
is that the wind, it is us and
it is up to us what we are sharing,
the level of security that we want in
place in our Azure, inside our Microsoft
Azure application. So it is up to us the
level and the features of Azure and
other technologies that we want to use to improve the
security layer of our systems.
Next, let's talk about some statistic information that make
us aware of where we are now and what are
the most important things that we need to take into account at
this moment in time. Around 80% of security breaches
involved privileged credentials,
meaning that we have a lot of people
inside our teams, inside our organizations
that have more rights,
more freedom that they should have
inside the systems, inside the application that
they are involved directly or interlocking. And the
best example here is if a product manager needs
to have access to an environment,
to Azure services, to the code repo or
to the pipelines, if he's not doing tasks or
things that are related to that part of the system, does he need
access to it, except maybe Azure DevOps dashboard or
jira? I don't know. It is up to you. But we
need to consider that going forward.
We need to not forget that around
49% of the databases are not
encrypted, even if we have a strong password.
Who needs to be aware that a backup of a SQL database
can be cracked. In 2016 I was joining Microsoft
Techhead in Chicago, and in a 90 minutes
session one of the security specialists from the market showed to us
with tools that you can find on Google,
how you can break the backup, how you can change
the hash of the password and after that
to access it. So it is important not only how
we are setting different credentials, but also how we
encrypt the data, the backups and where we are storing
it.
25% of organization have
cryptojacking activity with their environment.
One four people, one four organization
were involved directly or indirectly. We might not know it that
one of our colleague machines were hacked,
were cryptojacking,
but we need to be aware of this because this is highly risky.
And one of the stories that I really like to
talk is about VIM, that a few years
ago had the data breach not of their data, but of
a backup with some customer data. So a backup
of around 200gb data was stored
in an AWS S free storage and
was made public, available on the market in an
unscrew way. It was available for a few hours, but was more than
enough for a few of few of the guys from
the Internet to download that backup. What happened with that backup?
We don't know, but the backup was
not encrypted and was available on the market so somebody could
put their hands on the information. Officially it was just
customer data that were not very important,
but still that backup is very important. The same story could happen on an
Azure storage, so it's not important. The cloud vendor or the
company could have a pump, but it's more important to be
aware that we need to take into considerations all
the aspects, because in cloud everything can
be paid publicly if you don't have the right
policies and the right governance layer on
top of your services.
Now it's a good moment in time to present myself. My name is Radu
Radhuvale. I'm group head of cloud delivery for Endava.
My journey on cloud, more specifically my
Azure started in 2010 with the first commercial project that
went live I think in 2011, and from that
on I was working, playing and
enjoying the journey of cloud. I have a pretty good
experience on Microsoft Azure and also AWS. I'm Microsoft Azure
mvp and regional dive rector. There are
two more things that I really enjoy. Coffee. I have around ten
machines, ten coffee machine,
I have around ten coffee machines and I really enjoy playing with the coffee,
doing different types of coffee each day or during specific
time of the day. I'm a big fan of home
automation doing the harder part, but doing also the different
automations to reduce the consumption of electricity
or improve a little bit the way
how you enjoy the working from home. What is
agenda talking? A lot of things about different cloud,
different azure services and ways of working.
And let's start with the first thing
on the agenda that we need to not forget.
Most of the technical people are aware about shared responsibility
model. Nevertheless,
at management level, at project management level,
sometimes the leadership has
the expectation that once you go to a cloud vendor,
once you start to use the services of a cloud vendor,
most of the things will be the responsibility of the cloud vendor, not of
the technical teams. So they forget to invest into programs,
into efforts to secure and to
harness that system. So talking about shared
responsibility model from the cloud security point of
view, we need to consider that is a general responsibility.
The CSP will offer you the security foundation
of the physical assets of the data center
operation and of the fabric that is
behind the infrastructure. Now it is up to
us, it is up to the customer, to the technical team to
ensure that we have the right network
and VM security layer to be
sure that we have the services and the functionality in
place and configured aligned with our own needs to
ensure that our apps and workloads are running in
a secure way and the data is stored at a
security layer that we expect. Security level that
we expect. Now, what is the first
thing that we need to take into account? Talking about security,
there are four pillars, networking,
operation, monitoring and cloud platform. On top of
that we have storage, we have data, compute and identity
and access management. And of course of that we
have the application. Depending on the way and how we
are consuming services, how we are building the application,
this part b, these things might be in the scope
of us. If you have an internal application that you are building from scratch,
if you're using a software service or you
are paying a subscription for different services, some of these
items might not be in your own
responsibility or might be less.
And things like the API and the CI CD,
the same story. Having all this
landscape in mind, we need to consider how
we are securing the storage, the data, the workloads
and what kind of identity and access management we are using.
Talking about the secret and access management, it's very important to
have a policy and a way how
we store the secrets where we are storing.
It's not enough to say I'm storing them in the repo where
you will store them in the database, what kind
of encryption you will use on top of that, because in the end
you can have the most secure application in the world.
But if you don't manage the secrets
in the right way, and if somebody puts their hands on the
secrets on your access token, to your
database, to your storage or to something else,
they will be able to get the data, they will be able to stall the
data and to sell it on the black market. So it's very important to
know exactly how you lock the system,
what are the services and what is the layer
on top of it. We have access keys, we have connections,
there are so many things that we need to be aware. And sometimes there's
a break between
infrastructure people and development people, because one
of them are doing the full configuration of the infrastructure, the other ones
are building the application. And if you are not having the right
policy for secrets and configuration management, you can miss
some things or to be stored somewhere
else where they are more visible,
more sensible to an attack.
Everything is a configuration, but it's important to know exactly where this configuration
is stored. So what is cloud vendor is
offering for us? Azure key vault. The keyboard
on AWS is AWS KMS. What is a
key vault? In the end it is a storage, a secure storage where
our connection strings our certificates,
our keys and our secrets are stored,
are stored in such a way that nobody can access,
see them in clear text without having the right access
to them. Once they get the access, well, it is what it is,
but if you manage them correctly, you can ensure
that that storage, that key vault as a storage for your
secret, will not be accessible
to anybody, depending on
what kind of compliance you need to have. Azure dedicated
HSM might be an option. It's like a key vault, an Azure key
vault, but a hardware dedicated only for you and
works pretty nice. Now one of the problem
with Azure key vaults and with the key vaults in general is how you
manage the access to them. And it's important
to remember that at the moment in time when
you are accessing the key vault, also the credentials
or the way how you're accessing the key vault are very important.
Usually when you access the key vault. Let's go back.
You need a client id, a client secret
to be able to access it. Be very careful how you
are stored them, especially on dev environments,
dev test environments, and to have a clear separation
between the instances of the key vaults that are used for production or
I wouldn't say not only for production, but for environments where you have
real customer data and the one that are used for testing,
for development and so on. Now,
keyword give us the ability to store the client id,
client secret and the tenant id inside
the environment variables of a machine. It's a very smart way to
build a development machine because even if
your computer, your laptop installed,
if that person doesn't have access to your
windows user, he will not still
be able to get access to the client id, client secret
and will be very specific to each user that
has that access. Of course, from the code you can retrieve
them and you can use them without any kind of problem. Everything is
built on top of role based access control.
Azure role based access control give us the ability to access not only keywords
but all Azure services and much
more. Not using a username and password,
but basically on service principle.
Meaning that if a virtual machine,
if an Azure functions, wants to access an Azure storage or
a SQL database, Azure SQL database, you will
not need to use the username and
password for no, no,
based on a role based access control, that Azure function
will be able to do an automated
authentication and authorization based on his service identity.
No credential needs to be stored. Everything will happen behind the scene.
Yes, the initial learning curve and
the initial configuration from the effort point of view might take a
little bit of longer, but once you have the system configured,
you are much much safer than using a token,
than using a username and password and similar things.
There are four items that we need to know
about role based assessment control. It's starting to be used more and more, but I
would say that we are still not
there yet to say that fully.
Most of Azure customers or most of the systems are built on top of Azure
are using role based control. So there's a lot of work behind it. There are
four items that we need to consider. The service principle can be a user,
can be a group, can be a service principle like a VM
or an Azure function.
We have the role basically what kind of operation you can do
to a specific service and the scope like Azure skits,
Azure SQL, like Azure storage, and so on. And you do a role
assignment where you specify that that
Azure functions will have only read operations
on that Azure SQL. And more
than that, you can specify exactly what are the tables that it can
access. So even if somebody would hack your Azure functions,
he will still be limited to do only some specific operations on
specific tables. So there are a lot of things like this that you can
use and one of them that is very very important is role
based access control. It's doing duty
segregation for the team and also for the services that you are
using. You can limit it and to specify exactly what
are the permissions and also you can avoid to specific
exactly based on tokens and things like that,
what are the operations and so on. Now the second
thing that I would like to talk about today is repo and cloud
secrets. Now repo and cloud secrets are something that
we already used with it and are very important because nowadays when
we are working from home, it's very easily for our
dev or DevOps hero or our test
hero to click on
a link to have his machine compromised and
a bad person from the Internet to get access
to the application repo to the infrared repo
and worst to have access to
the Azure subscription. We need to ensure that we have the
right tools not only to secure their machines, to limit
their access, but also to ensure that we don't have
any kind of secrets inside
the repo, inside application, infrared repo and so
on. One of the best way how we can do this
is to use tools like git secrets. What does git
secrets do? Basically it's allowing us to scan
for everything that is pushed to the repo or
through a pipeline to ensure that there are no secrets and
to refuse secrets like for example an Azure storage
account key or username or password of the database to be pushed inside
the code. And the code can be the
terraform script or an arm or
for example a C sharp or Java code and so on.
Now secret scanning can be done very easily. Git secret is one of the best
example how you can configure very easily. You just
install it, specify exactly what kind of plugin
for different cloud vendors, and after that you just scan it without any kind
of hassle on top of it without too
much effort. One way how you can do this is each time when
somebody do a commit you can scan it. If you identify
a secret automatic, you can reject that commit
and nothing more than that. There are a lot of tools on the market
and I would say that there's not the best one that
can fit everything as you can see here on the screen. I share
with you some of them with what are the pros and what are
the cons or the things that I consider them very relevant.
And I would like to highlight two of them.
The first one is git, all secret,
GitHub secret. It's great. I really enjoy the tool,
especially for learning internship
and why
it's so easy to configure. It's so easy to show and
to learn how you can integrate a CK scanning tool
inside the system or the value of it. The downside
is that it's more like an MVP.
The configuration is very basic and once you go deep and you
want to have different rules, different fluffs like that,
you'll not be able to do it. On the opposite
part, we have spectral Ops that has a great
UI. So the user interface I really enjoy not only for
the technical people, but also from the reporting point of view for a project
manager or a senior account manager has
a very strong ML mechanism and the number
of false positive number
is reduced a lot. That's great.
It's pretty complex for small projects, doesn't fit
very well. But if you're working for a large project where let's
say we have two or three or teams that are working day
by day on the same repo,
on the same project, or from the same program, spectral Ops
is something that you need to consider and to take a
look. Spectral Ops, it's not free, but it's a very good
value for the money that you are
paying for it.
Okay, let's talk about configuration, application configuration,
because this is important. Where we store this configuration, we talk
about key vault. So we already have a
repo for your secrets. We talk about Azure role basics control.
So we already know how we can access the key vault or other Azure
services from our workloads,
but where we can store the rest of the configuration.
The application configuration application configuration
is very sensitive. Even if you don't store
secrets, it can reveal a lot about how you are building the
application, how you are communicating with different components,
different configurations that once they are changed might affect how
the system would work. A very good example here is the logging
and audit level because somebody
once is hacking your production environment, he might say okay, if I
have access to the configuration, let's put it to the verbose mode.
Even if I don't see any relevant or private
data, I will still get the flocks from which I will
understand exactly how the landscape looks like.
To understand better, how can I attack more that system?
So key and secrets different from application settings
is very very important. And also the role management who
get access to what? One of the things that we have
available on the market is systems
like application configuration and are very very useful because
for example for an application we have the
backend, we have the ETL, we have that main layer,
some recurrent jobs and we have the API app. Everything goes well
for each of them. We have different configuration, keeping them in different locations.
Well yeah, you will say it's a lot of duplicated content
and sharing across different teams and different roles.
It's not easy and it's hard to maintain. Yeah.
Nowadays in most of the cases we have a central
repo like for example Azure
app configuration or AWS app config that works
very nice. And the main purpose
of them is to push all the configuration
from your application, from your configuration in
only one place. And that's awesome.
On top of it we have a very strong integration
with Azure keyword. And what does this mean is that for
example for Azure app configuration, and let me show
here, because it will be more simple, we have the app,
our own application, we have app
configuration and we have
key vault. If our application needs
to access a configuration based on role
based access control, he will be able to access app configuration.
Now what we can have in the configuration, we can have a reference
to a secret, meaning that if
our application needs to access a keyboard value,
for example a secret, he will go to application
configuration. It will require it. But because we
have here a reference for our system to be able to fetch this data
from the keyboard, a role based access control needs to be configured
and it needs to have access to that value.
So if our system is hacked and somebody is getting
access to application configuration, it will not be enough to get the secret
because also the system needs to have access to the
secrets themselves. And depending on the component that we have
here, each component might have access only
to specific secrets and keys
and certifications from keyboard. So it's another layer
of security that we add on top of that.
Storage desk management I think is one of the primary, one of
the most basic things that is part of all
cloud services of all Microsoft Azure. And we are
forgetting, and a lot of them are still seeing
projects that are using account name and account key
to get access to storage.
That's bad, that's very bad. We have so many
other options that we can use.
Azure SAS based on signature
goes very very well. If you need to provide temporary
access to a third party to your system
or to temporary access to another external system,
and you can generate a shared access signature for
a short period of time with only specific rights. For example,
I get you access to that file
for read operation for the next 2 hours based
on the ip that you are using and nothing more than that.
You can generate that access key on the fly.
It's limited availability. What I highly recommend you to do
to have these keys, sas keys with a very
limited lifespan if it's
possible. Five minutes, ten minutes, 15 minutes, don't forget. It's very
cheap to get to provide another
key. If you need to provide long access,
for example to services, to system and so on.
Don't use accounting key. You have Azure role
based control that can be used all the time.
And don't forget about the firewall
rules that are part of Azure storage. I usually call
them like Windows XP firewall
like because basically you
are just whitelisting the IPS. But it's very useful because you can limit
very easily at least
the public ips that can access your storage.
It's one step forward. It's another layer
that you are adding on top of your system.
Sql let's talk about Azure Sql.
Yes, except accessing them through
username and password we already talked about. And we know that we also have
other options we need to take into account that we need to encrypt
the data, the backup we have the firewalls
and the ip for the rules. And please try
to have a clear policies how you're updating the
IPs that can access the database. If you are just adding
ips, adding ranges, it will doesn't work because
in the end, especially if you are working remotely and you
add the ips of each person that is working and not
the range of IP that is used by the company or
by the team from that city, you might be hacked
very easily and also use as much as possible authentication
using identity tax and management. We have the ad,
we have the role based access control. Now on
top of all object level permission, there are two main features that
I would like to talk, but before going to that I would
just want to highlight the treat detection
system that is available on Azure SQL and can detect behaviors
that are not normal or are not happening normally to your database
and can give you a notification, can alert you or you
can define a clear policy. What should happen in
this ended case.
Now column level encryption. It is another core
service of Azure SQL.
And what does this mean? We can specify that for a specific
role we
will have column with hidden value or for example
with a default value or random value and very very useful. For example,
if the support team needs to access environments,
I don't say production environment but environments where you have customer data.
So you can ensure that somebody, for example from support, even if
needs to get access to
the database, he will still not be able to
see a specific column where you have sensitive data. You can have
all the column except the id or even the id
randomly depending on your own needs.
At the same concept you have cell level encryption that
is on the other dimension. You can decide exactly
what are the cells
that will be encrypted and will have some default values.
It goes very well when for example, you have teams that needs to provide
support and you can have some rows in
your database, in your tables with maybe negative
ids that are used only for, not even by
real users, only for some smoke best
or some tests that ensure you that the production system
works as expected.
Endpoints, web endpoints, best API and APIs
are part of our life. I think that
let's say 99.99 of
the systems are providing APIs that are public available
on the Internet or for private consumption
on which they're exposing data, functionality,
business and so on. Now we need to
validate, we have a lot of parameterization and we
encode it and we already know about oaps and
all the best practices, but we
need to build
application with all the functionality that is provided
also by each cloud vendor. And just give you an example, the OAS
protection or to avoid SQL
injection or for example lidos attacks and
so on. We don't need to rely on the application that
we are building. For example, Azure application
gateway is offering us WAF.
It's a level seven load balancer with
a firewall built inside that that will protect us
from oops, attacks and many more. So we
are moving, we are externalized that security
layer of building internally to
Azure application gateway to an external service. What is the benefit?
We can focus more on the business.
We can reduce the workload on the processor and
just focus on the things that we care, the things that are generating business
and value to our customer.
We have also Microsoft Defender for cloud and we need to,
I have a typo here for cloud that
is giving us the ability to do active scanning
of our cloud infrastructure, on our Azure infrastructure and
automatically can detect when we have misconfiguration,
when for example, we are not complying with a specific compliance
that is required. For example, Microsoft Defender can do active scanning of
PCI, DSS 3.2, level one, basically adding infrastructure
layer. And when we have a misconfiguration of something is not configured as
it should be, it can alert us. It can even provide us recommendations
or sometimes, and I will say most of the cases above them,
that when we click it, it will automatically fix the
problem for us. We have a security scoring,
we can do inventory and many more. And additionally
to this we have Azure advisor. This is not only on security, it's also on
liability, performance, cost and operational excellence.
So why I'm saying this? I wanted to highlight the cost because
Azure advisor can provide us recommendations related
to how we can optimize costs based on different patterns,
based on specific tiers
or number of instances that we have allocated,
but we are not fully using them
now. What are the conclusion?
We should remember that we
are the one that are responsible
to build secure application inside
Microsoft Azure. We have all the right tools
to make and to grow secure application.
We have a lot of security features, services we
don't need to install on on prem, a lot of system it is
at the distance of a button, but we need to be aware
of them and we need to configure them and we need to
consider all the features that each cloud vendor like Microsoft Azure is providing
to us. I would highly
recommend to take a look on sky high
network. They have a great cloud security blog where
they have a high level guide for Azure security.
What are the most important thing? And they're covering seven categories
like security policies, identity and asset management, storage account,
SQL networking, vms and
Michelle like for example subscription, something like that.
Just take a look. It's a very good starting point. And don't forget
about best practices
and recommendations that Microsoft is providing to us through security,
best practices for Azure through cloud adoption framework
and WAF that also you'll find similar ones for
other cloud vendors. Thank you. Thank you for listening me
and if you have questions, feel free to reach
me over LinkedIn and Twitter or Twitter.
And why not? Let's have a virtual or physical
coffee next time. Thank you and have
a great day.