Hi, welcome to the session on growing your company with AWS Container Services.
My name is Mesaido Kasingh and I'm a developer advocate with the ECS service
team. Before we start, I would like to give you an idea of what a
developer advocate does with inside a service team. We work closely
with product managers and system engineers in the team to help them understand and
collect the signals and trends from our customers based on your feedback and help
us all improve our products. Instead of going
through architectural details and how things work under the covers, you'll see some
of that. Don't worry. I decided to do today something different. We're going
to go through the story of an imaginary company which is based on the stories
of many real world scenarios and customers. The names of course are not real,
but the actual use case is they are an early stage startup and we
are going to company them on their journey from the early stages.
As they continue to grow from were, we'll jump over to a demo of how
they deploy the solution. Last but not least, we'll also see how they continue
to evolve over time, how their priorities changed, and how
they utilized the continues services within AWS in order
to allow growth and handle complexity. So welcome
to any company. Any company has a brand new product, something new
in tech that will enable you to bring any product from any industry
to market in less than eight weeks. They do this by streamlining the process,
fully automated, allow you to upload a few artifacts and they will take care of
the rest of everything for you. Marketing channels, advertising,
partnership, press releases everything will be done from a to z.
Automated managed AWS a service Scott, the founder
of any company, wanted to solve a personal pain point that he had with his
previous companies that he started. Launching a product is hard.
It has a number of moving parts, relationships that need to be formed and coordinated,
hiring multiple people to track the whole process. And in his experience,
it never ever went smoothly. There were always hiccups along the way,
things that were forgotten, things that he wished that they'd done better.
So he was thinking, why not create a service that will take you
through all the checkboxes and manage it for you? That is what brought Scott
to any company's mission statement. Any company is a small startup
in the early stages. They're just getting started. Meet Scott,
the CEO. He's also the chief marketing officer. He's trying to
raise funding, create a company at the same time. And he lives
more in the air, in hotels than he usually does at home.
Diane's the CTO, the technical visionary for the company. She came
up with the technology and process to make the product possible.
Alice is the vp of engineering. She's a coder at heart,
hands on, and also has great leadership skills that will grow the company.
So as founders do, they got together
and made a strategy for the first six months of the company. And these are
the bullet points that they came up with. Most important things they needed to do.
The first thing they needed to do was create a web presence. They needed to
get the word out to the world about their new technology and a new service.
Of course, they need to find customers, build a product, and build a company in
the background. But the most important thing was to build a web presence
as soon as possible and as quick as possible. So Alice took
on the responsibility for getting the website up and running. She has previous experience with
containers and knows that the technology is sound and it will allow
them to grow in the future. She does not really want to have any time
to maintain the infrastructure underneath that runs the website. And she wants something that
is fire and forget. The product is going to be awesome, of course. So it
will need to handle significant load and Alice does not want to have to
do that on her own. And the most important thing as a developer,
git flow for life. So Alice was started to look for a suitable service
that would search her needs. She contacted the AWS account team and they
decided together to go with AWS apprunner. Let's have a look what apprunner
is. So at the top here is the customer's application coming out of
a container registry like ECR public or ECR private in your account
or source code repository. For example,
GitHub. Sitting underneath that is apprunner. We have a front end API,
a very familiar AWS oriented API that you are
accustomed to working with, along with a very robust AWS
console experience. We've invested heavily from the user experience
perspective into designing a service that takes the different
areas of the AWS console and folds them into
one easy to use product. Everything you see in
the console is also backed by the front end API.
That also allows you to interact directly with the service programmatically.
Underneath is the orchestration workflow. That's what's handling the end
to end story that takes you from a git push all
the way into a running application deployed on the AWS cloud.
With apprunner, there are a variety of these components that you do not
need to manage. A build system, pipeline, load balancers.
All of those are set up automatically for you.
AWS also sets up and handles the author scaling of
the application based on the number of requests apprunner
is still a fairly new service, but the building blocks and the shoulders on which
it is standing are very, very tried and tested.
App runner is built on these mature services that we've encapsulated together into
one simple service. And by leaving the undifferentiated
heavy lifting to us, you don't need deep AWS domain knowledge
to get up and running and be successful with your application.
Apprunner is suitable for many types of applications.
Were are the characteristics that we see most of our customers using for
apprunner applications, web applications and rest APIs
that serve HTTP requests. Also, these applications are stateless.
They store their information in an external data store,
for example DynamoDB RDS. And these applications
are long running applications that can serve many requests,
sometimes simultaneously. In order to handle load,
let's have a look at the user experience in apprunner. Developer writes
the code in their ide and pushes it to a source code repo, for example
GitHub. Or they can create a docker image and upload it to their ECR repository.
They then create an apprunner service which has a number of configurations, the build
and runtime compute resources, a health check to know that tour application is
actually working, auto scaling parameters and the deployment details.
All that information is then used to provide you a customizable
public secure URL with which you can access your
application. So let's have a look what happens when you deploy
an app runner services. Your application is deployed in an AWS
managed VPC where your application is taken
and packaged as a container and deployed on a fargate
task running in that VPC in multiple subnets.
Your customers, when they access the application, will make a DNS request
to route 53 where they will receive an FQDN
which is pointing to the service URL which is actually a network
load balancer. They will make the HTTP request to the load
balancer. From there they will be forwarded to a managed
router inside the app runner service, and each of those requests will
be forwarded to each one of your containers based on the number of containers
running, just so that you know,
apprunner can also scale down to zero, which means that if there are no
requests coming into your application, you will not be paying for any of the requests
coming in and you'll be able to save and optimize your costs
from there. Any application which needs to make a
request out to the Internet, for example to pull down dependencies
in the application or modules, or any other
kind of code will go through the managed. Net gateway
out to the Internet in order to pull those dependencies down into
the application itself. Time for a demo. Let's go
through a scenario that people in any company
would go through in order to deploy their application. So first things
we're going to start with is of course shell,
because there's no other reason why not to.
And here we have simple git repository where
sorry, not a git repository show where
alice decided okay, I have an idea what I would like to do.
I've got some kind of a boilerplate template or
boilerplate design where I would like to base my website upon. She found
something on git, cloned it to her repository, to her local
machine, and for the purposes of
this demo I created a script which will
do a couple of things to make the flow of the demo tiny bit easier.
What this does will make a couple of files, but in the meantime just going
to download the file were to this repository and
the repository is simple, is a node JS application. All I did
was added the demo bash
script. I'm going to run the script at the moment. What it will do will
create a few files for me in this repository, in this repo,
so that I can make my work a little easier. A docker ignore
file docker file a build script, a customized script
just to save time.
Standard default, not a JS application which will create a static website.
So I'm going to run my build script which will build a docker
container for me. Also in the interest of
saving time, this build script is going to go and build
my container locally, but also above and beyond that. It's going to push
it to an ECR private repository which I've already configured
with my account. So I'll be able to use that same
docker image further along the way. It's going to also add two tags
to the same image as well, one with
latest and one with a timestamp based on the
amount of the specific date and time that I'm working on. Takes a
couple of seconds for this to work completely
building the image. Now it's pushing, as we say to my repository in my AWS
account because I've already pre populated the image,
or at least part of it with of the image into my repo is going
a little bit quicker. Some of the layers are already there and
it pushes the second one of the same with a different tag does
it a very quick push and
my image is roundy is ready. I'm going to run this locally on my machine
because I want to see how this actually looks? So I'll run it with a
port 3000, open up my own browser and
look at localhost 3000 to see exactly what this looked like. So,
boilerplate website with some kind of design.
It has a video file and some animations going
on in between. Looks pretty professional. Everything which
was done with the default template was the name of Elementor, was the name
of this website, and it
looks like a good base which I can start upon, but I want to make
some changes because it has to be suitable
for any company, of course, for my website, for my company.
So builds a script which will go
in and modify this boilerplate website
with a number of customizations. Mostly in this case
it's going to be replacing
anywhere where it says Elementor, almost anywhere where it says
elementor into any company you can see.
Made a number of changes in my repo,
in my files, and I'm going to build
a new container based on these changes. So it goes through the
process again using of course docker
caching. It should be a little bit quicker the second time when I'm doing it.
Once the image is built again, push it to my ECR repository
again with minimal changes. Most of the layers are already there so it should be
pretty quick. And the second push is just to add a new tag
which will be even quicker.
And Alice says okay, I want to just see exactly what it looks like and
see if my changes were all right. And aws we had originally the previous
version of the website with the video animation.
And after refreshing you can see these things have changed. Any company has
been replaced, has replaced all the text were it's at elementor,
that video is no longer there. All the customizations I made
any company is more looking something which is more
suitable for my personal website and
the website for the company. So it looks there are a couple of things which
didn't replace properly
because they're graphic elements, which of course Alice
would be able to do properly when she works in more detail on making the
website 100% presentable for the rest of the
world. So Alice has her container
which is ran locally on a machine, but now she wants to take that same
container, same application she wrote, and push it into
apronaut so it will be accessible from the rest of the world. So let's go
to the apparatus console were I already have an any company web
service which has been running built in the background which is watching a git repo
or an ECR repository in this case to make
changes based on every new push so as soon as I pushed
my previous versions and I was pushing them, up until now it has been
making those changes and deploying a new version for my
service. But let's go through how we would create a new service.
So as we said, you can have either a container registry AWS,
your source, or a source code repository,
for example GitHub, where you would create a connection to GitHub.
Choose your GitHub
repo, which branch you would like to work off. In this case, I'm going
to be working off the option of a container registry
where I can choose either ECR public or ECR private.
I'm going to choose my repository where I have this container called
Summit demo with a tag which I've tagged it, and every time this tag is
updated, a new build will occur. I have the
options of choosing how I would like my deployments to work,
either on a manual. In other words, I would initiate these deployments
in a manual fashion or automatically. If there would
be a new push to the GitHub repository or the ECR
repo a new version, then a new build
will kick off and start. You have to give the
service a iem role so it will allow it access
to pull the ECR, the docker image from the ECR. And here
we configure the service and give a number of different options as well.
Choose the amount of cpu and memory that I'm giving
the service, which port it's listening on, and how I
configure. Auto scaling auto scaling is done by the
user configuring how many requests their application
will be able to handle, and as soon as it goes over the number
of requests, concurrent requests to that Docker container,
it will scale up and bring up a new node.
When the number of requests diminishes,
then it will go back down and scale those
containers down. You can create your own custom configuration. In this case,
I'm going to use the defaults.
I can continue a health check to know that my application is up and
running properly. I also can
add an IEM role to the container itself. If I wanted to
perform actions on my behalf into the APIs of AWS,
I can configure what kind of encryption I would like if it's
an AWS owned key, or my own key if I would like to provide
it as well. The next option is networking. If I would
like this application to have access to resources
in my own private VPC, I would choose custom VPC.
If I only want access or access into
the container and without having that container or the application
have access into my own resources, I would choose public for this case.
For the website we are going to choose public, click next and
deploy as
we said console that you all know and recognize
different tabs. For example, the activity tab will give me what's happening with my service
and all the different actions which are currently occurring or have occurred in the
past. The metrics will give me the service metrics of the container, how it's
performing. This will give me a summary of my configuration and
I can change it. And over here I have the option of configuring
a custom domain. By default every service
is provisioned with a region awsaprunner.com
fqdn but of course for
each of tour customers custom applications they would like to have a more recognizable
and usable name. So you can link a route 53
hosted zone to the service and create a AE
record or a CNamE record that will be able to attach
and link to this apprunner service. So your users and
your clients will be able to access through a
generic or your own private FQDN instead of
having coming through the apprunner domain
names in FQDNs. If we quickly
jump into the previous one, you'll see this is what the event log looks like.
It gives me a status of how what everything is happening when
we deploy applications in apprunner and update those applications.
There's a pipeline in the background which deploys a new version in a blue green
deployment so you do not suffer
any downtime when you update your applications and only when your
application has been tested and verified based on your health checks
that everything is up and running, it will switch
to a new version. That is why
you can see that in my case I'm still using a previous version
of my application which hasn't got the updates
for any company in the customization because the
process is not completed of deploying a new version yet and therefore I'm
still running my old version where my
first push of my docker container when I started this demo only
had these original or the same default
template which I was using.
That's how you use apprunner. Thank you very much for watching this
demo and let's go back to the rest of the presentation.
So let's continue with any company's journey. They're growing at
an insane rate and six months have gone by and
of course AWS all founders do they have another meeting
to understand were they want to go with the next six to 18 months
and they came up with these three bullet points that
they need to build a product as fast as possible with minimal maintenance.
They need to bring revenue into the company and of
course they need to gain market share, which means customers. So over
the past six months, the company of course has grown. Instead of the three people
which were doing everything from running around finding
customers to developing a website, they have expanded.
So instead of having one person doing everything,
they now have teams underneath. And most of the employees
are now working on creating a product under Alice, who is
the vp of engineering, who still likes to code, of course, by the way.
So they said, alice, can you build us a product?
That's of course what she was hired for. But the requirements stayed
pretty much the same, except for two things which were added to
the end. The product has to be of course secure because they
don't want to lose any customers because of a security breach or information leaking
or landing up on the front page of the New York Times by any chance
because they didn't guard their customer PII.
And the second thing, of course, it's not only going to be a website that
they built up until now using apprunner, because there is going to be information and
data and things which they need to store and they need to be
stored in place where that can be accessed on a regular basis,
can be used in different ways. So these two different extra
points on the requirements were added and let's
see what Alice did. So Alice
reached out to her account team, spoke to the solutions architect in AWS, and asked,
what can we use, which is similar to the way we're working
now. And after looking through a number of services, they decided to
work on ECS. Amazon Elastic container Services
what is ECS? ECS is a fully managed
control plane and AWS. Fargate is a fully managed data plane.
That means it is the compute that runs the containers that you
provide for your applications.
Customers don't need to maintain any Amis or container host clusters.
It's a big and huge operational savings. Because everything is
managed by AWS. It's easy to scale to ensure better utilization
and cost savings. And of course even further and above and
beyond that, you can use Fargate spot and savings plans to provide
you further saving options in your account and your applications.
The core concepts of ecs are really simple, but really, really powerful.
A task consists of one or more containers. This is your
application that you're running. You can run these tasks on
an EC two instance or a Fargate instance.
And you can also use, of course in order to save money. The spot variants
of those either EC two spot or Fargate spot.
Multiple identical tasks create a service
tasks in a service can be connected to a load balancer, which is automatically
done by ecs and groups of services and
tasks are located in one single cluster.
Customers can create many clusters mapped to teams and workloads.
A cluster is simply a logical grouping.
Any company is leveraging the newly released VPC support
for Avroner to access resources that reside in their VPC.
This ensures that the private information in their databases is
not accessible from the public Internet, which meets the requirement of
security. How is this connected to ECS? Besides the fact
that appraunner uses AWS Fargate for running the
tasks in the background, these other background tasks that they will be starting will be
pulling the information that is collected through a front end application
that is running on apprunner, pushed into an RDS database,
and based on which is stored inside that
database, they'll be able to provide business insight into their customers and
the way they're using their products. So what did we see here
today? We saw an example of a company by the name of any company was
actually not really real, but could be your company or mine.
Makes no difference. They managed to deploy
their resources, meet the requirements in a very,
very simple and easy way, the way they used to working in the AWS
cloud and above and beyond that allowed them to grow further
as their business grew, as they collected more customers and more market
share. The second thing we touched today was serverless containers,
which we by that I mean Fargate and apprunner, where you provide the
container image and the configuration that goes along
with it. And you do not need to manage any of the underlying infrastructure underneath
in order to run the container. All of that is managed and taken care
of by AWS in the cloud. So before
I leave you to go into your next session, I want you to put here
two links to different resources that you can dive
deep into. I kind of geek out on the details
of how things actually work and these two blog
posts will be able to give you a lot more information, a lot more insight
into how both Fargate and how apprunner works underneath,
and how they can bring benefit to you. Thank you very much for your
time. I hope you enjoyed the session and hope you learned something new about running
containers on AWS and how you can benefit from the services which
we have offering you today. My name is Mesaido.
Casing. My emails here are up on the screen. The easiest way to get hold
of me is to ping me on Twitter. My dms are open.
Anything you would like to discuss. I'm always happy to hear from our customers.
Thank you very much for your time and have a great day.