Hi, I'm Ankit and I have close to four years of experience
in web development. Today we are going to talk about
unlocking the power of Shadow Dom. So let's get started. So here's
what we are using to cover. We'll start with what is Shadow Dom?
What are the different types of Shadow Dom? Real world examples of
Shadow Dom in action. How you can implement Shadow Dom
in popular web developers frameworks like React and angular. Then we are
going to end with a hands on demo to put it all together.
So what is Shadowdom? In simple terms,
it is a fundamental web technology that helps you encapsulate your web
components and styles, making them immune to global
scope. Think of it as a protective shell around your
components, ensuring that your code won't interfere with or be
interfered by other parts of your web application.
Shadow Dom comes in two flavors, open and closed.
The distinction between them is how much they expose the outside world.
Open Shadow Dom allows you to style your components from the outside.
To create an open shadow dom you can use this code,
whereas the closed shadow Dom keeps everything hidden away from the global
style. To create a closed shadow dom you can use this code.
Shadow Dom has been embraced by some of the most popular web
applications including YouTube, Google Maps and even material UI.
YouTube utilizes shadow Dom for its video player,
ensuring that your custom styles don't break the player's layout.
Google Maps uses Shadow Dom to encapsulate the maps component,
providing a seamless integration experience.
You can also use shadow Dom in all popular frameworks like React,
angular or just simple web components. Here you
can see to use Shadow Dom in react, we use
the attached shadow function on the reference of a JSX
element. Shadow Dom is at the core of angular's
component encapsulation. You can see that we can add
can encapsulation property in the component directive
of any angular component. You can also create shadow DOm
and simple web components using the attached shadow function.
Now comes the fun part. Let's look at shadow Dom in
action. Here you can see we have created a simple web page.
Here we have a tag that says custom button in the
script. We have reference to this custom button element
using the query selector. Then we are creating
a shadow dom using the attach shadow function.
Note that the mode is closed. That means other
components cannot access this shadow Dom.
We are also creating a style for our button.
Then we are attaching the styles to the shadow Dom.
Then we are creating a button using the create
element and we are naming the button unlocking.
Then we are attaching the button to the shadow dot here you can see
the output. Now since this is closed, if I
just add in a style on the button and
say background color equals to green and
save it, you can see that no changes occur.
Now if I just change this mode to open
then also this doesn't work.
This is normal in shadow Dom because how shadow
Dom works is it creates encapsulation, right?
So to access the open shadow Dom what we can do is
we have to create a script tag and then we'll just type in
document getelement by Id.
Then we have our custom button shadowboot
queryselector. Then we will select the
button style.
Then here we can change the background, choose the background
color and set it to green. Now you can see the color
of the button has changed. Now if I just change this
mode open to close and save it,
you can see that the color is reverted back to
blue. If I check console, you can see that
cannot read properties of null. That means
the shadow Dom is not accessible. Now if we
just go to elements and expand this custom button, you'll see
a shadow root and in bracket you can see closed.
This means the shadow Dom is there, but it's not accessible by
the other components. You can see all the styles
as well as the button here,
but it is not accessible. So if we change
this to open and save, you can
see that the color of the button changed and the shadow
root is now again changed to open. You can still see the styles
and modify it using the JavaScript functions. So this
is how you can use shadow Dom in your web applications.
You can scan this QR code to connect to me on LinkedIn and also
access the port. Thank you for joining in.