Welcome to the lightning talk on Athens to algorithms,
what the ancient greek philosopher Zeno can tell us
about tech leadership in the 21st century.
I'm Jim Murphy. I'm going to be talking about this topic for
roughly 15 to 20 minutes. A quick lightning talk.
And I like to start my presentations with a
story that humiliates me. I do this for a couple of reasons.
I do it because I want you to understand why this
topic is meaningful for me and why I put it together to hopefully
help you empathize with the content. But I also do
it so that you feel sorry for me and vote my talk highly.
So hopefully I can do that. The story I'm going
to tell is actually putting together this talk. I love
mathematics. I love learning about mathematics.
And I learn about a greek mathematician,
Xeno, and things like Xeno's paradox and
the work that he did in that area. And I
also learn about stoicism and the concept of
stoicism. And I had this person,
Xeno, in investigating this. I thought these two Zeno
were actually the same person. And I put a whole introductory
part to this presentation about the mathematics
that Zeno did, only to present it for the first time and
have a good friend of mine say, andrew, those are two different
Zeno. Turns out Zeno is the
John Smith of the ancient greek era,
and these two xenos have nothing to do with each other. So I am
not going to be talking about Xeno's paradox. I'm not going to be talking about
turtles and arrows. I'm going to be talking about Zeno
of Sitium, who was an ancient greek philosopher
and created and helped create a lot of concepts,
the one of which we're going to talk the most in depth about today
is stoicism and how stoicism can
be tied into technology leadership. So I mentioned,
I'm Andrew Murphy. I want to tell you a little bit more about me
before we go into the meat of this presentation.
I am a long term father of a flock of chickens,
or as we call them in Australia, chucks.
I'm a short term father of a flock of humans, or as
we call them in Australia, financial burdens.
And I really like travel. I love getting around the world. And this
will come into play a little bit later in our discussion from
a professional point of view. I've been a coder
and a programmer for as long as I can remember.
I learned to write code very, very early,
and I've been paid to write code for about
20 years at this point. But I also had a few formative
experiences that got me into the told of
technology leadership really, really early. By the
time I was 24 years old, I was running
a team of ten people. And I don't say that to say,
wow, aren't I awesome for running a team of ten people?
I sucked at it. I was a bad leader.
What 24 year old knows how to be an
employee, let alone a leader of people? And so I
made a bunch of mistakes. And unfortunately, when you're a leader and you
make mistakes, often those mistakes are at the expense of
the people you lead. So this lent
me to go on a pathway of learning to be a
better leader, learning to understand the skills of leadership. Two, the point
where I taught other leaders how to lead,
taught new leaders to understand the concepts of leadership and the
difference between being an excellent individual contributor
and an excellent leader, and what the difference between those two
was. This has now led me to run my
own company, tech leader's launchpad, which focuses solely
on helping new and emerging tech leader understand their roles
better through training, coaching,
and consultation. Let's talk
a little bit more about Zeno.
Zeno was an ancient greek philosopher. He was born on
the island of Cyprus. Cyprus is in the middle of the Mediterranean.
It's an island that I've been to many, many times, if you
can't tell from the accent. I grew up in England, and so
Cyprus was a mere four or five hour plane ride
away, which might sound a lot for those of you who live
in Europe, but now that I live in Australia,
you get on a plane for 4 hours and you're still in the country.
So it's something I miss. Being from Europe
is that ability to travel. Zeno is part
of a whole tranche of philosophers who came up about the same
time at around the third to fourth
century BC. They focused on learning
a lot about philosophy, coming up with a bunch of theories and concepts
and ideas that in the modern
era, we just kind of take as part of who we are.
The three that I've highlighted at the bottom in those pictures on that slide
are logos. The first, the idea of logic.
Somebody had to invent the idea of logic, which just seems
so strange to us nowadays, that logic didn't exist
at some point and somebody created it. But he,
along with a few other people, created and fundamentalized
the idea of logic and predicates and things that
are either true or not true, and how you can reason and
decide whether one thing is true based on other things being
true or not being true. He also was
fundamental in a concept called cosmopolitanism.
Not the drink
that you see in the picture, which is named after the concept,
but cosmopolitanism is this idea that
we are not citizens of a country or a city
or a tribe. We are citizens of the world.
You are either an individual human being,
or you are a citizen of the world. And there is nothing in the middle
of those. You don't belong to a tribe or a creed or
a race or a country or a region.
You are part of the world. And I really like this
idea. As somebody who was born in northern Europe and now lives
in Australia, I love the freedom that we can have to
travel and see the world and to learn and to become part of
it and to break down those boundaries. I think there's nothing better and nothing
more important in the world than seeing it and
seeing the people that are in it.
And lastly, the main topic of the discussion today.
He was fundamental in the creation
of stoicism. He taught a
whole idea around stoicism,
which is fundamentally in that one image.
That image in the bottom right is stoicism in
a single image. Let's go into that, and let's talk about the basics
of stoicism. This is stoicism in a single image.
It's represented as a triangle.
And the points of the Triangle,
the angles of it, represent the three tenets
of stoicism. At the bottom
right is something called the dichotomy of control. That's fundamental.
Two stoics. It's the idea that you should focus
on that which you can control and only that which you can
control. You should forget about or accept
those things which you can't control in order to
save the time and energy to focus on the things you can control.
And we'll dive into that later. The top
angle is, take responsibility for
the actions you take, the judgments you make. Take responsibility
for those things which are in your control.
So if we are separating the world through the
dichotomy of control into things we can control and things
we can't control, then we should take responsibility
for the things we can control. Then in the bottom
left is hopefully through doing those
things, through focusing on the things we can control and
taking responsibility for them. We can live
with arate, which roughly translates
to living your best self.
And by doing these things, we hopefully
lead towards this concept of eudaimonia,
which literally translates as happy inner
demon. But modern usage of
the word demon doesn't really translate in the same way. You can
think of it more as happy inner self.
And so by focusing on what we can control,
taking responsibility for it,
focusing on improving ourselves. By living with arate,
we hopefully reach this state of eudaimonia, this happy
inner spirit, if we want to use that word.
And that's the three core
tenets that no matter what happens to us around
us, we should focus on what we can control,
take responsibility for our judgments, and live
by constantly improving ourselves with
arate. So at this point, you're probably asking
me, Andrew, we're almost ten minutes into this talk. What does
this have to do with tech leadership? Let's get there.
Let's talk about how these concepts of stoicism
apply very directly to being a tech leader in 2024.
The first concept is applying the stoic dichotomy
of control. Focus on what we can control. So, really,
what it's saying is, we can control our actions,
reactions, and attitudes, but we cannot
control external events or other people's
actions, reactions, and attitudes. We can influence
those things, but we cannot control them.
And so if we look at what that means in
leadership, there are a certain list of things
that are in our control, and we should focus on those things,
and there are a certain list of things that are not in
our control. And so what's
in our control, for example, is managing
our team effectively. We can control this. It is within
our power to affect change in that area.
What is not in our control are the team dynamics,
when you join your team, and we could often
find ourselves, when we join a new team, going, oh, I wish things were
different, or, why did they have to get into this? Or they've got bad mindsets,
bad habits, bad skill sets.
It's so frustrating the way they are, and it's just
causing me two kind of give up hope that I can ever
help this team become the best they can be.
The stoic would say, it doesn't matter why
they got to where they are, and you weren't
in control of that situation, but you are in control
of how you go forward with it. You are in control with how
that makes you feel, and you are in control of the judgments
that you make in order to progress
forward. Now, we can have an interesting debate
around the fact that you don't want
to completely ignore how the team got
to where they are, but fixating on it
and using it as an excuse for
why you can't progress or feeling like it's
an obstacle you cannot overcome in order to improve the team
doesn't help anybody. Another thing you can't control
are market dynamics. I'm recording this
at the start of 2024.
2023 was a rough
year. 2022, end of 2022 was an even
rougher period for our industry. We can't control that.
We can't control the market dynamics. But what we
can do is constantly develop our team, their skills
and their ability to handle these situations.
If we just throw our hands up and go, the market is terrible,
there's nothing we can do, and woe is us, then that's not
going to help you. It's going to just give you an excuse.
It's just going to make you frustrated and give up.
Whereas if you focus on the things you can control, which is how you
respond to that situation, you can focus
on the development and improvement of your team to help them
better respond to the situation. Lastly, in the
things we can't control, user and client decisions.
For those of you who work in consultancies, you know that often
clients don't make decisions that are in their best interests or the best
interests of their users. And so you can often feel frustrated and
angry that the client just doesn't get it. And why are they making these decisions?
That is not productive and conducive to a healthy relationship with
the client. But it's also not useful for you as an individual to
feel this sense of anger, frustration and resentment constantly.
And letting go of that and accepting that that is
the way it is and we have to respond to that,
means that what we should actually be doing is focusing
on building teams and prowess and systems and software
that are responsive to change, and that
enable us to innovate and adjust
and improve the way we do things when these decisions
inevitably don't go the way we expect, or when those decisions
are changing constantly. And so all
of these things, this dichotomy of control and this
giving, not allowing those things
that are not in our control to drive our emotions to such a deep
extent, but also accepting our part in how
we move forward, means that we're leading towards rational
decision making. As a technology leader,
understanding this dichotomy of control means we
can understand the things in which we have influence over
and the things we don't, and therefore devote our
efforts where they are most effective.
Second, in our stoic principles is taking responsibility
for our judgments. What do I mean by judgments? I don't mean
wearing a wig and making proceedings
over things in a courtroom. I mean the decisions we
make and the actions we take based
on things that happen to us, the events that happen in our lives,
and also the emotional responses that those
events trigger. We cannot control the
emotional response that we get to certain circumstances,
there's always going two be things that push us beyond
our ability to stay composed and our ability
to not trigger an emotional response.
We have this word trigger, which means we are sometimes
rationally or irrationally emotionally evoked
by certain circumstances. And this
idea of taking responsibility for our judgments is
not about having a suppression
of those emotional responses. It's about understanding
the reactions, the actions, the judgments we make
after we feel those emotions and allowing
us to change those based on those emotional responses.
It's really difficult for us to change those emotional responses
themselves. But what we can do is control
the judgments, the actions, reactions that we
take because of those emotions.
So you can think about this as a process,
as a series on a flowchart. There's the
event that happens. We have no control over
that at all. There's the emotional response
we have because of that event. We have very
little emotional control over that. We can,
through other processes, like CBT and
like, we can influence that. But sometimes it's really difficult to change
those emotional responses. But as logical
homo sapiens, we do have control over the
actions and reactions, or as stoicism will call them,
the judgments. We do have control over those. And so that's
where we should focus our energy. That's where we should focus.
Our effort is accepting the fact we can't
control the events and the emotions, but we can control those actions and
reactions, and therefore, we should take responsibility
for those. Really what we're talking about here
is emotional resilience, understanding those things
that are within our control and what emotions those evoke
and allowing ourselves. Two, understand that those emotions are
sometimes not able to be controlled immediately,
but we can control the actions and reactions that
those emotions evoke in us. Lastly is the
concept of living with arate by expressing
our best self. What am I talking about with that?
Well, this is about living up to your full potential through empathy and
constant learning and development. We have
so much around us that enables us to improve ourselves.
And the world is constantly changing. The industry
we're in is constantly changing. The technologies are constantly
changing. And if we just accept status quo,
then we're not living with arate.
And this means we can't reach that state of eudaimonia,
this happy inner demon. And so constant
focus on what we can do to improve ourselves
is living with a stoic life.
What are the areas in which we can improve? What are the areas in which
we can strengthen? What are the areas in which we can invest time
in improving ourselves? This means we're going to be able to tackle
everything better. We're going to improve our judgments. We're going to be able to
increase the sphere of influence of our dichotomy of
control. We're going to be able to improve ourselves constantly.
This isn't about investing
every single hour of every single day into getting better, but it's
just being aware that there is this stoic
principle of just what have you done this week?
What have you done this month? What have you done this year to improve yourself?
Because living with stoicism is constantly improvement
as a leader. There's another interesting dynamic here,
which is that in doing this, we're setting an example for others to
follow. If we show ourselves
as somebody who wants two improve, wants to get better,
then we're encouraging that behavior in other people.
And what we're also doing is showing that we're not perfect.
We have flaws, we have things we can get better at. And that enables
other people to be open about the areas in which they can
improve and they can get better at. So we're talking here about
the concept of continual self improvement
calls, right? So I want to end with a quote
from Zeno themselves, which is that
man conquers the world by conquering himself.
I apologize for the very gendered language in this quote.
Zeno, like I said, is from three to 400 bc.
We would write this very differently nowadays, but hopefully the
concepts resonate, which is if we want to exert
influence on the world, we have to exert influence on ourselves.
And we can do that through many ways. One of them that
Zeno himself would advocate, and I would advocate,
is by living with the principles of stoicism,
especially if you're a technology leader.
To wrap up, I want to share a couple of links with you if you
want to know more about me and what I do. I do regular live streams
on LinkedIn where I talk about technology leadership topics.
I also post content on there pretty regularly,
and I have a blog. All of
those are in the QR codes that you can see in front of you.
There's also a link to tech leader's launchpad,
which is my online technology leadership training
platform where I've got a bunch of great courses that help you become
a better technology leader in whatever area you need
help in. If you've got any questions, feel free to reach
out to me. I love talking about this stuff and
will love to have a continued conversation about
where you see this fits in with your lives. I'll see
you next time.