Good morning. Good afternoon everybody. Today we are going to discuss the challenges
platform teams face on their day to day operation, and then
we're going to discuss the tips and tricks on how those challenges
can be overcome. First, a little bit about myself.
My name is Marco, I'm italian born, but I'm based in
southern Spain. I've been working in thoughtworks for about
three years. I like to call myself a technologist
and a tinkerer and my true passion lies in animal
rights activism. I've been working for the last
three years in a consultancy company called Fluttworks.
It's us based but it has offices all around the world.
We've been building extraordinary impact. Together with
our client worldwide, we try to amplify positive
social change and revolutionize the tech industry.
Across the years we created innovative products
such as cruise control, which was the first continuous
integration server. We created selenium.
We invented the technology radar which you might be familiar
with, and we keep pushing the
envelope and try to make the technology landscape
better. Also, we have technical
expertise that is showcased by the sheer
amount of technical books we publish in orally and in other
providers. So we like to say whatever
topic, technical topic you can think of, we have written
the book on it. The agenda for today will be first
we'll delve into the unique challenges that are specific
to platform teams and to platform products.
Then we're going to spend some time discussing how these challenges can
be overcome and we'll conclude with a couple of zoom
ins around practices and products.
Starting with the challenges group
is definitely around ux, so we can
highlight five categories. Centricity is
the first one. Developers need to be put at
the center all new product development.
We need to bear in mind what their needs are.
We need to understand what their requirements and aspirations
are. We then need to be able to provide them with
a consistent experience across different
products and services so that there's a seamless experience for
them and they don't even have to notice
when they are using one service or another.
A common problem writing software
or writing products for developers is their
traditional lack of feedback. Developers are quite
eager to get feedback on their work, but whenever a tool
doesn't fit their objectives,
just gonna drop it and look for another one.
Categories that are tied together are simplicity and
usability, and we should aim for both,
meaning that a product should be both simple
and usable. But whenever there's a trade off between the
two, we should always favor usability.
So we don't want a product to always have
the most basic functionality. So being simple, but we want
it to be easy to use and provide an
additional range of functionality that can cater to advanced
users. The next set of challenges is
around business. Here we can think of the common lack of
insights platform teams have into the long term
organizational strategy and even into the roadmaps of
individual products. When this happens, it becomes
harder for platform teams to be ready with the functionality product
teams need in time for when they need them and to
make sure that they are battle tested. There can be
a common distrust of platform technologies,
especially from senior stakeholders. When this happens, it becomes
harder to embrace cloud native technologies,
to move to the cloud, and to embark on innovative
initiatives such as the cloud
carbon footprint measurement, a misconception
about what the ideal operating model for platform teams
should be. And here we can think of platform teams that
are thought as support teams or just
CI CD squads that only focus on helping
development or product teams when they get stuck.
The next set of challenges revolves around technology. Here we
can think of the high cognitive load platform teams are
subject to. All the CI CD
monitoring, instrumentation database tools
that are required for the organization to function,
need somebody be well versed in, and most
often these people are in
order to be able to support the product teams
that use this technology, platform teams need
to work with a number of different tools
at the same time, and this also requires a
lot of context switching for them. Then we can think
that platform teams should really focus mostly
on their intended roadmap. They should have their own
product backlog and they should make constant improvements to
make sure that development teams get the functionality they need.
But most often they get interrupted and they need to firefight
and help product teams with urgent escalations.
On top of this, there can be additional workloads coming
from business requests and they can become
the point of contact for third party vendors.
Still time from their work on the internal roadmap and
platform teams can feel a sense of disconnection because they
are at least two levels apart from the
business, so they might not feel that they are contributing
that much into the overall, there's a set of
challenges that include working with many different stacks,
solution and vendors. Here we can think of platform teams
having to interact with product teams using different
tech stacks such as Java, Kotlin.net, Comma, Golang,
Python and being able to support them.
Then there's the presence of
many different vendors which need to interact with
and there's always a platform team that is responsible for
the interaction between these vendors and the product teams needing their
services. Using so many different technologies means that
platform teams need to spend a significant amount of
their time keeping up to date with this changing landscape.
Not doing so can be a risk in terms of security, can be
a risk in terms of missed opportunity if we are
not able to use the new features whenever there's
an upgrade. New services can also mean that
we might be using something that is not enterprise grade
or does not mean the required SLA and Slos for our
company. So platform teams might need to step
in in those circumstances and being able to cover
the slack for those products that
have been chosen and are not up to par.
Finally, there's a risk of a vendor lock
in. So our technology choice was
made some years ago, some time ago,
and then there's no way out of it. So essentially the company
is stuck using these providers and
there's no alternative in the market or there's no reasonable
path out of it. How can we overcome these
challenges? Starting with the devex ones,
we can think of having research,
segmentation and experimentation in place.
Start by building the smallest possible feature that
can fulfill the requirements from the product teams
and then from there iterate. This is akin to having
an agile mindset applied to the platform teams.
We then can move on to have concepts from experience
design, meaning that we should profile and understand.
Our internal users should have Personas built
around them and we should understand their goal, aspiration and needs,
and we should base our future development based
on the outcome of this experience design.
We can then have an internal developer portal which would allow
all documentation to be put in one place and then
would allow developers to quickly create new
repository and service and have a quick way to deploy
those new services into production quickly. Platform teams will
have to spend less time with their product
teams and this can be accomplished by having comprehensive
documentation that details possible problems
and how they they can be solved.
Finally, we can think of eliciting continuous
feedback from the development teams, for instance,
scoring how the help was whenever
platform teams came to their help,
and then also asking for feedback on how things could be
improved. Moving on to the business challenges something
that platform teams can do is to try to understand
better the challenges of the organization and
what the ultimate goals are. This can translate, for instance,
to platform teams attending business hold hands,
asking questions, trying to have additional sessions with
the platform with the product teams.
Next, platform teams should make sure that the internal
platform roadmap is aligned with a roadmap of
the product they serve. This does not mean only
in terms of functionality, but also in terms of timeline
and completeness of those features.
We don't need to have something 100% ready
from day one, but we can the
functionality that is required from the beginning and then iterate on
it. We need to provide a strong foundation that
then the product teams can build upon. And this foundation should
revolve around practices such as having a good
governance in place, having security by default,
SRE practices, and launch innovative
initiatives such as phenops and carbon footprint
reduction. Next, we can look at the set of challenges
that are specific to technology. It's important to
build a platform product as an ecosystem
where different solutions integrate different
solution, even coming from different vendors, should be
one single product by the internal users. So we should be
able to provide a seamless experience across these
different products and services to
our internal when we decide to use
a product, a technology or a service, we need to
have well established evaluation techniques in place,
meaning that every time we go on the market
or look for an open source software to solve a specific business
or technological need, those evaluation
techniques should be in place and should be
stable and should be approved by the organization at large.
We then need to treat the platform
products their own life cycles, meaning that we
need to establish specific criteria for when
a new product should be created, when it should be
maintained and when it's time to retire it.
We should opt to vendor agnostic technologies
whenever possible. This could mean, for instance, to use terraform
rather than cloud formation rather than biceps,
because terraform are specific cloud providers,
but the same technology can then be used for other purposes
such as terraform code for the
Octa configuration, for instance. We need to be
able to cultivate the relationships internally
and externally and showcase the value delivered.
We need to make sure that all our internal and
external stakeholders understand the value the platform teams
are providing and making sure that the functionality
offered is improving over time. It's then important
to allocate some time to choose
the right toolset and technology to try them out
and set on the best one, not picking the
first one in a rush. The evaluation
needs to reflect metrics such as enterprise
grade, SLA's extensibility,
how much it's used in the industry, and even the
reputation of the producer of these tools.
We need to make sure that the platform roadmap is tied
to the organization and the business strategy so that
the goals are aligned and we are seen contributing
to the overall strat, the overall success of the
organization at large. We should strive to
make sure that development teams are able
to work independently and they don't need handholding
from the platform teams. This can be achieved by self service
portal having very effective onboarding here.
For instance, the North Star for the onboarding could be
making sure that when a developer joins their team,
they can commit and deploy to production in one day. This is
very aspirational from an organization, but it's something a
company should work toward, providing playgrounds so
that developers can try out new things without risking an
accident in production. Next, we can have a couple of zoom
ins about practices and product thinking.
Platform teams implement agile first and foremost,
it's important to have a clear definition of the client,
most often the client of a platform team and
internal development teams. It's important to understand the
differences between the internal development teams,
what kind of need and aspiration they have,
what kind of stack they use and what drives
them. It's then important to work
in new features with an MVP mindset,
meaning that we should be able to deliver a product
that fulfills only the strong requirements
that are asked for by the development teams,
and we can then iterate and prioritize
subsequent improvements. We'll most likely have
competing priorities between different services and
different teams, so we need to be able to balance providing
additional functionality with a timely delivery.
It's also important to measure success. How can
this be measured success for platform teams?
Development teams are happy with the work we've
been doing, thinking about something more tangible,
that they are able to go to production quicker, that they
have fewer accidents in production, that the onboarding
is smoother. So we have both
qualitative and quantitative measures for this next
platform teams should have a clear definition of their software
development life cycles. We can start with testing,
meaning that platform teams should have a testing mindset and should apply
the same practices that are often used in development
teams around testing. It shouldn't be an excuse
that infrastructure is harder to test, as many
technologies such as terraform have comprehensive frameworks
that allow for unit integration and end
to end tests. So we can have a pyramid of
tests in the same way we have for
development code bases. Another strategy that
can be used to have a better delivery is
using feature toggles. This will allow us to
deploy new functionality to production from day
one without the risk of breaking existing things.
This will allow us to also showcase new
functionality to specific users or specific
roles. It's important for platform teams
to provide abstractions to the development teams
that use that are provided by,
but it's also important to have the right level of abstraction
in place. In software development, there's a concept
of which means that our abstraction is leaking
concept from a concept, from the underlying layer.
This makes it very harder for the user
of our abstraction component kind of concepts
in mind when they're using our library. So hitting the right
level of abstraction is notoriously hard,
but it's also extremely important and having
a clear definition of done, it's extremely
necessary for platform teams. So it's important to understand when
a new feature is completed. Is it completed
when the code is pushed to master,
is it completed when it's deployed, is it completed when a new
library version is released, or is it completed when all
the internal development teams are using the new version?
You need to be able to measure who's using which versions
and provide incentive to update to the latest version.
Finally, we can think of having the
ideas from team topologies applied so
platform teams can act as enablers
at times. So they should be able to come
in and help development teams adopt the
best practices such as monitoring effective
deployment instrumentation, having an effective
kubernetes deployment, for instance, whenever a development
team is not able to do it on their own.
The important part here is that it
should be done on a case by case basis, and it
should be done with the goal of making sure that the
development team can be self sufficient in those respects.
After an agreed upon timeline, it's important
that the platform teams specialize and focus on providing
core building blocks that then the product teams
can reuse and customize according to their needs.
They shouldn't be providing the ultimate we
can think of having domain driven design also in platform domains,
so having this segregation in place will allow us
to have a better definition of what each platform team should
be responsible for and avoid the painful and
costly context switching that oftentimes happen in
platform teams. We should aim at having independent
dev streams where the development teams
are able to ship new features
without intervention from the platform team, and they should
be able to solve production issues and improve their
internal codebases and deployments without
need of intervention from the platform teams.
We can also apply concepts from product or
portfolio management to platform teams. So whenever we
decide to build an abstraction on top of existing
products, especially third party products, we need to make sure that
the abstraction makes sense and that is actually providing a value.
If not, we should maybe reconsider using the underlying
direct implementation that most likely is already well tested and
documented. We need to be able also to
think about how we can abstract from organization,
process and rules. So if you can provide a
strong default on the configuration
that adheres to the organization rules, it will
make the developer's life much, much easier.
We can also think about treating the product and services
of the platform team as part of a service portfolio.
Each product and service will have a different maturity and will
have a different lifecycle stage product
metrics for the products of the platform team, so we should understand what
their cost is, what level of adoption they have
and extensively used they are across the organization,
and how much financial sense they make. We should
be able to define the ROI for these products from
their inception, making sure how long it will take to
recover from the investment and then
this return doesn't materialize. We can decide if
we want to pivot or if we want to change approach,
or if you want to continue on the trajectory course having
some enterprise foundation would
mean providing some safety net to the developers, making sure that
it's harder to misconfigure a service and potentially
disclose sensitive information, or leaving
a door ajar for potential attackers.
So we should also evaluate the enterprise grade
of our internal platform solutions, making sure that they comply with SLA
and slos that are mandated by the company at large and
the products provided by the platform teams should be integrated
in a seamless ecosystem, making sure that the development
experience is consistent. So thank
you very much for attending. Today. We covered a lot of ground.
We talked about the most common challenges that platform team
face on their day to day operations, and then
we analyzed how those challenges can be addressed and even
how platform team can shift their mindset into
a more agile and product driven mindset. Thank you very much for attending.