Everyone, my name is Michael Zion. I'm the co
founder and CTO at Meteorops. We are a DevOps
services company, and I'm here to talk to
you today about DevOps course,
but more specifically, a handbook that I created for
ctos mostly, but actually
it's for anyone that wants to understand,
in simple words, what's DevOps and
wants CTO get simple principles
in order to make decisions easily.
And hopefully by the end of this talk, you'll have
a bunch of principles that are useful with
some examples of what you should be doing
and when. And, yeah, let's jump right into
it. So maybe you are a CTO,
maybe you're a DevOps engineer, maybe you're VPR and D in your
company. Either way, this handbook is
useful. Hopefully it's useful for you.
Okay, so the goals, it's mostly
to understand what's DevOps in simple words.
And why am I saying in simple words? Because for some
reason,
with every role in the R D organization,
if you ask someone what this role is and someone gives you a definition,
no problem. But with DevOps, try telling someone what DevOps
is. Somehow it's controversial. People will
tell you, no, it's something else. Every company
whats its own philosophy. So I'm aiming to give you a very simple,
very common definition and practical
one as well. I want to tell you what's possible. So many
founders don't know what to expect from DevOps.
They don't know. Okay, so I heard about this thing called DevOps.
I heard it should help me do this and that,
but what should I expect from it? So, what's possible?
And I'll provide you with some simple examples.
And the final thing is when to do what. This is the
principles part. This is the part where I
give you some use cases, and you
can take those use cases and apply those
scenarios in your company. I don't have
everything from the handbook in this talk, so I
do have a link. At the end of the stock,
you can scan the QR and go to the
full handbook. And, yeah, let's jump right into it.
So, first part, understand the desired result.
So, as a software company,
you have two goals. One is
to serve your product to your customers, of course.
And the second goal is in order to
do the first one, you want to be able to build and improve your system
all the time. Okay, so what
do you need in order to be able to build and improve your system?
So, in essence, run experiments and test changes.
When it comes to software engineering, it's computer
science, right?
There's a reference from a lecture of Uncle
Bob. It's the clean code guy. He said he
was talking about Dixta. Diexta is one of the
founding fathers of computer science. And he thought programming
is going to be a mathematical discipline. He thought
people will, programmers will write functions,
mathematically prove them, and then we'll
have sort of a library of mathematically proven
functions which will be used to build more and more elaborate
functions. Of course that's not the case.
We don't mathematically prove functions,
we test them. We treat it as
a science, not as a mathematical discipline. So we
do something and then we test if it works, and if it does,
that's good. So second thing is,
DevOps has a simple meaning. And I
know some people won't agree with this definition,
but I'm using this definition because
I find it useful. Or for so
many companys that adopted this definition,
just found it easier to go forward with DevOps.
So the idea is this,
originally it's a culture,
originally somewhere in 2008.
Whats just about the idea that developers and operators
should work together in practice today the
definition is developers operate system.
And I'll say what it means in a sec, you already see it on the
screen of course. And DevOps engineers enable
developers to operate the system and
to some extent operate the system themselves. So when
I say operate I mean provision.
So provision is creating infrastructure,
resources, et cetera, test, course,
deploy. This means we did something, we want to
push it into the system. So introducing
changes, monitor. So this means seeing the state of the system,
getting alerts for it, et cetera, secure.
So this means limiting the
network access to the system, limiting access
using authentication and authorization,
limiting and preventing any potential issues,
vulnerabilities, et cetera. So next thing is configure.
So configure is just a way
to sort of modify configurations
in your system. This could mean changing
configuration in git, could mean changing configuration in a database or
in any KV store, something of that sort
and scale up and down, scale the system up and
down based on the demand. So taking
all of that, I think some people might already look
at this slide and say this guy is delusional,
developers should do all of that. So I'm saying yes
to some extent, and the DevOps engineers should do
the rest. To some extent. When I say the rest,
I mean both developers and DevOps engineers have responsibility
over operating the system. And every
company chooses the balance between how much the
developers should do it, how much the DevOps engineers should do it.
From this slide, the key thing I want you to take is this words
enable. So the main function of a DevOps engineer is
to enable to operate, okay? So if
you had to take one thing from this slide. So now
choose a balance. We said in the previous
slide, developers operate the system. DevOps engineers enable
developers to operate the system and operate some of it themselves.
And operate some of it themselves. How much do
they operate it? This is choose the balance. So when I say choose
a balance, there are three things within
this balance that you can tweak.
So you can, as a
DevOps engineer, like the DevOps engineer in your company,
can choose how much they enable,
how much they do, how much they automate.
Okay? There's overlap between
these things. So enabler, an enabler
provides tools and knowledge, okay, so a tool could be
ready made, community built tool could be
a tool that some company built and sells.
It could be a script that you built,
any abstraction that exists.
And knowledge, of course, it's the knowledge for how to achieve something.
So that's enabler,
Doer does the tasks,
of course that's the most time consuming for the DevOps engineer
and the least scalable way of doing things because
it's completely relying on the available capacity of the
DevOps engineer in the moment. Okay,
automator. So automating
any repeating tasks. So this means you're
taking some of the stuff that you did and you automate it.
This is before enabling it for someone else,
meaning maybe you,
let's take the example. So a developer asks for DB,
an enabler gives them a script or
some tool to create the database. The doer
just creates the database, goes into the UI,
clicks some stuff and gets the database.
The automator will maybe
create a script, but give it to the developer or
sorry, no, the automator will create a script
and use it himself. So that's one step before the enablement.
Okay, so one principle here is tools
have bigger leverage, better leverage than
knowledge, and enable has
much more leverage than doing so.
If I want you to take one thing from here is
this line, because that's the guidelines principle
for your decision making. And every
company has it differently. Meaning I saw
companies whats just decided to
give developers full freedom and make
sure part of the onboarding process is them learning some tools.
So they went completely with knowledge. I saw some
companies that the DevOps engineer abstracted away everything.
The developers don't need to know anything about it.
And that's another discussion.
The next thing is choose the right tools. So when
I say choose the right tools, this one is
so important, it's about
tackling common use
cases using solutions that were already
built to tackle those use cases. And I
found there to be three things that are the biggest
time savers. One is that the tool
whats native state management built inside, like terraform
does, like Kubernetes does, like Pulumi
does. So just to name a few examples of tools with
state management. And why is it such a time
saver? Because when you operate a system,
as its complexity grows,
understand what the current state is,
is crucial in order to introduce any change. Because if
you don't know if something exists or not,
it's very difficult to make any change to
the system. We know that with Git,
for example, git is a perfect example, right? You want developers
to collaborate, they have to agree on what the source of truth
is. They have to agree on what the truth is. That's the entire idea of
continuous integration. Again, another conversation.
But in order to collaborate, in order to
introduce changes, you need to understand the state. Managing the
state of the system is not trivial. If you don't have native
state management, you'll have to implement it yourself. Second thing, it has
a big community and good docs. Why is
that important? Because when you
stumble upon any issue, if there isn't
a community there that you can get their assistant,
their assistance, and if you have no
good documentation of the issues,
so you'll find yourself solving problems,
that you'll have to
solve them yourself. So the more common a
tool is, the more popular a tool is, the more likely
you are to have solutions or common problems
somewhere. Okay, so that's the idea. Saves time.
Debugging stuff. Whats multiple interface types?
API cliui why is that? This is
because when you use a tool,
it's not the only thing you use. Probably, you're probably using other tools
as well. You might use some scripts to glue stuff,
you might write service cto glue stuff,
you might do all sorts of things. And having
a native interface that you don't have to hack around
in order to understand how it works and
integrate it in non native ways. So having official
APIs or having an
official CLI, having a UI, having all
of those interfaces, makes it easy to integrate
the different parts of the system, which is something you are
most likely going to do. So as
multiple interfaces. So these are the biggest time servers.
Okay, so next up is set useful
goals. What do I mean by set useful goals? I mean
you want to do
DevOps. And of course we gave some abstract
definitions, we gave some practical definitions we
discussed some very practical things, right. But now
what should your goal be? There are some goals
that are derived from the previous things we discussed,
and I'm not going to cover all of these,
but let's take two examples. So one
click environments. So earlier we said software
engineering is a science discipline,
it's a scientific discipline, meaning in order to
understand if your system works or if it
works as expected, you perform a
test, you run an experiment. So one
click environment is something that says, it's a goal that says let's be
able to, we want the ability to create an
entire environment of the system with one click,
run, keypress, you name it. So in some
companies it could be Jenkins pipeline that
creates everything, in other companies,
something else, maybe a script that someone is able
to run. The idea is I want an entire
environment in order to run an experiment in order to introduce a
change to the system. Okay, so another
goal, let's take this example. So split shared and end
specific resources deployment. What does that mean?
So as your company scales up,
let's say you want to run an end to end test on every pull
request. So when your company scales
up, this becomes difficult. Why does it become difficult?
Because deploying an entire environment
is one, it costs a lot as
your company scales, of course. And two,
it might take a lot of time. So let's say
if you create a database, every time you deploy a
new environment, this one click environment. So this
takes time, it takes budget.
So the idea here is let's split
the shared resources.
What could the shared resources be? Database,
the network. Let's say
everything is running on Kubernetes cluster. So the
Kubernetes cluster and the NF specific
resources. So what's the NF specific resources?
That's the application.
Maybe a migration that you can run in order
to create a new database within your
database instance. So the idea here
is when you deploy a new environment, you only deploy the end
specific resources, the shared just
underlying infrastructure that stays there, you deploy
on top of it. So just
to name a few. So atomic commits
and automating local dev to production.
I can elaborate on that.
I'm not going to do it now, just save you some time.
But feel free to reach out and ask me about
it. What does it mean? I'll be available Twitter,
LinkedIn discord.
So I'll be happy to answer
any questions about that. So let's
do some examples. So when to do what? So when
you walk alone and the system is simple,
so you should simplify development. So dockerizing
your application doing some post commit test.
The idea is don't complicate things, just keep it
simple and make it easier for you
to work and introduce changes into the system.
And yeah, I see many
founders this stage writing telephone code and
wondering why. Maybe in some cases it's
justified, but most cases not sure.
So you need new ends quickly for devs,
for clients. Let's say you have a new client, they want a new environment.
If you are b two b startups startup,
maybe it's a hospital and they want it on their
own cloud account for compliance reasons or
whatever. Or maybe it's for developers, they want to
test changes separately. So this is
probably when you want to implement a one click environment. When you have
this demand from developers and clients,
end to end tests become hard. There are
many code changes. So let's say you used to
create an entire environment on pull request
and run an end to end test,
and now it hurts. Now you
have, let's say 30 open pull requests
at any given moment. So if you
deploy a Kubernetes cluster per pull request, of course that's very expensive,
very painful, very slow. So split
your one click environment into shared and
specific resources. So that's the example I gave earlier.
Now your system's complexity increases and
you need to standardize how you operate it. Have a typo.
So that's probably when I
would say implement an orchestrator,
just something that's very useful to standardize different
processes. With something
like kubernetes, there are more when to do what
use cases, and it's all in the
full handbook. Again, you'll have a QR
at the end of the presentation. You can go into
the handbook and see everything there. And again,
feel free to ask me anything. So regarding that
part, of course that's not necessarily the case,
but I'm just oversimplifying it to
sort of get the point across. Let's do
a quick recap. So this is the full CTO
DevOps handbook. You can scan the QR and get to the
original blog post to do a quick recap.
Devs operate. DevOps enable and operate.
You have to choose a balance. The balance is between
an enabler, a doer, and an automator.
I had a nice phrase that
sort of encapsulates this balance.
The phrase goes like this. It's called other phrase,
it's a term, it's called automation. Automation is
sort of choosing the balance between these three goals
are leveraged, use them wisely.
Tools can be a huge time saver. They can
also slow down your operation to
such an extent where it's detrimental for
it. Set useful goals.
So if you want to be able to words,
you have to have goals to work towards
when it comes CTO DevOps there are very useful goals that
you can set and that of course,
they depend on your roadmap, your company's requirements
and so on. So set useful goals.
We mentioned the one click environment, the splitting,
shared and specific resources. And the last
thing is, know when to do what.
Again, there are some more examples over the handbook.
I think that's it. If you want to ask me
anything, you can go
over Twitter. That's my handle. Feel free to
follow and send me a message. And you can also
use this QR code to reach out
to me on LinkedIn. Just say something that starts with,
I was over your talk, I have a question or
I have a note. I know that you came
from here and.
Yeah, I guess that's it.
It was a pleasure giving this talk. I hope I didn't miss
out on anything important. And yeah,
looking forward to hearing from you guys.
Cheers.