Hi, my name is Roman Zhukov and I am from intel. Today we
are going to talk about how to fit SeC into DevOps,
probably without security team. Let me start with a mandatory
disclaimer. Sorry about that guys. Today I'd like to
express my own opinion and my own experience that doesn't necessarily
reflect the official views or opinions of my employer. So I'm
going to just share with you some public examples and cases.
So there is neither confidential information today nor marketing
stuff, only practice. So some
links and names on my slides may seem small, but don't mind it
please. Everything is clickable. My plan is to share slides with organizers
so that you can follow them offline, if you would,
and without any further delay.
Here we go. Let me introduce myself
real quick. I am practices cybersecurity expert
with more than twelve years experience with
the most recent area of my interest in product security and
broader end to end secure development lifecycle
well known as SDL or SDLC.
Formerly I also brought to market new cybersecurity products services,
manage complex security projects, consult firms
like banks, telcos, retail, you name it.
Also, I conduct classes at universities
and private centers. In my spare time I do volleyball.
I'm fond of hiking, running bikes,
swimming, and basically of every single sport
that is easily feasible.
Okay, not for advertising purposes,
but satisfying everybody's curiosity. Probably you
might think why the silicon company talks not only
about hardware, right? Intel and software.
What is all about? Intel actually
DevOps a lot of different proprietary and open source software
products, including actually industry pioneering
confidential computing products like SGX,
Project Amber and ET cetera.
Also we are providing some, as I mentioned,
open source stuff, even in security space.
And I will share with you along with
other open software. So what we do and
what we share with community, actually, maybe you
don't know, but intel over the five
or more years top four contributors to open source
according to open source contributor index. So along with
other respectful companies. So we know how to
do software, we are consuming software, we are running of
course our own devsecops practices. So that's why
we can talk about that.
Okay, let's start with myths breaking.
Actually, I believe if you're for
example, an RND or it professional or SRE or DevOps
engineer, right? You may likely face some concerns about
security or
even struggle with your own company centralized security
team, right? And you know what?
I can't blame you guys for that, because let's say classic
or traditional security approach doesn't really fit well
to software development, to development
departments or it specific companies
that's true. Let's admit it. In all of these areas,
baking security into DevOps actually can
help. Let's see, five myths
as you can see on this slide, right? Security team and their tools
are aliens for RND. I think that
is maybe clear for some of us.
RND has their own KPI, right?
And I heard a lot over
my practices about how can we establish these trade offs
between security and feature development,
et cetera. We don't need to do that. We are going
to make the robust and best quality
products in the world. So this is all connected, no trade offs,
no conflicts. Of course, if you do it properly,
it is yet another vulnerability, right? Why should
I care about that? Nobody will
exploit that. It's not going to work. It's yet
another myth. I mean, the fourth one, security doesn't contain
good metrics or clear value or clear benefits.
It's not true. If you do right security and
you fit SEC into your development and DevOps practices
correctly, so you are going to take these benefits. And the
last one, my lower one, security is boring and unnoticeable
for everybody. It's not truth. Again,
security is really exciting, even for,
let's say, ordinary engineers, not security guys,
because the right security, the proper security is
mostly about the technology, right? Of course it contains
some compliance part, but it's also about technology,
about inventing new things. Please leave me.
Today I'm going to provide you with four, remember this number
with four practical recommendations that could probably close 80%
real could security problems related to development.
Let's talk about benefits,
actually what SAc in DevOps protests and modern development
practices can bring to the business.
This is definitely increasing time to market faster
development. So security, along with all other DevOps
practices, speed up development. It's scaling,
definitely without properly including seC. It also
will be the burden will be the only compliance, and it's not scalable
flexibility.
I will bring you the one example about flexibility a
little bit later. Transparency.
If you automate everything, if you have clear metrics and all this
stuff, it will be transparent and predictable.
And of course it's bringing trust and
positive brand appeal and et cetera. If you are doing
the good practices,
if you support security.
The only one example, I have a lot of examples, but in the sake of
time, I will bring you the only one example of real value of
fitting security into the modern development.
Let's bring up the case study. I think this is kind of common practice
and this is only one story, but we experience a
lot of the similar story, right? The community
unexpectedly discovered a critical vulnerability and extremely
popular third party, right?
Do remember lock for shell. Please rise your hands.
Of course we remember this story. And if
you are actually without DevOps, without security,
properly integrated and automated,
it takes you three days only for inventory.
If you're medium or big company, it's really changing,
right? To understand whether you really have
this lock for j
companies, right? And whether you're affected one week for auto
cycle release, probably if you're a software company or for
updating all your systems, because actually it's
not so one time if you
don't have security in your DevOps practices,
additional surprise, you can find other third practices living
for years in your code, right?
That's a big deal. But with security,
please pay attention at the right side of the slide. With security in
DevOps, it's simple, thanks to implemented
continuous security, right, we understand
all our components so that we store logs,
we can really quickly understand where
we are affected, right? And probably even if we are big
company, we're spending two to three days for out of cycle release
for our software or for our services or whatever. Thanks to
automation, thanks to SEC, properly integrated into
the DevOps, that's a real practice,
real example of benefits that
security can bring up to your business.
The most popular security box guys, this is a
barely fresh statistic this year from
the wear code. Don't really
dig into the graphics, but I just prepared
for you the outcome of this statistic that show
top four most popular security bugs.
I mean, they probably have
been changing a little bit over the year, but anyway, this is again,
buffer overflow. Underflow. We have been talking about that
for over the years, over decades,
maybe error and input handling, crypto implementation.
All of this stuff appears, and appears as a bug, as a security
problems that could lead to the real breaches, that could lead to the
lose of the reputation and et cetera. So SEC
into DevOps can help solve these problems.
How we are going to do that in practice,
right. The first advice,
of course, to build up the full SDL
or SDLC security development lifecycle. All this stuff,
this is heavyweight, but if you're big or
even the medium company, probably you must do that.
For example, modern companies, the industry leaders
like intel, build up their heavyweight systems.
And I encourage you to take a
look at the white paper, which is free, which is accessible supply chain
threats made by senior engineers from intel.
So there's a lot of considerations, including actually DevOps
considerations and practice and recommendations.
You can do that by following the
standards, by following the industry leaders.
It's of course the first thing that comes to
your mind. But remember our topic,
to build security and
security into the DevOps without security team.
So this is probably heavyweight. Still good practice,
but heavyweight because usually when we
start to think about security,
you guys as a developers,
as engineers, not really 100% security
professionals may think, well,
it take me, I don't know, years to
integrate all these practices. I like this diagram
by accelera because it's representing or
summarizing the common 17 devsecops
controls that you may need to implement
to build the, let's say true heavyweight devsecops
process and everything. But the
thing is that small and even medium companies, for example,
often don't have time or resources to do that,
right? To implement all of that stuff.
So I really encourage you to take a look at the
points that really matters. And from my opinion that could
you help to solve up to 18%
of all security related problems or your security
related stuff in your development cycle.
On your flexible development process, you might
ask what to do first, right? With the most valuable quick
wins. That's why let's have a look at the practical recommendations
that doesn't require actually a security team. At the nutshell,
of course, it's good to have fully dedicated security professionals,
but you can implement,
at least at the certain level, these four recommendations without
security team. And you remember what I promised
you, four recommendations, but I lied a little bit.
Sorry about that. Actually it will be
four and plus two bonuses.
In summary, six recommendations.
Let's take an example, the GitHub.
Let's turn back for a sec. These four recommendations
will relate to static analysis, to software
composition analysis, to roles and secrets, and to vulnerabilities
scanning. Again, I pose that
that is very important, at least if
you are starting, because everything else could
follow, right? Okay, let's return to the examples.
These four areas could and should be
covered primarily by your native
development tools that you're really utilizing.
I have been talking over and over again,
like don't try to buy and to
implement a lot of security tools, a lot of security stuff,
of course, that's good. But first of all, please take a look
at the native tools that you probably already have,
right? If you're using GitHub, if you're using GitLab
or other great development
tools, please pay attention to its native
security features. I bring up the GitHub
not for advertising, just for an example. Again,
GitLab and other stuff. They include
their own security embedded features that you're going to use
first, instead of trying to implement something alien,
right? For stack analysis, GitHub has Codeql.
For SCA, it has dependable which is basically a
free and open source renovate bot. This is a
great stuff for checking and automatically updating your
dependencies. For secret scanning, this is yet
another embedded feature and for vulnerability scanning as well.
Part of that is free, especially for open
source. For your open source project, if you are developing
closed source proprietary some
of these features, you need to buy the subscription.
But again, please pay attention to embedded features because
it will save you a lot of time not to try to implement
something external. But firstly pay attention to embedded stuff
that could be done without security team,
especially stuff like dependable stuff like secret
scanning and everything else. I mean
that's simple. That's really simple. I haven't experienced to turn
it on by the small companies
and that cost nothing. I mean in terms of resources.
Another example about open source and free tools. If you
want to leverage not only your
development environment and devsecops
tools, you can use external tools.
But there are a lot of open source stuff that I share with you right
now. Please take it and use it.
I put the asterisks here because
not of this tool is free for everybody and for every case and for
every programming language, but it's still kind of
free for something. For example, Bandit, right? This is
a native tool for scanning Python and this is free.
This is not really static analysis tools, rather scanning for security
practices. But anyway, this is native for languages.
And when you're going to choose static analysis tools to
scan your source code for insecure functions
for all this stuff, I would suggest you to use
the tools that's specifically designed for languages.
I mean even, especially if you are looking for
open source bandit, this is for Python, for example,
rips, this is for PHP, samegraph, it's good for C
sharp, go Java and eT are of course
there are a lot of tools that,
let's say support multilanguage,
but some of them good with only
specific languages. And this is great. I mean, one size
doesn't fit. All right, for software composition
analysis, the blue square on
your screen, there are a lot of great proprietary
tools, but you can use the free stuff. You can use open source stuff.
For example, dependency check dependency track is
fully free for understanding
your bomb software, bullets of materials and
vulnerabilities of your third practices that you're consuming,
that you're integrating to your code for binary
tools. Actually there are lack
of good tools, but we at intel
internally build the CVE binary tool.
CVE checking for CV and we have open sourced
that. Please feel free to use that for secret
scanning. It's also not a big deal. So you can use Gitgarden,
which is proprietary but still have a free plan for
somebody it fits. Git leaks whispers this is free.
Please, you use some special stuff for secret management.
Again, this is all either open source or free.
You can easily integrate that. And again,
I intentionally brought up all of these tools because they're
really easy to be integrated into
your development processes without, let's say,
a lot of specific security knowledge. Again, it's really good
to have security team and to use their experience. But if you don't
have any, these tools could be integrated
because the most of them are really development
centric, not security centric for
vulnerability scanning. Of course we have a lot of free stuff.
It depends on what you're really looking for in terms
of vulnerabilities. But there are a lot of tools still
available, even for free. Okay,
let's switch to the first bonus. This is for
containers and kubernetes. Again, this is small
text on the slide, but it's all clickable so you can follow
the links and check it out offline.
Pretty much everything that we as a developers
build up, guys we offer as a containers,
right? Or even we build our infrastructure based on
containers and use some kind of steering
stuff like kubernetes or Openshift
or whatever. So there are four key
messages I wanted to deliver to you. Don't forget, of course, to secure
your container on Kubernetes stuff. The left side of the slide represents
the answer to the question, what could possibly go wrong in
the container world? A lot of stuff could wrong,
right? Escape from containers, leakages,
escalation of privileges. There are a lot of real
world examples. I don't have time to show all the real
world examples. And it's happened again and again. You know, every single
year we see some major breach,
for example, or data leakage or attack
or whatever, or ransomware even, right? Because of
breaching container stuff. So first of all,
select image responsibly, right?
It's really crucial to understand
what base operation system image you're
going to use. Please pay attention and scrutinize
and figure that out. That probably
it would make sense to use scratch
or barely scratch the operation system,
distros, busybox or whatever.
The second advice is utilize all, of course best practices
when your code, when you write
up your docker files, your configurations use official
docker security guidance, use OASP cheap sheet, for example,
when building containers from docker files, right?
Run scanning tools and intel
tools like headerlint for example, or Trevor or Taber,
which could help you to understand your
configurations. And this is really good, these tools.
I'm going to share you that these tools are used
by the major companies even because as the developers
even we are really professionals,
we don't have enough bandwidth, right? And physical ability to
understand, to figure out all our code,
all our mistakes. Please use this automation.
Again, our today's talk is about how to integrate
SEC into DevOps.
Everything that I'm sharing today is
easily integrated, is easily automated. Each single
tool that's on my slide.
So could be automation inside your pipeline,
right? The next one verify secrets. That is
clear. A lot of examples how secrets
could squeeze into the yaml files container images
through the different layers and then could be exposed to the
public. Tokens, internal information,
passwords, et cetera. Please pay automation to that. And the last
one about containers. Consider runtime security when
you are running your Kubernetes clusters, right?
Use official Kubernetes security guides or openshift security
guides or ranger security guides, right? Depends on
what system are you using. There are
a lot of hardening guides provided by
state, for example NSA or CISA best
practices or whatever. Please do not hesitate
to implement the
policy agent, the service mesh
and everything that already exists
by nature in kubernetes could and
the last one, guys, I wanted to share,
bonus number two, make all artifacts trusted.
That is something that's advanced.
I can say you are going
to do that at the very beginning when you're just thinking
about setting up your devsec ops
environments, right? It's for more major companies. But I
have to mention that because all of these supply chain
problems that we have, really hard companies
around the world, hard customers and users
and et cetera. So what is Salsa? Salsa is
an open framework that help you to understand and justify
originality of every artifact on each
development stage from intake or make source
to build and release, right? And to
achieve that. So basically you need to keep so
called provenance as an example.
At the right side of this slide you can see this
provenance, what is it? It's metadata or
full history about how an artifact was produced at
each stage. The idea is pretty much simple,
right? Keep along with all your artifacts,
all your binaries, all your configurations, all your
stuff that you're producing during your development lifecycle,
from intaking third parties through development,
through packaging, to delivering
your products to the customer or to the world,
keeping the information, the history,
the origination information of all this,
how, when and why and by whom this
artifact was built. So this
is what provenance is
about. Basically the idea is simple implementation
is maybe more hard,
but anyway it's kind of not so big deal as
well.
It's open framework, you can easily find it
by the link and basically achieving salsa level two
level of maturity. It's not a big deal because that means
that for source code you have your version controlled.
Basically, I believe even for small companies you control
your versions, right? So it's just you have these vcs
systems and et cetera for build stuff,
scripted build and build service exist and is in place.
So basically you are not built manually,
right? You have a build system, you have artifactory,
Jenkins or whatever, all these tools in place and all
this automated. And you have all these YAML configurations,
you can check these configurations, everything is under control.
So this is what's all about. And the last one is provenance,
right? This metadata that
you store, you keep with all your artifacts,
it is available, right, for checking.
Provenance is authenticated and
service generated, basically generating automatically.
You of course can and could automatic provenance creation using
Salsa GitHub actions, for example, if you are using GitHub
or easily integrate these tools to your existing
CI CD tools. If you are not using GitHub, for example, if you use Jenkins,
Travis CI or whatever, it's not a problem. You can
integrate into these systems.
That's another great tool, insertoid station tool. You can
attest that and use cosine for generating and verifying
signatures of that stuff. Again, this is kind
of framework and more the idea
that you can take and use and think
about that again, this is idea is pretty trivial.
But if you start to do that,
there will be more trust to your artifacts,
even by yourselves and by your partners, of course your
customers or whatever. And again, that is
all automatable. That's why I bring
it up and would like to pay your attention to this
stuff. It all could be integrated into your DevOps
CI CD pipeline easily and that
helps you to fit sac really easily
to your DevOps practices. To have the full devsecops.
And actually sometimes without really security team.
That's basically pretty much it. I wanted to talk about today.
I hope you learned something useful. Got an idea?
Please do not hesitate to follow all the link and reference I share. That's all
free. And please reach out to me in case if
you have any questions. That was my pleasure folks.
Please enjoy the rest of your day and take
care.