Imagine us. It's Monday, the last sprint
of a project you just had planning. You agreed
with your team that you need to fix two bags, you need to write the
documentation, and you're basically ready to release th
you feel good, you feel motivated, excited,
excited for the release. You've worked so hard.
You're excited for the future and new project that's coming.
It's Monday, but you feel great. You feel that what
you planned with your team is achievable.
So let's just do it on Tuesday,
engineering manager comes to the room and she says,
look, I think it would be good if we run this through
the security just before the release.
And in this case, it would be great, means we
must do it. So you go to the meeting with a
security team, and they ask you tons
of questions, and they look at documentation that
hasn't been finished yet.
And after the meeting,
you end up with a whole bunch of
bugs to fix. And if
you ask me, I also have no idea what a snail is doing
among all of these other bugs. Snails are not bugs.
Right? I've been in this situation
way too many times. Way too many times.
And every project, we would have this lovely
meeting called project retrospective. Do you know this meeting?
And we would be like, oh, you know what? Having security
review at the last sprint of the project,
it's not good. It's stressful. It adds work.
We don't want to do it this way. And the moment,
trust me, the moment the meeting ended
and we closed the door of this
meeting room, we would all
forget. But it. And this
review, security review in the last sprint would
hunt it over and over and over again.
I mean, it would hunt us over and over and over again. To put
things a bit into perspective, my name is Wiktoria Dalach.
I was born in Krakow, Poland, but I'm based in Berlin,
Germany, and I've spent the last decade
building software. Two years ago,
I decided to switch the perspective and
join the security team. And it was great opportunity
for me to see how organization works from
different perspectives, because when I was an engineer,
software engineer would go to the meeting with other engineering
team and other engineering managers, and we
would be peers. We would be like, yeah, let's build it, let's improve it.
Let's do something, whatever this
something was. But when I started working
as a security engineer and I started saying, oh,
this is what is important,
I got pushback. I was like, I was not a peer anymore.
I was another stakeholder. So I
realized that there are some low hanging fruit
like things that you need to pay attention to in order to
create good, secure products. And today
I'm sharing those with you. All the notes from this talk
are available under this link. So no stress about taking
notes or something. We can just enjoy
our one on one conference experience. So first of all,
pay attention to access control. You cannot grant
admin access to everything
and you cannot give it as a freebies.
No, you need to be very careful how
you structure the access control and what
kind of resources people have access to. And look,
this is very difficult for us engineers
because we are like, oh, but we want to see
this feature. We develop some feature,
why can't I access it on
production with my customers data? Right,
you can get the pushback like that. But please be
very strict with the access control.
The role structure in this access control will
not necessarily match the structure of your organization.
Pay attention to that. Even if you are a
senior software engineer, you don't necessarily have to have access
to everything. Even if someone is the CEO of company,
they don't have to access all of their AWS
instances. For example, pay attention to that.
When you are embracing the cloud
native and cloud architecture,
you probably deal with a lot of services,
services that microservices that talk to each other.
And here's the thing, I've heard so
many times that oh, this is an internal service,
we don't need a special authorization for it because,
well, only we know about this
address. This is not true.
This is actually the easiest way to cause a data
breach. So secure your API, secure the connection
between your services and again restrict
the access. Make sure that authorization is
in place. Low hanging fruit,
but super important misconfiguration hurts
if you use defaults. If you
store credentials as a plain text, it's a horrible
threat to security of your product.
So educate yourself. Like search
for the best practices, update your servers,
make sure that if attacker comes to the
system and breaks into your server, for example,
they cannot just read their credentials
for the admin account in plain text. Educate yourself,
read the best practices and follow them. Sometimes it
can be annoying because maybe no one will check it,
but don't overlook it.
Misconfiguration is one of the biggest security
threat for your product. The good thing is that you don't
have to do all of this alone. Lent machines
work for, I mean apps that can
scan your system. So the most popular
solutions are SAS and dust.
Dust is dynamic application security testing
tool and it means that it's
an application that works with
your front end, your web application, and it just
sends malicious input, malicious data there
and sees the response. And if the response is, well,
bad, then it will inform you, alert you about it.
The other type of application
security testing tools is SAS. SaFt is static
application security testing tool.
So the thing is that instead
of dealing with your web
app, SAS tool just goes
into your code base and scans it. So it's
very handy when you're developing things because you can integrate SAS
into your pr, for example, into your workflow.
And every time you
add something new, the SAS tool will run analysis
and tell you, whoa, wait a minute. You just
created a potential SQL injection or misconfiguration.
It is worth implementing, especially if you are
growing organization. If you're a small startup, then maybe,
well, you need to navigate between speed
and security. I understand that. But if you are
already in a growing organization, the sooner you
implement those tools, the better,
because the culture of your organization
will grow with the security in mind, which is
very difficult to implement later. And now
I would like to share something that absolutely blew my
mind when I became my transition
from software engineer to security engineer.
The problem with security is that from
the product team perspective, the product
people. So designers, product managers treat security solely
as an engineering problem. And engineers are
so focused on delivery and on
scoping their mvps that
security features are very often put on
the shelf called nice to have.
The other problem with security is security is an
ocean. It's a vast topic. You have application
security, infrastructure security, cloud security, you have it
security. You have human security. In application
security, you can think, but threats, you can think about vulnerabilities.
It's an ocean, and you're just one developer and
you should deliver secure product.
Right? This is overwhelming,
but I bring you hope.
And the hope is that
we all agree that when
we think about threats, when we think about the dangers for
your product, there is an infinite
amount of threats. It's like an ocean.
Like you cannot analyze enough and find
all of the attack vectors because it's such a dynamic
field. Like every week you get new vulnerabilities.
Every week you hear about a new data breach.
So there is an infinite
amount of threats.
But all
of those threats can be assigned
to one or three categories.
It is so amazing when you think about,
so this ocean,
this ocean, you can
assign to three categories, and these categories are
confidentiality, integrity, and availability,
which are called the CIA triad.
I could make a joke about spice right now,
but the only spice I like to think about are Spice Girls.
So I will skip it.
What it means the CIA triad it
means that you can put the whole ocean,
the whole ocean into three buckets.
Confidentiality, integrity, availability.
The whole ocean and three buckets.
That's amazing. Before I
jump into how to do it,
let's establish what confidentiality,
integrity and availability mean.
Confidentiality means that we want secrets to
be secret. If we are exchanging emails,
I want only you and me to be able to read those
emails. Integrity means
that we get what we expect. When you log in to
your Instagram account, you want to see all of the posts, all of
the followers, all of the following, right? If suddenly
you log in and suddenly everything is wiped out,
that would be suspicious.
Integrity. We get what we expect.
Availability means that we can always access the
information. You can send me an email
right now. You can send me an email in 10 hours,
like during the night. It doesn't matter. You always have access
to your emailing system and you can send an email.
How is it helpful? How is it helpful?
Why am I talking about it?
This is helpful because instead
of approaching the ocean, when you're thinking
about your security, instead of being confused
and looking, oh, should I make sure that this vulnerability
is fixed so we don't introduce this vulnerability or that vulnerability?
Instead of that, instead of
looking at security as an ocean, you can use
the question. The question which
is, how can the CAI of this thing be broken?
Now, I would like you to think, but the project you are working on right
now, and you got it,
you can ask the CIA question for it, how can the CAI
of the project you're
working on be broken? And it changes completely the
way you can approach security. Because instead of being like,
oh my God, I don't know what to think about you look at
the thing that you're building and based
on your building on what you're building, you're asking the question,
it is amazing because
it will work for you. Whatever technology you
use, whether you're
front end, back end, cloud,
no cloud, whether you're, I don't
know, junior me, senior staff director,
product manager, designer. You can always ask
this question. And of course, based on what
you are working on, it won't be just one question.
You will ask questions for each of the categories for confidentiality,
integrity and availability.
For confidentiality, you can ask, who can
see this resource? This is the most basic question.
How do we store credentials?
Do we use default credentials or
credentials? Easy to guess. What do we stored in the logs?
Integrity? Who can create, update and delete a
resource? Is there any way that
a malicious actor sends us malicious code or
malicious data? Via form. Like what happens then?
Is there any way to see a malicious actor
just deleting all the resources of our customer?
Is there a way to prevent that availability?
Of course, the most obvious question
is like is this endpoint rate limited?
But also as developers, we introduce so
many dependencies between our systems. So what happens
when a product that we rely on is down?
Does it mean that the whole product is down or some capabilities
are limited? Asking CI questions
will help you design with security
in mind. And the
question is when should you do it? Like you know what to
do, you know that you should ask the question, but when should
you do it? I cannot tell you
about it without telling you about shifting security left. Shifting security
left is this new approach to security when we
look at the SDL fee. So software development
lifecycle, it is lifecycle if it's a circle of life.
But here's the problem. I don't know about you, but from
my decade experience of developing
software, this is never a cycle. But from my experience,
usually software development timeline
happens. So instead of going around,
going round, you just go analyze, design, develop, test,
maintain, release, basically, and you move
on to a next project. So shifting security left looks at it
and says, well look, remember the story I told you at the beginning,
like when we had security review in the last,
basically last sprint of the
project, shifting security left is
like, no, we ain't going to do it. This is not a good approach.
Let's shift security left, which means let's shift security
to the basically design phase. And why
is it very powerful? Because when
you have code, when you already have design in place,
every change will be very expensive, every change will be
time consuming, every change will be stressful.
But if you design, if you
only have some sketches, then changing your
system is very easy because you just need to move
some lines. So shifting
security left and designing with
security in mind and for security will help you immensely
to build better software and to prevent you from much more
stress and costs. And here's the thing,
how do you implement the CI Triad in your organization?
So first of all, present it to your peers. You can send them this
presentation. You can just email me if you want. I can tell
your company about it. It's not a problem. I would love to help,
I would love more people to use it because it's so easy yet super
powerful. You discuss it with your team, you see
how can you fit in the CIA triad and those questions in
the design phase. And you make it a part
of your process, make it a part of your process
and make it visible. Which means, for example,
you look at templates of, I don't know, the documentation that
you need to write for each project. Maybe it's a solution.
Brief enhancement proposal, request for comments
and you add security section there. Exactly that.
Like how the
CIA of this can be broken. This is the question.
You can add more if you're nice, but basically
you inject security into your product development
process and
that's basically it. And it will help
you develop better solutions for your customers.
And look, there is no week
when we don't hear about a new breach,
about new security vulnerability.
We are in this moment, in this magical moment in history
when we as an industry need to agree
that the time of move fast and break things is over
and we held too much responsibility and
our products influence lives of
so many people that we need to take responsibility and we
need to create better, more secure software
and using the CIA triad. Any tips
that I share with you today is the right good step.
Enjoy the rest of the conference. Thank you
for listening to me and I hope this presentation
was helpful. If you have any comments or questions,
please reach out to me on LinkedIn. Thank you.