Hello everyone, welcome. Today we are going to talk
about tracking says with CDK and typescript.
I hope you discovered and seeing after this session honeycomb
CTO cart manager said observability isn't just
about knowing what's happening in your system right now.
It's about being able to ask any question
of persistent at end time. But let's
put it plainly, it's like having a crystal ball for your
software where you can summon answers to your burning
questions whenever curiosity strikes.
Hey system, why did you decide to take a cough
break during peak trap? What is with the hiccups
every time we deploy a new code? So to achieve it,
we are going to use CDK. So I'm going to give you
a brief smell about the benefits of
CDK. So what is CDK? CDK is a framework that
allows developers to define cloud infrastructure,
a YAAC basically like terraform,
using familiar programming languages like typeScript,
typescript, Python, Java and C sharp. Today we
are going to use typescript. Okay,
so basically what is the
benefits when using AWS CDK
you can abstract your cloudformation complexity.
You can use reuse and
share components. You can integrate everything with AWS
ecosystem because yeah, it was built
by AWS. Let's to
the star of the night star of the night is SES.
What is SES says is like
your digital postman. Ensure your
emails reach their destination safely and on
time. In the chaotic Internet world, it's your
superhero sidekick, managing your email,
saving them from the dead, red spam folder and
cyberspace fight, all while
wearing a virtual cape and mask. I hope so.
If you'll take a look here into this GiF,
you can have an idea about
the role of okay, so let's
go to how SES works. Says works
here in the first part. In the first one here,
we have sender. Then sender send
the email to the SES. In the first part here,
client application sends emails. So picture this.
Your client app feeling like a hotshot email sender
send a request says to whisk away your message
to its lucky recipients. In the second part
here says play the email fairy.
So says being the gracious host it is,
accepts the email with open arms. It's like
getting the golden chick to the email party.
In the 30 part here,
the great Internet, you would say. In fact, like the
SES takes your email by hand
and sends it flying through the Internet
at a lightning speed, like a digital superhero delivering
messages faster than a pizza on a Friday night.
Fourth one here they email destiny revealed,
in fact. So we have the receivers here.
And in the first scenario, for instance,
like three scenarios here,
the first one is inbox nirvana. The recipient's ICP
happily delivers your email straight to the inboxes
like a smooth entry into email paradise.
The second scenario, we can have the phantom email
like oops. Turns out the recipient's email address
is a ghost town. The ICP sends a bounce
notification back to SES like here informing
that it's a ghost and says
notification back to says, which turn gently breaks
the news to you. So bounce to the SES and then bounce again
to the center. The 30 scenario it's
the span saga. Your email arrives,
but oh no, it says demon, the black sheep of
the inbox and Mercad Aspen. The recipient
hits the panic button and complains to the ICP.
Says being the messenger of truth relays the complaint
back to you like a carry pinion with
some bad news. So it's a brief
explaining about the flow of Mayo Sandy
and you can take a look in more detail if you want in the
documentation. But the big picture is basically
this. So let's take a look on the
SAS components. SES components we have two
components basically here to explain this in a
summarized way.
So what is a verified identity? Well,
it's like having your name on the guest list.
It proves you are legit
and not just in email pressure trying to sneak into
the party. So whether it's
your domain, subdomain or email address,
getting verified is like getting the stamp of approval
for the email gods. From the email gods
you have also got these things called
configuration lets. Think of
them as your party playlist. There are ses of
rules you can apply to your verified identities to make
sure your emails hit all the right notes
with the congregation set you can fine tune how
emails behave and where they go. Want to
track who is opening your mails? Done. Need to
monitor boss ranks or complaints? Easy peasy.
Configuration set let you call the shots and
keep your email game on point. So next time you are sending
out those email invites or blasting out
your latest new latest newsletter,
remember, verified identities and configuration sets
are your backstage crew making sure your email
rock the box. Okay,
so let's go to our
common problems when using lets.
Basically we have two common problems to summarize
here. The biggest problem in my perspective is
the email deliverability issue because
we are trying to ensuring that email reach recipients
in box and avoid being mercury as span could
be challenging. Maintaining a good sender reputation,
adhering to email sending best
practices and regularly monitoring email
deliverability metrics are essential to mitigate
this issue and the second one is monitoring
SES metrics.
We have a lack of monitoring and reporting
because we don't have things made
directly by the AWS. So when
we are analyzing mayo delivery data,
we think it's a kind of essential thing for identifying
issues and optimizing email campaigns.
Users should regularly review bounce rates,
complaint rates and other metrics to improve email deliverability
and engagement. Like you are trying to
figure out how many people
clicked on your campaign about the new sneakers
that you released yesterday.
This kind of thing. You can improve your
product, for instance, and give
you more arguments and more
things to think when you are trying to create a
new product or trying to prove your
concept to the product
managers and something like that. Why should
I track it? Yeah, tracking salesmetrics is
a crucial because it's like having a dashboard for your
mayor campaigns. It lets you see
how your email perform, who is opening and
ignoring them and where they get lost in
the digital winderns. With this data,
you can fine tune your email strategies,
improve engagement and ensure your messages hit the
mark every time. It's like having a GPS
for email journey, helping you navigate the
twists and turns of the digital landscape with let's
understand a little bit about sesmetrics.
Says metrics play a crucial role in the email delivery
because this provide us insights
into the performance and healthy over Mayo campaigns.
These metrics help email senders understand how recipients
engage with their email and identify areas for improvement.
And here's why says metrics are significant.
I'm going to explain a little bit about
each metric so delivery hate the first
metric here is SES metrics
that track the delivery rate, indicating the percentage
of email successfully delivered to recipients in boxes.
High delivery rates ensure that emails
reach intended recipients and are not lost or
market as a spam. The open rate metrics
show the percentage of recipients hoping at the
email. A higher open rate suggests
that the email content is engaging and relevant to
recipients. The click through rate CTR
CTR metrics measure the percentage
of recipients who clicked on links within the email.
A higher CTR indicates that the email contains resolated
with recipients and encouraged to then to
take an action. Important thing when
you tracking to track your audience.
After that we have bounce rate. I explained a little bit before,
but bounce rate metrics track the percentage of emails that were
not delivered successfully due to various
reasons such as value email addresses or full inboxes.
High bounce rate may indicate issues with
email list, IGN or deliverability.
There are two types of bounce we have hard bounce.
Basically it's the email brick wall.
Imagine your email hitting a brick wall but
with few words instead of bricks. Yeah, that's a hard
bounce. It's like sending a letter to Hogwarts where
you are a Morgo and it's just not going to
happen. Soft bounce is the Mayo
trampoline. Picture this, your mayo hits a trampoline
side of brick wall. It's a soft bounce like
when you throw a ball too hard and it bounces back.
The mailbox might be full or the Internet might
be having a melted off. Then we have
complaint rate. Complaint rate metrics indicate the
percentage of recipients who market they email as
a spun or unwanted. A high complaint rate can
negatively impact sender reputation, so you need to.
After that we have the rendering
ferry, the hindering ferry.
It's like you have a template mail and you forgot
to send a parameter to the template
so it will give you
a handling failure. Basically,
overall sales metrics empower email senders to
monitor the effectiveness of their email campaigns
and identify areas of improvement and optimize
strategies to enhance deliverability and engagement
with recipients.
Let me show an example of metrics here.
Here we have some SES metrics like bounce,
click, compliance, delivery. Here welbe core
having great peaks of sending email
that was sent successfully. We don't have
a lot of opens here, so this
can give us an idea that welbe core
not having a good couch
to action emails. So this kind of thing
could help you and help your product managers
to understand your audience.
So let's hands on because
yeah, this talk we're going to get
our hands dirty. Here we have the code.
Let me give some zoom here.
I think it's better to read now.
Here we have basically an echoic structure.
I'm going to share with you GitHub this
structure about CDK and how you can configure that.
Here we have the class called email developability
that extends the stack. Stack is a part
of the construct. In there you
can create stacks of many kind
of resources and put everything together.
To start here we need to create a class
and the context is email availability to
be easier to achieve the names and IDs
for the resources. Here we have the register
event, but before the register event
we need to create our configuration set. So here
we create our config set, passing the sending
enabled that we are going to know
the configuration set name. Basically it's the
context name. We are setting the habitration metrics
because we are trying to know how
many emails was sent and this kind
of thing. So it's our objective
here, trying to understand the reputation metrics.
So we need to set this as true.
And it's a pretty easy way to configure
this. Here we are configuring the
event destination like SNS,
because here we have SNS topic.
In this SNS topic we receive all
our heputation metrics, like the sendings,
the rejects, the bounces. So if you want to
plug in a lambda to process all the information in
a different way like we have, this could
be your upstream resources upstream
event, and then you can give this to
your downstream system to process it as
you want. So you can
plug in metrics, another kind of thing
to log this, like for instance
data dog or any kind of thing you want.
If you want to send everything to the clogue watts logs,
you can basically do it using this.
And then we have here some clothes watt dimension.
Clogged watt dimension is where you can create
the dimensions to classify your metrics
like I showed before.
And you can open up the metrics and see everything
there. So you need to create some cloud watch dimensions to
metrify your sending
rate, your bounce rate, for instance. So here
we are going to add another event
destination, and this event destination needs
a cloud watch dimensions. So because of that we are creating these
cloud water dimensions here and using
these events, passing all events we are trying to
track. So the enable needs to
be true because yeah, we are trying to track it. After that
we have the creation of alarms.
So here I'm passing the top
because you have for instance,
top and it's like you want to receive some notifications
when everything crashes. So because of that we need
that topic. It's a different topic from the
another topic because the first topic we are trying to give
information for downstream systems. And here welbe care, trying to notify
our workforce,
our employees, like our DevOps guy,
or, I don't know, some person that
can act when
an alarm will be triggered.
So here we are creating alerts. So I'm passing the
top and events to alarm with threshold.
The threshold is basically when you want
to alarm it. Like when I have a bounce
rate, I want to alarm it, for instance. So it's basically metrid
by thresholds. So here we are passing
that. So it's a record string here.
So then we pass a list, I'm going
to pass a list and then create an alarm for each event,
like here. So we are creating a new alarm,
passing the metric, in fact, namespace of the metric,
the metric name the type of
statistic in fact we can use Sam, you can
use average, minimum,
maximum P 99 for instance.
And we have the evaluation period here,
the comparison operator if you want this
should be greater than only or greater than
or equal to the threshold that you are passing here.
We want to enable that actions and
here description and the creating missing data,
the treating disclosing data is when for instance
when you don't have any kind of data here,
you don't want to alert your workforce.
So yeah of that we need you to
pass away how you can want to treat missing
data here. Okay. And then you
are going to add alarm action you can use
like I told you for this example
we are going to choose topic to
notify our worker core.
But here you can basically trigger
a lambda for instance or you can use
another of action here like we
have a couple action fix here. You can pass the iron of
the action here as is the console.
We are going to register event because first
of all we provide the create alerts function
and the configuration set function and then we
have the register event to register everything
we are trying to achieve. For instance
here we have our topic. I don't know if you remember
yet but before I told you, you can
use l one, l two and l three constructs. Here it's
l three constructs. Basically here we are creating
a specific topic to handle all the
configuration lets configuration set event
destinations and here we have
this topic, this lack topic. I'm importing this
laptop. So because of that I have this import valley.
So let's picture this. You have an infrastructure
project and there you create
all your core resources like topic.
And after that we are going to call our
configuration lets that we created before passing
the mail delivery top. And here welbe core creating our
alarms, passing the slack top. It's your
notification top and with
the object of event, the event you want to tracking to
create alerts and it will show that you want to be notified
if this could be greater
than and as I explained in the preach
alarm. For instance like I'm passing here, if I
have one reject I'm going to
alarm my work. So basically is
this here. It's a quite simple way to
achieve it. But yeah
we have a lack of configuration
and a lack of observability because SAS
doesn't provide us a deep observability
into the system. Because of this I'm
trying to explain this is a discovered
it is an unsync. Whenever you are working with
SES you can have a lot of trouble trying to
figure out who received it and who clicked your emails.
Yeah, and I will tell you about a case
we had at OLB. We were trying to find
out how many people had received and
made about safety regulation and we
didn't have that visibility and so we
had to develop a way to understanding of understanding
our audience. And I think this is a crucial thing
that you want. That we want because
we need observability. We need to know the
whys of our system.
I think this is a brief way to
understand SAS and everything you can take
a look into the code. I'm going to share you.
I hope you enjoyed and learned a little
bit of SAS.
If you have any questions please lets me know.
Send me an email or you can find me at my
name is Marcos Henrique. If you have
some opinions and any feedback to share,
please read this care code.
I will enjoy your opinion because it
was my debut. Talk them will enjoy your
opinion so thank you.