Hi everyone, my name is Tabrez and I am part of the team
at Aviatrix that is implementing AI, machine learning and
generative AI initiatives. Aviatrix is a
multi cloud networking company dedicated to simplifying
cloud infrastructure management and security across major cloud providers
including AWS, Azure, GCP and Alibaba.
Trusted by over 500 enterprises worldwide,
Aviatrix offers a comprehensive platform that ensures
visibility, control and security, enabling businesses
to adapt quickly and move forward efficiently.
Today, I will be showcasing some of the innovative AI
and ML solutions we've developed to drive efficiency and transformation
within our organization. Let's dive into the detail.
The first initiative I am going to talk about is the network mission
briefs for customers. The mission brief integrates real
time customer insights from multiple sources,
providing a comprehensive 360 degree view of customers.
This initiative empowers the sales team with data driven decision making
capabilities, enabling them to close deals more efficiently
and maintain a competitive edge. By aggregating data
from various platforms, Aviatrix ensures that all relevant
customer information is easily accessible, enhancing the
overall customer engagement and support processes.
The mission briefs utilizes tools such as Coda for document
generation, copy AI for AI narratives, and xeno
data lake for data storage. We've generated over 500
mission briefs. This initiative has reduced our sales cycle
time by 30%, doubled data accessibility speed,
and achieved a 95% accuracy in insights,
significantly enhancing our sales team's effectiveness. The next
initiative is the lead scoring app. The app leverages
AI to streamline the lead qualification process by
matching leads with the ideal customer profile or ICP.
The app automates data retrieval from various sources and
assigns detailed lead scores based on multiple factors,
enhancing sales efficiency and precision.
By providing a comprehensive view of potential leads,
the app helps prioritize high value prospects, ensuring the
sales team can focus their efforts on the most promising opportunities.
Our lead scoring app leverages AI tools like copy AI
for content generation, coda for workflow automation,
and Salesforce for CRM. By integrating these
technologies, we score over 5000 leads monthly,
resulting in a 25% increase in lead conversion
and a 15% boost in sales productivity. The next initiative I'm
going to talk about is the AI powered customer support chatbot.
The chatbot utilizes AI and machine learning to autonomously
handle common customer inquiries and efficiently escalate complex issues.
To support teams operating through the Aviatrix support portal,
the chatbot integrates with the Zendesk ticketing system,
logs tickets automatically, and directs them to the relevant support
tier. This initiative significantly enhances the customer support
experience, ensuring timely and accurate responses to customer queries.
The chatbot utilizes copy AI for content automation,
intercom for real time chat, and Zendesk for ticket management.
By integrating these tools, we achieve 80%
automation of common inquiries, reduce response time by
60%, and decrease support tickets by 50%.
This tech stack significantly enhances our customer support efficiency and
effectiveness. The next featured initiative is implementation of
GitHub Copilot at Aviatrix. This initiative revolutionizes
code development by leveraging generative AI and
machine learning to assist developers. This AI powered
tool analyzes developers intents,
suggests improvements, automates tasks, and even writes code.
This initiative allows developers to focus on more complex aspects
of their projects while maintaining a high quality codebase. The GitHub
copilot leverages machine learning and generative AI for code completion
integrated with visual studio code. By utilizing machine
learning models for code analysis and suggestions,
and integrating with our CI CD pipeline, we've increased
development speed by 50%, boosted developer productivity
by 40%, and contributed 30,000
lines of code. This tech stack significantly enhances
our development efficiency. The last featured initiative
I would like to talk about is present AI. Present AI
transforms business communication by leveraging AI to create
engaging and effective presentations. This AI powered
platform significantly enhances productivity by automating
the creation of slides, ensuring brand compliance,
and facilitating visual storytelling.
By reducing the time spent on preparing presentations,
present AI allows employees to focus on delivering impactful
and interactive content tailored to the audience's needs.
Using present AI, we've achieved a 70% reduction in presentation
preparation time, a two x increase in presentation engagement
rates, and a 30% increase in content personalization.
This AI powered platform significantly enhances
our efficiency and impact in creating engaging, customized presentations.