You. Hello and thank
you for joining me for accessibility testing 101.
Few little disclaimers just to get out of the way.
I will mention some regulations in the
course of this talk, but I am not a
lawyer and thus am not. I don't feel comfortable
with consulting too in depth th on
individual regulations and how they might apply to you,
how you might meet them, that kind of thing.
Additionally, any views or opinions that are expressed by
me are not representative of my company,
necessarily my employers. They are mine.
So just kind of a little cya there.
Today we're going to be learning about what is accessibility?
Why make things accessible? How do we decide what
is accessible? Building accessibility test
plans and tools and resources that can help you along the way as
you work to make things more accessible.
So, first off, what is accessibility?
Simply put, accessibility is how well can someone access
your content, services, facilities,
regardless of whether or not they have a disability?
And then with disability we're going to
focus on it being a mismatch
between the person and their environment, whereby the environment
creates a barrier to them accessing
information, services, facilities, things of that nature,
and then assistive technology. Or you might also hear it referred to as
adaptive technology. This is just any kind of software
hardware that someone may use to help balance
out that mismatch a little bit and allow them to access
services and information more
easily. And then you may also see the numerom a
one one y, which a numero im is just when you swap out some
of the better in a word for numbers,
kind of like nerd speak in a way, and it's usually
the end result is representative of what the original word was or what it
meant. In this case, a eleven y means accessibility,
and it stands for the fact that the word accessibility starts
with the letter a, ends with the letter y, and has eleven
characters in between. And you'll often see it used, maybe kind
of an ode to sort of the nerdiness of numero nyMs,
you'll often see it used for digital accessibility in particular.
Now the following are just some different categories that you
can use to kind of help you begin to think about how
disabilities may impact someone's ability to access services,
how you might be creating barriers unintentionally.
These are not necessarily all inclusive. You'll sometimes see
people divide them up a little bit differently. Here I've got them
divided up based on types, time and visibility.
For types I have hearing. So like someone having
being hard of hearing, or being in an environment where maybe
auditory signals just aren't going to be
effective. We've got
vision, so it can be, of course, like sight loss
or being in an environment where visual stimuli
or signals are not going to be effective at communication
mobility. So someone could have be carrying a child in
their arms and thereby have limited mobility for the
time period that they're carrying the kid around. It could also be someone
who has a limb amputation,
a broken arm, someone who has
sprained their ankle, anything of like that nature could
technically be a mobility disability.
And then comprehension. This could be things from ADHD,
dyscalcula,
dyslexia. It could also be things like
if someone is in a state of panic, because think about it,
if you're panicking, you are not thinking as clearly as you
are when you're not panicking. This can be someone who has
ADHD, like myself.
Any of those kinds of things could technically count as comprehension.
For time, we're looking at how
long is the disability impacting, how frequently is it
impacting the person? So it could be temporary.
If I break my arm, ideally like
six weeks, maybe a couple of months, my arm is going to be
hopefully healed up and back to normal, for the most part situational.
This would be something where, like, for instance, the parent carrying around
the child, they're only impacted while they're holding the child,
and then once they set the child down, things are good.
It could be someone who has an anxiety disorder. There may only be certain
situations where their anxiety tends to peak,
certain things that cause them to get
worked up. Permanent would be things like
someone who has a limb amputation,
that the limb is gone, unless medical science
figures out a way to resolve that.
And so that's kind of a permanent disability.
Or if someone loses their sight because of a permanent
injury or birth defect, something like that, that's not
going to go away, most likely,
and then visibility visible versus invisible.
So just whether or not the disability is visually apparent
to outside perception,
for instance, someone who is blind,
it may not necessarily be visible to outsiders
that they are blind, or to what extent they are blind.
For instance, in some areas,
depending on the level of sight loss, someone may still be able
to drive a car. So it may not be readily apparent that
that person is blind.
Someone who has a mental health condition, you're not necessarily going to
realize it visually that there's something going on,
versus if you see someone in a wheelchair or
someone with the iconic white
cane or a service dog, it's a little bit more visually apparent
that, oh, there's a disability at play.
May not be 100% sure what all is
at play because there can be a combination. And that kind of is a
thing across all of these is you can see a lot of overlap. You can
see things that kind of vary
back and forth between whether or not they're visible, invisible, or what
types of disabilities, in terms of like hearing, vision, mobility,
comprehension, are impacted.
And also especially because a lot of disabilities,
they'll have comorbid or other conditions that
tend to happen with them. So, for instance, someone who
has adhd or autism, it's very common for them to have
other sensory impacting conditions.
Someone who has certain musculoskeletal
conditions, they may be more prone to having other
issues at play. So there's kind of a mesh
going on there.
So why make things accessible?
Well, simply put, by creating an experience where
people can all access the same information and services, we help
people. We help people make more
informed choices for themselves and their communities.
We help people feel more welcome, which can lead to
better employee and customer retention. In a business world,
we encourage diversity in our communities and workplaces because
we're making people feel more welcome. And this can in
turn lead to us being more innovative, because we have these
more diverse lived experiences.
So more chance that someone may have an experience
that helps them think of an idea to a
solution, to a problem that maybe no one else would have
had the forethought to think of. And then there's also
the fact that you won't miss out on the market because
that little added monetary incentive,
fortunately, sometimes it's kind of necessary.
I've actually got an article here that is linked a hidden market,
the purchasing power of working aged adults
with disabilities, by the American Institutes for Research.
It is very informative article. I really highly recommend
checking it out. They actually state in that
article that through research, it was estimated that
the total disposable income for US adults with disabilities
is about 490,000,000,000,
which is comparable to other significant market segments,
such as different racial segments and
other age segments. You can read more in the
article if you'd like. And it's also important to remember that
according to the CDC, it's about one
in four people that have a disability, and you tend
to see that number be fairly consistent around the globe.
So that can be potentially a huge number of people
that if you're not making things accessible, you could be missing out
on having those people as customers, because, I mean,
if you're not making things accessible, they're not going to feel like you
really want them as your customer. They're not going to have as good of an
experience. They're not going to want to be your customer.
They're not going to want to be an employee if you're not making them
feel welcome and allowing them to participate.
So how do we decide what is accessible?
There's kind of a mixed thing at play here.
It's a mixture of your own personal experience, because as
you build different experiences, different facilities,
sites, web applications, anything of that nature, you're going
to be able to see for
yourself kind of what impacts different experiences
have. You'll be able to get user feedback which is going to
feed into that experience and help you better
identify different issues that
might cause barriers.
That user feedback in particular is very
important because going back to the other slide,
the whole having a diverse array
of customers and employees, when you
have that greater diversity of employees and customers,
you're going to get more different lived experiences, because even
amongst people who have the same disability,
it may present different, they may have different
symptoms at play, they may have different comorbid conditions.
It just may impact them a little bit differently.
And so getting that wide array of user
feedback is really going to help with building your experience
and making it easier for you into the future to design
a more accessible experience. Additionally, we have guidelines that
we can use. Most notably is the different
worldwide web consortium, or w, three c guidelines
made by their web accessibility initiative.
The most known one, of course, amongst these is the Wikag
or the web content accessibility guidelines,
which is currently in version 2.1. And version 2.1
is what the majority of regulations around
the world are based off of. However, it is
important to note that when it comes to different guidelines
like wakag, these are starting points.
Even in the Wakag guidelines, if you read the sort
of the introduction portion of it, they very specifically
state that it's not going to capture every
experience. Again, just because people can have such
different presentations of different disabilities can
be impacted differently by different visual, auditory and
whatnot elements.
And so it's very good to like, you want to try to be
compliant with some of these guidelines, but don't be too strict
because otherwise you may miss out on opportunities to make things more
accessible. Some other w three C guidelines
are the ATAG, which is the authoring tool. Accessibility guidelines
basically deals with tools that you use to create content.
So like Visual studio,
Microsoft Word, Adobe Acrobat, things that you're using to
create digital content. There's the user agent
accessibility guidelines, or UAG. And this
is basically browsers, media players,
things that you would use to ingest or view
digital content. There's the accessible
rich Internet applications, or aria.
This is a technical specification used to help make
dynamic or interactive content in digital scenarios
more accessible. And then I've got another
one that I've got thrown in here that is not by the w three C,
it's actually by the US
government, a different portion of the US government whose name has
just eluded me. But it is the accessible electronic documents
community of practice. And this is basically just a set of guidelines
to help with creating more accessible documents,
presentations, spreadsheets,
pdfs, digital documents of that nature.
So very highly recommend checking that out. They've got some great
test plans and stuff that you can use to help with checking
whether or not those kinds of things are accessible. And then
of course there's regulations. That's the part that a lot of
companies are incredibly worried about, because obviously
you break a regulation, you open yourself up to lawsuits,
fines, things of that nature.
I will say that whole idea of getting sued for
breaking accessibility regulations, yes,
there are the people who do the drive by lawsuits, but the
majority of the time when you see lawsuits for accessibility issues,
it's because people have reached out, they've tried
to get things fixed and not
been successful, and so then they resort to a lawsuit to
try to force the company's hands.
So just keep that in mind. I think
that's important to keep in mind that you
can encourage your users to reach out and you can
work with them to make a more accessible experience before you
ever have to worry about getting sued. If you are actually listening
to user feedback. Some common one regulations
now I primarily deal with like north american regulations
just because of my location.
So the Americans with Disabilities act, or ADA
section 508 of the Rehabilitation act of 1973,
the Accessibility for Ontarians act, or AODA,
which is a Canada regulation.
And then if you want to learn more, the w three C under their web
accessibility initiative actually has a page entitled
Web Accessibility laws and policies. It's not always
guaranteed to be up to date, and it's not going to be all
inclusive, but it will give you a good
starting point for looking up different regulations based on particular
parts of the world. So how do we go
about really building our test plans, coming up with
how we're going to create accessible content?
Well, the big thing is shift left.
You've probably heard this before. If you've done any kind of software development,
it can really be applied though to any kind of
effort that you're making in a company, whether it be
designing and deciding upon how to create a new facility,
creating documents, a marketing strategy, anything like
that. The shift left ideology really can benefit
you with accessibility, and it's just the idea of including
accessibility as early in the process, as early
in the discussions, the designing, all of that as possible.
So that way you're more likely to catch
potential issues early on when it's a
little bit easier to make sure that you do
things correct and in
the best way possible, versus waiting until the
very end when things are about to go to production or already are
just out in the wild and testing it
and being like, oh wait, it's broken now
we got to go back and potentially redo a whole lot that we
didn't have to do. And that's also like the
whole waiting until the last minute. That's kind of why there's the
whole myth that accessibility is expensive.
Usually it's not accessibility itself that's expensive.
It's the fact that people wait until the very end,
find out that they've made a huge blunder,
and then they're having to go back and redo everything.
And you'll see that if you're designing anything
that can be a problem. If you don't bother
to have users test something until it's already out in production
and you're getting complaints, it's obviously going to be a lot more expensive
to fix any issues than it would have been had there
been testing and discussions earlier on to catch those
potential issues.
Having a good, healthy balance of manual testing and
automated, I know people want to go automated,
so there's less work, hopefully, and less
repetitive tasks, less human error, that kind of
thing. But with accessibility, you really want to have a
nice, healthy balance because automated testing,
I think the last number I saw was
something in the 30% to 37%
range somewhere in there of accessibility issues that
could be captured by automated testing. And also
because if you just depend on automated testing, you can have a site
that's absolutely inaccessible, that completely passes automated tests
with flying colors if people do things
the wrong way. Right? If that
makes sense, I've actually got an
example that you can see. I've got a GitHub repo that I'll
have shared at the end of this presentation, and I actually have a good
site example and a bad site example, and they both look
identical. And if you run the automated tests on
them both, they are absolutely just,
they pass with flying colors, even though one is atrocious
when it comes to navigating it with any kind of assistive
technology or just in general compared to the
other. So again, having a
healthy balance of manual and automated, then there's this.
You may hear the term nothing without us used in the accessibility community
a lot. And this is the idea of include
people who actually are living with disabilities as
early as possible. Kind of combine that with the shift left to
include those people in the discussion early on.
And this is also where that whole diverse customer
and employee base can come in handy. Because again,
you can have three or four people that have the same quote
unquote disability who present very
differently. So you want to try to include a good
array, like a good diversity of individuals
with lived disability experience, so you're more likely to catch
those issues, maybe get that feedback early on.
Now, you also will often hear, when you're looking up
accessibility testing, the emphasis on screen reader and keyboard accessible
just because something is fully screen reader or keyboard accessible
isn't necessarily going to make it perfect.
But typically if something can be consistently
and well navigated with a screen reader
or a keyboard, and I also emphasize the
idea of using multiple screen readers,
we'll talk more about that in one of the next bullet points.
But if you can get things consistently and well
navigated with keyboard and screen reader, it's going to typically
be more likely that other
assistive technologies will provide
a consistent experience.
You don't want to put 100% focus on screen reader and keyboard
only, but just know that it does help
quite a lot. But then again,
going back to the nothing without us, that's also why it's important to then bring
in other people with different disabilities who
might catch issues that the screen reader and keyboard only users
wouldn't have caught.
Remember that a lot of accessibility plans are typically
based around WiCAg,
because that's just what a lot of the regulations are based off of, and because
the WiccaG tends to be broken down in such a way that it's a little
easier to build individual test plans based on some
of the guidelines. But it's important
to remember, again, that those guidelines are not going
to be all inclusive. They're not going to catch all the different accessibility errors that
may be present. And that's why it then becomes important to
make sure that you're getting that user feedback.
And also with the Wik guidelines,
another thing that sometimes people get a little caught up in is as
of 2.1, there is three different levels
of conformance. This may change with later versions, at least how it's split up.
There'll probably still be conformance levels that just might be labeled
a little different, but right now they are AAA.
And AAA A is basically like
the accessibility things that you really shouldn't even
be having to try. If you're using good practices, you should be
hitting those things just no problem.
Which also means that if you are breaking some
of those, you really need to fix that stuff and maybe fix
some of your practices. Typically what
a lot of regulations are based around. And that's kind of like the
good standard to try to hit.
IsAA is
like special use cases or nice if you can.
It can make things a little bit better,
but you don't have to be 100% aaa compliant.
And in fact within the guidelines, it even kind of says
that if you try to be 100% aaa compliant,
you may cause accessibility engineer other areas. So you've got
to be kind of careful about how you apply some of the AAA
requirements. And then there could also be instances where some of the
guidelines just don't apply. For instance, if you don't
have pre recorded audio video content,
obviously those guidelines are most likely not going to apply
to you. So that's just something to kind of keep in mind.
And again, making sure that you're being flexible build
upon. You might use the Wik guidelines as a starting point, but then
you want to build upon that to make more
robust test plans. Another important thing,
and this is kind of what I was kind of hinting at with the
screen reader point, but you want to customize
your test methods for different environments and you want to try to test across as
many environments as possible. So like with screen
readers, there is typically jaws
and NVDA and narrator for Windows.
If you can test across all three of those screen readers,
that is awesome.
Mac and iOS have voiceover,
Android has talkback. You want to
try to test across those different screen readers and environments when possible,
because just the way that content can be interpreted
by those different screen readers can vary slightly. There may be slight differences
in what Aria, for instance, are compatible with
those screen readers, or how those screen readers interpret that
content, or even how different browsers interpret that content
and operating systems. So it's really good to try to
test across all those platforms.
Testing across different browsers. Now,
there may be some exceptions. So, like for instance, if you just
have a native app on a phone
and it's only available on Android for a
particular business reason, obviously at that point you're
only testing in that one environment. If you have
an embedded system, something like on a smart refrigerator,
well, obviously you're just testing it on that refrigerator. You're not testing it
on your browser, your mobile device,
that kind of thing. There's that flexibility there. You want to
make sure to try to hit all the different environments that you can so you
catch those little side issues. Unless you have
a specific use case where it's limited to a particular environment.
You can see a lot of example test plans.
Two that I've got listed here are VGAR, which is the visa global accessibility
requirements. This is just visas publicly
available accessibility guidelines. They've got some little
example test plans, tools and other resources that can be
helpful. There's also the section 508 ICT
testing baseline for web.
This is as it says, it's section 508 testing. You'll see
it used for the Department of Homeland Security trusted tester
certification, as well as just general section 508
compliance testing. There's also a
few other examples that I'll mention later on, but those are just two
for now to get you started. So now onto tools
and resources. These are basically tools that for the
most part may be already available to you and you may just not realize it
or are freely available. I'm going to mostly focus on
things that are free here because those are of course usually the easiest ones
too. If you're trying to pitch to your employer
to get them to let you have access to things,
those are going to be the easiest ones to get them to let you have
access to. So first off, things that are built into
your browser here
I have the Chrome devtools
that are available within Chrome and the Chromium based edge
browser, as well as the lighthouse
testing options that are within the devtools.
The first set of devtools on the left, those are actually the
rendering options that are available within the Chrome devtools.
And those are accessed by, when you open up the devtools, there's a little
ellipses that's labeled with, I think, customized devtools.
If you hover over it and when you go into that, then there's a more
tools option and then you can access these rendering tools
and they just give you some nice little extra features that might help
with making it a little easier to identify
flashing content, simulating what it might be
like if someone is using custom CSS,
because that's what some people will do. And it's kind of
like the effect that some of the assistive
browser extensions, what some of them do is they're injecting
custom CSS into a page to cause an
effect that makes something more easy for someone to interpret.
It also gives you color filters that will help to kind of
simulate what it is like if someone has
certain types of colorblindness.
So it has a lot of nice nifty tools that might be helpful.
Lighthouse is available within the
Chrome devtools, and it's just a set of automated tests
for accessibility, SEO, things of that nature.
Now, this does fall into that whole be careful. Just because
you get 100% on the lighthouse doesn't necessarily mean
that your application is 100% accessible. Next, we have
some that are actually built into your operating system.
So on the left here I have the accessibility options for Microsoft
Windows. I think this was specifically Windows ten.
And then on the right is the accessibility shortcuts that are available
within macOS. And there's kind of some similar
ones that are available in iOS as well.
Now, a lot of these are meant to help make things
more accessible to users with disabilities. But of course,
what better way to know if your content is going to be accessible
to someone with a disability than to actually use the tools that that person
would be using. So, for instance, there's different color filters,
there's the built in screen readers. So for windows, that's narrator,
iOS, Mac, it's voiceover.
There's different zooming options, text scaling, things of that nature,
even color filters that you can use to sort of get
an idea for how accessible your content
may be to users who are using those very tools.
Now, there's also some different desktop applications you can get.
The first one I'm going to show here is the color contrast analyzer,
also referred to as CCA a lot of times by
the Picello group, which is usually shown as TPGI.
Now, if you just search for CCA by TPGI,
it'll actually come up as this should be like one of
the first results that comes up. And it's a free desktop application for
Windows and Mac that just lets you see
if you have a particular foreground color
with a particular background color, how much contrast
is there between those colors, and is it enough to pass
different Wicca guidelines? And it actually
lists three of the WiCCa guidelines that it's comparing against.
And it'll tell you whether or not it would pass based on the
regular size text for that guideline or the
large text for that guideline. And it gives you a nice little
description for each of those guidelines on what counts as
regular text or large text and what the
actual contrast ratio is that you have to meet. So very
nice. And it's simple to use, so it's a
good option. There are other browser extensions too that operate sort
of similarly. This is just one of the common ones that you might see
used, and it's free. Next I have Microsoft
accessibility insights. Microsoft accessibility Insights
is available as a browser extension for
Chrome based browsers and also as a desktop application
for Windows. The Windows desktop application
has a there's an accessibility insights for Windows
and an accessibility insights for Android that's
both downloadable to Windows OSS and the
for Android one is meant to help with. If you're developing Android applications
versus the for Windows one, you can just test anything on Windows.
And then additionally there are pipeline options that
you can actually use to test when someone
submits, like a pr request for instance, or if someone goes to build
the application, it may run some checks during the
build process. So something that could be very helpful to a
lot of people. The nice thing about the browser
extension is that it does give you fast pass
options which are like your automated tests. And then it gives
you an assessment option which combines the automated
tests with a manual test plan which you could
theoretically use as a starting point for building your own
custom test plans. And then it also
adds a few different little ad hoc tools which are just different
little tools that you can use for testing color,
contrast, tab order, and a few other
different things as they add on to the application. And it's also
open source. So if you see something that you notice is an
issue, you could actually go in and recommend a
fix for it yourself. I've actually submitted a pr
to it. I was really happy about that. It was cool.
Next im showing on the screen here is the wave tool.
The wave tool is accessible through a browser extension and
through a website interface. The website
interface actually gives you the option to paste in the URL,
or I think it gives you the option to actually paste in
the source code and it'll spit out a
report about different accessibility issues.
If you use the URL, it'll actually display the
page with an overlay and it'll highlight different potential
issues on the page or things that you're doing right. So it's kind of
nice to be able to see some of the good and the bad and
the maybe a problem things on the page.
It also gives you the option to right click on the page and it'll say
wave this page.
And then on the right here I have the browser
extension for Axe devtools.
Axe dev tools is made by DQ and there's a
free option and a paid option.
The free option will let you do a general scan.
I think the paid option adds in like some automated color
contrast checking and some best practice sort of testing.
Similar to accessibility insights,
it does also provide some manual guided testing options
as well. In fact, accessibility insights is
based off of the same Axe core API that Axe
devtools is based off of. It's just different interfaces
and a little bit different added features for each
one. So you can kind of pick and choose which one you like best.
One thing I will note too with a lot of the automated tests
is say you have a page where you have different
modals and such that open up, or frames
that only get added if you click on certain buttons.
When these things run their tests, they're only running the test on
what's on the page in that moment.
So they're not going to be testing like those different little modals that can pop
up. They're not going to test if the page is different sizes and different
just proportions that could cause things to reflow differently
and for other things to move about on the page.
So that's another reason you want to really keep
in mind that automated testing is not conclusive.
Next we have the W three C markup validation service.
This is going to identify some accessibility
issues and also a lot of parsing issues.
So it can help you to note whether or not you've got maybe some
HTML best practices that you're not following as well as you should.
Maybe you're misusing some aria using bad values,
and it'll just kind of give you a report. As you can see
here, you can either upload a file, just give it the URL
for the page, or actually paste in the
source code, and it'll just give you a nice little report that you can actually
export into different file types. So if you
wanted to share the results with someone else, it would be very easy to do
that. This does have the same limitation though, that it's
only testing the page as it would be when you first open
it, and it's not necessarily going to catch issues that might
only appear when certain modals open up and things of that nature.
Finally, we also have accessibility bookmarklets.
Bookmarklets are like little snippets of JavaScript
that you can drag up onto the bookmark bar that's
usually in most browsers. You may have to turn on the bookmark bar
if it's not on by default, but you drag these to the bookmark
bar and then let's say you have a web page up and you want to
see what kinds of heading structure you have on the page
that's recognized you might have a headings bookmarklet.
There actually is one under this accessibility bookmarklets
option here and it
would actually highlight all the accessibility bookmarklets.
There's basically bookmarks like for bookmarklets
for checking for just about anything, aria, form,
structure, landmarks, text spacing and
then one of the more robust ones is the Andy tool.
I might try to actually show that one here real quick
when I get done here, depending on how much longer it
takes me to get through all these slides.
Also, there's a lot of books out there that can help. Three that I've got
here are inclusive design patterns by Hayden Pickering,
form design patterns by Adam Silver, and inclusive
components by Hayden Pickering. Inclusive components in particular
is really nice because Hayden actually has
a website version of the book that's completely free and
it shows a lot of great examples for how to make certain components
in an inclusive way. It is important though, to remember with anything like
this that just because someone
suggests hey, here's one way you can make a drop
down menu, here's one way you can make this particular form component.
Doesn't mean that that's the only way, but this just gives you
a good starting point. Additionally,
there's some other resources I have listed here. Links for NVDA,
which is a free open source screen reader that a lot of
individuals with sight loss use. There's accessibility
insights that I mentioned earlier,
information about narrator, voiceover,
Talkback, the Microsoft Accessibility page,
Microsoft's accessibility fundamentals course, a link to
Andy and the accessibility page on my own personal site which
if you go to the accessibility page on my corgi dev.com site,
I do actually have every resource that is listed
in this presentation is also present there,
as well as links to my GitHub where you can view
these specific slides if you'd like.
And in fact right here I'm just going to show on my little thank
you slide my corgi dev.com
site as well as my GitHub site which is
GitHub Comcorgydeva
eleven materials.
If you go to that, it will actually have
this presentation under presentations and then
2023 presentations. And with that
we're just going to switch over to another screen here so
that I can actually show you some
of the tools and concepts that I discussed earlier in this
presentation in action.
So first off here you'll see I've got my
good site, bad site.
Neither one is really a good site, it's just good for this
example, but visually they
have the same general layout.
We've got the header logo, some navigation links
and then some headers, paragraphs and images that
constitute the main content of the page. And some
footer links and a little copyright down here
for the footer. Now if
I actually inspect these pages,
the big thing that you'll notice here is that there's
the head, the body, but then inside the body it's basically
all divs. For the most part.
All the text is inside of either paragraph tags
or spans. There's no header elements. All the images
have alt attributes that are null,
which would indicate to assistive technology that they are just
decorative and not informative, which is not the
case here.
There are no nav elements to
help describe what
areas are navigation links.
There is again no headers.
The footer is just a div with a list
and then a div that has some text in it.
Versus if I go over to my good site example
and I inspect that one, you'll notice that
inside the body I actually have a header that headers the
image. It has an alt attribute. All the images on here have alt
attributes that actually have good values
because that's the thing. I mean you can have an alt attribute,
but if it doesn't really convey what the information is
intended to be gained from that image by the user,
it's not really good. Alt attribute text.
I have navs now since there's a nav in the header
and in the footer, you'll notice I actually have an AriA label on
each one to help differentiate them. This is because some
assistive technologies will actually list off the landmark elements
for the user. And so if you just had two navs,
they're just going to show up as two Navs. But if you add that Aria
label, it'll actually label them for the user. So they
say nav and then like main navigation nav,
social media links or something like that. That way the user just
knows that there are different types of links, maybe in each one,
which can indicate to someone what they may
expect to find there. Because if you think about it, when we visually look through
a website, we're tending to look at how is the
content grouped together, where is it positioned
visually on the page. And that's giving us an idea of oh well,
I can probably expect to find links for this thing I'm looking for.
If I go down to the footer versus the header, we can
look at how headings differentiate in view
compared to regular text to help us pick them out really quickly
and skim through and maybe identify what
text has what purpose or what section is
most likely to contain the information that we need. And so using
all this proper semantic HTML, you're essentially doing that
same thing for someone using assistive technology. You're allowing
them to sit there and go through and just view a list
of headings and skim through to the one that they
actually need. You're allowing them to immediately
go to the footer and look there for the
content that maybe they're looking for and they expect will most likely be there.
In my main, I do have some divs because divs are
okay to use if you're just wanting to apply particular formatting
or something to a section, but it's still good to
make sure to use the semantic like I've got sections here,
each section has an aria labeled by so we know what that
section is actually for. Got my
headers. My headers are all proper h one h two h
three s. I've got paragraph text because that's
perfectly fine to have nothing against having paragraph
text. Again, I've got
all my different links and whatnot
laid out here with proper semantic HTML,
and that's going to help with someone that's got assistive technology that they're using.
Now, if I go to axe devtools,
as one would expect, once I close the like
pro info, you'll notice it
has zero issues. It's good to go.
However, if I go to the bad one and
I also run that, it's also going to come up with zero.
That's because automated tests are only going to be able to do so much.
So like for instance, it's not going to know whether or not
these images need to be null alt attributes indicating
that they're decorative, or if they need to actually have an
alt attribute with a value. They're not going to know
if whatever value I give that alt attribute is
meaningful and conveying the purpose of the image, or if it's
just random generated lore mipsum text.
It's kind of like how if you do AI generated alt attributes,
it's not always going to be the accurate meaning of
the image. So it's just something to kind of keep in mind. You don't want
to completely depend on automated testing. You want to make sure
to have a little bit of that manual testing in there as well.
Okay, now im going to actually go back over here to my corgi dev
accessibility page. Actually, I'm going to open this up
in Chrome first, just because for some reason Lighthouse
has been giving me trouble in edge the last week or
two. Not sure what's going on there? So to
show you Lighthouse, which again, as I mentioned earlier,
Lighthouse is the automated testing tool
that is available within Chromium based browsers
like Google Chrome or the new Microsoft soft edge,
you open devtools and you just select Lighthouse.
It gives you a few different options here that you can pick from,
including like you can actually do mobile versus desktop,
which can help with that whole thing I mentioned earlier where automated
testing isn't going to necessarily capture all the issues
because it's not going to necessarily capture modals and stuff that might
come up on your page that could have accessibility issues.
It's just going to test what is visible on the page in
that moment. Now im going to analyze page load here.
Now the one good thing about it is since it does this page load,
if you have tooltips and stuff that modals that just pop up
when you initially load the page in,
it will be able to test those, but it's just not going to test other
things that might open later. As you can see, it'll give me this nice
little rate layout. If I had issues that it picked up,
it would display them here for me to be able to see them.
And it also gives you options to export them,
open them in a different viewer, different options that allow you
to share them.
Since we already have devtools open here,
if I go up to this top, ellipses labeled customize and
control devtools by its tooltip and I click that and select
more tools and rendering, I get this
little option window down here at the bottom and
you'll notice it has things like paint flashing. There's no flashing content on
this page right now. So that's not going to really do me anything right now.
But it does give me some different emulation options,
including this nice little one down here that
gives me an idea of what different kinds of
vision. I don't really like the word deficiencies
impairments, but like vision differences, how that might impact
how someone views your page. It is important to
note that with any of these, it's not
going to be as accurate as having someone that actually has these conditions since
how these present amongst different people can vary
from person to person. But you
can get an idea, it can give you an idea if there might be some
apparent contrast issues that could be problematic and
then go back over here to edge.
And we also have accessibility insights.
Accessibility insights. The nice thing with it is, again, like I mentioned earlier,
you have some of the automated options,
but on top of the automated options you also
have this assessment, which it does have the automated checks,
but then it also gives you these guided manual tests.
Now these are not going to be like all inclusive of different
platforms that you could be testing your content on, but they give you a
good starting point. And it can be helpful for developers who
may not have as much accessibility testing experience
just to kind of be able to have something that they can go through and
they can get an idea of where they might need to make improvements.
Additionally, we also have the ad hoc tools
which you'll see. It just gives me options to highlight,
do color contrast checks, tab stops,
landmarks. I actually kind of like the way it
displays landmarks better than some things
that need review, the accessible names
of things,
and even some of the automated checks.
Now the other thing that I mentioned during the presentation was bookmarklets.
And I'm going to start with Andy. Now, I don't think I mentioned this earlier,
but Andy was actually developed by the Social Security Administration
and it's used for section 508 compliance testing,
including the Department of Homeland securities trusted tester
certification. And it just will pick up on different
elements that it picks up on the page, which can be helpful too, because like
for instance, there's a table and a frames module
that can pop up with Andy. And so if you have
a table on the page but the Andy table tool isn't popping up,
that could indicate that you've got an issue with how you wrote your table
and it's not going to be interpreted correctly by assistive technologies.
Let me see. I don't know for sure. Okay, so now with
some bookmarklets, one thing that's important to know is some of them you can just
click the bookmarklet again and it'll close it. Other ones you actually have
to refresh the page. So I've also
got bookmarklets here for headings.
I've got one for text spacing because some people that have like dyslexia
or low vision may have stylings that
they use to increase text spacing. So it's important to see that
your content is going to adjust to that.
There's a little code sniffer one here that'll give me some little
tidbits of information about issues that might be on my
page lists.
You can find all kinds of these
bookmarklets. And again, if you go to my accessibility page
on my site, you can actually go to the reporting and testing
resources section. And there are all the different
desktop applications, bookmarklets and more that I covered
during this presentation today that can be found here.
And so with that, I do just want to say thank
you for listening to my talk and I hope
you'll check out my corgi dev site as well as
my GitHub repo, which again is GitHub.com
corgi Dev a eleven
ymaterials and this
presentation. The slides will be under presentations and 2023
presentations. With that, hope you enjoy the rest of the
conference.