Hey everyone, I'm Colby Fayock. We're going to talk about maps. We're going to talk
about the impact they can have on the world. And we're also going to dive
into how you can build them with little bit of javascript. So who am I?
I'm Colby fak. I'm the one hugging bb eight and Kylo Ren over there.
I work on the UX and front end side of things at element 84.
Find me pretty much anywhere on the web by just googling my name, as I'm
the only one in the world. So looking at these first slide, it's a screenshot
of Google Maps in downtown Alexandria, Virginia. Here in the United States,
this is element 80 four's hq. We're all probably pretty familiar with Google
Maps or Apple Maps. They provide us with a ton of features that we use
every day. Lives here we can check, but some points of interest nearby. We can
find out where. We can grab a quick cup of coffee. We can find the
best sushi, which is Momo's sushi by these way. Or just look at some pictures
of the area. This next screenshot is of public transit directions. It's showing
the metro that I would take to get from my last apartment to work.
My wife and I share one car, so when I don't have it, I was
able to get a good idea of how long it would take to get downtown.
And this next one shows some driving directions. This route is where I would take
to get to my mom's house where I grew up. The time here is a
little bit optimistic, though. It never actually took under 4 hours to get there with
traffic. And how many of you like to travel? Well, I know as
much as we'd all love to be in another country every month, that's usually not
feasible, especially now. So my wife likes to take virtual vacations around the world,
which is a little bit better for our budget. But google Maps helps her easily
travel around and check things out. Here we're getting a good look at
the great pyramids of Giza. We can get an overhead view from above
and see what the area actually looks like. The cool thing about this though is
we can actually get a close up look with street view. We can get an
idea of the scale of this structure. It's huge. And we can get
an idea of how big it really is. When I was talking to my wife
about this, she was in the middle of one of her journeys. She wandered to
a place called the Valley of Geysers, which is located in Russia. On the Komchika
peninsula. It turns out this geyser field is the second largest concentration
on Earth. It seems wild to me that we can get a look at this
place and it's all because someone took the time to take a picture of this
remote place. These particular picture was from a local guide,
so that means any of us can do this. And the neat thing is we
can check out this kind of place even if we'll never have the opportunity to
go. It's obviously not these real thing, but we're still able to get a glimpse
of what remote places around the world look like. So where do we actually get
the data to build out all these features? Well, first you have an obvious one.
You have scientists and analysts. This is just a stock photo I found on these
GIS university website site. But they're constantly hard at work collecting and
processing data and I really have to hope that they're always looking this happy.
You also have technology. Thanks to the cars and the people that build street view,
we get a close up look of the pyramids and we can also get some
fun Easter eggs along the way. This also includes a ton of people around
the world, like I showed in Russia. There are local guides all over contributing
pictures and data. And did I mention there's Easter eggs? Thanks Tokyo.
There's a ton of ones like these all over the Internet. But then we have
satellites. There's a bunch of different types. Some collect imagery, some collect more
in a data format, but they all help to produce assets which we can use
to create our maps. A good example of this is cryosat from ESA.
It uses its onboard instruments to measure changes in it thickness.
It can measure changes as accurate as zero 7 year.
The example on the right is showing Antarctica mapped out in 3d using the data
it collected. Another example of this is NASA's modus terra.
Using its image sensors, it covers every point on Earth,
every one to two days. It collects large scale global dynamics
like cloud coverage, ocean processes and changes in the atmosphere. The shot
on the right is a photo over Lake Erie in the United States. NASA alone
is working all the ones that you see here. They published this image to show
the state of their missions operated by their Earth team. It shows satellites
in orbit now and out until 2023. But NASA and ESA aren't
alone here. There's thousands of satellites like these flying over us right
now. Some of them aren't even working, but a lot of them are challenging images
and data about our planet. These satellites are also cool from
a consumer point of view. NASA and other teams put up pictures on Instagram
for our daily those from above. At the top, you see International Space
Station, which isn't a satellite, I know, but it shows the earth at
night, which I just think is kind of cool. The bottom is from daily overview,
which is showing a look at Lake neutrons in Tanzania, which is just mind
blowing. Then on the right, we have a gorgeous look from NASA Earth, which is
a picture of Mergawi archipelago, which is on the border of Burma and Thailand.
It's awesome to be able to see these kinds of inspiring pictures right in our
Instagram feeds. But switching back to maps for a second, this is just
another look at downtown Alexandria. But behind that, it's OpenStreetMap.
OSM is an open source project. It maintains a huge set
of metadata that includes the attributes and properties that define specific
geographic areas. It allows mappers all over the world to contribute.
So with their tooling, anyone can identify points of interest and update
features. With our powers combined, that means another source
of this data is you. But millions of people all around the world have mapped
on OSM. There's meetups and communities all over. Others just
work alone as individuals, but thousands of people work on this every single day.
You also see big companies who use or contribute back to OSM, like Apple
uses its regions for where commercial data isn't available, and Lyft contributes
back with their work. They're all adding points of ventures and drawing streets. And it's
more for just learning what's in the United States. But for third
world countries all around the world, it's incredibly helpful from a humanitarian aid
perspective, where here we can see an identified refugee camp on
the border of South Sudan and Ethiopia. A lot of times, people in
these areas might not know where they can be safe, but OSM allows
these people to identify the features and help others survive. So where am
I going with all this? Well, the point I'm trying to make is that maps
are more than just driving directions. Maps are literally giving people
tools to save the world. There's tons of research going on from different
areas, from climate change to agriculture. By taking collected data and
applying into a map, we're providing another visualization medium for scientists that
can actually make a difference in people's lives. Some examples that you can find
online are like NASA's worldview. Here we can see tropical cyclone edai,
which was one of the worst cyclones on record to affect Africa in the southern
hemisphere. It affected close to 2.2 million people in eastern
Africa. It's insane to see the scale of this storm. Another is NASA's
firm service. It allows you to see active fires all around the world. Here we're
seeing a cutout of the barefire wildfires that are occurring over in
California. We can see the number of active fires in each area. You can
even see the gray smoke compared to the clouds in the fire. It's devastating.
But tools like this help people manage teams and resources for
determining how to help in these scenarios. And another thing that's pretty current,
which is why we're all online. We can take a look at this map from
Johns Hopkins University. It shows the number of coronavirus cases all around
the world, showing the visualizations lives. This on a map can help people identify
the larger parts of impact. Similarly, this map from
Nextstream shows the evolution and spread of the virus. If you visit this page,
you can actually play an animation that shows how the virus spread.
These types of tools are incredibly helpful for anyone in the science community that's trying
to understand and study more about this virus. But also on a lighter note,
people are also having some fun with maps where here radio.
They have a map that lets you select a country in a period of time.
So I can listen to music from Germany in the can listen to
brazilian music in the 30s. But there are a ton of wellknown teams doing
really great work trying to help. These are just some of the ones in the
United States. We have usgs helping to map out earthquakes.
USDA is monitoring food access, and they're not just monitoring food in the US,
they're monitoring all around the world. They are all working towards providing more information
to people who can actually make a difference, which is directly translating
to livesaved. So how does all this stuff actually work? It definitely can
seem really intimidating. There's a lot of information there, but getting started
probably isn't as bad as you think. So let's break it down a little bit.
Mapping applications look like your standard Jamstack app. So for those unfamiliar Jamstack
sites are JavaScript APIs and markup. It's pretty much a static HTML
website, but utilizing JavaScript in the browser to make any requests to
your APIs that would provide dynamic data. It's not necessarily a
new idea, but the architecture's got a cool name now, which also
comes with some cool references. Boom Shakalaka. But the Jamstack concept
is pretty much what you're working with out of the box with maps. First you
have the javascript that makes the map and the libraries that run the map load
and layered on top of that are your APIs, which for maps look like your
underlying imagery. And anything you put on top, that compiles down
to your markup, which the output is your standard HTML and that ultimately gets served
the person using the app. So let's start at the top with JavaScript. We're going
to look at leaflet. While it's not the only one, it's one of the most
popular mapping libraries available right now. Here we have a simple maps example
that we get from Leaflet's homepage. It's pretty basic map.
On top we have some simple markers and a pop up, but behind that we're
using OpenStreetMaps that's providing our base map layer. So how
do we get there? Well, believe it or not, this small snippet is all it
takes. So let's break it down. From the top we create a map instance.
That map instance takes an id, which is the id of the div we're mounting
on. The concept is kind of similar to what you would expect from react
when you're mounting a component. But next we have the view of the map using
latitude and longitude. We also set the zoom level that allows us
to determine how far into the map we're actually zoomed in. Next we describe
the layer that we want to add to the map. This part is called the
tile layer. We'll get to tile layers in a little bit these, but we're going
to set up a new tile layer instance using an endpoint URL. We also provide
an attribution to give the surface credit. So this will give us the base of
these map. But how do get those markers? This last snippet creates the marker using
a leaflet marker instance, we set the position of where we want the marker to
be using latitude and longitude again. Then we bind the pop up to
the marker and we set sensible text and we continue to open it up
in its place. And after that we have our basic map.
All right, so if you're anything like me, you like to build your applications in
react. Luckily we have react Leaflet, which is a library that takes leaflet
and builds out native react components to help us quickly get started
with maps. Here we have an example that's shown on the react leaflet homepage.
If you notice, it's the same map that we saw before, but it's now built
out using react components. Breaking this down again, we have our map component that
wraps everything. We set our latitude and longitude using the center prop and
we set our zoom using the zoom prop. Inside our map we have our tile
layer component. Then we add our endpoint and an attribution. Then we add our marker
component, set the coordinates with the position prop. Inside that we include a pop
up component which we can nest with our simple text. And again,
we have our basic map example. There are also some other flavors of leaflet available
if you find yourself in another framework. Angular and Vue both have libraries that help
you get started. Unfortunately though, I couldn't find a logo with the angular and leaflet
mashup, so getting to that point isn't too bad. But let's talk about the data
that actually goes into building the map. When dealing with maps, I like to think
of a poorly drawn cake. The base map is the actual cake. Then you
have your overlays that are your icing, and then you have some data sprinkled on
top. Your base map typically looks like something like OpenStreetMap or modus
terra. As we saw before, your overlays could be anything like a small
sample of high res imagery or heat maps to visualize the data. On top
of your data can literally be anything, such as active fires or evacuation zones.
Starting to dig in a little bit further to the base map. This is essentially
the map imagery that you have that's available to cover the entire globe.
This will be the foundation of your map. The map image layers are called tile
layers, which are composed of a bunch of small tile images that make up one
large image. If you can see at the top, we have our tile layer endpoint.
There's a few properties that get programmatically swapped out, like our
date zoom and x and Y axis. The nice thing about this endpoint
scheme though, is it's really common, so we can just as easily swap this out
for OpenStreetMap, for instance. The reason though this gets broken up into
smaller images is you don't want people having to pull down huge image
files where the entirety of these map could be over 1gb in size,
where realistically, someone using our map might only use a
fraction of that. Overlays are similar to your base map, but a lot of times
they just don't have nearly the same amount of imagery available, which is why they're
called an overlay. This could be if you have some higher resolution imagery only
for a little part of the map, or if you wanted to show a different
kind of image for your map, like a heat map. Here we have an image
overlay of the predicted 2020 population city over
open street maps. We're showing the northeast United States where we
can see. On the right we see Philadelphia, and you can also see DC
and Baltimore on the left. This is just another example of some of the imagery
NASA provides. And then we generally have data using shapes.
We can visualize data really any way we want to. Here we're
adding individual points of interest to show active gives, but you can also
use lines, circles, polygons. Here we can see a fire boundary for those same
wildfires on top of OSM. The points are helpful
for seeing active fires, but seeing the boundary can be easier to comprehend for
areas of danger. The point though is there really aren't any requirements for
visualizing data, but there's just standards for how it interfaces with
leaflet. Now, some of the data is free, some of it's not. NASA provides a
ton of public data and tile endpoints. It makes it really easy to get started
in a kind of plug and play kind of way. I showed you a few
of those already, like the population heat map and our base maps.
But others, such as digital glow, provide access to limited data.
They have an open data program that gives access to imagery for disaster areas.
This helps immensely for teams that are trying to put together solutions that are trying
to help fighting disasters, but the rest of it would be a premium product that
you would have to pay for. All right, so once we have our map and
our data on top of it, we need to compile it down and serve it
to the browser. This is actually the shortest step of the group. Compiling the app
is pretty much what you would expect for anything standard on a webpack based app.
You can use your favorite tool, like create react app, or Gatsby, those compiled
down to a static site which outputs the HTML, CSS, and JavaScript.
Once you have that compiled version, you can serve it wherever you want. At that
point, it's really just object storage. So whether you want to put in a bucket
on s three or use Azure's new tool, you have a lot of options.
So what can we build with this? We've been working hard at element 84,
trying to come up with a way for first responders and disasters scenarios to
have a really easy to use UI. The goal here is that we'd be able
to get the UI to a point where they don't have to think hard to
get the information they want from the maps. This is a picture of first responders
Trevor Skaggs took when he was up against the campfire wildfires in
California from 2018. There's many natural disasters like
this that unfortunately take place every year just like the barefire wildfires,
but it's intense and it impacts people's lives. We want to try to
help, so we want to try to put tools in people's hands that can actually
make a difference. Those tools can help them fight current disasters and
be more prepared for the next. We call this film drop. Dr. This is showing
the east coast of Australia. I'm sure some of us are familiar with the bushfire
wildfires that devastated their east coast. We can plug and play
really any data source and provide can easy way to visualize that.
Here we're showing active fires on top of satellite imagery. The hope
is that whether someone wants to look at active fires or the boundary way,
they don't have to fumble around with advanced settings to get there. After talking to
some of the people that were actually in the field, like Trevor, we determined that
we need to get this thing to a point where an operator can understand it
in less than 15 minutes. As much as some of the other uis available have
really great granular control. There's just not enough time to try to explain that and
simply try to figure it out. With a simple toggle, we can get a completely
different perspective for how a fire is impacting an area. This particular
shot is from California campfire wildfires, where we can see active
fire points and boundaries over satellite imagery. And we can also
see some high resolution imagery and active fires over street maps.
Another feature we added is the ability to add data points to the map.
If someone wants to report somebody that's missing, they can easily add this data,
point to the map and sync it up to the cloud for others to see.
The cool thing about this, though, is we can store this locally in the browser,
so if a person doesn't actually have network connectivity, they can still sync
it up later. We also want to provide the ability for people to collect insitu
data and make it immediately available. Someone with a drone can map out
an area, upload it to their computer and sync it and make that available
as a new layer that can really provide some powerful, up to date imagery
for better understanding your surroundings. The imagery is actually from a co worker of
mine who flew his drone up over Lake Lansing in Michigan. Film drop
also gets a little bit more interesting on the data side. Not to go down
a rabbit hole, but we're building this to be able to upload data directly to
an AWS snowball edge, which is that gray box that the laptop
is sitting on there, and it's basically a cloud in a box.
And this gives people on the field, another level of processing power and capabilities
that they just didn't have before. So what makes this impactful? Well, the hope here
is that it can help first responders get the information they need to be
more productive and efficient in the field. That could directly equate to more
lives saved in many scenarios. So, realistically, imagine someone can area
without cell service. They can fly a drone, upload that data to a snowball
edge, and process that to visualize it on a map. This can help show
things like what areas are impacted by a fire that are no longer safe to
go to, that can immediately help save someone's life. And I know it might not
be summer for everybody, but how about a road trip? Of course, we can have
a little fun with this, too. I put together this simple demo that tracks a
road trip on the east coast of the United States. This is actually a road
trip with my wife in the summer of 2015. Ignore the
stray lines out to Las Vegas. We actually flew through that part, but it allows
us to simply get a look at all the locations we wanted to stop at
throughout the United States. The cool thing, though, is if we select one of the
points, and we can get a little itinerary with a picture of when we were
there. So, how did I put this together? So, the first thing I did was
starting to collect the locations I wanted and put them in a structured data format.
Once I had that, I spun up a base of the app using a Gatsby
starter that I created with leaf split. I'll get to the starter in a little
bit here, but for now, it's going to be a little bit of hand waving
with those locations. I needed to take the structured data and translate it into
something that our mapping library would understand. This particular format is geojacent,
which I was able to create by mapping over the locations and making shape groups.
I actually needed to do this two times. Once in the example where I created
the different latitude and longitude points, but also in a separate instance that
I was able to create lines with two points.
But after we have our data in our desired formats, we can take those raw
JSON data sets, and we can plug them into a new leaflet Geojson instance,
and simply apply it to the map. We'll also notice that I'm getting
the bounds of the geojacent here, which is essentially the area that the geojacent
data takes up on the map. So once I have those bounds, I can tell
the map to view its current view to those bounds. So how about those
tooltips so in the last slide we showed that our geojson sets
with a custom option point to layer, which I've highlighted here.
But this allows us to pass in a function which we can modify the layer
being created in leaflet from our data. So what we're trying to
do for each layer that gets created or each point is create a
new marker. Within the marker we behind a pop up to it, similar to
what we saw in our basic intro earlier. But within that we create some custom
HTML in a string form that allows us to set the custom
content for the pop up. And with all that we have our maps with some
custom tooltip pop ups. Not too bad, right? But even if we wanted to extend
this a little bit, we could sync this up to dynamically pull images from Instagram
and show a gallery of images during our trip. We can use today's date and
highlight these on the trip we're at for that day. We can even add a
timeline where maybe we can scrub back and play the road trip. But to get
here, the starter takes out some of the need to bootstrap the app so we
can get productive right away and start playing with the data. If you're curious or
interested in getting your hands dirty, the source code for this is all up in
my GitHub. I'll post it to Twitter later. That's not a hint to follow me
or anything, but also included in my talk notes and also what makes this impactful.
Well, for me, it was just fun to build. I love road trips, but I
think it's fun to take a normal event and make it a little bit more
interactive to share with a map. Now, when I talk about we, I really mean
all of us, I want to drive home the point that any of us can
do this. The tools that we have available make this accessible for anybody to
use. So as I mentioned before, I started this demo app with a starter
to help get people more productive quickly with maps, I created a Gatsby
starter for leaflet. We can very quickly spin up a new mapping app
with very little fuss and immediately become productive. Using the
Gatsby Cli, you can create a new project with the git address. This grabs the
project and installs the NPM dependencies. Then you can run yarn
or NPM develop whichever you prefer and this starts your local server.
And then we have our mapping app. It's simple. I've been trying to add features
little by little, but it's a good foundation to get started with a mapping app
in react and as a bonus, the summer road trip demo can actually be used
as a Gatsby starter. Similar to the leaflet one. You can instantly spin
up a new road trip mapping app. You would just use the Gatsby Cli like
the other starter. I also wrote a tutorial that actually walks you through setting up
one yourself. Step by step. It goes right through the functionality and it
has split but commits. For easy reference, I'll include the link with my talk notes
as well, or you can also deploy it right to netlify if you have an
account that makes it really easy to spin up fast and just a note.
This works for anywhere in the world, not just the United States. Just remember to
update the photos. I also have a few other guides available.
Lives. You can create a travel bucket list, or you can create a Stats dashboard
for the Covid-19 pandemic. I'll include the links to those in my talk notes
as well. So, did I inspire you to learn a little bit more about maps?
Well, if I did, I have a ton of resources for you to get started.
In addition to those tutorials from before, I just recently launched a course
on egghead IO that walks you through building a map from scratch for a react
app. I also have a bunch of free lessons available if you're not ready
to quite dive into a course yet. Also include those in my link notes
and that's it. Thank you. Feel free to reach out if you have any questions
about mapping or anything else about the jamstack.