Hello everyone.
Hey warm.
Welcome to all of you and thank
you for joining the session today.
My name is from Synchronous
Technologies USA.
Today I will be speaking on a topic
that is becoming more crucial in the
modern IO IOT ecosystems, a GA for Smart
Camera I, IOT devices, real time image
processing without cloud dependencies.
Now before we dive in,
let's frame the big picture.
For years, IOD cameras have been heavily
dependent on the cloud, but the current
real world requires something faster,
more private, and more efficient.
And that's what exactly HGA steps in.
Cloud Central bottleneck.
Before we understand why a GA is
so important, we first need to
understand the limitations of the
traditional cloud-based approach.
The side explains the major bottlenecks.
That occur when smart cameras
dependent fully on cloud processing
bandwidth becomes a major problem.
Every camera that streams video to
the cloud consumes network bandwidth.
As soon as you add more cameras, the
bandwidth requirement rises rapidly.
In real world places like.
Construction sites rural areas,
and densely urban neighborhoods.
Network strength is unusually limited,
so when multiple cameras try to
stream raw video at the same time,
the systems become slow and unstable.
We can simply say the network cannot
handle so much continuous video traffic.
Latency is too high for realtime use.
When everything goes to the cloud,
the device must wait for the video
to upload, for the cloud to process
it, and then send the results back.
Even in good conditions.
The delay can be 50 to 500
milliseconds for realtime application.
Like security alerts, industry
automation or safety monitoring,
this delay is unacceptable.
The system must react immediately,
not half a second later.
Privacy and compliance issues,
sending a video to the cloud rises.
Privacy concerns.
Users do not want the personal
life footage uploaded continuously.
Regulations like GDPR and CCPA
make this even more challenging.
A GA solves this by keeping data local
and sending only essential information.
High cloud costs, streaming
video nonstop requires cloud,
compute, storage, and bandwidth,
all of which cost money at scale.
With the dozens or hundreds of
cameras, the cost become unsustainable.
So the traditional cloud
only setup does not scale.
It is too slow, too expensive,
and too depend on strong internet.
This is why industry is
shifting towards edge ai.
Now we understand that the
cloud problems, let's look how
RGA can solve these problems.
This slide explains why
running EA directly on devices.
Such a powerful shift processing
happens directly on device with the RGA.
The camera does not send video
to the cloud for analysis.
Instead, the AI model runs
next to the camera sensor.
This makes detection and decision
making almost instant because
this, there is no network delay.
Huge reduction in bandwidth.
Instead of streaming full video, the
device only sends important events such
as person detected or object found.
This reduces the bandwidth.
Uses by 85%, making the system much more
easier to deploy anywhere, including
low connectivity environments, big
improvements in battery life because
the device uploads for less data and
performs fewer network operations.
Battery life will be more.
In many cases, battle life improves by
four to five times, which is critical
for outdoor cameras and IOT devices.
Under 50 50 milliseconds, latency
enables realtime performance.
The AI runs locally, there is
no wait time for cloud response.
This system can process frames in
under milli 50 seconds, enabling
real-time alerts, tracking and
analysis, better privacy and security.
Since the raw video stays on
the device, user maintains full
privacy, only the final result, not
the video is shared to the cloud.
This is a major advantage.
In smart home systems, public
environment, and regulated industries.
So NGA completely changes the game.
It gives us speed, efficiency,
privacy, and reliability
all directly on the device.
This is why modern iot camera systems
moving away from the cloud dependence
and adapting edge first approach.
Evolution of IOT cameras to understand
why a GI is so important today.
Let's quickly look how IOT camera
systems have evolved over the years.
The slide shows three major stages in
the development, early local processing.
In the beginning, cameras
had very limited hardware.
They could only do simple task
like detection, motion, recording
a video, or sensing alerts.
There was no intelligence,
just a basic device behavior.
These early systems were
reliable but extremely limited.
Cloud dependence, intelligence as
cloud computing become more popular.
Companies started shifting all the
heavy processing to the cloud servers.
This allowed cameras to perform more
advanced tasks such as facial recognition,
objective detection, behavioral analysis.
But this come up with several problems.
Bandwidth usage, cost is high,
increased latency, privacy concern.
This was the phase where people realized
that relaying completely on cloud.
Was not scalable.
The edge intel in intelligence era.
Now we are in the third phase.
Modern embedded hardware has
become more powerful enough to
runa models directly on the device.
Today, smart cameras can do real time
detection, classification, anomaly
detection, low light enhancement.
All on the device itself.
This evolution has brought us to the
point where a GA is not optional.
It's becoming the standard approach
for all IOT camera systems, neural
net network optimization techniques.
The slide outlines the main techniques
we use to make a models small.
Fast and efficient enough
to run on edge devices.
Let's go through the each one.
In the simple terms.
Quantization reduce the precision of
the numbers inside the model from 30
32 bit to eight bit, and helps reduce
the power usage with very little impact
on accuracy knowledge legislation.
This is a training technique where
big model teaches the small model.
The small model learns
how to perform almost as.
As well as the big one, but with a
fraction of size and compute requirements.
Architecture selection.
Here we choose model structures that
work well with on limited hardware
models like mobile net, squeeze
net, or design specifically to run
on mobile devices and IOT devices.
Neural architecture search can also
automatically generate efficient designs.
Pruning removes unnecessary
parts of neural network.
It gets rid of connections that don't
contribute much to the performance
by reducing the model size and
speeding up efficient architectures.
Finally, we adapt to lightweight
model families, such as
mobile net and squeeze net.
These models use depth wise, convolution,
and streamlined layers to maintain good
accuracy while staying extremely small.
All these techniques work.
Together to transform heavy cloud-based
model into an edge friendly one
a GA has station.
Now let's talk about hardware
that makes a GA possible.
This slide explains why specialized
process like TPUs and NPUs
are critical for real time.
AI on small devices.
Why CPUs alone are not enough.
Traditional CPUs are
general purpose chips.
They can do a bit of everything, but
they're not optimized for heavy metrics
calculations that AI models require
Running AI solely on CPU U would
be slow and consume a lot of power.
The role of TPUs and NPUs, this is
where TPUs, tensor processing units and
NPUs neural processing units come in.
These chips are designed
specifically for a workloads.
They contain parallel processing
units, fast metrics, multiplication
engines, optimizing memory pathways.
This makes them 10 to a hundred times
more efficient than CPS for a task.
Example of edge acceleration.
Some examples include Google
Coral, TPU, Qualcomm, hexagon,
DSP, apple Neural Engine.
These accelerates allow iot
cameras to run complex models
while staying energy efficient.
Without these hardware accelerators,
realtime AI on battery powered
cameras simply would be not possible.
This slide presents the full
system architecture used to run
AI efficiently on edge devices.
It's organized into three main
layers that work together.
H-A-L-H-A-L hides the
difference differences between
various hardware platforms.
It provides a consistent interface for
memory sensors and compute functions.
The this allows us to run CMEA
code on different devices without
rerating everything neural
network optimization layer.
This is where model gets
transformed into an.
Edge Ready version.
It goes through quantization pruning,
architecture, selection, and compilation.
The output is small, fast and
efficient model, Tyler, efficient
to the devices capabilities,
real-time processing pipeline.
This pipeline is responsible for
handling the live video stream.
It manages frame capture,
pre-processing, AI interference.
And post crossing this goal is to
maintain smooth real-time performances
no matter how busy the device gets.
The layered architecture ensures the
flexibility, efficiency, and reliability
across wide range of hardware platforms.
Hardware platform support.
This slide shows the different
hardware platforms we support from
very simple devices to advanced edge
processors, interrelated level devices.
These are basic systems with 512 MB two
one GB Ram, such as arm cortex processors,
adrenal broads with external accelerators.
They can handle lightweight
models for basic de detection
tasks, mid-range platforms.
These include devices like Raspberry
PI three and Raspberry Pi four.
There are popular for smart home
and consumer camera applications.
They offer good balance between
cost, performance and power
usage, high-end edge processors.
These platforms are designed
specifically for industrial
or professional applications.
Examples include Google,
coral, TPU, Qualcomm, hexagon,
DSP, Nvidia Jetson Modules.
These systems support large
models, foster interface.
And more complex analytics.
Supporting this wide range of hardware
ensures that our edge AI solutions
can use anywhere from low cost home
devices to advanced industrial systems,
neural network optimization pipeline.
This pipeline is essential because.
It prepares our EA models
to run efficiently on small
resource limited edge devices.
Remember, cloud models are often
large, slow, and power hungry.
Edge devices cannot run such
models directly, so we use a three
stage optimization pipeline to
convert a standard neural network
into an edge optimized version.
Architecture selection.
That is the stage one choosing.
Highly effective architectures
like mobile net, squeeze net,
mobile net V three, optimized fur.
General vision tasks on mobile
or edge hardwares squeeze net,
extremely small footprint, ideal
fur, very constrained environments.
Lightweight encoder decoder
networks with residual connections
achieved two to five MB model sizes.
These models use.
Techniques like depth wise, supportable,
solution con convulsions and efficient
residual blocks, allowing them to
run quickly while keeping accuracy,
high quantization and compression.
Stage two where the model
becomes truly ad differently.
A standard AI model uses 32, put
32 bait floating point weights.
We FP 32, but FP 32 is very heavy.
It takes more memory, more
energy, and more compute.
So we apply quantization converting FP
32 volumes, values to eight bit integer.
This gives four times reduction in
model size, faster interference speed,
much lower power consumption, and.
The accuracy loss is usually
under 2%, which is completely
acceptable for most applications.
Stage three platform specific compilation.
This is where we use edge focused
compilers, such as tensor flow, light
for arm, process edge, TPU, compiler
for Google, coral hexagon, and
then compiler for quantum Qualcomm.
NPUs specialized compilers
for N-P-U-T-P-U acceleration.
During compilation, the system performs
graph op graph optimization, which removes
unnecessary operations operator fusion,
combines multiple operations into one
for speed, memory layout optimization.
This makes sure memory
access or efficient.
The stage ensures that every
part of model runs our most
efficient compute unit available.
C-P-U-N-P-U or TPUs.
Real time processing architecture.
Now let's see how real time processing
pipeline works inside on a GA camera.
This pipeline is designed so the camera
can continuously process videos at
30 plus frames per second, even when
workload changes image acquisition.
The first step is capturing incoming
video frames from the camera sensor.
We used something called as a ring
buffer, which basically means the camera
is always collecting frames in a loop.
This is important because it
prevents the system from dropping
frames if the processor is busy.
So even if there is a temporary
spike in processing, the camera keeps
capturing smoothly pre-processing.
Once a frame is captured, the
next steps is pre-processing.
This include tasks like resizing
the image, adjusting the colors,
and normalizing the pixel values.
These steps must be extremely
fast, ideally under 10,
10 milliseconds per frame.
To achieve these, we use SIMD
acceleration, which allows
multiple pictures to be processed
at once in simple dumps.
Pre-processing is about getting
the image into the exact same.
And format that a model expects
neural network execution.
Next comes the core steps.
Running a model on the frame
on mid range hardwares.
This takes about 30 to 45 milliseconds
depending on the complexity of the model.
This is where the camera detects objects,
identify patterns, recognize the faces.
This model has already been optimized
for our previous pipeline, so it can run
quickly, even with the limited hardware
post processing, making the output useful
after the model gives its predictions.
We performs post processing.
The, this includes tasks like filtering
noise, applying thresholds, drawing
boundary bonding boxes, or converting raw
model outputs into actionable results.
For example, instead of just giving
numbers, the system says person
de person detected confidence.
95% or no anomaly.
Found the steps, prepares the
results for app, user interfaces,
and automated station making systems.
These four steps capturing
pre-processing AI inference.
And post processing work
together continuously to
maintain real time performance.
Even when the camera faces variable
workloads, the architecture ensures smooth
processing without delays are frame drops.
This is what allows smart cameras to
react instantly and operate reliably
without depending on the cloud
energy efficiency optimization.
Now let's talk about energy
efficiency, which is one of the
most important parts of deploying
AI and battery powered iot cameras.
Energy devices cannot
afford to waste power.
And this slide explains how we
reduce energy usage by 60 to 70%
compared to the cloud-based systems.
Computational optimization,
the first area is competition.
Running AI models normally requires
a lot of CPU cycles, especially when
using 32 bit floating point operations.
But on edge devices, this would
drain the battery very quickly.
So we use techniques like
quantization and operator fusion.
Quantization reduce heavy 32 beat
operations to efficient eight.
BEAT operations Operator.
Operator fusion combines multiple
operations into a single step.
Together.
These reduced CPUs is approximately 60 to
70%, and when hardware accelerators like
NPUs or TPUs are available, they offer
four to 10 times better energy efficiency
per interference, memory optimization.
The second area is memory.
Most people think computation users most
power, but in reality, accessing DRAM
actually consumes a hundred to two times.
200 times more energy than
performing a math calculation.
To solve this, we compress models,
use efficient data structures, and
carefully manage memory buffers
so that data is reused instead
of repeatedly loaded from dram.
This greatly cuts down unnecessary memory
access and saves significant energy.
The final area is controlling the cameras.
Other components like sensors,
radios, and supporting hardware.
We don't keep everything running
at full power all the time.
Instead, we use smart scheduling.
The camera sensor reduces
power during low activity.
Wireless radio transmit
data only when needed.
AI interference happens more
frequently when motion is
detected and less often when this.
Seen as ideal by a, by adapting to
real world conditions, the system
saves a large amount of energy while
still delivering accurate results.
So overall, through this competition
optimization, memory efficiency, and
smart peripheral control, we achieve
massive reduction in energy usage.
This is what makes a GA practical
for long running I OT cameras that
need operate reliably for days or
even months without frequent charging
performance evaluation.
Now let's go over the
performance evaluation results.
This slide shows how well we optimize.
The neural network runs across
different hardware platforms.
And it highlights why a GA is
strong replacement for cloud-based
processing memory footprint.
This is the fast metric.
Our optimized model is extremely
lightweight, only around 600 KB
insights, even when we include runtime
buffers and intermediate ssars.
The total memory used is only
four to eight mb to put that.
Into perspective.
A typical edge device today comes with
one GB of ram, so our solution uses
a small fraction of that around 3%.
The small footprint is what allows low
cost boats like Raspberry Pi or entry
level iot chips to run advanced TA without
any memory appraiser, energy consumption.
Next, we look at how much energy.
Each frame requires during pre-processing.
Running AI models continuously
can run batteries quickly, but our
optimization significantly reduce
power use on a regular OM CPU.
Each frame uses 0.5 to 0.8 joles, but
when we use dedicated AI accelerators
like NPUs and TPUs, that number
drops to just a 0.1 to 0.2 jaws per
frame, almost five times improvement.
And if you compare this, a
cloud-based setup, when devices
must stream video continuously, the
energy difference is more dramatic.
Cloud streaming can consume up to
three jts per frame, meaning a GA
is more efficient for long running
deployments, bandwidth savings.
Finally, let's talk about bandwidth when
cameras, process videos on device itself.
The only spend send important
events are small summaries to the
cloud, not full video streams.
Cloud streaming usually needs
around 1.2, 1.8 MVPS per camera.
But with the LGA, we reduce
this number to 52 60.
52, 200 kps.
This is an 85 to 95
reduction in bandwidth usage.
This makes deployments practical, even
in rural areas, construction sites
or places with limited connectivity.
It also lawyers monthly data
costs and improve reliability.
So overall, the performance
evolution clearly shows the
benefits of our a GA approach.
These results confirm that realtime ai,
realtime EA on edge devices is not only
possible it is efficient, scalable,
and ready for real world deployment.
Let's look at some
application case studies.
These case studies show how technology
performs outside the lab in real world.
Environments with real challenges.
Smart Doorbell security.
Our first example is Smart Doorbell
Camera, built on Raspberry Pi three.
Even though this is an entry level
platform, the optimized AI model
performs extreme level by processing
video directly on the device.
We achieved 72% reduction in
bandwidth usage, 4.25 times
improvement in battery life.
Instant on device detection.
Better privacy since raw video
isn't not uploaded in case study
two, industrial defect detection.
This second case study is from an
industrial automation environment.
Factories often use dozens of
cameras to check the defects on
fast moving production lines.
In this prototype, 50 plus smart
cameras were deployed with LGA.
Each device could detect anomalies in
under a hundred milliseconds, which allows
system to catch defects immediately.
We also reduce the data being
transmitted by over 90%, which is
extremely important in factories where
network stability cannot be guaranteed.
This real time response is something
cloud processing simply cannot deliver.
The third example is smart home
security setup with multiple cameras.
In many homes, internet bandwidth
is limited and people also care
deeply about video privacy.
A GA solves both the challenges, the
systems analyze the video locally.
And since only essential alerts to
the cloud, this reduced streaming
cost, protects user privacy
and ensures the system works
even when internet is unstable.
These case studies clearly demonstrate
AGI is practical, scalable, and
ready for different, real different
industries future directions.
Now let's move on to what the
future looks like for a GI Systems.
The technology is evolving rapidly.
And the next steps will make
smarter devices even faster, more
private, and more intelligent.
Federated learning In the future, devices
will be able to learn from new data
without sending dry images to the cloud.
Instead, each device trends locally and
send only model updates, not videos.
This keeps data private while
improving overall accuracy.
This approach is perfect for home
cameras, healthcare devices, and any
systems where privacy is important.
Collaborative edge intelligence.
Another exciting direction is
device to device collaboration.
Imagine multiple cameras in a home
or a factory sharing the workloads.
If a, if one device is busy or
has low battery, another device
can take over the processing.
This creates a distributed intelligence
layer where devices support each other.
It makes the whole system
more reliable and efficient.
Next generation head hardware.
We expect more powerful NPUs,
TPUs, and specialist chiefs with
much higher performance per.
Devices will run larger AI models
without consuming more power.
This enable analytics like multi object
tracking, behavior prediction, and
even on device video summarization,
standardized application framework.
Finally, we expect platforms
that allow developers to build.
Once and deploy anywhere
these, this means yay.
Applications will run across
all types of hardwares from
doorbell cameras to industrial
robots with without major rework.
These advancements will help speed up
adoption and reduce development cost.
Conclusion.
To conclude a GA is not
just an enhancement.
It represents a complete shift in
how smart camera systems operate.
We are moving from cloud centered
intelligence to a world where
intelligence lives directly on the device.
Toward the presentation.
We have seen this approach gives
us major improvements, like
under 50 milliseconds, latency.
For real time processing works on
devices with little less 512 MBM
80% or more, reduction in bandwidth
usage, four to five times improvement
in battery life, high reliability,
even low connectivity environments.
These results show the A GA is practical,
efficient, and highly scalable.
As a final statement, the future is smart.
Camera is edge first.
With optimized AI models, efficient
hardware and intelligent software
architecture, we can unlock fast,
private, and reliable AI ware.
Thank you.
I'm happy to take any technical questions.