My name is Ram Krishna.
I'm working in a medical
as a solution architect.
Today I'm going to present a reactive to
pre predict to transform, transforming
medical device reliability through
Secure, secure I architecture.
Okay, so the traditional approaches
whenever healthcare oration typically
responds to the medical devices
failure after they occur in any
medical failures that is leading to the
downtime and the delayed diagnostics
and increase the operational cost.
So this rare two parum creates a
inefficiency in a resource allocation
and impacts the patient's care delivery.
So our vision is okay, is a data
driven predictive maintenance.
So that means, so the reactive
system so we'll fix that.
Any medical device values, whenever
it is phase, then we'll apply the fix.
And also it's a schedule maintenance.
Whereas our reactive processes, predictive
processes is a datadriven intervention
and also automated optimization.
So that means we're transforming
the react to responses to prior two.
So through IT enabled strategies
and anticipate failures before
they impact on clinical operations.
The Secure iot Architecture
Foundation is completely like
completed in three components.
One is cloud platform, and so
here we are using a very zero
trust security principles.
We are using MQ TT and HGTP protocols.
So these two protocols you'll use
the transfer the data from medical
devices to the cloud computing.
So then once, so we have, we transfer
the data, then we do the edge computing.
That means we'll apply the
local pre-processing to reduce
the transmission volumes while
detecting a critical anomalies.
And third one is HIPAA compliance.
So that means, so this is a
mutual transport layer, security
authentication with certificate
rotation and real time revocations.
So that pipeline of architecture
is in in five steps.
One is a device telemetry.
So that means we are continuously
monitoring operational parameters
from the diagnostics devices.
And local analysis and filtering to
identify the critical patterns and
anomalies in that, the edge processing.
And we securely transport the data from
transfer to the, from medical devices,
the cloud computing infrastructure,
using a security protocol that
is three TPS and MQD protocols.
And we'll store that in the time series.
So then we'll optimize the database
for the telemetry data and advanced
analysis for further processing.
And finally analytics engine.
So there we dub the my machine learning
models to generate predictive insights
and maintenance recommendations.
So the zero trust implementation
is a mutual TLS authentication
for all device communications.
So certificate rotation schedules
with the automated management.
So that means we will automatically
roll out the certifications on schedule
basis for the each medical device.
And real time revocations, that means
for the, any compromise credentials.
So that means if you feel like if
you suspect anything which is not
working, then we will revoke that
security certifications and under in
a real time revocations capabilities.
And last one is we also do the audit
trialing for the compliance reporting.
So whenever you make any changes
on the medical devices, and we
do have a documentation for the
further the documentation for the
auditing added trail for the further
the processing and reporting.
So the machine learning development
is the feature engineering.
So that means we'll transform the raw
telemetry data into meaningful predictive
indicators using a signal processing,
static statistical analysis, and
domain specific knowledge integration.
And also we have a class
imbalance handling.
So address the unique challenge of
rare failures, events in your medical
device, data sets through specialized
sampling and weighing techniques.
And explainable predictions.
So we develop the in interpretable
models that meets regulatory
requirements for software as a medical
device into a controlled healthcare
environment, continuous learning.
So that incorporated the
technicians feedbacks and adapt
to revolving the device behavior
patterns for further improvement
prediction accuracy over the time.
So the feature engineering processes is a
signal processing, so we will extract the
meaningful patterns from raw sensor data
through a frequency analysis, filtering
and transformation techniques and static
analysis drive key metrics including
trends, variance and correlation patterns
that indicate device health status.
And domain knowledge that is integrate
a clinical and engineering expertise
to identify the features which
proven diagnostic significances.
So the main key improvements are,
or optimize the resource location
through predictive analysis.
So based on the analysis, and we can
optimize the resource allocation for that.
Fixes and automatic ticketing
system integrates a maintenance
and workflow streamlines the
maintenance of the workflows.
So whenever device can use occurs,
our workflows will trigger to
create the automating of system
automated out the ticketing system.
And also we develop the
realtime dashboards.
So visualizations enable that
data driven decision making.
So that means we can predict, add
the based on the data visualizations
and so we develop the reports and
dashboards the stake, enhance the
stakeholder communication across the
clinical and the technical teams.
So that is the major key improvements
with benefits of this solution.
Okay.
So regulatory compliance framework.
So we also have a FDA requirements.
So address software as a medical
device, regulations with the
comprehensive validation and
verification protocols details.
Maintain a complete documentation
of all the system activities,
predictions and maintenance actions
for the compliance reporting.
And we also have a quality management,
so we'll integrate with the existing
quality management system framework to
ensure continuous co and accessibility.
So we implement the
workflow in the five steps.
One is the assessment.
In this section, what we'll do is we
evaluate the existing infrastructures
and identify the critical
devices for the iot integration.
And second bit is
architecture data design.
So we love the secure iot architecture
with the HIPA compliances and
the Zero trust principles.
Okay, so then pilot development
deploy the edge computing units and
establish a secure data pipelines
for the initial device plate.
So that means we will identify,
we will roll out this initially
only for the thousand devices and
not for the, we don't roll out for
the major clinicals and hospitals.
And then once we roll out the
solution, then we'll our model
training, we'll collect the tele
data and develop a predictive models.
With the validation protocols
and scale and optimize, expand to
full device fleet and implement
continuous learning mechanisms.
So the future innovations and reaches
directions is embedded diagnostics,
so meme sensors which resides in
the medical devices so that sensors
integrate directly into the device
for enhanced monitoring capabilities
and rail them health assessment.
Okay.
Based on that MIM sensor data, we
will do the assessments for each
medical device and federated learning.
So privacy preserving analytics
across distributed device plates
without a centralizing sensitive data.
And these still twin technologies.
So we develop the simulation
based on the maintenance planning,
using a virtual replicas for the
scenario testing and optimization.
So we have some simulators, exactly
a medical device, so where we
can use for the, for testing.
And we can see, we can capture the,
all the test scenarios and also you
can use for the training purposes.
And the success factor says
the stakeholder engagement
across the clinical, technical,
and administrative teams.
Okay.
Comprehensive to training programs
for maintenance personal and
clinicians, the clear communication
of benefits and measurable outcomes.
Phase rollout implementation
approach to minimum disruption.
Okay, so continuous feedback loops to
refine predictive models and workflows.
Okay?
These are the major success
factors with our solution.
Key takeaways for implementation is
security first, so we'll established
a robust zero trust architecture
with the P compliances before
collecting any patient adjustment
adjacent data from medical devices.
Start smaller scale smart.
So begin with the A pilot deployment.
As I mentioned, we roll out for the
small and local hospitals like, hundreds
and thousands on critical devices to
validate the models and demonstrate
value before enterprise rollout.
So then we can test for so
before rolling out, so we'll
demonstrate on the local clinicals.
MS continues learning that third one.
So every we year, we built the
feedback mechanisms that incorporate
technicians expertise and adopt models
to evolving device behavior patterns.
Okay.
And last one is focus on
operational integrations.
Ensure predictive insights translate into
a actionable workflows through automated
ticketing and decision support systems.
So as I mentioned, whenever device
value occurs, our workflows will
trigger, require automated ticketing
system and will use the two solution.
Based on the, model what we developed.
So our models will trigger and identify
the air predict to a solution to
the technicians for the, device fix.
So that is the end of my presentations.
If you have any questions feel
free to ask here, and thank you so
much for giving me the opportunity.