Hello everyone.
Welcome to the Con 42 Group, native
2025, and welcome to my session on
Ballerina, where I'm going to discuss
in detail about how Ballerina will help
you for the cloud native integrations.
So before starting the session,
let me introduce myself.
I'm a MA currently working as a
director and head of engineering
for the integration business unit.
Software development company specialized
in the API management integration
and identity and access management.
Before deep diving to the today's
topic, let's first understand
what are the problem, what is the
problem that we're trying to solve?
Most of the days most of the time if
you are coming from the development
background, the developers are busy with
the code and designing the applications,
and the DevOps team members and
others are busy with the deployment.
This store is not fully disconnected,
whether you are deploying it on-premise
a setup or in a cloud deployment
developers has to think about it and the
application design and all the aspects
of the application depends on that.
Definitely cloud native deployments
is much easier compared to on-premise
deployment, but at the same time.
It has more and more other
complexities, different challenges
that we had to consider during
the application design itself.
So the developer journey, as
well as the deployment aspects
are not totally disconnected.
So although developer has to worry
about the business logic and the
implementation part of the problem,
they have to think how they're going
to deploy their applications as well.
So cloud native deployment is like
conducting an orchestra with lot of
musicians and each musician or each
service play a beautifully, play a
beautiful piece of things on its own.
But if you don't have a proper
conductor that outcome will not be.
It'll become a noise.
So Kubernetes play a big role here to
seamlessly connect everything at the same
times when it comes to developers context,
ballerina helps a lot to reduce that
complexity of integrations and make sure
the integration, application development
as well as deployment is seamless.
So if we look at the challenges
in the cloud integrations nowadays
when we are moving to microservices
and smaller services, we had to
think about multiple such services.
It's not mono, it's that
we are developing nowadays.
So cloud integration means we had to
integrate with various services, APIs,
SaaS applications, data services,
things like that, and we need to
make sure they are working together.
Environments are highly
dynamic with containers.
They add more complexity.
Also the configuration overhead,
that is also bit of complex
because there are multiple services
and how we manage deployment
configurations, how we scale services.
And also on top of that monitoring and
other runtime related configuration
overhead is getting added.
So likewise, we had to
manage all these things.
Finally, security and compliance every
date of law, we need to make sure it's
secure and compliant to various protocols
and other things, because in the world
of integration, security and compliance
is something that we cannot forget.
So ballerina is a technology for
simplifying cloud native integrations.
I would say it's a technology
because it has many aspects on it.
So let's first look at what is riina.
Vina is cloud native.
Open source technology, which is
highly optimized for integration
based application development.
So it's developed by WS oh two
in 2016, and we released our
first version in February, 2022.
So it has a rich core system of different
services, data formats, rich types
system, and also set of connectors
to help with the integration story.
And also it has great.
Textual as well as graphical capabilities,
which I'll discuss in the upcoming slides.
It'll make, it's very efficient
and effective for the developers
to write the piece of code.
So this is a very high level
timeline on how Ballina has evolved.
It took time because we, it's a
full system along with the compiler
to compile the source code and
the rich ecosystem around that.
So what is the differentiation?
Ballerina provides, right?
Abstractions for data,
network, and concurrency.
So data is the heart of the
integration because at the end of
the day, what we are doing is we are
communicating data and we receive data.
We, send data.
And also we need to represent data.
Data can be in many different formats,
shapes, and we need to manipulate data.
So that's a fundamental
thing in the integrations.
And also integration
means it's in the network.
So communicating data across
different clients and services with
various protocols is mandatory.
And finally, concurrency.
So the last thing because.
Integrations are, integration
applications are inherently concurrent.
That means we need to make sure
concurrency safety protocols are,
or mechanisms are available in place
for developers to develop concurrent
applications easily and effectively.
So Ballerina provides abstractions
for these three different layers,
and I'll go through some of them
in detail in the upcoming slides
and I'll show you how it can.
Help the developers to
develop the applications.
So the first part of the thing is
stories, the development, and also how
we are going to maintain the application
since Meina is open source language.
Open source technology, I would
say, and also we can categorize
it as a programming language.
First of all.
I'll come to that part later.
Because it's a language, because of its
language nature, it can work with V Code
id and we can commit a source code into
GitHub and we can use CSC CD pipelines
to deploy it or have a CS CD pipeline
on your own tools, and we can deploy it.
In Docker, Kubernetes, or
whatever the platform you want.
And finally, during the runtime, you
can monitor, observe using existing
tools, support open telemetry, and you
can connect with the existing tools
like J Grafana all analysis stuff.
So that is the ecosystem comes
with the familiar tool set.
So if you are.
One problem in language because
Ballina, we can classify it as
a problem in language as well.
It has its own syntax, own language
specification, and also own compiler.
So you might wonder because it's
a new language, how easy or how
difficult it is to learn as a language.
So it's a cc plus family language and if
you're familiar with any of the existing
c family language, like cc plus Java
go it's very easy to learn ballina.
And only thing is like you had to learn
a couple of new abstractions or new
constructs that we are providing along
with the language to make it easy.
So this is how we write the first
ballerina package you have to
use Be New Command, and it'll
generate the ballerina package.
It's like any other programming language.
You can simply create a ballerina package.
So once you create that,
you'll create a, it'll create
a folder with couple of files.
So the most important files here
are the main bell file, where the
ballerina source file resides, and
the Ballina Toal file, which identify
a given package as a ballerina.
You directory as a ballerina package.
Now let's look at what are the key
differentiators of this language
and how it differs from typical
programming language or ecosystem.
So first thing is the graphical view.
For every program or every
integration that you are writing
using Ballina, you have equivalent.
Piece of source code as well as a diagram.
So that means we maintain pro code
and low code parity and it happens
automatically by the initial studio
plugin or the toolkit that we are having.
You don't have to do anything, so that
means you can write the program in the
source code side if you are pro code
developer and if you are more towards
low-code developer and you want to deal
with the diagram not to mess with the.
Programming side of the code,
you can add constructs or do
everything from the diagram side.
And also not only that because it's
coming with set of full tool set, it has
certain other helper kind of tools to make
it easy for the integration developers.
So service designers are
that you don't have to write.
Code from scratch, or you don't
have to design everything by
diagram from step by step.
There are service designers kind
of thing where you can easily
design the services HGTP services
or a services, GraphQL services.
And so you can, it provides form like
view so that you can define the HG
GTP methods you want and parameters.
It can be part parameters
or something else.
URL parameters, and it can
provide advanced properties that
define the responses and so on.
And same goes with GraphQL when it
comes to graph, where we are mostly
dealing with data, set of data which
are interrelated with each other.
So that view is properly
provided by the ballerina.
Visual designer and it's very
easy to design such applications.
And also data transformations
has very comprehensive data
transformation capabilities.
That is what we call data map.
So you can map the data
in the visual mode.
You can, this is the visual data map.
And also you can edit the expressions
in between because most of the
time it is not one to one mapping.
We have to do some calculations or some.
Processing in between before we
map data from one field to another.
So Bellina has that capability
as well, and also debugging.
It is very important at the
developer level how we debug
the applications because it has
both low code and code parity.
We have the debugging capabilities, both
in the diagram level as well as the source
code level, given that Bella is language.
It has all the debugging capabilities
that a normal language is having.
Apart from that, we have the
diagram debugging capabilities.
You can add a debug point in the
diagram node and debug your application.
And also everything comes under one roof.
So these are the various protocols that
integration developers has to deal with.
And we have the support, first class
support for all of these services and
client types and services and clients
are part of the language itself.
So defining a service or
defining a client is really easy
and connectors and templates.
When it comes to connecting with
other applications or integrations,
connectors plays a big role.
It can be connectors for various
network protocols, or it can
be databases, or it can be SARS
applications, messaging platforms.
Likewise, we have set of a huge set
of connectors, great set of connectors
to connect with all of these things.
So these are the list of.
Central, which is our
repository management system.
You can see all of these connectors
and also we have persist capabilities.
This is more or less a kind of
diaphragm capability where you can
see 80 D relationship, a d. When you
are working with per persist, when
you are persisting data, this is
very familiar for the diagrams in the
database world, but somewhat similar
to what we are visualizing here.
When you have set of data that you
want to persist in the database or
some other data persistent layer,
this capabilities really helpful.
And also there are many
other integration tools.
I'll not go through the
details of each of them.
These are kind of EDI tools, pro
of tools, GraphQL tools, because.
Most of the time what we are getting
is a contract in different protocol.
For example, open API specification is
a contract that we are getting so ball
and now with using this open API tool,
we have the capability to generate.
Service and clients based on
that open API specification
by executing a single command.
So that flexibility is there for
many protocols, metadata types.
So that is very easy.
You can generate the ballerina code
automatically with these tools.
And also there are in AI capabilities,
we have in inbuilt IS system,
what we call ballerina, copilot.
It helps you to generate
the code automatically.
It acts like a built in.
Companion to pair programming.
You can give the input in the
natural language and it'll
generate the code for you.
And also we have automatically auto
map capability to map the data.
From one type to another, automatically
using the auto map feature of
the data map that will help you.
Let's say you have two records, two
data types to map with large number
of fields, and it's not that easy.
So the auto mapping feature
will help you there.
It analyze existing fields
there, data types and context.
You can provide additional context
if needed to help the assistant to
understand what sort of mapping you
are doing with additional calculations,
and then it'll do the job for you.
So that is about the development part,
and have you maintain the source code.
And let's look at a quick demo,
which I was already developed.
So this is about Music for
Mother, which is a rest service.
In simple terms, what it is doing is
it provides a capability for a user
to get a playlist, which from Spotify,
a music playlist, which is matching
for the given weather condition.
For example, if it is a sunny weather,
you want to listen certain type of
playlist, or if it is rainy weather, you
want to listen to different set of music.
Likewise, you can.
Check the current weather in a
given location and map the weather
to a given mode, and finally get
the music list for that given
mode and it'll return to the user.
So this very simple integration,
which involves a multiple APIs in the
weather, API, as well as this Spotify.
So that is the one that
I'm going to discuss here.
So this is already implemented
application in ballerina.
This is Ballina plugin, which
is installed in VS code, and
the application is developed.
I wanted to highlight a
couple of things here.
This is the design view where you can
see in high level the services and
various endpoints that you are working.
So it'll give you very high level
understanding of how many services
you have, how many resources you
have within each of these service.
And what are the end
points that it is talking?
Likewise.
And when you click here, you can
see the service designer, which
I talked earlier, so you can add
more and more resources here.
This is service resource which
allows you to add more resources.
You can add parameters, but
if you don't add anything, you
can simply add a resource here.
And once you go back to the
service designer, you can see
another resource is getting added.
So all these things in the diagram
level, but at the same time, if you
go to the source file, you can see
the mapping source code of that.
So this is a service
in ballerina, which is.
Listen on a given port service in
Ballina is part of the language syntax
itself, so it's very easy to develop.
A service for ballerina services
can be of many different types.
As you can see here, it, once it is
attached to different protocol listener,
it'll become a service of that protocol.
So this is.
This one is HT DP listener, which is
listening on Port 90 90, and it has
three resources to accept incoming
requests, all luggage resources.
One fundamental principle in
ballerina is we model all of these
things, even whether it's a network
invocation, network resource function.
It's like a normal function which
has name of the function which is
getting mapped to the resource path.
And input parameters and return types.
So developers has to focus
only on the business logic.
And it is very easy for the developers
to stay out of the complexity
of the network, and that is the
abstraction that we are talking about.
And connect seamlessly or develop
the business logic effectively.
And same with the client.
Defining a client in is real easy.
This is a client, Spotify
client that we have created.
This is how we are defining client.
In the syntax level.
You can provide relevant
parameters, URLs, and other things.
And since this is HTTP client,
you can in HT P. Get post
resources using this client.
And also the other thing is type system.
This is Ballina record, which is
the record representation, which
is a canonical format in Ballina
where we can represent the data.
Like if it is Jml, whatever it is, we
can represent it using the record types.
And even in the visual
view, we can see the types.
Effectively in the types view.
So if you open it up, you can see there
are multiple types and the diagram
itself is showing the relationship
between the different types.
If you look at the source code
of the types, it is not easy to
understand these interrelation.
The relationships and other things.
It's more like a er, if you're familiar
with the database, so you can see the
connecting to the items and it has owner.
Whether data has current information
and it's associated with the
location, likewise we can see
all the fields and how they are
interconnecting in the type suite.
So all these graphical tools and
graphical views gives you a very good
understanding about your application, and
it is really helpful when, visualizing
and maintaining the application.
So other thing I mentioned is the
visual diagram capability and the
parity that we are maintaining.
So every piece of code that we are
writing, there's a equivalent diagram.
So that can be a flow
diagram or a sequence diagram
depending on the invocation.
So this is the same.
Thing that I showed in the demo.
Basically, when we are explaining
over application to someone,
we are using sequence diagram.
So the same flow you can see in the
diagram itself because integration
applications means it's always
connecting to different endpoints
and get the results and so on.
So this flow view.
In the flow view, you can
actually edit, you can add many
different constructs and so on.
Let's say you add a if condition
for the simplicity I'm adding.
Making the condition as true.
You can see the if condition is got added
with two parts to and false, and if you
go to the source code, you can see the
same thing got added to the source code.
That's why I'm saying we are
maintaining the parity between
the source and the diagram.
So whether you are developing it
in the source level or the diagram
level you can continue in either way.
So when it comes to the
deployment of ballin applications,
there are multiple ways.
One way is you can build a
self-contained executable Java file
and deploy it anywhere that you want.
So simply you can issue Bell
bill command and deploy it.
So if we go to this application, I can
simply issue bell bill command here.
And it'll compile the source code
and it'll generate the artifacts.
That's one way I'll clean the artifacts
here to proceed with the next steps.
And the other thing is code to
cloud aspect, which is the main
topic of today's discussion.
So it allows people, developers to
write code without thinking about the
complexity of the deployment platform.
So it simplifies a lot
about the development.
Experience as well as how the
developers has to think about.
Because usually when we have to de deploy
our application in Kubernetes kind of
environment, we had to build the docker
images and we had to write Docker files.
And yamal files in the Kubernetes
world, these a bit, two complex tasks.
You had to understand
all these complexities.
But in Ballina we have the
capability to, build the DO or
Kubernetes artifacts easily.
Before doing that, let's
quickly run this application.
I'm using Bell Run command
to run the application.
You can see it's now running and we
can try it using the try tool available
within the language itself or tool itself.
You can provide a location here, let's
say for example, testing and you can.
You can see the current weather
of INE is sunny and you will get
the list of play playlist from
the Spotify to match with that.
Let's say let's pay the
location to London, maybe.
You can see it's different with the
condition at and different playlist.
So this is how easily you can test and
run the application locally as well.
And then it's a matter of deploying
it to the right environment.
So to build the docker artifacts,
the first thing that you have to do
is issue the be command command with
the relevant artifact type you need.
For example, let's first look at
how we can create the Docker file.
The existing artifacts and then
you have to show bell build minus,
minus cloud with the docker option.
Then you can see to compiler
the, compile the application
and build in the Docker image.
Once you go to the Target folder,
you can see the Docker file log image
Docker file with the dependencies.
And then the next thing is how we
can deploy it into the Kubernetes.
So when it comes to the Kubernetes
platform, usually you have to write
the Lam files manually, but in
Ballerina you can do it by issuing.
Let me clean the artifacts first
and let's issue command again, bell
build cloud with the parameter As the
Kubernetes, you can see it is compiling
and generating the Kubernetes artifacts.
Once it is done, you can
see the commands to execute.
And you can see the target files
the Yamal files is generated.
Lemme open it up.
So the generated yamal file is reading the
port and other information from the source
file, and also it comes with the default.
Defaults imposed by the compile
extension for various CPN memory values.
And if you want to change them,
you can add a configuration file to
the folder and get them replaced.
So the next thing is how we can run it.
You can see the commands
run it here itself.
First, let's see whether
the dokey image is created.
Let's issue the Docker images command.
You can see the Docker image
is created 56 seconds ago.
Let's issue this command to deploy
this in the Kubernetes cluster.
So the service is created.
Deployment is created.
So if you issue the Kubernetes
command month to CTL, get deployments.
You can see the deployment is created
and let's expose it as a service.
We are not port using this command.
Now
the service is exposed.
Let's see the group ct.
Let's use the group.
CTL.
Get service command to see the service.
You can see this service is there.
Which exposed with this point.
So likewise, without writing
any piece of Yammer file, you
can deploy to the Kubernetes.
So same applies to other
serverless functions like AWS
Lamb, Azure functions as well.
We have the similar capability to do that.
So that's the deployment part.
So thats, or that fills the
gap between the developers and.
Deployment aspects.
And finally, the operation part.
I will not go through the detail,
but it, we have the capability
to observe the applications.
It can be metrics, tracing, login
activities, and we can connect
to different existing tools and
platform and monitor like this.
And that's about my session today.
So finally, I would like to say
one thing about Ballina community.
We are open source project and
we are conducting many community
events, tech talks, trainings, unity
programs, and also we are participating
in major conferences and events.
So you can visit to Ballina official
website, Ballina io, and you can
download ballerina, try out Ballina,
and you can even contribute to ballerina
because it's an open source language.
Framework and also you can get certified
and you can use, become a user of it.
We have a community around us who
can help you when you have problems,
join the discord and flow as well.
Thank you very much for joining with this
session today and would like to, I would
like to see you in the Ballina community.
Thank you.