Hi.
Good morning, good
afternoon, good evening.
I am going to talk about observability
in Kubernetes, unlocking the power of
EBPF, so pretty honored to be here.
So let's start with this presentation.
How it's going to be helpful.
Pretty sure about that.
It's an observability in Kubernetes.
A cha a key challenge in
modern container environments.
So first, and first, I am Alex Alejandro
Mercado Rice and Bar in Mexico City.
I am the Bobs.
I am E-V-P-F-M two CS for sure.
So I would like to.
Start this presentation with this
phrase that this observability
is another data problem.
So I went to a conference and I got this
phrase that I think is pretty accurate.
So the problem is how to get this
data, how to clean this data, how
to get advantage of this data.
So observability is a data problem.
That arises when trying to understand
complex systems to effectively observe
complex systems, you need to solve
classic challenges of managing large
scale teal time sensitive data.
It's about that this data management
challenges must be addressed while
maintaining the performance needed for
real time operational decision making.
This talk is focused on Kubernetes,
but EVPF, it's a wide range, can be
applied to a wide range of technologies,
but I heavily use Kubernetes, so
this is my main topic of interest.
So Kubernetes provides
a high level abstracted.
View of container
orchestration, as you may know.
So Kubernetes is a pre brief introduction.
Of course, Kubernetes hides low
level system details from application
developers and heavily relies on core
Linux functionalities underneath.
Kubernetes inner workers are in
their inner workings, are deeply
rooted in the powerful functionality
of the Linux operation system.
So what is EBPF?
Maybe you have heard about EVPF.
It's quite famous now that
actually it's not a new technology.
It's can, has been around too many
years, but it's, I can say that no
nowadays is taking new dimensions.
So EVPF is a kernel virtual machine that
allows you we can think about EVPF as
a kernel virtual machine that allows.
Due to run sandboxes programs,
and this is quite important
because it is going to be safer.
We, we are going to talk a little
more about that in a second.
So allows due to run sandbox programs
internal space without changing kernel
source code or loading kernel models.
So it provides the benefits
of programmability.
Without the risk of
traditional current models.
Yep.
Yeah.
This is going to be like the advantage.
So have you ever used EVPF?
Maybe yes.
But you didn't notice because
maybe it is like a low visibility
technology, but it's heavily used in.
Many application and companies of course.
So eeb, pfs, sobi, and applications.
We can say that.
Building on the previous slide
overview of Eeb PS, we can say that
EVPF has become OBI and versatile.
It's evident driving natural
and ability to interact with
various NEL objects have enabled.
To find a wide range of applications,
for instance, EBPF Powers, load
Balancing and DDoS, the denial of
service protection on major website.
So it ensures reliable
and scalable performance.
It's also being used to create data
statistic apps on Android devices.
Providing users with value valuable
insights in the Kubernetes ecosystem.
EBPF is at the heart
of network management.
We are going to see in a few moments,
tools like cel, leveraging it for advance
monitoring and networking capabilities.
Yeah, so the Kubernetes ecosystem and
EVPF may, maybe you have heard of one of
these applications that we can see a lot
of applications moving in this space.
Security networking and service mesh.
So moving to the service mesh
landscape, we can find Kuma and
Helium service mesh, both of.
W, which leverage EVPF to
enhance service to service
communication and provide robust
observability and security features.
For system security, we can
find Falco, TeraGo and Tracy.
These tools have emerged as a
powerful solutions for runtime,
security monitoring and policy
enforcement in Kubernetes environments.
So maybe you have heard about them.
If you are using Kubernetes, these
tools can detect and prevent a wide
range of security threats from unitized
access to system level anomalies.
We can mention this is just one
of many this is open source.
We can mention Pixie.
This project utilizes EBPF to offer
deep visibility and insights into the
performance and behavior of Kubernetes
applications and infrastructure.
P'S EVPF base in instrumentation provides.
Comprehensive observability enable
developer and availability engineers
to 25 and resolve issues quickly.
Of course, there are many other tools, as
I said, in the proprietary and open source
sites in both sides of the technology.
So as we have seen EV pfs has
become a transformative technology.
In Kubernetes, in the Kubernetes
ecosystem, empowering users to enhance
networking, service, mesh security,
and observability, of course, within
their containerized environments.
This, I think that showcases the
variability and power of VPPF.
So we are going to send in
this next slide, so yeah,
to talk about the power of.
To talk about the power of
EV pfs, it's about that.
It's about how we run these programs.
So building on the previous slides
overview of how the Kubernetes
ecosystem ES EVPF, we can say that
the power why are we using EVPF
in these cases, scenarios and.
I align it to why many companies are
using EBPF is because EBPF is a powerful
Linux cardinal technology that extends
the classic BPF, the Berkeley package
filter that is, was done many years.
So it allowed programs to be
attached to various kernel projects.
Including key proofs, trace
points, and net network schedulers.
So this gives developers and system
administrations administrators
unprecedented visibility and
control over the system Behavior.
I can say that EBPF programs
can observe and modify the
behavior of the Linux carload.
In real time.
Imagine that.
So providing a level of access and
observability previously unattainable,
this makes E-B-P-F-A crucial technology.
So it is a major player, I can say for
enhancing network performance security
observability within the Kubernetes
ecosystem, as we saw in previous slide.
So moving forward, we will explore the
unique position of the kernel space
and YVPF ability to operate within
this privilege domain is so impactful,
so well, as you may know, we have
the kernel space and the user space
if you come from this background.
If not, don't worry.
We are going to.
Get deeper in into this explanation.
The kernel space is where the core of
the operation operating system resides.
This is a highly privileged and
critical component, as you may know,
as it manage access to the systems
system, physical resources such as
memory disks, and the net worth.
So the kernel exposes the resources
in abstracted forms like files,
sockets, and processes, providing an a
standardized interface for applications
to interact with the hardware.
This separation of concerns
between the kernel and user space.
Applications is a fundamental design
principle of modern operation systems.
So we will explore the distinction
between kernel space and user space
and how application must interface with
the kernel to access system resources.
Oops.
The Cornell expose these resources in
abstraction ledgers, as I said, such
as files, sockets, and processes.
Now let's turn our intention to the,
to the user space.
Just let me change the slide.
Yeah, so the user space, which is the
domain where application processes run.
In, in, so in the user space,
application processes have access
to the resources provided by the
kernel, but they cannot directly
interact with the physical hardware.
So this is like a pretty big
difference between the spaces.
All access to resources must go
through the kernel, which act,
act as an intermediary between
the user space and the hardware.
This separation concerns between
the kernel and user space is a
fundamental design principle of modern
operational system operation systems,
and it's essential for maintaining
stability, security, and efficiency.
So how do we do that.
We are going to explore
system calls or system calls.
So system calls or calls are the primary
interface between the kernel and user
space, allowing application to request
the kernel to perform a variety of tax.
However, these system calls
come at a cost system calls.
I can say they're quite expensive
operations requiring hundreds or even
thousands of CPU cycles to complete.
This is because they required
transitioning between the user space and
nel between the user and Cardinal modes.
Which involves flu chain, the C,
the CPU, catchy saving and restoring
registers potentially other overhead.
The high cost of system calls is an
important consideration for application
design and performance optimization.
So developers should strive to minimize
the number of system calls where possible.
Batch or combine them.
So this will help to reduce
overall overhead and improve
the application efficiency.
So looking ahead the next slide, we'd
explore some options for applications
that require new kernel features, such as
implementing the functionality directly
in the kernel or asking the kernel to
send all relevant data to the application.
So understanding these trade offs
will be crucial for designing
high performance scalable systems.
So you can see at this slide
the cost of system calls.
As I said this, you have
to take care about that.
This, these trade up.
The kernel space and
user space trade offs.
Building on our previous discussion
of the cost of the system calls,
we now turn to the trade offs
between implementing new features
in the kernel versus in user space.
So applications may offer, require
new kernel features to support
their needs and maybe you are going
to ask what kind of new features.
So it just can be new network
protocols, advance load,
balance, the algorithms, traffic
redirection for sidecar containers.
I dunno, it's just a couple of examples.
So generally there are
two main options for.
Implementing these new features
so we can ask the kernel to handle
everything for the application.
For example, sending all the internal
traffic to the application to implement a
new protocol or maybe this approach well,
but this approach is costly in terms of,
or very expensive in terms of performance.
We have the second alternative
that is to implement the new
feature directly in the kernel.
Of course, this allows for more
efficient and optimized implementation.
Implementation, but it requires
close collaboration between the
application and the kernel developers.
So it's not that easy.
It's not that easy thing I can say.
So the decision to
implement in the kernel.
Our user space involves carefully
waiting the trade off between performance
flexibility and development complexity.
So take a look of these
cartoons that are hilarious.
By the way I'm going to share the
slides, so don't worry if you want
to take a look after this talk, but.
It's going to be public available,
so yeah, that's the problem.
If, the colonel is controlled by
a committee, so it can take, I can
say a year to, to make a change
because, it's pretty important.
So everybody must agree.
And and again, when you get
the new release, maybe this is.
Not useful anymore for your application.
So having this new approach of eeb PF
based development, but you can have a new
feature or capability in a couple of days.
So this is quite, quite a fun phone.
So moving forward.
Kernel programming with EVPF, is we
can do or build this or develop this
program with c it is the main language,
but also you can use roast or but
it's like in constrain it is not like.
The full C version that we
currently own it's limited.
So EBPF programs are load directly into
the kernel, allowing them to interact
with the core system at low level.
It's not assembly but we are
allowed to interact with the
core system at the low level.
These programs can be attached to
various barriers or many events such as
receivable, net network packet packets,
or packages or calling kernel functions
and other system level activities.
So the E-E-B-P-F program is executed
for each occurrence of detached band.
En enable you to monitor, manipulate,
or filter these in real time.
So this powerful integration with
the kernel is a key strength of A
BPF, but also cause some risks, which
we will discuss in the next slide.
One question that is.
Very common is that if EBPF is dangerous
we have we need to understand potential
risk and how to use this powerful tool
responsibly while EBPF does provide
access to the kernel internal is,
it's not in the inherently dangerous.
Remember about the sandbox?
But the key is to be mindful of how
you utilize this capability as you
can, as you see here, the way or how
you use it, it can be dangerous so
concerns around EBPF often stem from
the fact that it allows code execution
in a highly privileged kernel content.
How, however, by default administrative
privileges are required to
load eeb EBPF programs, which
helps mitigate unitized access.
That said, the potential for
meat use is real reals, for real.
For example, you could attach a
an E-E-V-P-F program to all kernel
function or block the entire
network, or all system calls this is.
I, I don't know.
Why do you want to do that?
But it can be done.
So it's important to strike a
balance as A BPF can also make
the kernel more resilient, making
it harder to crash by mistake.
So the developer is
responsible for using EBPF.
Judiciously, I can say with
a deep understanding of its
capabilities and limitations as
we will see on the next slide.
The Kubernetes ecosystem, this is
slide, is increasingly leveraging EVPF
to enhancing networking monitoring.
And security in container
based environments.
By leveraging EBPF in a careful and
controlled manner, we cannot lock its
vast potential while mitigating risks.
So you can see this we have already
talked a little bit about cilium,
but we have other use cases.
So yeah.
Cilium is one of the biggest or
more important projects in the
Cloud Native Computing Foundation.
So it's a networking project that
leverage EVPF to provide dynamic
network control and visibility, I
can say for container basis systems.
Looking ahead, we will explore
how another Kubernetes tool.
Like WPO scope, employee CBPF to
accurately track TCP connections between
containers and what's the point of that?
It's offer valuable insight.
So many observability tools or
platforms or solutions are using it.
This is a little bit more about cilium.
Which is very famous of
course, based on EBPF.
Maybe you have heard
about web wave of scope.
It's about tracking TCP connections, so it
also leverage EBPF technology to provide
the talent insight into the network
activity, which in a Kubernetes clusters.
If you ask or wonder if I can use the
VPF along with other tools, of course
you can integrate it with, we're going
to talk a little more about that.
But of course you can use any
backend, maybe Prometheus,
maybe graph, you name it.
Met in this case, WaPo scope
uses EBPF to track TCP connection
between containers accurately.
By attaching A BPF programs
to current level proofs.
So WaPo scope can observe and report
on the network traffic, offering
valuable information for troubleshooting
and performing optimization.
So looking ahead, as we explore the
potential of EVPF and Kubernetes,
we will see how this technology
can be applied to collect detailed.
Per boat or per container network
statistics enable application defined
sandboxing and even audit cube, CTL
accept sessions further expanding
observability and control capabilities,
which in the Kubernetes ecosystem.
But before that we can see
another potential EBPF use cases.
It's this because of, based on
the EBPS, flexibility allows for
a wide range of applications from
granular network monitoring to
find grain security controls.
So one key use cases is PO and
container level network Statistic.
So by attaching EVPF program to see
groups, we can collect detailed purpo
or prayer container network statistic.
So this way we can provide deeper
insight into resource utilization
and potential bottlenecks.
So be pretty sure that we
are going to hear more about
EBPF solutions new use cases.
This is for sure I can guarantee.
Another innovative application is
applied LSM, with all of this movement
about ai, we are going to see applied
application applied on LSM, which
allows unprivileged applications to
build their own sandboxes and restrict
their own actions using the VPF.
This enable enhancing security
and isolation with the need
for elevated privileges.
So this is one of the key advantage.
So we, in the kuber talking again
about the Kubernetes systems.
We can audit QCTL exec sessions,
recording a login, the exact
sequence of comments executed
during these interactive sessions.
So this improves security
and accountability, which
in the Kubernetes clusters.
As EVPF continues to evolve,
we can expect to see even more
groundbreaking applications that
pushes the boundaries of what's
possible in the Kubernetes ecosystem
and unlocking new possibilities for
observability, security and performance.
Yeah I am repeating a lot.
This word, security networking.
Observability because right now there are
the main use cases, but for sure we are
going to see more and more eventually.
So as a conclusion, if you want
to take something from this talk,
I want to say that about them or
remark, the powerful combination of
Kubernetes and EVPF, the ability of
EVPF to dynamically attach to kernel
objects and execute custom programs.
Execute custom programs provides
in parallel visibly visibility
and control, visibly and control
of anything, because we have the,
this visibility and control are the
Linux kernel level, so we can enable
Kubernetes tools to enhance networking,
monitoring, and now ING capabilities.
For instance, we can use EVPF to collect
detailed per part, per container network.
A side card network statistics
provide valuable insights
into the network behavior.
What else?
Maybe additionally, A BPF based
landlock LSM allows some privilege
application to, with their own sandboxes.
And restrict their own actions
in enhancing the security of
their Kubernetes environment.
Furthermore, EBPF programs can be used
to record and log the exact sequence
of comments executed during QCTL exec
sessions so you can know or enable robust
auditing capabilities, governance and.
Who is doing what, or performing
activities is important of not just
big company event, small, medium
companies needs to know and to have this
governance visibility and transparency.
So EPF is giving us, given us this
capabilities, so as EVPF continues
to evolve, we can expect to.
See even more in innovative applications
that push the boundaries of what's
possible in the Kubernetes system,
locking new possibilities for
observability security a performance
between container based systems.
So just to conclude the next
slide, we explore the integration
of Open Telemetry and EVPF.
Like I, I think that this
a winning combination.
And maybe you are asking how or
what's the point of using both
technology and think about it.
In the OI model open Telemetry
works on layer six and seven.
So it's more about the application.
So the data that is
collect is more about them.
Layer six and seven, as I said, and EBPF
is on the one and layer one and two.
The correlation of the information of
the logs, it's going to be actually
there are a couple of projects
also under development about this
combination of correlation of data.
So it's going to be.
About bringing the boat
of these two world.
So yeah it's not one or another.
I think it's going to be the best
of the boat technology, so yeah.
So this integration will enable
advanced use cases such as those
distributed tracing metrics, collection,
logging, while benefiting from the
performance flexibility of EVPF.
And as I said the metrics
collected in the application.
More visibility, more data, and
more insights that we are going to
get from these 2 1 2 technologies.
So this integration will enable
advanced usage case and Kubernetes
also well in the Kubernetes systems.
So
last but not least.
I just want to conclude my
presentation with this list of
recommended reading readings.
If you wonder where to go from here
this list of recommendations will
help you to explore EBPF in that.
So this includes the Eeb PF
compiler collections, which provide
a set of eeb PS based tools.
And examples for working with
this power field technology.
There, there is also a video that
I like pretty much about Brenda,
Greg is I can say an expert in the
field that provides an overview
of EVPS capabilities and cases.
And of course you can explore the ZI
project, how the ZI projects leverage.
EBPF or networking and security
and you can find a lot of
resources on the internet.
And of course in the EBPF foundation,
they have a lot of resources,
lot of tutorials and blocks.
So exploring these resources, we
gain a comprehensive understanding
of EBPF and its diverse
application and why it's taking.
The word by the storm.
Yeah, I think that at itself for me.
So this is my contact.
I am going to be around
if you want to reach me.
Please add me to LinkedIn.
And yeah, that's it.
Thank you very much for
listening to me and have fun
with this with EVPF technology.
Bye-bye.