Hello.
Good day everyone.
I'm very working as a senior
resident computer program with Search
Technology Solutions here in us.
So here I am today to present
my ideas on emergency response
using AI driven cloud computing,
robotics, and predictive analysis.
With all this being said let
me start my presentation.
So before getting into the actual
presentation, I would like to first
provide you some insights on what are
the present challenges that we are
facing with the options that we have
with the traditional emergency responses.
So here I would like to
emphasize on two points.
The first one being the
growing disaster intensity.
So when I say growing disaster intensity.
I am more emphasizing on the climate
change that accelerated the frequency and
severity of national disasters worldwide.
So the traditional emergency response
systems build on legacy infrastructure and
manual coordination struggle to keep pace
with the speed and scale of modern crisis.
And that being said, these conventional
approaches rely heavily on human
decisions and soil communication
channels and reactive rather
than being proactive measures.
So creating dangerous gaps in
response times and resource
allocation with this existing options.
So the first one being
growing disaster intensity.
The second one is
systematic vulnerabilities.
So when I say systematic vulnerabilities,
they are like more of the fragmented
data sources preventing unified situation
awareness and slow information, limited
predict to capabilities and inadequate.
Cross jurisdictional coordination
mechanisms and also some
communication bottlenecks.
So these are a couple of issues that
we are facing with current day options
with respect to the emergency response.
Let's start with a new patterning
of safety and security operations.
So here when I say a new paradigm,
it's more of integration of artificial
intelligence with cloud computing,
robotics, and predictive analytics.
Which represents a fundamental shift in
how safety and security operation systems
that is SOS functions during emergencies.
And by unifying disparate technologies
into cohesive frameworks, we create the
system cap capable of processing vast
data streams and predicting disaster
trajectories and automating critical
decisions and deploying resources with
unprecedented precision and speed.
So now for this speed and to achieve
this strength, so I would like
to concentrate more on three core
technologies, which actually are
powering our intelligence response.
That is power lifting
our intelligent response.
The first one being machine learning.
So the pattern recognition
algorithms that the machine
learning analyzes using historical.
Disaster data to predict event
likelihood, severity, and
optimal intervention strategies.
And the next one is visual deep learning.
When I say visual deep learning, it's more
about the computer vision, the systems
process, like the satellites are providing
as the imaginary, sorry, imagery and the
drone footages and surveillance speeds
to assess damage and identify hazards.
And the next one being NLP.
That is natural language
processing here in NLP.
We use engines that extract action
level intelligence from emergency calls
and from, say, some social media and
other news channels using the filtering
signal from noise during the crisis.
So that being said I also want to
emphasize on transforming fragmented
data into actionable intelligence.
Here we are using three concepts.
The first one is data collection, AI
processing, and actionable insights.
These three actually transform
the fragmented data into
an actionable intelligence.
So first one, as I said,
is data collection.
So with data collection we more rely
on the satellite imaginary imagery,
the IOT sensors, the social media,
and some emergency communications.
So coming to AI processing be
more to utilize the real time data
pattern detection, threat assessment,
and some prediction models.
And the last one being
actionable insights.
So here in actionable insights sorry.
If we use some resource deployment,
evacuation roads and situational
awareness and decision support.
So using all these three
intelligent actionable items we can.
Converge multiple data streams, each with
different formats, update frequencies
at reliable levels and present both
technical and operational challenges.
And also, AI systems must harmonize these
inputs, validate information accurately.
And this being said, let's go to the
next slide where I want to showcase
the cloud native architecture.
Wherein I have utilized serverless
and continuous platforms, these two.
And let's get started
with the architecture.
So when I say serverless and content,
continuous platforms still mostly I'm
talking about cloud native architectures,
which enable emergency response systems
to scale dynamically during crisis and
leveraging serverless functions for
efficient data stream processing without
any infrastructure management overhead.
Okay.
And coming to the content rights
platforms so here, when I say content
rights platforms, it's more likely
about Kubernetes which ensures us high
availability through automatic failover,
load balancing, and multiple regional
deployment, and also guaranteeing
the operational continuity even
when the local infrastructure fail.
So considering these two platforms.
So we can also leverage the rapid
elastic scaling using automatic resource
allocation during demand spikes and
geographical redundancy wherein multiple
region deployment for disaster resilience.
And the last one being cross
jurisdictional continuity wherein seamless
data sharing between agencies and regions.
So this is about the native
cloud native architecture.
And coming to next slide
here, I want to showcase.
A smart city flood
management using AI inaction.
So what I'm doing here is I
consider a metropolitan area,
which is facing unprecedented
rainfall and rising river levels.
So here the traditional systems, like
we spoke about in the first slide
which mostly rely on manual process,
like on manual gauge ratings, weather
forecasts, and some historical flood maps.
All processed by human coordinators
making evacuation decisions really
extreme in, in, in real extreme pressure.
So what is AI doing here?
So AI system transforms this scenario
entirely, the predictive model
analysis using the rainfall patterns,
soil saturation, river flow rates,
and tide schedules to forecast
flood extent before water arrives.
So this this, all this data is
leveraged by ai and the other thing
is the comfort vision monitors for
managing the blockages in the systems.
And apart from that, we also have
the NLP which uses social media
posts and news channels for emerging
flight reports in the real time.
So these are some points
that AI is leveraged.
And coming to enhanced capabilities
through intelligent systems.
And these capabilities come
with three points here.
The first one being dynamic
evacuation planning.
So here the A optimizes evacuation
rules based on realtime traffic
and predicted flood parts and
shelter capacity and updating
recommendations as conditions evolve.
And the second one being
unified situation level.
Yes.
Here I want to talk about
integrating dashboards.
That is some consolidated data from all
sources wherein we provide these data
to the managers with comprehensive use
with the present unfolding situations.
The last one being intelligent
resource allocation.
Here we use ml, that is machine
learning, which predicts resource
needs by location and time.
Okay.
Using this data we can supply the
personal the personals to that particular
location before the crisis actually peaks.
The situation is out of control.
So this is about the intelligent systems.
And in the next site I want to show
you a scenario, a simulated scenario
with some geospatial mapping.
Using some predictive visualization.
So here let's say some advanced
geospatial systems create high resolution
urban models integrating terrain
infrastructure and population data.
This enables precise flood extent
predictions and impact assessments.
So in this scenario, the
simulation tools that analyze.
Allowing the emergency managers to
visualize consequences of various
interventions such as opening flood
barriers or issuing evacuation
items based on the scenario.
This simulations account for
cascading effects, ensuring informed
strategic planning for the managers.
And the next one is to
build this response.
We need some real time data.
And for if you want to use some real
time data, we should maintain privacy
and some ethical considerations.
So here are three points with respect
to real time data and the privacy and
ethical considerations with this data.
So I would like to talk
about three points here.
The first one being data minimization
principles wherein we collect only
information essential for emergency
response and implement automatic
data retention policies that.
Purge personal details once
immediate crisis results.
Okay, and the second one being
the algorithmic transparency.
So here with the emerging
emergency AI systems they provide
explainable decisions, particularly
when recommendations affect
individual rights or safety.
And the decision audit trials enable
post-crisis review and accountability with
respect to the algorithmic transparency.
And the last one with the real time data.
It's consent and community trust.
So here mostly in this third point, we
engage the community in the system design
and governance and clear communication
about data usage will be given to the
community and other consent mechanisms
for non-emergency periods and community
oversight which helps build public
trust essentially for the system
being very effective with respect to.
So this is what is the privacy
and ethical considerations
with respect to real time data.
And going to the next slide here, we
have some frontiers innovations looking
forward for the next you next innovations.
So here I want to talk about four
points over here with respect to
the forward looking innovations.
The first one being digital wins,
wherein the virtual replicas
of physical infrastructure
enabled continuous simulation.
Stress testing and optimization of
emergency response plans against
evolving urban environments.
So that being said, in the second
point we use edge computing.
So the distributed processing at network
edges enables ultra latency decisions
when cloud connectivity is compromised.
And this is about edge computing.
And the third one being
federated learning.
So the city's collaboratively train AI
models without sharing sense to data.
Wherein we improve predictive
accuracy while preserving
privacy and local autonomy.
And the last one being autonomous robots.
So here, basically what we do is at
the ground and aerial situations robots
perform delivery supplies wherein when
I say robots perform, it's only the
situation when humans by themself when
they cannot get into the situation
or cannot get into that environment.
Of rescue operations.
Then we use these robots, which do
the delivery actions, the risking
actions in those tough environments.
So these are couple of forward looking
innovations and going to the next slide.
So here, with all these points,
considering all these points and
accumulating all these points, I
built intelligent response framework
with some practical strategies.
And the first practical strategy
being assess capabilities.
So here I audit existing systems
and data to identify gaps.
And after that we established data
infrastructure wherein we deploy sensor
networks and secure cloud platforms.
And after that we develop AI models.
And in developing these AI models, we
train and refine AI on instant data.
And after the development of AI
models, we integrate it and test it.
And we connected it to AI, to workflows,
and then we simulate it and we test it.
And after simulation and
testing, we train the personnel.
That is what we do here, is we educate
the teams on AI capabilities and views.
The last point being iterate and improve.
So here what we do is we collect
feedback and based on the feedback,
we improve, like we continuously
improve and update and enhance the ai.
So after all these things let's talk
about some impacts life saved, resources
optimized resilience strengthened.
So here the first point about the
impacts is like the faster response time.
So the AI driven systems reduce decision
making delays and accelerate resource
deployment during critical windows.
And the second one being
improved resource efficiency.
So here some predictive allocation
prevents waste while ensuring
adequate supplies reach affected
areas in time when needed.
And the third one being
enhance situational awareness.
So here we use some unified data
platforms where we provide emergency situ,
emergency information to the managers.
It's significant comprehensive
crisis visibility to the managers
so that they can act accordingly.
And beyond quantitative metrics
intelligence, emergency response systems
fundamentally transform urban resilience.
And then cities become adaptive
organisms capable of anticipating
threats and acting accordingly, and
coordinating complex responses across
agencies and learning from each incident
how better we can improve in future
by providing a better performance.
So this is about the impacts.
And going to the next slide is here.
I would like to conclude saying, building
the future of emergency response is
always possible when we leverage AI with
cloud computing, robotics, and predictive
analysis fundamentally to protect
societies during this emergency crisis.
So as disasters escalate, the
rapid and responsible deployment
of intelligent systems is crucial.
The frameworks and strategies
discussed offer a roadmap for emergency
management professionals the city
planners and technology leaders.
So what I'm trying to say here is with all
the suggestions and the frameworks and the
technology points we can always achieve.
A better intelligent
adaptive AI response feature.
So this is all about the emergency
response using ai wherein we
leverage cloud computing, robotics,
and plate predictive analysis.
So I would like to thank you for giving
me this opportunity to put forth my
ideas and give a presentation about.
The emergency responses using AI platform.
Thank you everyone.
Have a good day.