Hello everyone.
Thank you for joining me.
I'm Raul Pingle from Wal.
I'm a technical Director at Wal West.
Today I'll be sharing how maternal
engineering, specifically in Wal Rings and
non-owned substrate, plays a direct role
in advancing iot connectivity robotics
sustainable building metal system.
This presentation is about how we
turn something as ordinary as wall.
Into active part of smart environment.
Let's start by looking at why our
current infrastructure isn't keeping
up with today's connected world.
Traditional building materials,
especially vinyl wall coverings,
face a challenge for smart buildings.
They often emit VOC block the
wireless signals and are difficult
to replace when sensors or
automation systems needs upgrades.
This means our physical space are
holding back digital progress.
To overcome this, we need a new
generation of material surface that don't
just decorate the wall, but actively
enables connectivity and automation.
Our team engineered three key
breakthrough that makes this possible.
Let's see, what are
those three breakthrough?
So this three breakthrough
one is nano barrier.
Coatings.
A Microsphere PSA technology and
multi-meter printability gives us
the better digitally enabled space.
So microsphere coatings for
superior moisture protection.
Microsphere system is for
responsible clean installation.
A multi-meter printability allowing
us use of, grab your digital flexo
printing methods together, this form of
sustainable iot ready surface platform.
Smart environments needs surface material
that interact, not just insulate or decor.
They must support embedded
sensors, RFID systems and QR
code automation while being safe.
Recycle and easy to remove or replace.
Essentially, the wall itself
becomes part of the iot ecosystem.
Let's take a closer look at each
of these technology, starting
with the nano barrier coatings.
Our water-based nano barrier coating
replace solid based vinyls based
coatings while matching their durability.
It's validated to ASTM 96 with the
moisture vapor transmission outperforming
most non ones under high humidity.
And because it's zero solvent,
there are no VOC emissions or
disposable issue making it safer for
both manufacturing and occupants.
Let's now see that how we have
solved the barrier challenge it.
Look at how we.
Tackle the addition, the conventional
additive for permanent form, the permanent
bonds that makes remote destructive.
Our microsphere pressure sensor
Additive technology creates a tiny
contact points instead of a solid
layer, gives high strength while still
allowing full removal without damage.
This means sensors, wall panels, or
digital display can be repositioned.
Are replaced without surface repairs.
It's ideal for iot enable
buildings that evolves over time.
Next come most exciting part, how this
materials enable printing, coding and
sensing directly onto the surface.
We design the subset to work
seamlessly with the NJ Flexography
and UV digital technology system.
That means we can print.
RFID, an antenna Q codes.
Conductive or conductive inks
stresses directly onto the surface.
This allows the wall itself to
communicate acting as a layer
for automation and robotics.
And this brings us to how
this metal integrate into the
iot and robotics ecosystem.
The smart walls enables three things.
Wireless transparency, maintaining a
signal strength for robotics and sensors.
Embedded sensors such as
temperature occupancy detector are
right built right into the wall.
Much readable markers like cure codes,
NFC Chiefs, that guides autonomous
navigation in short surface, become the
communication fabric for connected spaces.
But innovation only matters if it is.
Meets safety sustainability standards.
Let's look at the, our compliance.
Our platform meets strong V emission
testing like CDP 0 1 3 5 0 for
ultra low V-O-C-A-S-T-M 84 Class A
Fire Safety and complies with the
reach and well building standards.
It's free from ATE ha heavy metals.
This ensures smart doesn't come at
the cost of health and Ann enrollment.
We validated all this through
independent standard based testing.
Every compliance property needs barrier,
addition fire, UC performance, and is
verified through A STM and testing.
We even simulate five year
durability to ensure stability
across different climates.
This data driven validation, build trust,
especially in sector like healthcare
education where compliance is critical
and those are the exactly market where
we have already seen the strong adoption.
So we adopted this platform in over
more than 15 facility across North
America and Europe in hospitals.
It supports infection control and
integrates with the automation system.
In schools, it allows flexible
low emission learning space.
And in smart offices it enhance
connectivity for iot analytics.
This proves the technology is
ready and not just a theoretical.
So what does this mean for robotics
and connected environments?
So for robotics, this smart,
no-one surface serves as navigation
map data networks compliant.
Con infrastructure all at once.
They support RF transparency, embedded
sensing, asset tracking and damage
free updates, everything connected
space needs for autonomous systems.
And to scale this across industries
structure, adoption approach is the key.
So we developed a four step
framework for implementation.
First, align material cap capability
with automation needs Second.
Engage facility IT and
sustainability team early.
Then third, run small scale pilot
trials to validate the results.
And fourth, use the data to
scalable the trials efficiently.
This approach ensures every
deployment is both technically
and operationally successful.
Now, to wrap this up, let's
summarize key lesson from this work.
First smart material means smart
infrastructure, the enable IO,
OT and robotics, not just walls.
Second, data driven validation builds
confidence for large scale use.
Third multifunctional design, reduce
cost, and simplifies the procurement.
And finally, real world adoption
shows this technology isn't
futuristic, it's happening right now.
So how do we carry this momentum forward?
The future of connected environments
depends on material innovations.
Smart non surface from foundation of
intelligent buildings enable wireless
communications, embedded sensors,
and sustainable compliance that older
material can't catch or can match.
In short, material engineering
is infrastructure engineering
for connected ages.
I hope this session gives
you a new perspective on how
material science connects.
With robotics and
automations sustainability.
Thank you for your time and attention.
Okay.